<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="MVP Scoping Framework">
  <summary>Six-step process to scope an MVP: define the problem, identify core value, list features, apply MoSCoW, validate scope, and define done — with a hard capacity constraint on Must-Have features.</summary>

  <section title="What is an MVP">
    <p>Minimum Viable Product is the smallest version that solves the core problem, delivers value to early adopters, and allows you to learn and iterate. The critical distinction: MVP is about learning, not about launching a polished product.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every MVP must state a falsifiable hypothesis and a numeric kill criterion before the feature list is written.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a hypothesis, scope decisions have no anchor. Without a kill criterion, the MVP becomes a permanent v1 even when metrics miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MVP vs MLP">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ship an MVP to validate a hypothesis; evolve to MLP (Minimum Lovable Product) only after validation.</statement>
      <rationale>MVP targets early adopters who tolerate rough edges; MLP targets retention-sensitive mainstream users. Conflating the two inflates scope before the hypothesis is proven.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="6-Step Scoping Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Define the core problem using the template: "For [user] who [problem], our MVP proves [hypothesis] by delivering [outcome] in [timebox] with [constraints]."</statement>
      <rationale>Forces the problem statement to name a specific user, a hypothesis, and a timebox before any features appear.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Identify the ONE thing the product must do well; apply the value test: if you remove it, is the product useless?</statement>
      <rationale>Single core value prevents multi-axis scope — the most common cause of a 6-month MVP.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Brain-dump all features, then categorize each as Core, Important, Nice-to-have, or Out of Scope.</statement>
      <rationale>Separation forces explicit trade-offs before MoSCoW weighting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Apply MoSCoW: Must Have ≤ 60% of capacity, Should Have ≤ 20%, reserve 20% buffer. Won't Have must be explicit and list ≥ 3 items.</statement>
      <rationale>The capacity constraint is a physical ceiling, not a guideline. Won't Have is the scope-creep firewall.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Validate scope against five gates: solves core problem end-to-end; first user can complete core job; value is delivered without future features; buildable in target timebox; hypothesis is testable.</statement>
      <rationale>Each gate catches a different failure mode — incompleteness, user-flow gaps, dependency holes, schedule risk, and unverifiability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6 — Define done: acceptance criteria per Must-Have feature, definition of "good enough" quality, metrics to collect, and the next decision after MVP.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a definition of done, the MVP ship date is always "almost ready."</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/mvp-scope-doc.md">Full MVP scope document with all sections</reference>
  <reference path="templates/mvp-quick-check.md">5-question validator for fast scope review</reference>
  <reference path="templates/mvp-capacity.py">Capacity guard script: fails if Must days exceed 60% budget</reference>
</text>
