<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="mvp-scoping Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for mvp-scoping as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Must-Have list contains more than 5 features or exceeds 60% of capacity.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every additional Must is scope creep disguised as necessity. Cap is 3–5 items; above that, re-examine whether each directly tests the hypothesis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>MVP has no kill criterion — only a success target.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without a kill threshold the team always finds a reason to keep going; the MVP becomes a permanent v1. Force the field: "If metric &lt; X by date Y, pivot or kill."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>MVP takes 6+ months to build.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Six months is not an MVP — it is a product launch. Real MVPs fit inside 2–8 weeks. If the timebox is longer, the scope is wrong or the hypothesis is too broad.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Won't-Have is empty or has fewer than 3 items.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The Won't-Have list is the scope-creep firewall. An empty list means no trade-offs were made. Every MVP should explicitly exclude ≥ 3 tempting features with stated reasons.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>MVP has no learning goal — only a feature list.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Features without questions are just engineering work. The learning goal is what converts the MVP from "release" to "experiment"; if it is absent, there is nothing to learn from the launch.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Authentication and billing listed as Must-Have for v0.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Magic links replace full auth. Stripe checkout replaces in-app billing UI. Both are Should for v0 unless the hypothesis is specifically about the billing or auth experience.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>The same agent that proposes features also reviews scope.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Proposer bias inflates the Must list. Use a separate reviewer subagent that applies the 5-question quick check independently.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
