<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Advanced TikTok Strategies Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Advanced TikTok Strategies application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-hook-in-first-three-seconds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every video MUST land its hook in the first 3 seconds (pattern interrupt + claim). Intros / logos / 'hey guys' are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Watch-time decays sharply after 3 seconds; the hook gate determines reach.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-watchtime-over-frequency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan MUST optimise watch-time per video, not post frequency. Posting &gt; 2/day below 30% watch-time is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Algorithm penalises low-watch-time accounts; high-frequency low-quality is worse than weekly high-quality.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-trend-ride-within-48h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trend rides MUST publish within 48 hours of trend peak. Late-trend posts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Trend half-life on TikTok is 3-5 days; late publishing lands in the down-slope.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-conversion-path-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan MUST name the conversion path from video → bio → off-platform asset → goal. Untracked accounts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">TikTok-only metrics don't pay rent; the off-platform path is the actual funnel.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-growth-loop-built-in" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>≥1 growth loop (reply-as-video / duet / stitch invitation) MUST be wired into the format. Static one-way posts are rejected as the only format.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Growth loops compound reach; static posts depend on cold algorithm reach only.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
