<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-tiktok-strategies Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-tiktok-strategies. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test at least 5 hook variants (one per formula type) per topic before scaling frequency; below 5 variants is an insufficient sample size.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hook formula effectiveness is niche-dependent; what works for coding content fails for B2B SaaS. Only performance data from real publishing reveals which formula resonates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start mid-action, not with an intro; the first frame must contain movement, face close to camera, or unexpected visual.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">TikTok's algorithm measures average watch time in the first 3 seconds separately from total watch time; a static intro frame causes instant scroll-past.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Optimize watch time and completion rate before optimizing for likes; completion rate carries more algorithmic weight than any engagement metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The For You Page distribution algorithm weights watch time and completion rate "very high" and likes "medium." Accounts that optimize completion outgrow accounts that optimize for likes at 3-5x speed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post 3 videos at 70%+ completion rate instead of 7 videos at 40% completion; watch-time optimization outperforms posting frequency.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Low completion rate signals poor content quality; the algorithm stops distributing accounts with chronically low completion, regardless of volume.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post trend-adapted content within 24-48 hours of a trend starting; trends that are 72+ hours old deliver 50-80% fewer views.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">TikTok's algorithm boosts trending sound usage during the early adoption phase; late adoption gets no boost and may look derivative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Optimize the link in bio for mobile conversion; the profile visit → link click step is the highest drop-off point in the TikTok funnel.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Most TikTok traffic lands on a profile page then clicks bio link; a non-mobile-optimized landing page wastes the entire top-of-funnel effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target duet/stitch creators with 50K-500K followers in your niche; mega-creators (1M+) deliver lower follow-back rates and less targeted audiences.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mid-tier niche creators have more engaged, specific audiences that match B2B/SaaS ICPs. Mega-creator audiences are too broad for most product offers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review analytics weekly; focus on watch-time graphs (where do viewers drop off?) before any other metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Drop-off point analysis reveals structural problems (weak transition, too-long intro) that can be fixed in the next video; other metrics only confirm results, not causes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
