<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-hooks-and-algorithm" title="Hook Mastery and Algorithm Signal Optimization">
  <summary>Five hook formula types, visual hook rules, algorithm signal weights, and posting cadence targets.</summary>

  <section title="Hook Formulas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test at least 5 hook variants (one per formula type) per topic before scaling frequency; below 5 variants is an insufficient sample size.</statement>
      <rationale>Hook formula effectiveness is niche-dependent; what works for coding content fails for B2B SaaS. Only performance data from real publishing reveals which formula resonates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Curiosity: "Here's why [unexpected thing]..." (e.g., "Here's why your startup will fail...")</item>
      <item>Challenge: "Stop doing [common thing]" (e.g., "Stop using Google Docs for specs")</item>
      <item>Promise: "How I [achieved result]" (e.g., "How I got 10K users with $0 ads")</item>
      <item>Relatability: "POV: You're a [role] and..." (e.g., "POV: You're a founder and...")</item>
      <item>Controversy: "Unpopular opinion: [take]" (e.g., "Unpopular opinion: MVP is dead")</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Visual Hook Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start mid-action, not with an intro; the first frame must contain movement, face close to camera, or unexpected visual.</statement>
      <rationale>TikTok's algorithm measures average watch time in the first 3 seconds separately from total watch time; a static intro frame causes instant scroll-past.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Text on screen must appear in the first frame (not after intro)</item>
      <item>Face should be close to camera, not far away</item>
      <item>Movement in the first frame: hand gesture, item held up, screen recording starting</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Algorithm Signals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Optimize watch time and completion rate before optimizing for likes; completion rate carries more algorithmic weight than any engagement metric.</statement>
      <rationale>The For You Page distribution algorithm weights watch time and completion rate "very high" and likes "medium." Accounts that optimize completion outgrow accounts that optimize for likes at 3-5x speed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Watch time: very high weight — optimize with strong hooks and fast pacing</item>
      <item>Completion rate: very high weight — keep initial videos short to hit 90%+ completion</item>
      <item>Shares: high weight — make content share-worthy by being useful or entertaining</item>
      <item>Comments: high weight — ask questions; controversial takes drive comment volume</item>
      <item>Saves: high weight — actionable content (checklists, tips) drives saves</item>
      <item>Likes: medium weight — secondary metric, do not optimize at expense of completion</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Posting Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post 3 videos at 70%+ completion rate instead of 7 videos at 40% completion; watch-time optimization outperforms posting frequency.</statement>
      <rationale>Low completion rate signals poor content quality; the algorithm stops distributing accounts with chronically low completion, regardless of volume.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Minimum: 1 post/day, every day — never skip in first 90 days</item>
      <item>Ideal: 3-5 posts/day once content bank is established</item>
      <item>Best times: 7-9am (morning scroll), 12-2pm (work breaks), 7-10pm (peak usage) — test for your specific audience</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
