<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-growth-tactics" title="Growth Loops, Trend Usage, Conversion Funnel, and Case Studies">
  <summary>Trend adaptation workflow, TikTok conversion funnel, growth loops (duets/stitches/series), real case studies.</summary>

  <section title="Trend Adaptation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post trend-adapted content within 24-48 hours of a trend starting; trends that are 72+ hours old deliver 50-80% fewer views.</statement>
      <rationale>TikTok's algorithm boosts trending sound usage during the early adoption phase; late adoption gets no boost and may look derivative.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Check Discover page daily; browse For You Page for 10 min</item>
      <item>Identify the trend pattern: structure, twist, and audio type</item>
      <item>Adapt to your niche: same structure, your industry context, your unique angle</item>
      <item>Film and post within 24 hours of identifying the trend</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Conversion Funnel">
    <p>Views → Profile visits → Link clicks → Leads/Sales. The secondary path: Followers → Repeat exposure → Trust → Conversion.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Optimize the link in bio for mobile conversion; the profile visit → link click step is the highest drop-off point in the TikTok funnel.</statement>
      <rationale>Most TikTok traffic lands on a profile page then clicks bio link; a non-mobile-optimized landing page wastes the entire top-of-funnel effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Link in bio: Linktree or direct landing page (mobile-optimized)</item>
      <item>Pinned video: place your best converting video at the top of profile</item>
      <item>Comment replies with CTA: respond to questions with link mention</item>
      <item>Lead capture: free resource (checklist, template), Discord invite, newsletter</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Growth Loops">
    <rule>
      <statement>Target duet/stitch creators with 50K-500K followers in your niche; mega-creators (1M+) deliver lower follow-back rates and less targeted audiences.</statement>
      <rationale>Mid-tier niche creators have more engaged, specific audiences that match B2B/SaaS ICPs. Mega-creator audiences are too broad for most product offers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Duets/Stitches: leverage others' audiences, expect 2-5x views on duet videos</item>
      <item>Series content ("Part 1", "Part 2"): keep viewers coming back, higher follower conversion</item>
      <item>Cliffhangers: "Part 2 drops tomorrow" increases profile visit rate 3-5x — only use if Part 2 is ready to publish within 24 hours</item>
      <item>Collaborations: tag other creators in your niche for shared audience access</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Real Case Studies">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Developer tool — 0 to 150K followers in 6 months</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Strategy: Daily coding tips (15-30 sec), trending sounds + code tutorials, "Day X of learning [language]" series
Results: 150K followers, 2M+ total views, 5K newsletter signups, $10K in course sales
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>B2B service — 200 to 25K followers in 4 months</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Strategy: Industry myth-busting, quick tips for target ICP, case study storytimes, duets with industry content
Results: 25K followers, 15 qualified leads/month, 3 enterprise clients ($50K+ deals)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Analytics Review Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Review analytics weekly; focus on watch-time graphs (where do viewers drop off?) before any other metric.</statement>
      <rationale>Drop-off point analysis reveals structural problems (weak transition, too-long intro) that can be fixed in the next video; other metrics only confirm results, not causes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/analytics-processor.py">Script to process TikTok Analytics CSV and surface watch-time patterns</reference>
  </section>
</text>
