<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-tiktok-strategies Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-tiktok-strategies as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents generate hooks that are grammatically correct but tonally flat — TikTok hooks need urgency and pattern interruption, which requires explicit prompting ("write this hook as if the viewer is about to scroll away").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Default tone is neutral; TikTok's medium demands attention-grabbing urgency.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Series content drafted by agents often lacks a genuine cliffhanger — the "reveal" in Part 2 must be compelling enough to justify a follow; validate manually before posting Part 1.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents tend to generate logical conclusions rather than psychological hooks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Watch-time analysis requires actual data; agents asked to "predict" drop-off points without data will hallucinate statistics.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Only real analytics reveal drop-off patterns; predictions without data are fabrications.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Trend adaptation scripts sound generic unless the trend's exact sound, text overlay style, and visual pattern are described in detail to the agent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents need concrete reference material, not abstract trend names.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Do not ask an agent to select which hashtags to use — TikTok hashtag strategy is real-time and requires Creative Center access; use 3-5 niche hashtags chosen by a human.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Real-time trend data is outside agent training scope.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
