<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-trend-buckets" title="Product Development Trends 2026: Bucket Rubric and Snapshot Workflow">
  <summary>Four trend buckets with the state/confidence scoring rubric, snapshot JSON schema, and quarterly diff-to-ticket workflow for keeping the trend list grounded in dated primary sources.</summary>

  <section title="Four Trend Buckets">
    <list>
      <item>AI-augmented ideation: pattern recognition at scale, gap identification, surfacing weak signals from user research</item>
      <item>Continuous customer feedback: real-time product iteration, weekly interview cadence, assumption testing loops</item>
      <item>Rapid pivots: quarterly vs annual adjustment cycles, agile delivery over waterfall planning</item>
      <item>Cross-functional teams: PM + Design + Engineering collaboration as the delivery unit</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the four buckets as a rubric to score against dated primary sources — not as settled facts. Each quarter, re-derive the state of each bucket rather than quoting the previous snapshot.</statement>
      <rationale>The buckets are 2024-vintage consultancy talking points. Without re-verification they age into outdated claims that miscalibrate roadmap and GTM decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Rubric">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each bucket on: state ∈ {accepted, contested, declining, emerging}, confidence ∈ [0,1] (require ≥2 cited primary sources for confidence ≥0.6), and 3 supporting URLs with publication date ≤12 months.</statement>
      <rationale>A four-state rubric with confidence and source requirements makes trend claims falsifiable. "State = accepted, confidence = 0.4, one source" communicates very different certainty than "accepted, confidence = 0.8, three sources".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin primary sources to: Stack Overflow Annual Survey, GitHub Octoverse, ThoughtWorks Tech Radar, State of DevOps (DORA), Gartner Hype Cycle. Reject any source older than the previous quarterly snapshot.</statement>
      <rationale>These are the authoritative annual/quarterly measurements of actual developer and team practices — not analyst opinion pieces or vendor blog posts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Quarterly Diff-to-Ticket Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write snapshots to .research/snapshots/trends-YYYY-QQ.md and a JSON sidecar, never edit README.md to "update trends". The README is the rubric, not the answer.</statement>
      <rationale>Editing the rubric with each quarter's findings conflates the measurement instrument with the measurement. Future agents need the original rubric to re-score independently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When a bucket changes state (e.g., "rapid pivots" moves from accepted to contested), open an SDD ticket in .aidocs/backlog/ with: what changed, which roadmap items are affected, proposed action ≤3 bullets. Never edit roadmap.md directly from the trend scan.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated roadmap edits from trend scans bypass the human approval gate. Routing through SDD backlog ensures a human reviews the implication before it affects delivery commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/trend-snapshot.json">Snapshot JSON schema: 4 buckets with state, confidence, sources, delta_vs_last</reference>
  <reference path="templates/trend-snapshot-validate.sh">Pre-commit validator: 4 buckets, valid state, confidence range, ≥2 sources, no stale sources</reference>
</text>
