<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules-and-gotchas" title="Product Development Trends 2026: Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Source-freshness rules, survivorship bias guards, greenwashing prevention, duplicate-doc confusion handling, and AI-agent gotchas for the trend-scanning workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Source-Freshness Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin every trend bullet to ≥2 dated sources — at least one primary (Stack Overflow Survey, State of DevOps, GitHub Octoverse, Gartner) and one secondary (analyst commentary, Lenny's Newsletter). Reject any bullet with fewer than two dated sources.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-source trend claims are indistinguishable from one viral blog post that may not reflect broad adoption. Two independent sources pointing in the same direction provide meaningfully higher confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate publication dates with curl -I against the URL and reject 404s. Agents fabricate 2026-dated articles from publishers that have not published them.</statement>
      <rationale>Source-date hallucination is the most common failure in trend research. A URL that returns 404 or a date mismatch catches the fabrication before it propagates into deliverables.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Survivorship and Selection Bias">
    <rule>
      <statement>When citing "days not weeks" speed claims, name the benchmark cohort (e.g., "DORA elite performers, top 25%"). Do not quote elite-performer data as if it is the median.</statement>
      <rationale>DORA data shows elite performers; median enterprise still ships in months. Quoting the elite as median systematically miscalibrates expectations in planning and positioning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap consumer-trend bullets at 5. Require a third-party certification or measurable behaviour change per sustainability/ESG claim, not just a survey response.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents balloon consumer-trend sections to 20 vague items without evidence. "Brands that do good" is a ten-year recycled talking point — require a 2025-or-later primary source or drop it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Duplicate-Doc Resolution">
    <rule>
      <statement>When loading trend methodology content, require an explicit slug in the prompt (product-development-trends-2026 vs product-development-trends). Never load both without explicitly deduplicating.</statement>
      <rationale>Two near-identical folders exist. Agents asked to "load latest trends" may load the older one; the explicit slug prevents the silent loading of stale content.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Before another research round, resolve the two folders (product-development-trends/ and product-development-trends-2026/) — pick one canonical path and archive the other.</statement>
      <rationale>Duplicate content creates routing confusion for agents and version drift between the two files. One canonical path eliminates both failure modes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Confirmation echo: asked "is X still a trend in 2026?", agent answers yes by default without sourcing.</description>
      <reason>Force the rubric — state ∈ 4 values with citations, no narrative answer. "Yes" is not a valid rubric output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Buzzword bloat: "AI-augmented", "data-driven", "cross-functional" expand into paragraphs of nothing.</description>
      <reason>Cap each bucket's prose at ≤80 words in the snapshot. Length is inversely correlated with evidence density in trend writing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Vendor-source bias: McKinsey/BCG/a16z articles promote their portfolio narrative.</description>
      <reason>Require ≥1 community/OSS source (Stack Overflow, GitHub Octoverse) per bucket to balance the vendor-interest angle.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>"Cross-functional teams" treated as a recipe rather than an org change.</description>
      <reason>Cross-functional teams require structural org changes (reporting lines, incentives, co-location) — treating it as a methodology step produces vacuous prescriptions that agents cannot execute.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
