<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-concepts" title="Terraform Core Concepts, Workflow, and Module Design Rules">
  <summary>Providers, resources, state, backends, modules, and the plan-apply workflow; module sizing and composition rules; state security requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Core Concepts">
    <list>
      <item>Provider: plugin for cloud API interaction (AWS, GCP, Azure, Kubernetes)</item>
      <item>Resource: infrastructure object managed by Terraform (aws_instance, google_compute_instance)</item>
      <item>Data Source: read-only reference to existing infrastructure not managed by this config</item>
      <item>Module: reusable collection of resources; never configure providers inside child modules</item>
      <item>State: mapping between HCL config and real-world resource IDs; must never be local for teams</item>
      <item>Backend: remote storage for state (S3, GCS, Azure Blob, Terraform Cloud)</item>
      <item>Workspace: named state environments within one backend (prefer directory-per-environment instead)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow Commands">
    <list>
      <item>terraform init: download providers, configure backend — required after any provider/backend change</item>
      <item>terraform validate: check syntax and configuration (run in CI on every PR)</item>
      <item>terraform fmt -recursive: standardize formatting (run as pre-commit check)</item>
      <item>terraform plan -out=tfplan: preview changes, save plan to file</item>
      <item>terraform apply tfplan: execute saved plan (never apply without reviewing plan first)</item>
      <item>terraform destroy: remove all managed infrastructure (requires explicit confirmation)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Module Design Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the module tree flat; prefer composition over deep nesting.</statement>
      <rationale>Deep module nesting creates hard-to-trace dependency chains and makes plan output unreadable. Compose root modules from flat child modules rather than nesting child modules inside each other.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Size modules to one logical component — not single resources, not entire application stacks.</statement>
      <rationale>Too-small modules (single security group) provide no encapsulation benefit. Too-large modules (entire application stack) cannot be selectively applied and create blast radius for unrelated changes. Right size: VPC with subnets, NAT, and routing tables.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never configure providers inside child modules; provider configuration belongs in root modules only.</statement>
      <rationale>Provider config in child modules makes the module non-reusable across provider versions and authentication methods. Root modules own provider config; child modules inherit it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="State Security Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Remote backend required for all team environments; never commit state files to version control.</statement>
      <rationale>State files contain plaintext resource IDs, ARNs, and sometimes secrets. Local state causes concurrent apply conflicts. Committed state leaks sensitive infrastructure details.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Enable encryption at rest on state backend (S3: SSE-KMS or SSE-S3)</item>
      <item>Enable state locking: S3 use_lockfile=true (Terraform 1.10+), GCS built-in, Azure built-in</item>
      <item>Enable versioning on state storage bucket for recovery</item>
      <item>Restrict bucket access via IAM to Terraform execution role only</item>
      <item>Separate state per environment (separate key or bucket prefix per env)</item>
      <item>Commit .terraform.lock.hcl to version control for reproducible provider versions</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Project Structure">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
infrastructure/
├── environments/
│   ├── dev/
│   │   ├── main.tf        # root module: calls child modules
│   │   ├── variables.tf
│   │   ├── outputs.tf
│   │   ├── terraform.tfvars
│   │   └── backend.tf
│   ├── staging/
│   └── prod/
├── modules/
│   ├── vpc/               # main.tf, variables.tf, outputs.tf, versions.tf
│   ├── eks/
│   └── rds/
└── tests/
    └── vpc.tftest.hcl
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/backend-s3.tf">S3 backend config with native locking and provider default_tags</reference>
  <reference path="templates/variables.tf">Variable definitions with validation blocks</reference>
  <reference path="templates/modules-vpc.tf">VPC module example</reference>
  <reference path="templates/github-actions.yml">Full CI/CD pipeline for Terraform</reference>
</text>
