<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="terraform-iac Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for terraform-iac. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep the module tree flat; prefer composition over deep nesting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Deep module nesting creates hard-to-trace dependency chains and makes plan output unreadable. Compose root modules from flat child modules rather than nesting child modules inside each other.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Size modules to one logical component — not single resources, not entire application stacks.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Too-small modules (single security group) provide no encapsulation benefit. Too-large modules (entire application stack) cannot be selectively applied and create blast radius for unrelated changes. Right size: VPC with subnets, NAT, and routing tables.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never configure providers inside child modules; provider configuration belongs in root modules only.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Provider config in child modules makes the module non-reusable across provider versions and authentication methods. Root modules own provider config; child modules inherit it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Remote backend required for all team environments; never commit state files to version control.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">State files contain plaintext resource IDs, ARNs, and sometimes secrets. Local state causes concurrent apply conflicts. Committed state leaks sensitive infrastructure details.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
