<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="onboarding-60-90-day">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Two-phase new-hire progression: Contribute (days 31-60, first owned project) and Execute (days 61-90, independent delivery). Each phase ends with checkpoints anchored to concrete artifacts.</summary>
    <category>onboarding</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>onboarding</tag>
      <tag>60-90-day</tag>
      <tag>new-hire-ramp</tag>
      <tag>performance-review</tag>
      <tag>milestones</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>60-90 Day Onboarding Phases</title>
    <summary>A two-phase framework for structured new-hire progression after the initial 30-day learning phase: Contribute (days 31-60, first owned project, active collaboration) and Execute (days 61-90, independent delivery, measurable results). Each phase ends with a milestone checkpoint anchored to a concrete artifact, not a self-reported activity.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>After the 30-day phase, new hires without explicit milestones plateau or drift below capacity. Separating Contribute from Execute sets a clear intermediate bar: the hire must ship something before being evaluated on independence. The day-45 skip-level and day-60 review catch misalignment mid-ramp when correction is still low-cost; discovering it at the 90-day formal review is too late.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A hire has cleared 30-day learning criteria and needs explicit Contribute (31-60) and Execute (61-90) milestones.</item>
        <item>Manager wants a structured second-and-third-month plan separate from the broad 30-60-90 framework.</item>
        <item>Roles with ramp quotas or feature ownership (sales, engineering) where deliverables land in this window.</item>
        <item>Preparing a defensible 90-day review with an artifact trail.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Hire is still failing day-30 criteria — resolve or restart the cycle first.</item>
        <item>Roles with multi-quarter ramps (Enterprise AE, ML researcher) — extend phases; do not compress.</item>
        <item>Senior autonomous hires who define their own deliverables.</item>
        <item>Contract placements under 60 days.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="contribute-phase-objective">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The Contribute phase ends when the hire has owned and completed at least one project end-to-end; "participating" or "contributing to" a team project does not satisfy this criterion.</statement>
        <rationale>End-to-end ownership reveals planning, execution, communication, and handoff capability. Participation in a team project reveals only the ability to execute a defined slice; it does not demonstrate the full delivery loop that the Execute phase depends on.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="contribute-phase-activities">
      <section name="projects">
        <p>Own first project end-to-end. Scope must be achievable within weeks 5-8 — not so small it is trivial, not so large it requires extensions. Project selection is a manager decision made at the day-30 review.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="collaboration">
        <p>Contribute actively in meetings — not just attend. Contribution is measurable: made a decision, raised a risk, proposed a solution. Meeting presence without contribution is not a milestone completion criterion.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="relationships">
        <p>Build cross-functional connections beyond the immediate team. Identify 3-5 stakeholders in adjacent teams and schedule introductions in weeks 5-6. Goal: the hire knows who to contact for decisions outside their team boundary before the day-60 review.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="feedback">
        <p>Receive feedback from at least two sources (manager and peer or cross-functional stakeholder) and demonstrate acting on it. "Acting on it" requires a visible artifact: changed approach, updated doc, adjusted behavior noted by the feedback giver.</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="day-60-success-criteria">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Confirm all five day-60 success criteria are met before allowing the hire to enter the Execute phase; missing criteria require a plan for resolution, not a deferral to day-90.</statement>
        <rationale>Deferring unmet 60-day criteria to the 90-day review compresses the Execute phase into the remaining time and produces a rushed, low-evidence review. Addressing gaps at day 60 while there is still 30 days of execution time is the correct intervention point.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Completed first project successfully (artifact exists: PR merged, doc published, milestone delivered).</item>
        <item>Receives positive feedback from team (at least one unsolicited or structured peer feedback).</item>
        <item>Works with minimal supervision on familiar tasks within role scope.</item>
        <item>Demonstrates core job competencies at the level expected for the role and level.</item>
        <item>Has documented goals for days 61-90 in a shared artifact, agreed with manager.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="contribute-phase-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Defining "contributing" as meeting attendance or activity counts rather than outcome delivery.</description>
        <reason>Activity-based milestones (attended 10 standups, joined 3 cross-team meetings) create false completion signals. A hire who attends all meetings but delivers nothing has not demonstrated contribution — they have demonstrated availability.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Assigning a project so small it provides no meaningful evidence of delivery capability.</description>
        <reason>A 2-hour task completed in week 5 does not demonstrate the planning, execution, and communication behaviors the phase is designed to reveal. Scope the first project to require 1-2 weeks of sustained effort.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="execute-phase-objective">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The Execute phase measures independence: the hire must handle most responsibilities without needing guidance; if guidance is still required for familiar tasks at day 90, the hire has not met the ramp bar.</statement>
        <rationale>The 90-day review is the formal transition from onboarding to standard performance management. A hire who still requires frequent guidance at day 90 is on an extended ramp that must be named explicitly and managed differently than the standard onboarding conclusion.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="execute-phase-activities">
      <section name="independence">
        <p>Handle responsibilities with minimal guidance. The target is: manager is a resource, not a required step. The hire should seek guidance for novel or high-stakes decisions, not for repeating tasks within their scope.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="delivery">
        <p>Complete a major project or milestone — larger in scope than the day-60 project. For engineering: medium-complexity feature. For sales: first closed deal. For PM: shipped feature with usage data. Milestone must be documented before the Execute phase begins.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="initiative">
        <p>Proactively identify at least one opportunity, risk, or improvement not assigned by the manager. Initiative evidence: raised the issue in a meeting or 1:1, proposed a solution, and either implemented it or passed it through the appropriate channel.</p>
      </section>
      <section name="mentorship">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Include a mentorship milestone only if there is a confirmed newer hire to mentor; never add it as a generic aspiration.</statement>
          <rationale>Generic mentorship milestones at day 90 fail when there are no newer hires; the milestone becomes unfulfillable and the review is forced to waive it, undermining the credibility of the other criteria.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="day-90-success-criteria">
      <list>
        <item>Meets or exceeds performance expectations on primary job responsibilities.</item>
        <item>Works autonomously on 80%+ of tasks without requiring guidance from manager or peers.</item>
        <item>Has delivered a major project or milestone with a verifiable artifact.</item>
        <item>Has a documented development plan for the next quarter, co-authored with the manager.</item>
        <item>Is integrated into team culture — participates in social and professional rituals without prompting.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="check-in-structure">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run a skip-level check-in at day 45; the manager is not the only signal source and may have blind spots the skip-level surfaces.</statement>
        <rationale>Manager-only feedback produces biased signals: managers unconsciously minimize problems they contributed to and amplify successes they credit themselves for. The skip-level provides an independent calibration point mid-ramp.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Day 45: skip-level check-in (hire meets manager's manager; format is a conversation, not a review). Day 60: manager review with documented outcomes against day-60 success criteria. Day 90: formal performance review with documented outcomes; transition to standard performance management cycle.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="metrics">
      <p>60-day project completion: 100% (tracked by manager). 90-day retention: target above 95% (track voluntary departures in this window). Time to productivity: role-dependent; defined in the plan before Day 1 and assessed by manager at day 90. Onboarding satisfaction: target above 4.0 out of 5 (survey at day 90). 90-day review scores: target above 3.5 out of 5 on primary competency rubric.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="execute-phase-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using the same milestone pace for all hires regardless of role level or prior experience.</description>
        <reason>A senior hire from an adjacent company may complete the Contribute phase in 3 weeks rather than 4-8. Rigidly enforcing the standard cadence frustrates fast ramps and signals the organization cannot adapt to individual capability.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping the day-45 skip-level because the manager reports the hire is doing well.</description>
        <reason>The skip-level's purpose is precisely to check when the manager reports success. Confident reports from the manager are the highest-risk scenario for a blind-spot review at day 90.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/checklist-60-90.md" purpose="Week-by-week checklist for both phases with 60-day and 90-day success criteria."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="onboarding-30-day"/>
      <link href="https://www.shrm.org/topics-tools/tools/toolkits/onboarding-new-employees"/>
      <link href="https://resources.workable.com/tutorial/30-60-90-day-plan"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
