<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-reel-strategy" title="Instagram Reel Strategy and DM Funnel">
  <summary>Reel optimization rules, weekly content schedule, DM trigger funnel, and engagement routine for Instagram growth.</summary>

  <section title="Reels as Primary Growth Engine">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize Reels over static feed posts for reach goals. Reels are redistributed via Explore to non-followers; feed posts are not.</statement>
      <rationale>Explore distribution allows accounts to reach audiences 3-10x larger than their follower base. Static posts reach only existing followers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The hook of a Reel must work with the sound off: text overlay and visual action are mandatory in the first 1-2 seconds.</statement>
      <rationale>A large percentage of mobile users watch video without sound. A sound-dependent hook loses this audience in the first second.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Use 3-5 highly relevant hashtags per post. Never use 30 hashtags — this pattern triggers shadowban risk.</statement>
      <rationale>Instagram's current algorithm gives no additional reach benefit beyond 5 hashtags. Large hashtag lists are a spam signal and can restrict distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Weekly Posting Schedule">
    <list>
      <item>Monday: Educational tip — Reel</item>
      <item>Tuesday: Behind the scenes — Story + Reel</item>
      <item>Wednesday: Trend or entertainment — Reel</item>
      <item>Thursday: Value or tutorial — Reel + Carousel</item>
      <item>Friday: Engagement or fun — Reel + Story</item>
      <item>Saturday: User content or testimonial — Reel</item>
      <item>Sunday: Inspirational or story — Reel</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Post Stories daily. Use polls and question boxes daily rather than passive image stories — these are the highest-engagement Story formats.</statement>
      <rationale>Story polls and question boxes drive replies and DMs, which are the highest-value signals for relationship-building and conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="DM Trigger Funnel">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use DM trigger campaigns ("DM me 'GUIDE' to get...") instead of link-in-bio for lead magnets. DM triggers convert 3-5x better than link-in-bio clicks.</statement>
      <rationale>A DM trigger starts a direct conversation with the lead. Link-in-bio sends traffic to a cold page with no relationship context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Caption: "I built a 30-day content system that doubled my engagement. DM me 'SYSTEM' and I'll send it to you." This creates a warm DM conversation vs. a cold landing page visit.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using ManyChat or non-partner DM automation tools to send bulk automated replies.</description>
      <reason>Non-partner DM automation is against Instagram ToS and risks account suspension. Use only Meta-approved partner tools like ManyChat for keyword triggers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/reel-script-batch.txt">Agent prompt to generate 7 Reel scripts per week covering all content types</reference>
  </section>
</text>
