<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="instagram-growth Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for instagram-growth as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using ManyChat or non-partner DM automation tools to send bulk automated replies.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Non-partner DM automation is against Instagram ToS and risks account suspension. Use only Meta-approved partner tools like ManyChat for keyword triggers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Only posting photos instead of Reels.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Photos reach only existing followers. Reels reach Explore audiences. Without Reels, organic growth stalls.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Inconsistent posting cadence — missing days or weeks.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Instagram's algorithm penalizes accounts with erratic posting patterns by reducing distribution. Batch-film content to maintain consistency.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Over-edited, heavily filtered content.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Raw, authentic content currently outperforms polished production on Instagram. Audience trust comes from authenticity, not production value.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>No face on camera for personal brand accounts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Accounts showing a real person consistently achieve higher engagement than faceless brand accounts in the same niche.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Not checking DMs twice daily.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>DM conversations are the highest-conversion touchpoint on Instagram. Delayed responses lose leads that were ready to buy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
