<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="roadmap-design">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Five-step process for strategic roadmaps: format selection, themes linked to objectives, confidence levels, audience rendering. Core rule: every initiative links to objective ID.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
      <tag>strategy</tag>
      <tag>product-planning</tag>
      <tag>now-next-later</tag>
      <tag>communication</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Roadmap Design</title>

    <summary>A five-step process for building a product roadmap as a strategic communication tool, not a delivery schedule. Covers four roadmap formats (timeline, Now-Next-Later, outcome-based, kanban) with a selection matrix, theme-based organisation, confidence levels, and audience-specific rendering (internal vs external). The core rule: every initiative links to one objective ID; orphaned initiatives are strategy leakage.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Roadmaps that list features with dates always slip and erode trust. The format mismatch is the root cause: a timeline roadmap implies commitment; a Now-Next-Later roadmap signals intent. Choosing the wrong format for the audience turns every missed date into a broken promise. The theme-plus-objective structure prevents the roadmap from degenerating into a backlog; confidence levels prevent "Later" from becoming a graveyard.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Communicating a 1-4 quarter plan to internal team, investors, or customers.</item>
        <item>Multiple stakeholders need a single source of truth linking strategy → themes → initiatives.</item>
        <item>Choosing between roadmap formats — use the selection matrix.</item>
        <item>Onboarding a new contractor or PM who needs a one-page direction document.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Less than 4 weeks of work — roadmap overhead exceeds value; use a sprint plan or release notes.</item>
        <item>Pure exploration phase before PMF — explicit roadmaps create anchors that bias discovery.</item>
        <item>Highly volatile environments (hackathon, week-by-week pivots) — keep a backlog.</item>
        <item>Feature commitment to a single customer — that is a contract, not a roadmap.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="four-roadmap-types">
      <p>Four roadmap types exist, each suited to different contexts. The selection matrix based on uncertainty level and external-sharing requirements determines which to use.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Timeline roadmap: date-based, quarters or months, committed work. Use when: external sharing required with committed deliverables, low uncertainty, high team maturity.</item>
        <item>Now-Next-Later roadmap: priority sequence, no dates. Use when: internal or limited external sharing, medium uncertainty, any team maturity.</item>
        <item>Outcome-based roadmap: metric targets per theme. Use when: strategic alignment focus, high uncertainty, external sharing acceptable at theme level.</item>
        <item>Kanban roadmap: live work state. Use when: internal teams only, pure execution visibility, no strategic communication needed.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Choose the format by uncertainty level first, then external-sharing requirement. High uncertainty + external sharing = outcome-based or Now-Next-Later (themes only). Low uncertainty + external sharing = timeline.</statement>
        <rationale>Format mismatch is the root cause of roadmap trust failures. A timeline roadmap in a high-uncertainty context creates commitments that cannot be kept, destroying stakeholder trust on every slip.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Format selection matrix">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Uncertainty high: outcome-based or Now-Next-Later
Uncertainty medium: Now-Next-Later
Uncertainty low: timeline or Kanban
External sharing required: timeline (committed) or outcome/Now-Next-Later (theme level only)
Internal only: any format
        ]]></code>
        <note>The matrix overrides personal preference or stakeholder bias. Let uncertainty and sharing requirement drive the decision.</note>
      </example>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For a solo founder, the roadmap must fit on one screen. If it does not, it is a backlog with a roadmap header, not a roadmap.</statement>
        <rationale>A roadmap communicates strategic direction. Anything requiring scrolling has too much detail for strategic communication and too little for task execution.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-design-process">
      <p>The roadmap design process consists of five sequential steps: strategy input, format selection, theme definition, horizon population with confidence, and stakeholder context. Each step depends on the previous one.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Step 1 — Gather four inputs before touching the roadmap format: company/product vision, business goals for the period, user research insights, and technical constraints. Output: clear objectives for the roadmap period.</statement>
        <rationale>A roadmap without strategy inputs is a backlog sorted by recency. The objectives from this step are the connective tissue between every initiative and the business direction.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Step 2 — Use the selection matrix as a deterministic first step. Do not let the audience or personal preference drive the format choice — let uncertainty level and external-sharing requirement drive it.</statement>
        <rationale>Format chosen by audience preference produces a timeline roadmap for high-uncertainty work because stakeholders always want dates. The matrix overrides this bias.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Step 3 — Group all planned work into 3–5 themes. For each theme write: name, which objective it drives, why it is prioritised now, and 2–3 example initiatives. No theme should be orphaned from an objective.</statement>
        <rationale>Themes without objectives are backlog categories, not strategic groupings. The objective link is what prevents "Later" from becoming a permanent graveyard of low-priority features.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Step 4 — Assign each initiative a confidence level: High (committed and scoped), Medium (planned, needs scoping), Low (exploring, tentative). At least 30% of items must be Medium or Low — if everything is High, the labelling is decoration.</statement>
        <rationale>Uniform High confidence strips the signal from Now-Next-Later. Stakeholders learn to ignore confidence levels that are never Low, and the roadmap loses its communication function.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Limit Now to 5 initiatives maximum. Past 5, the team is effectively planning a backlog sprint, not a strategic now-horizon.</statement>
        <rationale>Teams can execute 3–5 significant initiatives in parallel before coordination costs outweigh benefits. More than 5 in Now signals that priorities have not been made.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Step 5 — For each horizon, document: why you chose these initiatives, what you are NOT doing and why, dependencies and risks, and how success will be measured. The "not doing" section is mandatory — it stops scope creep better than any priority list.</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit exclusions, every reasonable idea becomes a candidate for this quarter. The not-doing list also creates a retrospective record of scope decisions, which is invaluable for explaining past trade-offs.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="maintenance-and-publishing">
      <p>A roadmap is a living document. Maintenance rules and audience-specific publishing rules keep it coherent and trustworthy over time.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every initiative must link to one objective ID. Initiatives without an objective link are strategy leakage — remove them or create the missing objective.</statement>
        <rationale>Orphaned initiatives represent work that is in the plan without strategic justification. They accumulate over time and eventually dominate the roadmap without anyone being able to explain why.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Update cadence: monthly review of the initiative list, quarterly rewrite of the full document. Never rewrite the whole doc each sprint — that destroys the historical diff signal.</statement>
        <rationale>Quarter-to-quarter diffs are the primary retrospective artefact. Frequent complete rewrites make it impossible to see how the plan evolved or why certain items moved.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always include an "Explicitly Not Doing" section with reasons. It doubles as a future review log for stakeholder questions like "why didn't we build X?"</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders re-request excluded items constantly. A documented reason closes each request with a reference instead of reopening the debate.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Maintain two artefacts: internal roadmap (full detail: outcomes, owners, confidence, metrics) and external roadmap (themes and benefits only, no confidence levels, no owners, no metric targets). Sync via script, not copy-paste.</statement>
        <rationale>Sharing confidence levels externally signals uncertainty in a way that customers interpret as incompetence. Sharing metric targets creates contractual expectations. Sharing owners exposes internal structure.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Never let an agent ship the external roadmap without human review. Review for commitments, NDAs, and competitive signalling — LLMs cannot assess business risk context.</statement>
        <rationale>External roadmaps are marketing documents with legal and competitive implications. An LLM cannot assess NDA scope, competitive sensitivity, or contractual interpretation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="examples-and-antipatterns">
      <p>Real examples from B2B SaaS and solo products show how roadmaps balance depth and simplicity. Antipatterns highlight common failures.</p>

      <example type="good" title="B2B SaaS roadmap">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Now (Q1): onboarding improvements (reduce time to value), API v2 launch (enterprise requirement), performance optimization (load times). Each tied to objective: "Improve activation rate to 40%".

Next (Q2): team collaboration features (confidence: High), Slack integration (confidence: Medium), advanced permissions (confidence: Medium). Depends on: API v2 stable.

Later: mobile app (pending user research validation), AI-powered insights (exploring, no commitment).

Explicitly Not Doing: custom themes, white-labelling — not on enterprise ICP roadmap this year.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Each initiative has confidence and objective. Next has mixed confidence (not all High). Explicit not-doing section present.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Solo product roadmap">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Now: core feature polish toward MVP, payment integration, basic analytics.

Next: email automation, template library, referral program.

Later: mobile app, team features, marketplace.

Not doing: multi-language support — insufficient international user demand to justify.
        ]]></code>
        <note>Fits one screen. Minimal theme structure. Not-doing has a reason.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Feature list with specific dates for every item.</description>
        <reason>Dates imply commitment. When any date slips, stakeholder trust erodes. Use confidence levels instead of dates for everything beyond "Now".</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No strategic connection — initiatives not linked to objectives.</description>
        <reason>Orphaned initiatives accumulate and eventually dominate the roadmap without anyone being able to justify why. Every initiative must have an objective ID.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>"Later" column becoming a permanent graveyard.</description>
        <reason>If items never graduate from Later to Next, stakeholders stop believing the roadmap is real. Review Later quarterly and either promote, archive, or move to not-doing with a reason.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Same roadmap shared with engineering, exec, and customers.</description>
        <reason>Each audience needs a different abstraction level. Engineering needs initiative detail; exec needs theme-level strategy; customers need benefit language with no internal jargon.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-constraints">
      <p>When using AI agents to generate or refine roadmaps, explicit constraints override default LLM behavior.</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>When prompting an LLM for roadmap generation: force confidence distribution (now=mostly High, next=mostly Medium, later=mostly Low), cap themes at 3–5, cap Now initiatives at 5, mark not_doing as a required field.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to "everything is High confidence", produce 8+ themes, and silently drop the not-doing column because it produces no generative content. Explicit constraints in the prompt override these defaults.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>When the LLM is fed a previous quarter's roadmap as context, explicitly instruct it to identify what changed since the last review — otherwise it will simply restate the prior roadmap.</statement>
        <rationale>Models are trained to be helpful, which defaults to continuity. Without explicit change-detection instructions, the agent produces a cosmetically different version of the same document.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/now-next-later.md" purpose="Now-Next-Later roadmap with vision, themed initiative slots, confidence levels, dependencies, success metrics."/>
      <template path="templates/quarterly-outcome.md" purpose="Quarterly outcome roadmap with objectives, initiatives by theme, explicit not-doing, risks, review schedule."/>
      <template path="templates/external-roadmap.md" purpose="Customer-facing roadmap: benefits language, no confidence levels or owners, subject-to-change disclaimer."/>
      <template path="templates/lint-roadmap.py" purpose="Python validator: checks required keys, Now initiative count, not_doing presence, confidence and objective_id per initiative."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog"/>
      <link href="https://www.productplan.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.mindtheproduct.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
