<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-status-reporting" title="Status Reporting: RAG Policy, Action Items, Antipatterns">
  <summary>Rules for producing honest, metric-grounded status reports and extracting actionable meeting outputs.</summary>

  <section title="RAG Headline Policy">
    <rule>
      <statement>The status headline must reflect the worst single metric, not the average. If schedule is RED and cost is GREEN, overall status is RED.</statement>
      <rationale>Averaging metrics hides the failing dimension. Sponsors need to know the worst, not the mean — they will discover it themselves and the trust damage is compounded by the delay.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Status reports must cite metric values or commit/issue IDs as evidence. Reject "good progress, all on track" without quantitative support.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and human PMs both default to optimism. Grounding on metrics or artefact IDs is the only defence against false green status.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Send status reports on a fixed day and time every week. Predictability makes the ritual; irregular cadence erodes trust.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders who cannot predict when the next report arrives start asking for ad-hoc updates, which costs more than the regular report.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Meeting Output">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every meeting must produce a decisions log and an action-item list. Action items must have: text, owner, and due date — or they are not action items.</statement>
      <rationale>Action items without owner and due date pile up as orphans. The list becomes a backlog no one owns and nothing gets done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document decision rationale, not just the decision. "We chose Y because Z given trade-off with X" is a decision record. "We chose Y" is not.</statement>
      <rationale>Decisions without rationale get re-litigated when context changes. Preserved dissent and trade-off reasoning prevent re-opening settled questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/action-extractor.py">Extracts action items with owner and due date from markdown meeting notes</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Status report with no risks listed when the risk register is non-empty.</description>
      <reason>Empty risk section signals either the PM is not monitoring or is suppressing bad news. Require at least the top-3 risks by impact.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Status reports sent at "9 AM" without timezone, distributed across multiple timezones.</description>
      <reason>Recipients in different timezones receive conflicting effective send times; pin UTC plus local timezone in all scheduled communications.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Escalation contact not reachable; no backup defined.</description>
      <reason>Escalation paths fail precisely when the primary is on leave or in a different incident. Always define primary + backup + out-of-office fallback.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
