<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="content-audit">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Systematically review all content on a website or application by cataloging what exists, evaluating quality against defined criteria (accuracy, relevance, quality on 1-5 scale), and deciding Keep / Update / Rewrite / Remove per item.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>content-strategy</tag>
      <tag>audit</tag>
      <tag>inventory</tag>
      <tag>seo</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Content Audit</title>

    <summary>A content audit is a systematic review of all content on a website or application — cataloging what exists, evaluating quality (accuracy, relevance, quality on a 1-5 scale), and deciding Keep / Update / Rewrite / Remove per item. Average score >= 4.0 → Keep; 3.0-3.9 → Update; 2.0-2.9 → Rewrite; < 2.0 → Remove.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a content inventory, redesigns and migrations operate blind. Duplicate and outdated content degrades credibility and SEO. Structured audits with defined scoring criteria replace subjective "this feels old" judgments with actionable, defensible decisions that content owners can act on.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before a website redesign — establish full inventory before structural changes</item>
        <item>Before a CMS migration — map old URLs to keep/redirect/remove decisions</item>
        <item>SEO improvement sprints — combine crawl data with analytics to prune low-value pages</item>
        <item>Rolling content governance — quarterly review of core pages, bi-annual for blog</item>
        <item>Scoring content quality at scale when 50+ pages need evaluation</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>New sites with under 50 pages — a spreadsheet and manual review is faster</item>
        <item>When the primary goal is IA redesign — audit catalogs content, not structure (use card sorting)</item>
        <item>Highly regulated content (medical, legal) where agent quality judgments must not replace subject-matter expert review</item>
        <item>When analytics access is unavailable — remove/keep decisions without traffic data produce low-value output</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="audit-types-scoring">
      <p>Quantitative audit — inventory what exists; count and categorize.</p>
      <p>Qualitative audit — evaluate quality against defined criteria.</p>
      <p>Comparative audit — check consistency across content items.</p>
      <p>ROI-focused audit — measure performance using analytics data.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always cross-reference remove/archive decisions with inbound link data before deletion.</statement>
        <rationale>A low-traffic page with high inbound links should be redirected, not deleted; removing it breaks third-party links and harms SEO.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scoring-criteria">
      <p>Apply a 1-5 scale to three dimensions:</p>
      <p>Accuracy: 5 = verified recently; 4 = accurate, minor updates needed; 3 = some outdated info; 2 = significant inaccuracies; 1 = largely incorrect.</p>
      <p>Relevance: 5 = core to user needs; 4 = useful to many users; 3 = useful to some; 2 = limited audience; 1 = no longer relevant.</p>
      <p>Quality: 5 = excellent, clear, complete; 4 = good, minor issues; 3 = acceptable; 2 = poor or incomplete; 1 = very poor.</p>
      <p>Action thresholds by average score: >= 4.0 → Keep; 3.0-3.9 → Update; 2.0-2.9 → Rewrite/consolidate; < 2.0 → Remove/archive.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define evaluation criteria explicitly before scoring begins; do not score against implicit criteria.</statement>
        <rationale>Subjective quality judgments without written criteria produce inconsistent scores across auditors and audit passes.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="audit-frequency">
      <p>Frequency recommendations by content type:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Core pages — quarterly</item>
        <item>Blog and news — bi-annually</item>
        <item>Help and support — quarterly</item>
        <item>Product pages — after major releases</item>
        <item>Legal and policy — annually</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="governance-workflow">
      <p>New content workflow: Draft → Review → Approve → Publish → schedule review date → track performance → update or archive.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assign a human owner to each "Update" action item before the audit is considered complete.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent recommendations without human ownership stall; unowned tasks do not get done.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Store the audit in a versioned spreadsheet; keep it for at least one full content cycle.</statement>
        <rationale>Version history enables tracking governance effectiveness and provides baseline for the next audit pass.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-scoring-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require the agent to declare confidence level per row when it has only URL/title and no body content.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent may confidently score pages based on insufficient information; explicit confidence flags prevent false precision in low-data rows.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Flag agent accuracy scores on specialized content (technical, medical, legal) for human expert review.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent accuracy judgments on specialized topics are unreliable without domain context; these categories require subject-matter expertise.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Batch large sites into topical groups and audit each group with domain-appropriate criteria.</statement>
        <rationale>Context window limits mean approximately 200-400 page rows per call; consistent criteria across batches requires the same prompt for each group.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="redirect-and-deletion">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Generate a redirect mapping before any deletion; "Remove" recommendations must include redirect destination.</statement>
        <rationale>Removing pages without redirects breaks inbound links and search rankings; agent should output redirect pairs, not just removal decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Final Keep/Remove decisions must be approved by a content owner or PM, not executed automatically.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated content deletion without human sign-off carries irreversible SEO and user-trust risk; agent output is advisory.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Incomplete inventory — missing PDFs, gated content, JavaScript-rendered pages.</description>
        <reason>An audit of 70% of content produces decisions that may conflict with unreviewed items; the inventory must be complete before scoring begins.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>One-time audit without ongoing governance.</description>
        <reason>Content decays continuously; a single audit snapshot becomes stale within months without a review schedule and owner assignments.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>All-or-nothing approach — auditing the entire site before taking any action.</description>
        <reason>Large audits stall on completion anxiety; start with priority areas (core pages, high-traffic content) to generate early wins.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A Claude subagent receives a CSV/TSV export from Screaming Frog (or similar crawler) containing URL, title, word count, status code, and last-modified date. It applies the evaluation criteria framework (accuracy/relevance/quality 1-5 scale) to each page based on title and any available meta content, then outputs a scored spreadsheet with Keep/Update/Remove/Archive actions. A second pass cross-references against Google Analytics pageview data (exported CSV) to validate decisions against actual usage.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Export the crawl before starting any redesign or structural changes — the audit is a snapshot, not a live view</item>
        <item>Define evaluation criteria explicitly before scoring; let the agent score against written criteria, not implicit ones</item>
        <item>Batch large sites into topical groups (blog, product, help) and audit each group with domain-appropriate criteria</item>
        <item>Always cross-reference remove/archive decisions with inbound link data — a low-traffic page with high inbound links should be redirected, not deleted</item>
        <item>Document the audit in a versioned spreadsheet; keep it for at least one full content cycle to track governance effectiveness</item>
        <item>Assign a human owner to each "Update" action item — agent recommendations without human ownership stall</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/audit-spreadsheet.md" purpose="Column definitions for the full content audit spreadsheet"/>
      <template path="templates/evaluation-criteria.md" purpose="Scoring guide (1-5) for accuracy, relevance, quality + action thresholds"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/content-audits/"/>
      <link href="https://moz.com/blog/content-audit"/>
      <link href="https://www.semrush.com/blog/content-audit/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
