<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="ml-engineering" count="195">
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/agentic-rag">
    <summary>Agentic RAG embeds autonomous agents into the retrieval pipeline to enable multi-hop retrieval, query routing, self-correction, and iterative refinement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-iterative-retrieval" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/agentic-rag-iterative-retrieval">
    <summary>Traditional RAG performs a single retrieval pass with a fixed pipeline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-query-decomposition" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/agentic-rag-query-decomposition">
    <summary>A planning agent decomposes a complex query into 2–4 atomic sub-queries that can each be answered with a single retrieval call.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-self-correction" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/agentic-rag-self-correction">
    <summary>A self-correcting RAG pipeline generates an answer, then runs a faithfulness verifier that checks each claim against the retrieved source chunks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-tool-using" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/agentic-rag-tool-using">
    <summary>Instead of always calling the vector store, a tool-using agentic RAG lets the LLM select from a registry of retrieval tools on each step: vector_search (semantic), keyword_search (exact match), sql_query (structured data), web_search (external).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-framework-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/agents-framework-selection">
    <summary>The 2025-2026 Python agent ecosystem has consolidated around six frameworks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-memory-system" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/agents-memory-system">
    <summary>Autonomous agents running long tasks overflow their context window without explicit memory management.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-production-deployment" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/agents-production-deployment">
    <summary>Production autonomous agents require five production-grade components beyond the core loop: (1) a typed tool base class with a shared registry, (2) YAML configuration with env-var substitution, (3) structured JSON logging for every LLM and tool call, (4) exponential backoff retry with circuit breaker for external services, (5) a repeatable evaluation harness that measures success rate, latency, iterations, and token cost.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-react-pattern" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/agents-react-pattern">
    <summary>ReAct (Reason + Act) is the canonical single-agent loop: the LLM thinks, calls a tool, observes the result, and repeats until the task is done or an iteration cap is hit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-safety-guardrails" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/agents-safety-guardrails">
    <summary>Autonomous agents require five categories of guardrail before production deployment: execution safety (iteration limits, timeouts), content safety (input validation, PII handling), financial safety (cost caps, rate limiting), action safety (sandboxed execution, blocked patterns), and human-in-loop gates for irreversible actions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-agent-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ai-agent-patterns">
    <summary>Six structured patterns for building agentic AI systems: ReAct (Thought-Action-Observation loop), Chain-of-Thought, Tool Use, Plan-Execute, Reflection, and Tree-of-Thoughts — plus multi-agent coordination topologies (Sequential, Parallel, Supervisor, Hierarchical).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-call-site-inventory" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ai/ml-engineer/ai-call-site-inventory">
    <summary>Prompt-engineering pattern for ai call site inventory — reusable prompt skeleton, parameter slots, and validation pass keyed to a concrete deliverable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-cost-attribution-schema" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/ai-cost-attribution-schema">
    <summary>Reusable template for ai cost attribution schema that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-failure-mode-taxonomy" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/ai-failure-mode-taxonomy">
    <summary>Shared vocabulary and decision tree for ai failure mode taxonomy — assigns every observed instance to one labelled class so postmortems and dashboards aggregate cleanly.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-build-buy-finetune-decision" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ai/ml-engineer/ai-feature-build-buy-finetune-decision">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for ai feature build buy finetune decision that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-ga-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ai/ml-engineer/ai-feature-ga-checklist">
    <summary>Concrete operating checklist covering ai feature ga checklist — the small set of items a practitioner runs every cycle so nothing high-leverage gets skipped.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-progressive-rollout" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ai/ml-engineer/ai-feature-progressive-rollout">
    <summary>Evaluation method for ai feature progressive rollout that defines test set, scoring function, pass/fail thresholds, and regression rules so quality is comparable across runs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feedback-triage-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ai/ml-engineer/ai-feedback-triage-protocol">
    <summary>End-to-end playbook for ai feedback triage protocol that walks an operator from trigger to closed outcome with named artefacts at each step.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-governance-compliance" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ai-governance-compliance">
    <summary>Comprehensive framework for AI governance, model risk management, and regulatory compliance in MLOps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-incident-triage-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ai/ml-engineer/ai-incident-triage-matrix">
    <summary>Numeric scoring rubric for ai incident triage matrix that converts qualitative judgment into a comparable 0-100 (or 1-5 weighted) signal usable across cohorts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-option-cost-grid-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/ai-option-cost-grid-template">
    <summary>Reusable template for ai option cost grid template that codifies the structure, named fields, and decision points so each new instance ships in minutes instead of being re-invented.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chain-of-thought" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/chain-of-thought">
    <summary>CoT prompting elicits intermediate reasoning steps before final answers, improving accuracy on multi-step problems by up to 18% (GSM8K) or 70% (with Tree-of-Thoughts).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/chunking-basics">
    <summary>Chunking is the process of splitting documents into smaller pieces for embedding and retrieval.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-code-ast" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/chunking-code-ast">
    <summary>CodeChunker splits Python source via the `ast` module at FunctionDef, AsyncFunctionDef, and ClassDef boundaries, emitting chunks with name, type, docstring, and line range.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-document-structure" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/chunking-document-structure">
    <summary>MarkdownChunker splits documents at header boundaries while propagating parent headers into child chunks as a header_path.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-production-service" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/chunking-production-service">
    <summary>ChunkingService is a production-grade orchestration layer over SemanticChunker, MarkdownChunker, CodeChunker, and the basics-tier RecursiveChunker.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-semantic" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/chunking-semantic">
    <summary>SemanticChunker splits text by computing embeddings for every sentence, then placing chunk boundaries where cosine similarity between adjacent sentences drops below a threshold.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-strategies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/chunking-strategies">
    <summary>Chunking splits documents into semantically meaningful pieces for embedding and retrieval.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-advanced-features" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/claude-advanced-features">
    <summary>Extended Thinking exposes the model's reasoning chain for complex problems.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/claude-api">
    <summary>Production guide for calling Anthropic's Claude API directly via the Python and TypeScript SDKs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-api-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/claude-api-basics">
    <summary>The single most important rule: pin model IDs with full date strings (e.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-api-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/claude-api-integration">
    <summary>Full Claude API integration patterns with client initialization, sync/async completions, streaming, tool use, vision (URL and base64), Extended Thinking for complex reasoning, Prompt Caching for cost reduction, and the Batch API for offline jobs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-best-practices" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/claude-best-practices">
    <summary>A set of production patterns for calling the Anthropic Messages API reliably and cost-efficiently: model tier selection (Haiku/Sonnet/Opus by task), prompt caching for repeated large contexts, Batch API for offline workloads, token counting for pre-flight validation, exponential backoff for rate limits, and a monitored client wrapper for cost attribution per subagent role.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-messages-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/claude-messages-api">
    <summary>The Claude Messages API is the single completion endpoint for all Claude calls.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-tool-use" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/claude-tool-use">
    <summary>Patterns for Claude's tool use (function calling): defining tools with JSON Schema `input_schema`, detecting `stop_reason == "tool_use"`, running the canonical agentic loop, forcing structured JSON output via `tool_choice`, and building custom MCP servers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-optimization" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/cost-optimization">
    <summary>LLM costs can be reduced 60-90% through model routing (50-75% savings), prompt caching (80-90% on repeated system prompts), response caching (70-95% for deterministic queries), token reduction (20-40%), and Batch API (50% discount on async workloads).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-reduction-strategies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/cost-reduction-strategies">
    <summary>Production LLM cost optimization through four orthogonal techniques: response caching (SHA-256 content hash key, Redis or in-memory TTL), prompt compression (whitespace normalization, redundant phrase removal), async batching, and model routing (default cheap model with fallback).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cot-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/cot-basics">
    <summary>Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting instructs an LLM to emit intermediate reasoning steps before producing a final answer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cot-techniques" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/cot-techniques">
    <summary>Advanced reasoning patterns beyond zero-shot CoT: Tree of Thoughts (ToT) for branching decisions, Least-to-Most for sequential sub-dependencies, and Self-Consistency for high-stakes answers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-chroma" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/db-chroma">
    <summary>Chroma removes all infrastructure friction for RAG prototyping: one Python import, one directory, zero Docker.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-comparison" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/db-comparison">
    <summary>Comparison of popular vector databases and selection guide for RAG systems.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-qdrant" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/db-qdrant">
    <summary>Qdrant outperforms Pinecone at production scale for self-hosted workloads (41 QPS @ 50M vectors) and exposes HNSW tuning knobs unavailable in Chroma.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-weaviate" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/db-weaviate">
    <summary>Vector database with knowledge graph capabilities and hybrid search.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/decision-framework">
    <summary>A structured decision process for selecting the right AI approach (prompt engineering, RAG, fine-tuning) and the right model tier for a given task.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-applications" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/embedding-applications">
    <summary>Benchmarking, vector database integration, and production usage patterns for embedding models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-caching" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/embedding-caching">
    <summary>Embedding the same text twice wastes API cost and latency.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-chunking-strategies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/embedding-chunking-strategies">
    <summary>Embedding models have token limits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-cost-optimization" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/embedding-cost-optimization">
    <summary>Five levers reduce embedding API cost without sacrificing retrieval quality: dimension reduction, batch API requests, aggressive caching, two-stage retrieval using a cheap filter model, and deduplication before ingestion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-generation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/embedding-generation">
    <summary>Embeddings are dense vector representations of text that capture semantic meaning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-generation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/embedding-generation">
    <summary>Converts text chunks into dense vectors using an embedding model so they can be stored in a vector database and retrieved by semantic similarity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-model-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/embedding-model-selection">
    <summary>Text embeddings are numerical vector representations of text that capture semantic meaning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-models" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/embedding-models">
    <summary>Different models trade off quality, cost, context length, and language coverage.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-batch-and-cache" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/embeddings-batch-and-cache">
    <summary>Two complementary optimizations for embedding pipelines: batching reduces API call overhead by up to 10x, and caching eliminates repeated computation (80% cache hit rate = 80% cost savings).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/embeddings-evaluation">
    <summary>MTEB scores are general benchmarks — always benchmark on your specific data.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-model-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/embeddings-model-selection">
    <summary>Choose an embedding model by matching use case (RAG, search, clustering, classification), constraints (budget, latency, privacy, language), and provider capabilities (Matryoshka dimensions, quantization, asymmetric input types).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-production-ops" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/embeddings-production-ops">
    <summary>Running embedding systems in production requires attention to latency SLOs, rate limit handling, cost tracking, fault tolerance, and model migration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-provider-apis" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/embeddings-provider-apis">
    <summary>Production-ready integration patterns for the four main embedding provider categories: OpenAI (symmetric, Matryoshka dims), Voyage AI (asymmetric, quantization), Cohere (multimodal, input types, multilingual), and local sentence-transformers (GPU, BGE-M3 dense+sparse).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="eu-ai-act-compliance" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/eu-ai-act-compliance">
    <summary>The EU AI Act imposes fines up to EUR 35M or 7% of global turnover for non-compliance.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="evaluation-benchmarks" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/evaluation-benchmarks">
    <summary>Multi-model comparison and continuous production monitoring methodology.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="evaluation-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/evaluation-framework">
    <summary>Python evaluation harness for LLM outputs combining offline batch testing (ModelEvaluator) with LLM-as-judge scoring (LLMJudge) and production sampling (ProductionEvaluator).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="evaluation-metrics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/evaluation-metrics">
    <summary>Metrics for measuring LLM performance across different dimensions including accuracy, quality, latency, cost, safety, and reliability.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-lora" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/fine-tuning-lora">
    <summary>Parameter-efficient fine-tuning of LLMs using LoRA (Low-Rank Adaptation) and its variants (QLoRA, DoRA, rsLoRA).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-lora" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/fine-tuning-lora">
    <summary>LoRA (Low-Rank Adaptation) fine-tuning methodology using PEFT + TRL: freezing base model weights and injecting small trainable matrices (rank 8-64) into attention layers, reducing trainable parameters by 100-250x.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/fine-tuning-openai-basics">
    <summary>Data preparation methodology for OpenAI fine-tuning: creating JSONL training examples in the chat messages format, validating structure and token counts with tiktoken, and generating additional examples with GPT-4.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-data-prep" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/fine-tuning-openai-data-prep">
    <summary>High-quality training data is the primary determinant of fine-tuning success.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-deployment" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/fine-tuning-openai-deployment">
    <summary>Deploying a fine-tuned OpenAI model to production requires: a production pipeline with logging and error handling, gradual rollout (10% → 50% → 100%), inference cost monitoring, model ID management in version control, and agent-specific patterns for asynchronous polling and event parsing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-dpo" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/fine-tuning-openai-dpo">
    <summary>Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) trains OpenAI models on preference pairs — a preferred response and a non-preferred response for the same input — to align model behavior to subjective criteria like tone, style, safety, or brand voice.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-eval" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/fine-tuning-openai-eval">
    <summary>Before routing production traffic to a fine-tuned model, evaluate it against the base model on a held-out test set using automated LLM-as-judge scoring and A/B comparison.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-production" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/fine-tuning-openai-production">
    <summary>Full OpenAI fine-tuning production pipeline: file upload, job creation with hyperparameter control, status polling, LLM-as-judge evaluation against a held-out test set, and model ID registry management.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-sft" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/fine-tuning-openai-sft">
    <summary>Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) customizes OpenAI GPT-4.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finetuning" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/finetuning">
    <summary>A general guide to fine-tuning LLMs covering the decision framework (prompt → RAG → fine-tune), technique selection (Full FT, LoRA, QLoRA, DoRA, OpenAI API), and framework comparison (Unsloth, LLaMA-Factory, Axolotl, TRL, Torchtune).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finetuning-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/finetuning-basics">
    <summary>Comprehensive reference for open-model fine-tuning techniques (LoRA, QLoRA, DoRA, full fine-tuning) and training frameworks (LLaMA-Factory, Unsloth, Axolotl, TRL).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finetuning-datasets" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/finetuning-datasets">
    <summary>Dataset lifecycle methodology for open-model fine-tuning: cleaning and deduplication, format conversion (Alpaca/ShareGPT/OpenAI JSONL), training hyperparameter selection, evaluation with LM Evaluation Harness benchmarks, and deployment to Ollama (GGUF), vLLM, or TGI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="function-calling-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/function-calling-patterns">
    <summary>Production patterns for LLM tool use: parallel execution of independent tool calls, a tool router that dispatches queries to the correct tool subset, an agentic loop with bounded iteration count, and argument validation before execution.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/gemini-api">
    <summary>Google Gemini API for multimodal AI applications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-api-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/gemini-api-integration">
    <summary>Google's Gemini API provides access to multimodal AI models capable of understanding text, images, audio, and video.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/gemini-basics">
    <summary>Core concepts, setup, text generation, streaming, and chat conversations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-function-calling" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/gemini-function-calling">
    <summary>Gemini function calling lets Python functions serve as LLM tools by using their docstrings and type hints as the tool schema.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-multimodal" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/gemini-multimodal">
    <summary>Gemini is the only frontier model with native video understanding (no frame extraction), native audio processing (no separate Whisper call), and a 2M-token context window.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="golden-set-curation-and-maintenance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ai/ml-engineer/golden-set-curation-and-maintenance">
    <summary>Generic methodology for curating 50-200 hand-labelled I/O pairs for any AI feature, plus a discipline for growing the set from production incidents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/graph-rag">
    <summary>GraphRAG combines knowledge graph construction with vector retrieval to answer multi-hop and global questions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag-indexing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/graph-rag-indexing">
    <summary>Standard vector RAG retrieves chunks by semantic similarity and fails on global questions, entity relationships, and multi-hop reasoning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag-production" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/graph-rag-production">
    <summary>Moving Graph RAG to production requires selecting the right graph database backend (Neo4j for scale, FalkorDB for speed, Kuzu for embedded), deciding between LlamaIndex KnowledgeGraphIndex and Microsoft graphrag CLI, managing indexing costs ($4-20/million tokens), and handling the known failure modes that affect agents operating on live graph indexes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag-retrieval" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/graph-rag-retrieval">
    <summary>After the knowledge graph is built, retrieval requires classifying each query into one of four types (GLOBAL, ENTITY, RELATIONSHIP, LOCAL) and routing it to the appropriate retrieval strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-ai-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/guardrails-ai-framework">
    <summary>Guardrails AI is best for output validation, structured data extraction, and schema enforcement.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/guardrails-basics">
    <summary>LLM applications face prompt injection, PII leakage, harmful content generation, and topic drift.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-concepts" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/guardrails-concepts">
    <summary>Guardrails (or "rails") are specific mechanisms for controlling LLM behavior.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-custom-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/guardrails-custom-pipeline">
    <summary>Custom guardrail implementation gives maximum control and minimum dependency footprint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/guardrails-implementation">
    <summary>Public-facing LLM applications receive adversarial input and must not relay toxic, hallucinated, or PII-laden content downstream.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-nemo" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/guardrails-nemo">
    <summary>NeMo Guardrails (NVIDIA) is best for complex conversational flows and multi-turn dialogs in enterprise deployments.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-testing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/guardrails-testing">
    <summary>Guardrail testing requires three distinct test suites: security tests (injection payloads that must be blocked), accuracy tests (legitimate content that must pass), and performance tests (latency and throughput under load).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-search" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/hybrid-search">
    <summary>Hybrid search combines BM25 (sparse/keyword) and vector (dense/semantic) retrieval to maximize precision and recall.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-search-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/hybrid-search-basics">
    <summary>Hybrid search combines dense vector search (semantic similarity) with sparse lexical search (BM25/keyword) and fuses the ranked results using Reciprocal Rank Fusion (RRF) or weighted linear combination.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-search-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/hybrid-search-implementation">
    <summary>Combines dense vector retrieval (semantic similarity) with sparse BM25 keyword retrieval, then fuses results using Reciprocal Rank Fusion (RRF) or linear alpha-weighted combination.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="image-generation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/image-generation">
    <summary>AI image generation from text prompts using DALL-E 3, Flux (Black Forest Labs), Stable Diffusion, and related APIs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="img-gen-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/img-gen-basics">
    <summary>DALL-E 3 is the gold standard for photorealistic image generation but has a 5 images/minute rate limit, rewrites prompts silently, and returns URLs that expire in ~1 hour.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="img-gen-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/img-gen-tools">
    <summary>Production image generation service covering DALL-E 3, Flux, and SDXL with caching, retry, and multi-provider fallback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="langchain" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/langchain">
    <summary>LangChain (LCEL pipe syntax) and LangGraph (state machine framework) for building production AI chains and agents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llamaindex" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/llamaindex">
    <summary>LlamaIndex solves the document retrieval problem that raw LLM APIs do not: loading heterogeneous document sources, chunking them optimally, indexing into a vector store, and synthesizing answers with source citations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-classifier-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/llm-classifier-design">
    <summary>An LLM classifier should answer one question per item with the smallest possible payload.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-cost-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/llm-cost-basics">
    <summary>Understanding LLM API costs, tracking usage, model pricing, and basic optimization for production applications.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-decision-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/llm-decision-framework">
    <summary>A systematic framework for choosing the right LLM enhancement strategy — prompt engineering, RAG, fine-tuning, or RAFT (hybrid) — based on data freshness, accuracy requirements, budget, latency, and team constraints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-observability" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/llm-observability">
    <summary>LLM observability is the practice of tracing, monitoring, evaluating, and debugging LLM applications in production.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-observability-stack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/llm-observability-stack">
    <summary>Production observability stack for LLM systems: tracing, cost analytics, quality evaluation, and alerting via OpenTelemetry.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-observability-stack-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/llm-observability-stack-2026">
    <summary>Comprehensive monitoring for production AI applications requires integrating multiple platforms: tracing (Langfuse), cost analytics (Helicone), evaluation (Arize Phoenix), and multi-agent tracing (Braintrust).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="local-llm-ollama" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/local-llm-ollama">
    <summary>Run LLMs locally via Ollama's HTTP API (port 11434).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lora-qlora" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/lora-qlora">
    <summary>LoRA (Low-Rank Adaptation) freezes base model weights and injects small trainable matrices into attention layers, reducing trainable parameters from 100% to 0.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-architecture" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/mcp-architecture">
    <summary>MCP is an open standard enabling seamless integration between LLM applications and external data sources and tools.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-client-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/mcp-client-integration">
    <summary>Agents consume MCP as clients: the host (Claude Desktop, VS Code, or custom Claude SDK app) launches MCP servers and exposes their tools to the model.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-dev-prompts" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/mcp-dev-prompts">
    <summary>A library of LLM prompts covering the full MCP development lifecycle: creating servers, adding tools, designing resources, debugging connection and execution failures, validating JSON-RPC messages, designing multi-server architectures, security review, performance optimization, test generation, and documentation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-security" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/mcp-security">
    <summary>MCP tools represent arbitrary code execution.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-server-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/mcp-server-implementation">
    <summary>Build MCP servers using the official TypeScript SDK (McpServer + Zod) or Python SDK (FastMCP for rapid development, mcp.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="model-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/model-evaluation">
    <summary>Systematic methodology for assessing LLM quality, latency, cost, safety, and reliability across offline (test dataset), online (A/B production traffic), and continuous monitoring modes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="model-onboarding-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/model-onboarding-checklist">
    <summary>Step-by-step checklist from "new SOTA model announced" to "gated in production" — pulls the right slices of gateway, router, eval methodologies into a single sheet.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-agent-design-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/multi-agent-design-patterns">
    <summary>Four canonical patterns for orchestrating multiple AI agents: Supervisor, Hierarchical, Sequential, and Peer-to-Peer.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-agent-systems" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/multi-agent-systems">
    <summary>Multi-agent systems coordinate multiple AI agents to solve tasks that exceed a single agent's context, parallelism, or role boundaries.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="negative-result-discipline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/negative-result-discipline">
    <summary>A 3-line negative-result convention for ML / RAG / embedding spike experiments so the same dead-end never gets retried six months later.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-agent-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ollama-agent-integration">
    <summary>Ollama exposes an OpenAI-compatible endpoint at http://localhost:11434/v1, enabling drop-in replacement of the OpenAI SDK by changing one environment variable.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-deployment" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ollama-deployment">
    <summary>Production Ollama deployment requires Docker Compose with proper GPU passthrough, volume mounts for model persistence, health checks, nginx reverse proxy with rate limiting and streaming support, and a systemd service for bare-metal installs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-prompt-engineering" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ollama-prompt-engineering">
    <summary>Local Ollama models require careful prompt engineering to match cloud model quality.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-python-client" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ollama-python-client">
    <summary>Ollama exposes a REST API at http://localhost:11434 and an official Python library (pip install ollama).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-setup-models" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ollama-setup-models">
    <summary>Ollama is an open-source platform for running LLMs locally.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-tool-calling" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/ollama-tool-calling">
    <summary>Ollama supports OpenAI-compatible tool/function calling and JSON schema structured outputs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/openai-api">
    <summary>OpenAI Platform provides Chat Completions, the Responses API (2025+, stateful), Structured Outputs, Batch API (50% discount), embeddings, Whisper, TTS, DALL-E, and fine-tuning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-api-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/openai-api-integration">
    <summary>OpenAI API provides access to GPT-4, GPT-4 Turbo, GPT-4o, and other models for text generation, embeddings, image generation, and more.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-assistants" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/openai-assistants">
    <summary>The Assistants API is a stateful layer over Chat Completions that manages conversation threads, file uploads, a built-in vector store (File Search), and a sandboxed Python runtime (Code Interpreter).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-chat-completions" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/openai-chat-completions">
    <summary>Complete guide to the OpenAI Chat Completions endpoint (`/v1/chat/completions`): request structure, model selection, parameters (temperature, max_tokens, response_format), streaming, vision (URL and base64), error handling with exponential backoff, rate limit headers, and cost tracking via tiktoken.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-embeddings" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/openai-embeddings">
    <summary>Generate dense vector representations of text using OpenAI embedding models and search them with cosine similarity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-function-calling" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/openai-function-calling">
    <summary>OpenAI-specific patterns for function calling (tool use), Pydantic-validated structured extraction via `client.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/prompt-basics">
    <summary>Core prompt engineering patterns: zero-shot, few-shot, chain-of-thought, self-consistency, and ReAct.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-changelog-discipline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/prompt-changelog-discipline">
    <summary>A lightweight prompt-changelog convention that pairs every prompt edit with a hash, intent, eval delta, and rollback path so production-prompt regressions can be correlated back to a specific change in minutes rather than days.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/prompt-engineering-evaluation">
    <summary>Prompts without a test suite degrade silently.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-fundamentals" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/prompt-engineering-fundamentals">
    <summary>Prompt engineering is the practice of crafting inputs to LLMs that reliably produce desired outputs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-production" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/prompt-engineering-production">
    <summary>Production prompts require versioning, retry logic, structured output validation, and tool-use scaffolding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-reasoning" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/prompt-engineering-reasoning">
    <summary>Complex tasks — math, multi-step logic, decision analysis, code review — require structured reasoning prompts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-security" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/prompt-engineering-security">
    <summary>Production LLM systems face prompt injection, jailbreaking, and data exfiltration risks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-techniques" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/prompt-techniques">
    <summary>Advanced prompting patterns, testing, and management strategies.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-version-pinning-runbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/prompt-version-pinning-runbook">
    <summary>A runbook for pinning prompt versions at the gateway: storage layout per environment, immutable version IDs, rollout (canary / shadow / 5/95 split), gateway-side enforcement, rollback in &amp;lt; 60 seconds, and weekly A/B review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/rag">
    <summary>A framework for augmenting LLMs with real-time access to external knowledge: embed query → retrieve top-k chunks from vector store → rerank to top-5 → inject context into prompt → generate with citations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag">
    <summary>A Retrieval-Augmented Generation pipeline ingests documents (load → chunk → embed → store), retrieves relevant chunks for a query (embed → vector search → rerank), and generates a grounded answer with source citations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-architecture" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-architecture">
    <summary>Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG) combines information retrieval with LLM generation to produce accurate, grounded responses.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-canary-rollout-plan" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-ops/rag-canary-rollout-plan">
    <summary>A staged-rollout plan for a RAG-backed feature with answer-quality-based auto-rollback — canary percentage curve, golden-eval guardrails, online-quality scoring, kill-switch criteria, and a 60-second rollback path.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-ab-testing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-eval-ab-testing">
    <summary>A/B testing for RAG configurations runs the same question set through two pipeline variants and compares their results.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-generation-metrics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-eval-generation-metrics">
    <summary>Generation metrics measure whether the RAG pipeline produces answers that are faithful to the retrieved context, relevant to the question, and sourced from contextually relevant documents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-eval-pipeline">
    <summary>A complete evaluation pipeline runs each test-set question through the production RAG pipeline, computes retrieval metrics (precision@5, recall@5, MRR, hit rate) and generation metrics (faithfulness, answer relevance, context relevance) via LLM scoring or RAGAS, aggregates results, and exports to JSON.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-production-monitoring" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-eval-production-monitoring">
    <summary>Production RAG monitoring logs latency, source count, and user feedback for every query, aggregates rolling summaries (24h default window), and detects anomalies against calibrated thresholds.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-retrieval-metrics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-eval-retrieval-metrics">
    <summary>Retrieval metrics measure whether the RAG system fetches the right documents before generation happens.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-strategy" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-eval-strategy">
    <summary>RAG evaluation strategy defines which metrics to run, when to run them, how to sample to control LLM-judge costs, and how to set explicit numeric quality gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-test-set-generation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-eval-test-set-generation">
    <summary>A RAG evaluation can only be as good as its test set.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/rag-evaluation">
    <summary>Evaluate Retrieval-Augmented Generation pipelines by measuring retrieval (Precision@K, Recall@K, MRR, Hit Rate) and generation (Faithfulness, Answer Relevance, Hallucination Rate) components separately.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-failure-taxonomy" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-failure-taxonomy">
    <summary>A shared vocabulary for clustering RAG failure cases — retrieval-fail / generation-fail / chunk-boundary / stale-doc / wrong-doc-ranked / prompt-instruction-leak — so weekly retrieval-quality reviews and customer-feedback triage produce consistent diagnoses across reviewers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/rag-implementation">
    <summary>Complete production RAG pipeline: document loading (txt/md/pdf/directory), chunking (fixed-size, sentence, paragraph, semantic, Markdown-header), embedding, Chroma-backed vector storage, retrieval, query enhancement (expansion, HyDE, rewrite), and LLM generation with strict "answer only from context" system prompt.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-pipeline-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/rag-pipeline-design">
    <summary>Production RAG pipelines ground LLM responses in domain-specific data through a retrieval layer (embedding + vector search + reranking) followed by synthesis.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reasoning-first-architectures" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/reasoning-first-architectures">
    <summary>Patterns for using reasoning models (o3/o4-mini, Claude Extended Thinking, DeepSeek R1) and chain-of-thought techniques to solve tasks requiring multi-step logic, self-verification, and planning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/reranking">
    <summary>Reranking is a second-stage retrieval technique that refines initial search results using more sophisticated models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-diversity-mmr" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/reranking-diversity-mmr">
    <summary>Maximal Marginal Relevance (MMR) reranking selects documents that are both relevant to the query and dissimilar to already-selected documents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-models" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/reranking-models">
    <summary>Two-stage retrieval: fast ANN retrieves top-50 candidates, then a reranker (cross-encoder or API service) rescores them to return top-5 for generation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-pipeline-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/reranking-pipeline-integration">
    <summary>Integrate reranking into a production RAG pipeline by wrapping the two-stage retrieve + rerank flow in a RerankingRAG class, supporting cross-encoder, Cohere API, and LLM-based rerankers.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-two-stage" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/reranking-two-stage">
    <summary>Reranking is a second-stage retrieval technique that refines initial search results using more sophisticated models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="semantic-xml-content" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/semantic-xml-content">
    <summary>A convention for authoring methodology content as semantic XML — not as XML for formatting, but as a tag vocabulary where each tag carries meaning the agent can act on.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="speech-to-text" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/speech-to-text">
    <summary>Speech-to-text (STT) methodology covering provider selection (OpenAI Whisper/GPT-4o, AssemblyAI, Deepgram, ElevenLabs Scribe), local model deployment (faster-whisper, whisper.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="speech-to-text-advanced" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/speech-to-text-advanced">
    <summary>Long audio processing (&gt;25MB), speaker diarization, and production TranscriptionService with provider routing (OpenAI, faster-whisper, local Whisper).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="speech-to-text-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/speech-to-text-basics">
    <summary>Transcribing audio to text using OpenAI Whisper API, local Whisper, or faster-whisper (CTranslate2).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structured-output" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/structured-output">
    <summary>Structured output ensures LLMs return data in consistent, parseable formats (JSON matching a schema).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structured-output-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/structured-output-basics">
    <summary>Patterns for getting LLMs to return consistent, parseable JSON: OpenAI JSON Mode (response_format), OpenAI Structured Outputs (beta.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structured-output-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/structured-output-patterns">
    <summary>Production patterns for reliable LLM structured extraction: Pydantic schema design, retry with error-message injection, streaming JSON handling, and the StructuredOutputService abstraction.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="text-to-speech" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/text-to-speech">
    <summary>Convert text to natural-sounding audio using TTS APIs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="thumbs-down-to-eval-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/thumbs-down-to-eval-pipeline">
    <summary>Closes the loop from a user thumbs-down (or hallucination report) to a row in the regression eval set within 24h, with PII scrubbing, judgment voting, and deterministic eval-set growth caps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tool-use-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/llm-integration/tool-use-basics">
    <summary>Enables LLMs to call external functions, APIs, and code by defining a tool registry (name → callable), converting it to provider-specific JSON schema, and running a request-execute-respond loop with a hard iteration cap.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tool-use-function-calling" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/tool-use-function-calling">
    <summary>Function calling enables LLMs to interact with external systems by generating structured JSON specifying which tool to call and with what parameters.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tts-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/tts-basics">
    <summary>Convert text to natural speech using OpenAI TTS, ElevenLabs, or Google Cloud TTS.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tts-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/tts-implementation">
    <summary>Production TTS service with multi-provider support (OpenAI, ElevenLabs, Google Cloud), content-hash caching, long-text chunking via LongTextTTS, real-time streaming via async PCM, and voice cloning via ElevenLabs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-database-setup" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/rag-engineer/vector-database-setup">
    <summary>Decision methodology for choosing and provisioning a vector database at the start of a RAG project: comparison of Pinecone, Weaviate, Chroma, Qdrant, Milvus, and pgvector; HNSW vs IVF vs Flat index selection; setup code for each provider; and a provider-agnostic VectorStoreBase abstraction.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-databases" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vector-databases">
    <summary>Vector databases solve approximate nearest neighbor (ANN) search at scale — finding semantically similar items without exact keyword matching.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-index-tuning" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vector-db-index-tuning">
    <summary>Configure HNSW index parameters (M, ef_construct, ef_search), choose a quantization strategy (scalar int8, product, binary), and select workload profiles (read-heavy, write-heavy, balanced) to hit defined latency and recall SLAs without over-provisioning memory.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-monitoring" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vector-db-monitoring">
    <summary>Instrument a production vector database with Prometheus metrics, configure Grafana dashboards, define warning and critical alert thresholds for latency, error rate, memory, and disk, and establish capacity planning baselines to prevent surprise outages before they reach users.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-security" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vector-db-security">
    <summary>Harden a vector database deployment against unauthorized access and data leakage: disable anonymous access, configure API key or OIDC authentication, enforce TLS for all connections, deploy in a private VPC subnet, enable encryption at rest, set up audit logging, and define PII handling procedures.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-setup-dev" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vector-db-setup-dev">
    <summary>Spin up any major vector database (Qdrant, Weaviate, Milvus, pgvector, Pinecone, Chroma) locally via Docker one-liners or pip install, connect a Python client, create a collection, and verify the stack is functional before writing pipeline code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-setup-prod" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vector-db-setup-prod">
    <summary>Deploy vector databases to production using Docker Compose (single-node), Kubernetes StatefulSets or Helm (multi-node), or managed cloud services; covers persistence, health checks, resource limits, high availability, backup/recovery, and the pre/post-deployment checklists required before serving live traffic.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-gen-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/video-gen-basics">
    <summary>Generating short video clips from text or image input using Runway, Luma, Replicate, or Pika.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-gen-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/video-gen-tools">
    <summary>API client implementations for Runway Gen-3, Luma Dream Machine, and Replicate video models (SVD, AnimateDiff, Zeroscope).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-async-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/video-generation-async-api">
    <summary>All AI video generation providers are async with 60-300s generation latency.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-production-service" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/video-generation-production-service">
    <summary>Production video generation services require a multi-provider abstraction with automatic retry and fallback, an async job API (FastAPI or similar) for caller decoupling, a priority queue for high-volume workloads, and ffmpeg utilities for clip assembly and processing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-prompt-engineering" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/video-generation-prompt-engineering">
    <summary>Effective video generation prompts follow the formula: Subject + Action + Setting + Style + Camera + Lighting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-provider-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/video-generation-provider-selection">
    <summary>Video generation has evolved rapidly with commercial APIs from Runway, Luma, OpenAI Sora, and Google Veo providing production-ready solutions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-accessibility" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vision-accessibility">
    <summary>VLMs generate WCAG-compliant alt text and extended scene descriptions for images at scale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-agentic-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vision-agentic-pipeline">
    <summary>Production vision pipelines use a three-subagent chain: image-router (classifies image type, selects VLM + prompt), vision-extractor (calls VLM, enforces structured output, returns Pydantic model), validation-agent (cross-checks extracted fields against business rules).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-applications" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/vision-applications">
    <summary>Production patterns for vision LLM tasks: OCR, document extraction, image classification, and content moderation using GPT-4o, Claude, or Gemini Vision.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/vision-basics">
    <summary>Analyze images with VLM APIs (GPT-4o, Claude Sonnet, Gemini Flash): single-image analysis, multi-image comparison, structured JSON extraction via Pydantic, and stateful visual Q&amp;A.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-classification-moderation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vision-classification-moderation">
    <summary>Image classification labels an image into one of N predefined categories; content moderation is a specialised classification that detects unsafe categories (violence, adult content, hate symbols) with severity levels.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-document-extraction" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vision-document-extraction">
    <summary>Document extraction uses VLMs to pull structured data from invoices, receipts, forms, contracts, and ID documents.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-provider-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/vision-provider-selection">
    <summary>Modern Vision Language Models (VLMs) enable image understanding — OCR, document analysis, visual QA, classification, moderation, and accessibility.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-agents" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/ml-engineer/voice-agents">
    <summary>Production voice AI agents built on real-time STT → LLM → TTS pipelines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/voice-basics">
    <summary>Building conversational voice agents that chain STT (Whisper) to LLM (GPT-4o) to TTS into a turn-based loop.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/geek/ai/multimodal-ai/voice-implementation">
    <summary>Production implementation of voice agents: RealtimeVoiceAgent with energy-based VAD and threading, ProductionVoiceAgent with state machine (IDLE/LISTENING/PROCESSING/SPEAKING) and async tool calling, and a FastAPI WebSocket endpoint for browser/mobile clients.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
