<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<index domain="ml-engineering" count="188" version="3.0" generated="2026-05-23">
  <description>L2 index of methodologies in the ml-engineering domain. The retriever reads this after picking ml-engineering from L1 domains.xml. Entries list slug + tier + summary; open the leaf AGENTS.md / content/*.xml for full payload.</description>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agentic-rag">
    <summary>Agentic RAG pattern: query routing, multi-hop retrieval, self-correction (CRAG), iterative refinement, with LangGraph state machine + Pydantic schemas.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-iterative-retrieval" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agentic-rag-iterative-retrieval">
    <summary>Produces an iterative-retrieval RAG agent class — LLM judge decides sufficiency, refines query, retries up to a hard cap; drift detection + dedup + per-step model routing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-query-decomposition" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agentic-rag-query-decomposition">
    <summary>Decomposes complex queries into 2–4 atomic sub-queries, retrieves in parallel, tracks coverage; falls back to single-pass when decomposition collapses to 1 sub-query.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-self-correction" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agentic-rag-self-correction">
    <summary>Generates an answer, runs a faithfulness verifier (different model) against retrieved chunks, regenerates with feedback up to a hard cap, escalates if ungrounded claims persist.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agentic-rag-tool-using" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agentic-rag-tool-using">
    <summary>Routes each RAG sub-query through an LLM-selected tool from a registry (vector_search, keyword_search, sql_query, web_search) and synthesises one answer from accumulated multi-source context.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-framework-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agents-framework-selection">
    <summary>Decision rubric to pick among LangGraph / CrewAI / AutoGen / Anthropic Agent SDK / OpenAI Swarm / no-framework for a new agent project.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-memory-system" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agents-memory-system">
    <summary>Three-tier agent memory: short-term buffer, episodic store, long-term vector store; with summarisation, eviction, and recall scoring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-production-deployment" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agents-production-deployment">
    <summary>Five production gates for shipping an agent: typed tool base, YAML config with env subst, structured JSON logs, retry/circuit breaker, repeatable eval harness.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-react-pattern" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agents-react-pattern">
    <summary>Single-agent ReAct loop: Thought → Action → Observation, with bounded iterations, typed tool registry, audit log, and termination guard.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="agents-safety-guardrails" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/agents-safety-guardrails">
    <summary>Five guardrail categories for production agents: execution, content, financial, action, human-in-loop. Each carries trip-conditions and a recovery path.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-agent-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-agent-patterns">
    <summary>Six agentic AI patterns (ReAct, CoT, Tool Use, Plan-Execute, Reflection, Tree-of-Thoughts) + four multi-agent topologies. Decision record picking the right pattern.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-call-site-inventory" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-call-site-inventory">
    <summary>Report cataloguing every LLM call site in the codebase — file path, model, prompt version, schema version, fallback chain — required before any model migration or audit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-cost-attribution-schema" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-cost-attribution-schema">
    <summary>Produces a JSON Schema + middleware spec that tags every LLM call with tenant, feature, route, model, prompt-cache-hit so cost reports are sliceable per dimension.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-failure-mode-taxonomy" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-failure-mode-taxonomy">
    <summary>Produces a closed taxonomy of 12 LLM failure modes (hallucination, IPI, refusal-bypass, schema-drop, latency-spike, cost-blowup, etc.) with detector + severity + linked methodology, anchoring every eval, alert, and incident.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-build-buy-finetune-decision" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-feature-build-buy-finetune-decision">
    <summary>ADR-style decision record selecting among build-from-scratch / buy-vendor-API / finetune-existing for a specific AI feature, scored on cost, quality, control, time-to-market.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-ga-checklist" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-feature-ga-checklist">
    <summary>Pre-GA checklist for an AI feature — eval gate green, observability live, cost cap enforced, refusal policy tested, rollout plan + kill switch in place.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-incident-runbook" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-feature-incident-runbook">
    <summary>Playbook step for on-call response to AI feature incidents — triage matrix, kill-switch criteria, mitigation ladder, communication template, post-incident hand-off to post-mortem.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-observability-four-pillars" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-feature-observability-four-pillars">
    <summary>Spec for the four observability pillars per AI feature — quality, latency, cost, drift — with dashboard panels, alert thresholds, and refresh cadences.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feature-progressive-rollout" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-feature-progressive-rollout">
    <summary>Playbook step that scales AI feature traffic by ring (1% → 10% → 50% → 100%) gated on eval delta + observability pillars + customer-comm checkpoints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-feedback-triage-protocol" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-feedback-triage-protocol">
    <summary>Routes inbound AI-product feedback (hallucination / refusal / wrong-tool / out-of-scope / cost-spike) into named lanes (ML eng vs product vs support) via 5-step explicit-signal protocol with owners + exit criteria.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-governance-compliance" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-governance-compliance">
    <summary>EU AI Act + NIST AI RMF aligned governance bundle: risk tier, model card, datasheet, fairness/explainability audit, audit trail, human-oversight plan, retention policy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-incident-triage-matrix" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-incident-triage-matrix">
    <summary>Numeric scoring rubric (1-5 anchored, weighted blend) that classifies an AI-feature incident across 5 lanes (model-regression / prompt-injection / data-drift / upstream-API / cost-runaway) and routes to lane-specific mitigation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ai-option-cost-grid-template" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ai-option-cost-grid-template">
    <summary>Builds an apples-to-apples cost+quality grid across AI option families (prompt-eng, RAG, SFT, DPO, vendor swap) so a decision memo cites a defensible comparison instead of vendor claims.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chain-of-thought" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/chain-of-thought">
    <summary>Chain-of-Thought prompting + extended thinking + self-consistency: when to use each, how to wire them, and how to keep CoT from leaking to the user.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/chunking-basics">
    <summary>Pick a chunk-size + overlap + splitter strategy for a RAG corpus by content type, measured in tiktoken tokens not words, with metadata attached at creation time.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-code-ast" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/chunking-code-ast">
    <summary>Splits source code at function and class boundaries via Python `ast` (or tree-sitter for JS/TS), emitting chunks carrying name, type, docstring, and line range for code-search RAG.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-document-structure" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/chunking-document-structure">
    <summary>Splits Markdown by header hierarchy and HTML by sectioning elements, propagating parent header paths into every chunk to preserve navigational context for retrieval.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-production-service" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/chunking-production-service">
    <summary>Production orchestration layer that routes documents to per-type chunkers (Markdown/HTML/code/recursive), propagates document-level metadata, and falls back to word-split on exception with a logged warning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-semantic" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/chunking-semantic">
    <summary>Splits text where cosine similarity between adjacent sentence embeddings drops below a threshold, so chunks capture coherent concepts instead of arbitrary token windows.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="chunking-strategies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/chunking-strategies">
    <summary>Document chunking decision rubric: fixed-size, recursive-character, semantic, structure-aware (markdown/HTML/code). Output is a chunking config + dispatcher.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/claude-api">
    <summary>Produces Anthropic Claude API integration code with caching, MAX_TURNS-guarded tool loops, forced-tool structured output, Extended Thinking budgeting, and Batch API submission patterns.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="claude-tool-use" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/claude-tool-use">
    <summary>Produces a working Claude tool-use loop — typed JSON Schema tool definitions, canonical agent loop with parallel tool dispatch, forced-tool structured output, max-iteration guard.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-optimization" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/cost-optimization">
    <summary>Produces an LLM cost-optimization plan (model-router config, cache policy, batch-routing rules, token-budget guardrails) that cuts per-stage LLM spend 60-90% without touching task quality.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cost-reduction-strategies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/cost-reduction-strategies">
    <summary>Applies four orthogonal cost levers — response caching, prompt compression, async batching, and model routing — and reports per-lever savings against a baseline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cot-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/cot-basics">
    <summary>Produces a chain-of-thought-enabled prompt that elicits explicit reasoning before answer — zero-shot CoT trigger, structured reasoning tag, parsed answer, fallback for non-CoT models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="cot-techniques" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/cot-techniques">
    <summary>Produces a selected advanced-CoT pattern (few-shot CoT, self-consistency, least-to-most, tree-of-thoughts) — config, runner, eval-lift report, cost guard.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-chroma" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/db-chroma">
    <summary>Embedded SQLite/HNSW vector store for RAG prototyping with zero infrastructure and idempotent get_or_create_collection ingestion; single-process only.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-comparison" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/db-comparison">
    <summary>Picks a vector database (Chroma / Qdrant / Weaviate / pgvector / Pinecone / Milvus) from a scored matrix anchored on year-1 scale, hosting model, hybrid-search need, and existing infra.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-qdrant" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/db-qdrant">
    <summary>Self-hosted vector store for production RAG (41 QPS at 50M vectors), with payload-filter perf, quantization, and built-in sparse vectors for hybrid search without a separate engine.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="db-weaviate" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/db-weaviate">
    <summary>Vector database for knowledge-graph + native hybrid (vector + BM25) workloads via GraphQL, with multi-vector multi-modal objects, scaling 10M–100M vectors self-hosted or via Weaviate Cloud.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="decision-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/decision-framework">
    <summary>Produces a decision record naming the AI approach (prompt / RAG / fine-tune / hybrid) and the model tier for a given task, with progressive-enhancement justification and a quarterly re-evaluation clause.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-applications" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-applications">
    <summary>End-to-end embedding pipeline — MTEB-anchored model selection plus domain benchmarking, batched insertion, normalized cosine, model-version metadata, Recall@10 quality gate.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-caching" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-caching">
    <summary>Embedding cache layer — SHA-256 keyed by (model+version+text), TTL aligned with model version, Redis/Valkey backend, cache-hit metric for cost audit.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-chunking-strategies" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-chunking-strategies">
    <summary>Picks chunking strategy (fixed-token, sentence-aware, recursive, semantic, structural) per corpus class plus chunk_size + overlap; benchmarks Recall@10 before deploy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-cost-optimization" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-cost-optimization">
    <summary>Five-lever cost optimization for embedding pipelines — Matryoshka dim reduction, batch API, aggressive cache, two-stage retrieval, dedup-on-ingest.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-generation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-generation">
    <summary>Produces an embedding-generation config (model id, dimension, normalization, batch policy, cache layer) plus producer code for semantic-search / RAG indexing pipelines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-generation-rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-generation-rag">
    <summary>Generates embedding pipeline — same-model index/query, batched calls (OpenAI ≤2048), SHA-256 cache keys, unit normalization, empty/overlong guards, provider-specific tuning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-model-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-model-selection">
    <summary>Selects an embedding model + dimension count for a RAG workload by matching quality, cost, token limits, language coverage, and latency to the corpus and SLA.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embedding-models" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embedding-models">
    <summary>Picks embedding model for a corpus class (general/code/multilingual) — pins model+version, handles Cohere input_type, OpenAI dimensions, Mistral/Voyage caveats, SentenceTransformer singleton.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-batch-and-cache" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embeddings-batch-and-cache">
    <summary>Produces an embedding-batch-and-cache config (batch size, parallelism, cache backend + TTL + key scheme) cutting embedding API cost up to 90% on repeat workloads via dedup + content-hash cache + async parallel batching.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embeddings-evaluation">
    <summary>Produces an embedding evaluation report (Recall@K, MRR, nDCG, A/B comparison + golden set design) that ranks candidate embedding models on the team's own retrieval workload.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-model-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embeddings-model-selection">
    <summary>Pick an embedding model by matching (use case, constraints, capabilities). Output is a decision record with chosen model + rejected alternatives.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-production-ops" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embeddings-production-ops">
    <summary>Production embeddings operations: latency SLO, rate-limit handling, cost tracking, fault tolerance, model migration playbook.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="embeddings-provider-apis" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/embeddings-provider-apis">
    <summary>Production patterns for the four main embedding providers (OpenAI, Voyage AI, Cohere, sentence-transformers local) with a unified client abstraction.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="eu-ai-act-compliance" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/eu-ai-act-compliance">
    <summary>Produces an Article-cited EU AI Act risk classification + compliance gap report flagging Article 5 prohibitions, Annex III high-risk obligations, and Article 50 transparency duties.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="evaluation-benchmarks" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/evaluation-benchmarks">
    <summary>Runs a multi-model comparison benchmark (held-out set + LLM-as-judge) and a continuous production-sampling job to detect drift across model swaps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="evaluation-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/evaluation-framework">
    <summary>Ships a Python evaluation harness that runs an offline batch (ModelEvaluator), an LLM-as-judge scorer (LLMJudge), and a sampled production evaluator (ProductionEvaluator) against a shared rubric.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="evaluation-metrics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/evaluation-metrics">
    <summary>Selects per-task metrics across accuracy, quality, latency, cost, safety, and reliability; produces a metric card that the eval harness consumes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-lora" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-lora">
    <summary>Produces a LoRA/QLoRA/DoRA/rsLoRA training config (rank, alpha, target modules, data mix) for a chosen base model, fitted to single-GPU or multi-GPU budgets.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-lora-mlops" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-lora-mlops">
    <summary>Runs a LoRA fine-tune with PEFT + TRL: freeze base weights, inject rank-8-64 matrices on attention layers, 100-250× fewer trainable params, fits on a single 24GB GPU for 7B/8B models.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-openai-basics">
    <summary>Prepares JSONL chat-messages training data for OpenAI fine-tuning, validates structure + token counts with tiktoken, and synthesises extra examples with GPT-4 when below the recommended count.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-data-prep" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-openai-data-prep">
    <summary>Produces a validated OpenAI fine-tuning JSONL training file plus a data-preparation spec covering schema, token counts, train/validation split, and reusable Python validators.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-deployment" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-openai-deployment">
    <summary>Produces a deployment playbook step for a fine-tuned OpenAI model: gradual rollout (10/50/100), cost monitoring, model-ID version control, and async job-polling pattern.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-dpo" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-openai-dpo">
    <summary>Produces a DPO training config + preference-pair dataset spec for OpenAI fine-tuning, applied after SFT to align model behaviour to subjective criteria (tone, style, safety, brand voice).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-eval" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-openai-eval">
    <summary>Produces an evaluation report comparing a fine-tuned OpenAI model to base on held-out test set using automated LLM-as-judge scoring and A/B comparison, with explicit pass/fail gate per metric.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-production" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-openai-production">
    <summary>End-to-end OpenAI fine-tune pipeline: file upload, job create with hyperparameter control, status polling, LLM-as-judge evaluation on held-out set, model ID registry.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="fine-tuning-openai-sft" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/fine-tuning-openai-sft">
    <summary>Produces an OpenAI SFT job config + launched fine-tune job, customising GPT-4.1 / GPT-4o on input-output JSONL pairs with eval-gate-gated deployment.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finetuning" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/finetuning">
    <summary>Produces a fine-tuning decision record naming technique (Full FT / LoRA / QLoRA / DoRA / API-SFT), framework, data plan, and budget — gated by prompt+RAG-first scoring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finetuning-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/finetuning-basics">
    <summary>Picks the cheapest fine-tuning technique (LoRA, QLoRA, DoRA, full FT) and the simplest framework (LLaMA-Factory, Unsloth, Axolotl, TRL) for the task and GPU budget.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="finetuning-datasets" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/finetuning-datasets">
    <summary>Cleans, dedupes, format-converts (Alpaca/ShareGPT/OpenAI JSONL), trains with hyperparameter sweep, evaluates with LM-Evaluation-Harness, and deploys to Ollama (GGUF) / vLLM / TGI.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="function-calling-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/function-calling-patterns">
    <summary>Produces a cross-vendor function-calling design — parallel tool dispatch, tool router, agentic loop with bounded iterations, argument validation, schema-enforced output extraction.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/gemini-api">
    <summary>Produces a production Google Gemini API client wiring up streaming, function calling, multimodal input (image/audio/video), context caching, and Live API for real-time voice/video sessions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-api-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/gemini-api-integration">
    <summary>Produces a working Gemini API integration — model selection (Pro vs Flash), 1M-context handling, Files API upload pattern, generation config + safety settings.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/gemini-basics">
    <summary>Produces a starter Gemini text/chat integration — SDK init, model pick (Flash vs Pro), single-shot generate, streaming, multi-turn chat, JSON response mode.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-function-calling" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/gemini-function-calling">
    <summary>Produces a Gemini function-calling integration — Python function declarations via docstring + types, manual-mode loop, JSON-schema response, optional Search grounding.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="gemini-multimodal" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/gemini-multimodal">
    <summary>Gemini native multimodal — image/audio/video/PDF + code execution + 2M context + 75%-cheaper context caching, with polling + file-expiry handling.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="golden-set-curation-and-maintenance" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/golden-set-curation-and-maintenance">
    <summary>Curates 50-200 hand-labelled I/O pairs (stratified buckets + anti-output + incident-derived growth + quarterly drift audit + versioned promotion) as the anchor dataset for AI-feature regression eval.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/graph-rag">
    <summary>Produces a GraphRAG pipeline spec: entity extraction → knowledge graph → community detection → hierarchical summaries → query-routing for multi-hop and global questions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag-indexing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/graph-rag-indexing">
    <summary>Builds the GraphRAG entity-and-relationship graph + community summaries from a document corpus, with deterministic chunking, entity dedup, and resumable batch processing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag-production" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/graph-rag-production">
    <summary>Production-ready GraphRAG deployment: query routing (GLOBAL/LOCAL/COMMUNITY), caching layer, incremental updates, observability, and cost guardrails.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="graph-rag-retrieval" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/graph-rag-retrieval">
    <summary>Routes Graph-RAG queries into GLOBAL/ENTITY/RELATIONSHIP/LOCAL strategies and combines vector candidates with graph neighbor expansion.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-ai-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/guardrails-ai-framework">
    <summary>Produces a Guardrails-AI-wired LLM output pipeline using Pydantic schemas + Hub validators for structured-output enforcement, PII detection, and on-fail reasking.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/guardrails-basics">
    <summary>Produces a 4-layer defense-in-depth guardrails spec — regex pre-filter, length cap, output schema, LLM classifier last — with per-layer latency budget and order constraint.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-concepts" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/guardrails-concepts">
    <summary>Produces a guardrail architecture report mapping rail types (input/output/dialog/retrieval/execution) to pipeline stages with action strategy and tiered-latency budget.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-custom-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/guardrails-custom-pipeline">
    <summary>Produces Python `GuardrailsPipeline` code module composing PIIDetector + PromptInjectionDetector + ContentModerator + optional HallucinationDetector with tiered checks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/guardrails-implementation">
    <summary>Produces a production guardrails pipeline — config dataclass + input/output validators + filters + structured violation log + audit trail + optional async fan-out.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-nemo" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/guardrails-nemo">
    <summary>Produces a NeMo Guardrails config (`config.yml` + Colang flows + custom actions) covering input/jailbreak/topic/output/fact-check rails for a multi-turn dialog application.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="guardrails-testing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/guardrails-testing">
    <summary>Produces a three-suite pytest harness (security red-team + accuracy false-positive + perf latency) for a deployed guardrails pipeline plus a monthly run report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-search" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/hybrid-search">
    <summary>Produces a hybrid-search config (BM25 + vector + RRF fusion, optional cross-encoder rerank, query-adaptive alpha) for a RAG retriever with measured precision uplift.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-search-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/hybrid-search-basics">
    <summary>Produces a tuned hybrid-search config (dense + BM25 + RRF or alpha fusion) for a specific corpus with a recommended alpha and rationale.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="hybrid-search-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/hybrid-search-implementation">
    <summary>Ships a production HybridSearchService that wires dense + sparse legs in Weaviate / Qdrant / Pinecone / Elasticsearch with RRF or alpha fusion and parallel leg execution.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="image-generation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/image-generation">
    <summary>Produces an image-generation pipeline config — model choice (DALL-E 3 / Flux schnell / SD+LoRA / GPT-4o), structured 6-element prompt template, batch concurrency, and brand-consistency strategy.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="img-gen-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/img-gen-basics">
    <summary>Produces an image-generation integration — DALL-E 3 / Flux / SDXL via Replicate, ImagePromptBuilder + revised_prompt audit + immediate download + rate-limit handling.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="img-gen-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/img-gen-tools">
    <summary>Produces a multi-provider image-generation service — DALL-E + Replicate (Flux/SDXL) + Stability adapter, S3 cache, prompt-template library, idempotent fallback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="langchain" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/langchain">
    <summary>Produces a production agent built on LangChain (LCEL pipe syntax) for chains and LangGraph (state-machine framework) for durable multi-step orchestration with checkpoints and human-in-the-loop interrupts.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llamaindex" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/llamaindex">
    <summary>Produces a LlamaIndex RAG / agent pipeline: heterogeneous loaders → chunking → vector index → query engine with source citations and async Workflow event pipelines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-classifier-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/llm-classifier-design">
    <summary>Produces a cost-minimised LLM classifier — single forced tool call, batched by numeric id, prompt cache on the system prefix, calibrated judge.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-cost-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/llm-cost-basics">
    <summary>Tracks per-call input/output tokens + cost, attributes spend by feature / tenant, and applies the cheap baseline optimisations (cache, truncate, route) before considering anything exotic.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-decision-framework" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/llm-decision-framework">
    <summary>Produces an LLM-strategy ADR choosing prompt-engineering / RAG / fine-tuning / RAFT-hybrid against scored constraints (data freshness, accuracy, budget, latency, team).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-observability" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/llm-observability">
    <summary>Produces an LLM observability spec covering trace coverage, cost analytics, quality evaluation, alert rules, and vendor selection (Langfuse / LangSmith / Phoenix / native OTel).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-observability-stack" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/llm-observability-stack">
    <summary>Produces a production LLM observability stack config: OpenTelemetry collectors, Langfuse / Prometheus / Grafana wiring, alert rules, and PII-redaction pipeline.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="llm-observability-stack-2026" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/llm-observability-stack-2026">
    <summary>Integrates Langfuse (tracing), Helicone (cost analytics), Arize Phoenix (eval), and Braintrust (multi-agent tracing) behind a one-line SDK wrapper so each tool sees the same span tree.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="local-llm-ollama" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/local-llm-ollama">
    <summary>Produces an Ollama local-LLM integration — model pull + Modelfile, OpenAI-compatible client config, GPU/CPU/RAM sanity guard, fallback to cloud.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="lora-qlora" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/lora-qlora">
    <summary>Configures LoRA or QLoRA (4-bit base + LoRA adapters) for memory-efficient fine-tunes on commodity GPUs (16-24GB VRAM) with rank 8-64 and bf16/nf4 dtype rules.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-architecture" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/mcp-architecture">
    <summary>Produces an MCP architecture spec naming server primitives (tools / resources / prompts), transport (stdio / HTTP+SSE / WebSocket), and host integration boundaries per spec version 2025-11-25.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-client-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/mcp-client-integration">
    <summary>Produces an MCP-client integration: agent host config (Claude Desktop / VS Code / custom Claude SDK) that launches MCP servers and exposes their tools to the model with same interface as native tools.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-dev-prompts" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/mcp-dev-prompts">
    <summary>Produces a curated library of versioned LLM prompts for the full MCP development lifecycle — creating servers, debugging, architecture review, security audit, performance, test generation, documentation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-security" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/mcp-security">
    <summary>Produces an MCP security rubric covering consent flows, prompt-injection defences, OAuth 2.1 PKCE, capability attestation, lookalike-server detection, and audit logging — graded per MCP server / client integration.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="mcp-server-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/mcp-server-implementation">
    <summary>Implements an MCP server in TypeScript (McpServer + Zod) or Python (FastMCP / mcp.server) exposing tools, resources, and prompts with stdio or HTTP+SSE transport.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="methodology-corpus-licence-bundle" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/methodology-corpus-licence-bundle">
    <summary>Per-customer methodology corpus licence record: scope (which tiers + which domains), redistribution rights, attribution, audit hooks, renewal cadence.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="model-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/model-evaluation">
    <summary>Produces a systematic LLM evaluation report covering quality, latency, cost, and safety across offline benchmarks, online A/B tests, and continuous production monitoring.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="model-onboarding-checklist" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/model-onboarding-checklist">
    <summary>Step-by-step checklist from new SOTA model announced to gated in production — pulls the right slices of gateway, router, eval methodologies into one sheet.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-agent-design-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/multi-agent-design-patterns">
    <summary>Picks the multi-agent topology (orchestrator-worker, hierarchical, sequential, parallel, debate) for a given workflow and emits a versioned design decision-record.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="multi-agent-systems" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/multi-agent-systems">
    <summary>Specifies a production multi-agent system: agent roster, message contract, shared state, error-recovery, observability, and termination conditions.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="negative-result-discipline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/negative-result-discipline">
    <summary>Captures every failed ML / RAG / embedding spike in a 3-line negative-result artefact (hypothesis, outcome, retry-condition) indexed by tags so the same dead-end is never re-run blind.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-agent-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ollama-agent-integration">
    <summary>Wires a local Ollama model into a LangChain, LlamaIndex, or custom agent loop with tool calling, structured output, and streaming support.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-deployment" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ollama-deployment">
    <summary>Configures Ollama for production: GPU pinning, model preload, host binding, reverse proxy, auth layer, observability, and resource limits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-prompt-engineering" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ollama-prompt-engineering">
    <summary>Tunes prompts for small local Ollama models: model-card conventions, system-prompt headers, JSON mode, and few-shot density for 7B–70B class.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-python-client" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ollama-python-client">
    <summary>Implements a Python Ollama client wrapper with retry, streaming, model warmup, JSON-mode parsing, and OpenTelemetry tracing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-setup-models" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ollama-setup-models">
    <summary>Installs Ollama and selects local models within RAM/VRAM constraints, producing a runbook that includes pulled models, quantisation choices, and HTTP endpoint smoke-test.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="ollama-tool-calling" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/ollama-tool-calling">
    <summary>Wires tool calling against an Ollama model: schema declaration, fallback JSON-mode parser, repair loop, and validation against the JSON Schema.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/openai-api">
    <summary>Integrates OpenAI Chat Completions / Responses API with pinned model versions, Structured Outputs, Batch API, max_tokens, retries, and prompt-cache hits.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-api-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/openai-api-integration">
    <summary>Production-grade OpenAI Chat Completions integration: client init, model selection, streaming, async batches, structured output, retries, token accounting.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="openai-assistants" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/openai-assistants">
    <summary>Stateful OpenAI Assistants integration: thread lifecycle, File Search vector store, Code Interpreter, polling vs streaming, resource cleanup.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-changelog-discipline" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/prompt-changelog-discipline">
    <summary>Pairs every prompt edit with a versioned changelog entry (hash + intent + eval delta + rollback hash) so production regressions can be traced to a specific change in minutes.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/prompt-engineering-evaluation">
    <summary>Evaluates a prompt against a frozen eval suite with deterministic metrics, LLM-as-judge, regression tests, and per-iteration diff reports.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-fundamentals" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/prompt-engineering-fundamentals">
    <summary>Builds prompts using the six-block structure (system, context, task, examples, output format, constraints) plus zero-shot, few-shot, and CoT primitives.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-production" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/prompt-engineering-production">
    <summary>Hardens prompts for production: model pinning, prompt-cache hits, latency budget, fallback strategies, prompt-injection defences, and observability hooks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-reasoning" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/prompt-engineering-reasoning">
    <summary>Designs prompts for reasoning-first models (o1, Claude extended thinking, Gemini Thinking): minimal CoT instructions, target-output framing, and step-budget tuning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-engineering-security" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/prompt-engineering-security">
    <summary>Hardens prompts against prompt-injection, jailbreaks, data exfiltration, and instruction-hierarchy bypass via structured input separation, output filters, and red-team tests.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="prompt-version-pinning-runbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/prompt-version-pinning-runbook">
    <summary>Pins prompt versions at the LLM gateway with immutable IDs, environment-scoped lock files, canary / shadow rollout, gateway enforcement, and sub-60s rollback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag">
    <summary>Specifies a production RAG pipeline: chunking strategy, embedding model, vector DB, hybrid search, reranking, prompt template, and evaluation hooks.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-architecture" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-architecture">
    <summary>Produces an architecture decision record covering chunking, embeddings, vector DB, retrieval, context, and quality metrics for a RAG system.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-canary-rollout-plan" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-canary-rollout-plan">
    <summary>Produces a RAG-feature canary rollout plan — fixed 1/5/25/100 curve, golden-eval gate per step, sampled online quality scoring, 60s kill switch.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-ab-testing" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-eval-ab-testing">
    <summary>Runs an interleaved A/B test of two RAG configurations on a shared question set and reports per-config metrics with a promote/reject recommendation.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-generation-metrics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-eval-generation-metrics">
    <summary>Computes the RAG Triad (faithfulness, answer relevance, context relevance) via LLM-judge or RAGAS and exports a per-question scorecard.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-eval-pipeline">
    <summary>Runs the full eval set through the RAG pipeline, computes retrieval + generation metrics, aggregates, and exports a JSON report.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-production-monitoring" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-eval-production-monitoring">
    <summary>Logs latency / source count / user feedback per query and exposes calibrated anomaly thresholds for production RAG.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-retrieval-metrics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-eval-retrieval-metrics">
    <summary>Computes Precision@K, Recall@K, MRR, NDCG and hit-rate for a RAG retrieval pass and exports a per-query JSONL.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-strategy" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-eval-strategy">
    <summary>Produces an evaluation strategy doc: which metrics, when to run, sampling policy, numeric quality gates.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-eval-test-set-generation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-eval-test-set-generation">
    <summary>Generates a labeled RAG test set with question / ground-truth chunk-ids / expected answer, balanced across query types.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-evaluation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-evaluation">
    <summary>Evaluates a RAG pipeline by measuring retrieval (Precision@K, Recall@K, MRR, Hit Rate) and generation (Faithfulness, Answer Relevance, Hallucination Rate) components independently.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-failure-taxonomy" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-failure-taxonomy">
    <summary>Produces a per-incident failure label from a closed RAG taxonomy: retrieval-fail / generation-fail / chunk-boundary / stale-doc / wrong-doc-ranked / prompt-leak.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-implementation">
    <summary>Ships a production RAG pipeline: ingest, chunk, embed, Chroma-backed store, retrieve, query-enhance, answer-only-from-context with citations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-pipeline-design" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-pipeline-design">
    <summary>Designs a production RAG pipeline — embeddings + vector DB + hybrid search + reranking + caching — picking the right tier (Naive / Advanced / Modular / Agentic) for query complexity.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="rag-rag" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/rag-rag">
    <summary>Builds an end-to-end RAG pipeline (ingest → retrieve → rerank → generate) with cited answers and a launch-gate at MRR&gt;0.7 and faithfulness&gt;0.9.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reasoning-first-architectures" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/reasoning-first-architectures">
    <summary>Routes only complex tasks to reasoning models (o3 / Claude Extended Thinking / DeepSeek R1) with explicit thinking budgets, sized by task type, gated by an eval that proves the reasoning model outperforms a standard model.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/reranking">
    <summary>Adds a cross-encoder reranker (Cohere Rerank, BGE, FlashRank) as a second stage after first-stage retrieval — retrieve top-N, rerank to top-K — for 20-35% accuracy lift on RAG when latency budget allows ~200ms.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-diversity-mmr" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/reranking-diversity-mmr">
    <summary>Reranks top-N candidates with MMR to balance query relevance and inter-doc diversity, returning a diverse top-K.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-models" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/reranking-models">
    <summary>Picks a reranker (cross-encoder vs Cohere/MixedBread API) for two-stage retrieval based on latency, cost, and self-host constraints.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-pipeline-integration" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/reranking-pipeline-integration">
    <summary>Wraps two-stage retrieve + rerank in a RerankingRAG class supporting cross-encoder, Cohere, and LLM rerankers behind one interface.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="reranking-two-stage" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/reranking-two-stage">
    <summary>Designs the two-stage retrieve→rerank flow: fast ANN top-50 then cross-encoder rerank to top-5.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="shadow-traffic-rollout-pattern" tier="pro" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/shadow-traffic-rollout-pattern">
    <summary>Mirrors production traffic to a candidate model/prompt in parallel (no user-facing impact), captures per-request diff vs baseline, blocks promotion until joint quality + latency + cost gates stay within named thresholds across a representative window.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="sota-onboarding-1day-runbook" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/sota-onboarding-1day-runbook">
    <summary>Wires a freshly released SOTA LLM into staging in one day: announce-scan → gateway adapter → smoke eval → bench vs incumbent → cost-quality readout → GO/NO-GO.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="speech-to-text" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/speech-to-text">
    <summary>Speech-to-text integration methodology covering provider selection (OpenAI, AssemblyAI, Deepgram, ElevenLabs Scribe, Whisper local), batch vs streaming patterns, custom-vocab tuning, and the API-vs-self-host break-even.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="speech-to-text-advanced" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/speech-to-text-advanced">
    <summary>Produces an advanced transcription service — speaker diarisation, word-timestamp alignment, vocabulary biasing, streaming via Deepgram/AssemblyAI, post-processing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="speech-to-text-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/speech-to-text-basics">
    <summary>Produces a Whisper transcription integration — OpenAI API or local faster-whisper, language pin, verbose_json timestamps, 25MB pre-split, format guard.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structured-output" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/structured-output">
    <summary>Forces LLM responses into a typed JSON Schema / Pydantic shape using provider-native structured-output features (OpenAI response_format, Anthropic tool-use json mode, Gemini schema) with safe-parse + repair retry.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structured-output-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/structured-output-basics">
    <summary>Reliable LLM JSON output: provider-native structured outputs (OpenAI response_format=json_schema, Anthropic tool-as-schema), Pydantic validation, retry-on-parse-fail.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="structured-output-patterns" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/structured-output-patterns">
    <summary>Advanced structured-output: Pydantic + retry-with-error + streaming JSON + StructuredOutputService abstraction with metrics, fallback, and provider-router.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="text-to-speech" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/text-to-speech">
    <summary>Picks a TTS provider (OpenAI tts-1, ElevenLabs, Google Cloud, Azure, Deepgram Aura, local Coqui) and ships a cache-by-text-hash service with voice-cloning consent gate and streaming fallback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="thumbs-down-to-eval-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/thumbs-down-to-eval-pipeline">
    <summary>Closes the loop from a user thumbs-down (or hallucination report) to a row in the regression eval set within 24h, with PII scrubbing, judgment voting, and deterministic eval-set growth caps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tool-use-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/tool-use-basics">
    <summary>Minimum-viable LLM tool use: typed tool registry, provider-agnostic JSON schema, request-execute-respond loop with bounded iterations.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tool-use-function-calling" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/tool-use-function-calling">
    <summary>Designs a tool-using LLM workflow — declare typed tool schemas, dispatch model JSON to real functions, validate args, sandbox dangerous tools, and gate irreversible actions behind human review.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="tts-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/tts-implementation">
    <summary>Produces a production TTSService with sha256 cache + eviction, LongTextTTS chunking, async PCM streaming, and consent-gated ElevenLabs voice cloning.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-database-setup" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vector-database-setup">
    <summary>Picks and provisions a vector DB (Pinecone/Weaviate/Chroma/Qdrant/Milvus/pgvector) with the right index (HNSW/IVF/Flat) for the RAG workload.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-databases" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vector-databases">
    <summary>Picks a vector database (Qdrant, Weaviate, Milvus, pgvector, Pinecone, Chroma) by operational profile (managed vs self-host, scale, filtering, hybrid search) and ships the connection + collection spec.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-index-tuning" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vector-db-index-tuning">
    <summary>Tunes HNSW (M, ef_construct, ef_search) + quantization (scalar int8, product, binary) + workload profile (read-heavy / write-heavy / balanced) to hit latency + recall SLAs without over-provisioning memory.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-monitoring" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vector-db-monitoring">
    <summary>Instruments a production vector DB with Prometheus metrics, Grafana dashboard, warning/critical alerts for latency / error / memory / disk, and capacity planning baselines.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-security" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vector-db-security">
    <summary>Hardens a vector DB deployment — disable anonymous access, API-key/OIDC auth, TLS everywhere, private VPC, encryption at rest, audit log, PII handling procedure.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-setup-dev" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vector-db-setup-dev">
    <summary>Spin up a vector DB locally for development (Qdrant / Weaviate / Milvus / pgvector / Chroma) via Docker one-liner or pip install, connect a Python client, create a collection, verify the stack — before writing pipeline code.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vector-db-setup-prod" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vector-db-setup-prod">
    <summary>Deploys a vector DB to production — Docker Compose (single-node), Kubernetes StatefulSet/Helm (multi-node), or managed — with persistence, health-checks, resource limits, HA, backup/recovery, and a pre/post-deploy checklist.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-gen-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/video-gen-basics">
    <summary>Produces a Runway / Luma / Replicate video clip with structured prompt (subject + action + camera + style + lighting) and ffprobe-validated output.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-gen-tools" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/video-gen-tools">
    <summary>Produces VideoGenerationService with Runway / Luma / Replicate adapters, multi-provider fallback, retry, streaming download, and per-provider rate-limit caps.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-async-api" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/video-generation-async-api">
    <summary>Async-API pattern for video generation providers (Runway, Luma, Veo, Sora) — submit, poll with exponential backoff, fetch artefact, retry on transient failures, with provider-fallback and idempotency-key.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-production-service" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/video-generation-production-service">
    <summary>Production video generation service — FastAPI submit/poll endpoints + priority queue + multi-provider abstraction with retry/fallback + ffmpeg post-processing — wrapping the async-api primitive into a full media pipeline service.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-prompt-engineering" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/video-generation-prompt-engineering">
    <summary>Composes effective video generation prompts using the Subject + Action + Setting + Style + Camera + Lighting formula, with provider-specific quirks (Runway, Luma, Veo, Sora) and a per-prompt eval gate before scaling.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="video-generation-provider-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/video-generation-provider-selection">
    <summary>Picks the cheapest provider whose capability matrix covers the task constraints (duration, audio, lip-sync, resolution) before any integration code is written.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-accessibility" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vision-accessibility">
    <summary>Generates WCAG-compliant alt text (≤125 chars, no 'image of' prefix, embedded text verbatim) and extended scene descriptions from images using VLMs.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-agentic-pipeline" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vision-agentic-pipeline">
    <summary>Wires a three-subagent vision pipeline: image-router (classifies + selects VLM), vision-extractor (calls VLM, returns Pydantic), validation-agent (cross-checks against business rules).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-applications" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vision-applications">
    <summary>Produces typed extractions for OCR / document / classification / moderation tasks via GPT-4o / Claude / Gemini Vision, with async batch + human-review routing.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vision-basics">
    <summary>Produces a typed Pydantic vision extraction (description, text_content, confidence) from one or more images via GPT-4o / Claude / Gemini, with sha256 cache.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-classification-moderation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vision-classification-moderation">
    <summary>Classifies images into predefined categories and detects unsafe content (violence, adult, hate) with severity levels, balancing VLM accuracy with cost on a managed-moderation-API fallback.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-document-extraction" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vision-document-extraction">
    <summary>Pulls structured fields from invoices, receipts, forms, contracts, and IDs via VLM with Pydantic-enforced output and a deterministic post-validator (totals add up, dates parseable, IDs checksummed).</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="vision-provider-selection" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/vision-provider-selection">
    <summary>Picks the cheapest VLM whose capability matrix covers the task (OCR accuracy, structured output, context length, doc-image throughput) before any integration is started.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-agents" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/voice-agents">
    <summary>Designs production voice agents on real-time STT→LLM→TTS pipelines with ≤800ms end-to-end latency, 1-3-sentence responses, stripped markdown, barge-in, and filler phrases during tool calls.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-basics" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/voice-basics">
    <summary>Produces a turn-based voice agent loop (Whisper STT → GPT-4o → TTS) with VAD recording, latency-budgeted components, and bounded conversation history.</summary>
  </methodology>
  <methodology slug="voice-implementation" tier="geek" path="skills/faion/knowledge/ml-engineering/voice-implementation">
    <summary>Production implementation of voice agents — Realtime/Production agent classes with VAD, async tool calling, state machine, FastAPI WebSocket endpoint.</summary>
  </methodology>
</index>
