<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="azure-vnet-hub-spoke Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for azure-vnet-hub-spoke. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use /16 for each VNet (hub and per-spoke). Use /24 for each subnet. Reserve /22 per spoke for AKS pod CIDR (AKS needs a large contiguous block for pods — typically /16 within the cluster but the node subnet must be sized accordingly). Leave at least 50% headroom in each VNet for growth.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Azure reserves 5 IPs per subnet. AKS with kubenet or Azure CNI requires large pod CIDRs that overflow small subnets. Planning /24 subnets avoids the common /28 or /27 that runs out immediately when adding NAT Gateway, App Gateway, and Bastion reserved IPs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hub VNet MUST NOT overlap with any spoke VNet or on-premises range. Spoke VNets MUST NOT overlap with each other. Use a CIDR allocation table (Markdown or spreadsheet) as the source of truth before writing any Terraform.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Peering fails immediately if CIDRs overlap. On-premises VPN/ER routes are also rejected. There is no in-place re-IP; you must delete and recreate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Application Gateway subnets MUST include a delegation to `Microsoft.Network/applicationGateways` (required since 2025). AKS node subnets MAY include delegation to `Microsoft.ContainerService/managedClusters`. PostgreSQL Flexible Server subnets MUST include delegation to `Microsoft.DBforPostgreSQL/flexibleServers`. Delegated subnets MUST be dedicated — no other resource types allowed in the same subnet.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">App Gateway v2 deploy fails without delegation as of 2025. Mixing non-delegated resources in a delegated subnet causes intermittent plan failures or silent drift on re-apply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>VNet peering MUST be created in BOTH directions (hub→spoke AND spoke→hub). A one-directional peering completes in the portal but traffic fails silently. Set `allow_forwarded_traffic = true` on both sides and `allow_gateway_transit = true` on the hub side when a VPN Gateway or ExpressRoute Gateway is present.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents routinely create only one peering direction, the plan shows no errors, and connectivity fails. Both directions are required for the peering to be in Connected state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never run `az network vnet create` or `az network vnet peering create` ad-hoc. All VNet changes MUST go through `terraform plan` review before apply.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ad-hoc changes create drift that breaks subsequent Terraform runs and produces stale state files.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
