<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sunset vs Fold Framework Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Sunset vs Fold Framework plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="criteria-matrix-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The decision MUST score the candidate product on five criteria (revenue, strategic adjacency, migration cost, team morale, customer concentration); decisions without the matrix MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — product-discontinuation audit 2025">Sunset vs fold is high-stakes and irreversible; the matrix is the structural gate against gut-only calls.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="fold-requires-receiving-product-owner-consent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Folding capability into another product MUST be ratified by the receiving product's owner in writing; unilateral folds MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — product-merge incident 2024-Q4">Unilateral folds create resentment and shipping debt; written consent is the only durable contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sunset-has-named-migration-path" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sunsets MUST publish a named migration path (alternative product, data export, refund policy) before the kill date; migration-less sunsets MUST be delayed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Killed By Google patterns">Sunsets without migration paths trigger refund waves and reputational damage; the migration path is the structural floor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="customer-notice-90-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Customer notice MUST be ≥90 days before the sunset date; shorter notice requires legal sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaS contract norms">Sub-90-day notice causes contractual breaches on annual contracts; 90 days is the safe default.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="decision-record-versioned-signed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The decision record MUST be versioned and signed by the founder + at least one VP; verbal decisions MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — decision-record convention">Verbal decisions on sunsets get re-litigated quarterly; the signed record is the closure mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
