<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-principles" title="Living Documentation Core Principles">
  <summary>Rules for treating documentation as code: co-location, auto-generation boundaries, and CI enforcement.</summary>

  <section title="Docs-as-Code Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store documentation in the same repository as the code it describes, updated in the same PR.</statement>
      <rationale>Co-location ensures the same review process catches doc drift. Separate wikis always lag behind code changes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every auto-generated section with `&lt;!-- AUTO-GENERATED: source=openapi.yaml --&gt;`. Never edit content inside AUTO-GENERATED boundaries manually or with an agent.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-generated sections are overwritten on the next generation pass. Manual edits inside them are silently lost. The tag makes the boundary explicit for both humans and agents.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Documentation failures (broken links, invalid API spec, failed build) must block the CI pipeline the same way test failures do.</statement>
      <rationale>Documentation that does not block deploys is treated as optional. Optional docs are not maintained.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="What to Auto-Generate vs Hand-Author">
    <list>
      <item>Auto-generate: API reference (from OpenAPI/JSDoc), changelogs (from conventional commits), code examples (from tests)</item>
      <item>Hand-author: Architecture Decision Records, design rationale, user guides, tutorials, onboarding docs</item>
    </list>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent overwrites an entire docs page on re-run, including manually-authored introduction sections.</description>
      <reason>Without AUTO-GENERATED tags, agents have no boundary to respect. Use explicit section markers and instruct agents to only update content between those tags.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write `llms.txt` at the repo root with one-line descriptions of top-level doc sections. Do not copy full section content into llms.txt — link to full pages instead.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents and LLM tools use llms.txt as a navigation index, not as full content. Over-detailed llms.txt files waste context budget on the index itself.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
