<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-toolchain" title="Living Documentation Toolchain">
  <summary>Generator selection criteria, linting tools, and CI pipeline steps for Docs-as-Code.</summary>

  <section title="Generator Selection">
    <list>
      <item>MkDocs + Material: Python projects, technical docs, fast builds, Material theme</item>
      <item>Docusaurus: Node.js/React projects, developer portals, MDX support</item>
      <item>VitePress: Vue projects, very fast builds</item>
      <item>Starlight (Astro): modern DX, content collections with Zod schemas</item>
    </list>

    <rule>
      <statement>Run `mkdocs build --strict` (or equivalent `--fail-on-warning`) in CI to catch broken references before deploy.</statement>
      <rationale>Non-strict builds silently skip broken includes and missing pages. Strict mode surfaces all issues at build time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Linting Pipeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add three linting steps to the docs CI job: prose lint (Vale), link validation (linkinator), and API spec validation (Spectral for OpenAPI).</statement>
      <rationale>Each tool catches a different failure class: Vale catches style drift, linkinator catches broken URLs, Spectral catches spec regressions. Running all three is the minimum viable doc quality gate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Running Vale with default rules on technical writing without customization.</description>
      <reason>Default Vale rules produce too many false positives on technical prose (passive voice warnings, capitalization rules). Configure `.vale.ini` and disable overly aggressive rules before using in CI.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents updating OpenAPI specs without running a breaking-change check.</description>
      <reason>Renamed fields and removed endpoints are breaking changes. Run `redocly diff` or `bump.sh diff` before committing spec changes to surface regressions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/docs-ci.yaml">GitHub Actions workflow for the complete docs CI pipeline</reference>
  <reference path="templates/mkdocs.yml">MkDocs Material configuration with recommended plugins</reference>
</text>
