<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="data-driven-requirements">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>Apply data analytics to requirements engineering for evidence-based prioritization. Six adoption gates, minimum infrastructure stack, agentic workflow, and AI gotchas.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>data-driven</tag>
      <tag>analytics</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>evidence-based</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Data-Driven Requirements Engineering</title>

    <summary>Apply data analytics to requirements engineering. Use evidence-based approaches to prioritization and validation. This is the BA-core variant covering fundamentals; deeper metric-layer and A/B-power material lives in the business-analyst sibling.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Requirements are typically based on stakeholder opinions rather than evidence, and prioritization is often political rather than value-based. Success metrics are defined after implementation rather than before, and analytics capabilities are underutilized in requirements definition.</p>
      <p>Data-driven BA practice starts at adoption gate G1 (structured events + one queryable store) and progresses through G6 (post-hoc validation discipline). The honest BA-core position: a Postgres read replica plus Metabase plus a metrics.md file is enough to do honest data-driven requirements for a team of fewer than 50 people.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>The team has at least one production system emitting structured events for 90+ days, and someone can already pull a baseline number from it.</item>
        <item>Stakeholders disagree on priority and the disagreement is resolvable by a metric (usage, revenue, error rate).</item>
        <item>A requirement under discussion has a measurable current state and a plausibly measurable target.</item>
        <item>Recurring rework or post-launch "we shipped the wrong thing" is attributed to opinion-based prioritization.</item>
        <item>BA is being asked for evidence by a finance/risk/steerco audience.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-product or pre-launch with no users — any "data" will be a vanity sample; use qualitative discovery instead.</item>
        <item>The org has zero data infrastructure: no event tracking, no warehouse, no BI — build the minimum infra first before claiming the practice.</item>
        <item>One-off compliance/legal/contractual requirements where the answer is "must, by date X."</item>
        <item>Pure UX/brand/accessibility floor work where the metric is downstream perception.</item>
        <item>Two-day decisions where running a baseline query costs more than shipping and reverting.</item>
        <item>Teams that won't agree on a single metric definition.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="data-driven-ba-competencies">
      <list>
        <item>Statistical Analysis — Validate assumptions with data</item>
        <item>Data Visualization — Communicate insights to stakeholders</item>
        <item>SQL/BI Tools — Extract and analyze business data</item>
        <item>A/B Testing — Validate solution options</item>
        <item>Predictive Analytics — Forecast feature impact</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="evidence-based-requirements-process">
      <p>The evidence-based requirements process flows from business question to built requirement: Business Question → Data Collection → Analysis → Insight → Requirement. Each step maps to a concrete action: What problem? | What data? | What pattern? | So what? | What to build?</p>
    </section>

    <section name="key-analytics-trends-2025-2026">
      <list>
        <item>91.9% of organizations gain measurable value from data/analytics</item>
        <item>65% of organizations have adopted or are investigating AI for analytics</item>
        <item>Data-driven companies are 23x more likely to acquire customers</item>
        <item>95% of enterprise AI projects fail without solid data strategy</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="analytics-informed-prioritization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prioritization MUST consider four metric types: usage data (page views, feature adoption), performance data (error rates, load times), business metrics (conversion, revenue), and customer feedback (NPS, support tickets).</statement>
        <rationale>Single-metric prioritization misses trade-offs between adoption and profitability, between user volume and user value.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="self-service-analytics-for-bas">
      <p>Modern tools enable BAs to perform analytics without data science expertise. BI dashboards (Tableau, Power BI) support KPI monitoring and trend analysis. SQL interfaces (Mode, Looker) enable custom data queries. No-code analytics (Dataiku, Alteryx) automate analysis workflows. NLP query tools (ThoughtSpot) allow natural language data exploration.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-ml-roi-measurement-framework">
      <p>Measure impact across four areas: Operational Efficiency (cycle time, throughput, error rate, rework %), Experience &amp; Growth (CSAT/NPS, conversion rate, retention), Financial (cost-to-serve, gross margin, working capital), and Risk &amp; Compliance (policy violations avoided, audit hours saved).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="adoption-gates">
      <p>Do not bolt this practice on without checking the team's stage. Each gate must be cleared before the next. G1 requires events emitted (≥1 event stream with user_id, event_name, timestamp). Without it, you have guesses. G2 requires one queryable store (DB read replica OR warehouse OR product-analytics tool with SQL); without it, you are hostage to whoever runs reports. G3 requires shared metric definition (at least 3 KPIs documented: formula, owner, source, refresh); without it, you have inconsistent baselines. G4 requires one "north-star" KPI per surface agreed across PM/BA/Eng; without it, priority debates lack a tiebreaker. G5 requires baseline freshness rule ("stale after N days" stamped on every baseline); without it, requirements are written off aging numbers. G6 requires validation discipline (each shipped requirement has a post-hoc "did the metric move?" check); without it, the learning loop is broken.</p>
      <p>A BA practice at G1-G2 should write data-informed requirements (numbers as evidence, not the verdict). G3+ is where data-driven prioritization becomes honest.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="minimum-data-infrastructure">
      <p>The fundamentals do not require a warehouse. Event capture at minimum requires a server-side event log to a single table (events(user_id, event, ts, props_json)). Storage can be a Postgres read replica or a single PostHog instance. Query interface can be psql, PostHog SQL, or Metabase question. Metric definitions should be a markdown metrics.md in the repo with formula and owner per KPI. Visualization can be Metabase (OSS) or Superset (OSS); both are free. Experimentation can start with manual feature flag plus cohort comparison; no platform required. Catalog and lineage can be the same metrics.md plus a glossary in Notion. Quality checks can be a weekly SELECT sanity script.</p>
      <p>The honest BA-core position: a Postgres read replica plus Metabase plus a metrics.md is enough to do honest data-driven requirements for a team of fewer than 50 people. Anything heavier is premature.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive the BA-core variant as a three-pass loop, simpler than the business-analyst pipeline. (1) Frame — a sonnet agent reads the requirement draft and outputs {business_question, candidate_kpi, hypothesis, data_source_guess}. (2) Baseline — a sonnet agent runs (or asks a human to run) one SQL or PostHog query, returns {kpi, value, n, as_of, query_url}; refuses values without n and as_of. (3) Wire-up — an opus agent rewrites the requirement using the README template, fills baseline plus target plus measurement method, and lists the one validation step that will be checked post-launch. Humans own: business-question framing, target ambition, and the post-launch yes/no review.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-brainstorm — diverge on candidate KPIs and on what "success" actually means before a baseline is fetched.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — gate the requirement file: refuses entries with missing baseline, missing as_of, missing measurement method, or "TBD" success metric.</item>
        <item>faion-feature-executor — execute the implementation tasks once the requirement passes the gate, scoped by the success criteria.</item>
        <item>faion-improver — quarterly meta-loop: read the requirements shipped 1–2 quarters ago, re-fetch the success metric, log calibration error per author.</item>
        <item>metric-lookup-agent — input {kpi_name}, output {formula, owner, source_query, last_refresh} from the team's metrics.md catalog. Refuses unknown KPI names.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>psql — Run baseline SQL against the prod read replica; the cheapest viable analytics stack. Bundled with PostgreSQL.</item>
        <item>posthog (REST) — Self-hosted/SaaS product analytics with first-class API; pull funnels and retention. https://posthog.com/docs/api</item>
        <item>metabase (REST) — Open-source BI; agents read saved questions as canonical KPI sources. https://www.metabase.com/docs/latest/api</item>
        <item>dbt (optional, post-G3) — Version-controlled metric definitions. https://docs.getdbt.com</item>
        <item>csvkit / duckdb — Local sanity checks on exported CSVs. pip install csvkit duckdb</item>
        <item>pandas + scipy.stats — Confidence intervals on baselines, segment splits, sanity stats. pip install pandas scipy</item>
        <item>gh + jq — Pull GitHub issue counts / labels as supplementary baselines. https://cli.github.com</item>
        <item>claude CLI — Run the frame / baseline-prompt / wire-up passes. https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/claude-code</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <list>
        <item>PostHog (self-hosted) — OSS, agent-friendly (REST + SQL). Single-server install covers events plus funnels plus dashboards; ideal BA-core default.</item>
        <item>Metabase — OSS, agent-friendly (REST API). Cheap BI; agents reference saved questions as the canonical baseline source.</item>
        <item>Postgres read replica — OSS, agent-friendly (psql / DB drivers). The most underrated analytics stack; works until ~50 GB / 10M events.</item>
        <item>GA4 — SaaS (free), agent-friendly (Data API). Web-traffic baseline; small-team default for marketing-side requirements.</item>
        <item>Stripe (data API) — SaaS, agent-friendly (REST). System of record for revenue baselines; cross-check against product analytics.</item>
        <item>Notion / Confluence — SaaS, read-only. Where the metrics.md catalog lives if there's no monorepo.</item>
        <item>Superset — OSS, agent-friendly (REST). Heavier than Metabase; defer until governance demands it.</item>
        <item>Mixpanel / Amplitude — SaaS, agent-friendly (REST). Step up from PostHog when behavioural-graph features are needed.</item>
        <item>GrowthBook — OSS, agent-friendly (REST + SDK). Lightweight A/B platform when one experiment per quarter becomes routine.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adoption-stage mismatch: a BA practice that pushes data-driven requirements before the org has a reliable warehouse.</description>
        <reason>Tag the practice's maturity (see "Adoption gates") and don't skip stages. Requirements with placeholder baselines that nobody trusts fail faster than no requirements at all.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Definition drift: "active user" means three different things in three dashboards.</description>
        <reason>Without a metric catalog, two BAs pull contradicting baselines for the same KPI on the same day. Keep a single metrics.md before reaching for a metric layer.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Survivorship bias: heavy users skew the data.</description>
        <reason>The cohort that already churned is invisible — the requirement looks well-justified and is solving the wrong problem. Slice baselines by ≥1 dimension (channel, plan, geo).</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Single-source bias: pulling from one tool (just GA, just Mixpanel) inherits that tool's tracking gaps.</description>
        <reason>Cross-check with the system of record (DB, Stripe, support tickets) before locking a baseline.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Confidence theater: stamping a number doesn't make it correct.</description>
        <reason>Always include n, as_of, and source_url next to every baseline. A number without those three is gossip.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Causal claims from correlational data: "users of feature X retain 2x" almost never means "shipping X for everyone doubles retention."</description>
        <reason>Self-selection eats the effect. Add a causal_evidence_type field; observational claims must be hedged.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy/consent: requirements built on data the org cannot lawfully use under GDPR/CCPA.</description>
        <reason>Fail at legal review even when statistically sound. Restrict warehouse roles, and run a redaction-checker before commit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Dashboard fixation: BAs start prioritizing what's easy to query (page views) over what matters (retained revenue).</description>
        <reason>Tie every metric to one sentence about the business outcome it maps to. If the BA can't write that sentence, the KPI is vanity.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Start at G1–G2; write data-informed (not data-driven) requirements until G3 is real.</item>
        <item>Keep a single metrics.md in the product repo before reaching for a metric layer.</item>
        <item>Always include n, as_of, and source_url next to every baseline.</item>
        <item>One primary metric plus one guardrail per requirement.</item>
        <item>Tie every metric to one sentence about the business outcome it maps to.</item>
        <item>Reject any baseline that came from a screenshot. Insist on a query URL or dashboard link.</item>
        <item>Pre-decide what counts as "post-launch success" before shipping; revisit on a calendar trigger.</item>
        <item>Refuse to score requirements with KPIs not in metrics.md.</item>
        <item>Treat agents as drafters, humans as deciders for: (a) the business question, (b) target ambition, (c) ship/no-ship after measurement.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs invent plausible KPI values without citation.</description>
        <reason>Force every cell to cite a source URL or query, and have a verifier agent re-run the query.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents collapse different metric definitions ("conversion", "completion", "purchase") into a single number.</description>
        <reason>Resolve names against metrics.md first. This blocks the most common silent failure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Date drift: an agent fetched a baseline last week and will reuse it forever.</description>
        <reason>Add the freshness gate as a finalization step. Enforce as_of in the schema.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Vanity-metric capture: agents pick the easiest-to-query metric over the most-business-relevant one.</description>
        <reason>Constrain the schema to require a downstream business KPI (revenue, retention) and a "why this matters" sentence per requirement.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sycophancy: an agent finds data supporting whatever the question implies.</description>
        <reason>Add a counter-evidence pass before finalization: "find the strongest signal that this requirement should NOT be built."</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy leak: agents may pull PII columns into the evidence section.</description>
        <reason>Restrict warehouse roles, and run a redaction-checker before commit.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adoption-gate denial: agents will happily produce data-driven requirements at G1 with placeholder baselines.</description>
        <reason>Hard-code the gate in the prompt: refuse to ship a requirement labeled "data-driven" if metrics.md has fewer than 3 KPIs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>BA-core data-driven requirement writer: inputs are business_question, draft_requirement, baseline (kpi, value, n, as_of, source_url), target_state. Output the populated README template. Constraints: reject if baseline.n is missing or less than 30, or as_of older than 60 days. Every success metric MUST have a measurement_method that is either a SQL/event name or a dashboard URL; no "user feedback" without a structured signal. Define ONE primary metric and at most ONE guardrail metric (BA-core scope — multi-metric portfolios belong in the business-analyst variant). Output a one-line "why this metric ties to a business outcome" sentence. If you cannot fill any cell from the inputs, write "UNKNOWN — needs human" rather than inventing a number.</p>
      <p>Metric-lookup agent: input kpi_name. Read team metrics.md. Output JSON: {known: bool, formula, owner, source_query, last_refresh}. If known=false, return suggested_aliases[] from fuzzy match and refuse to proceed. Never invent a definition.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="example-metrics-catalog">
      <p>The 5-file methodology pack here (checklist, templates, examples, llm-prompts) is currently a stub; the README's "Data-Driven Requirements Template" is the canonical doc shell. Below is a minimum metrics.md block — the foundation the practice depends on.</p>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# metrics.md — team metric catalog

## checkout_conversion
- formula: COUNT(checkout_completed) / COUNT(checkout_started) within session
- owner: @growth-pm
- source: events table (server-side); confirm against Stripe `payment_intents.succeeded`
- refresh: hourly (Metabase Q-117)
- aliases: cvr, conversion, completion_rate
- last_validated: 2026-04-10
- known caveats: includes refunds for 24h; exclude with `status != 'refunded'`

## monthly_active_users
- formula: COUNT(DISTINCT user_id) WHERE event IN ('app_open','api_call') over 30d rolling
- owner: @product
- source: events; PostHog persons API as cross-check
- refresh: daily 06:00 UTC (Metabase Q-23)
- aliases: mau, active_30d
- last_validated: 2026-04-12
- known caveats: bot traffic excluded via user_agent regex; doc in source query
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="freshness-validation-shell-helper">
      <p>A 10-line shell helper to refuse stale baselines at requirement-finalisation time:</p>
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/env bash
# fresh_baseline.sh — usage: fresh_baseline.sh <as_of_date> <max_days>
set -euo pipefail
as_of="${1:?as_of date required (YYYY-MM-DD)}"
max="${2:-30}"
age=$(( ( $(date +%s) - $(date -d "$as_of" +%s) ) / 86400 ))
if (( age > max )); then
  echo "STALE: baseline is ${age}d old; max=${max}d. Re-run query before commit." >&2
  exit 2
fi
echo "FRESH: baseline ${age}d old (limit ${max}d)."
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="when-not-to-use-data-driven-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not attempt data-driven requirements without at least one of the adoption gates G1–G3 complete. Tag the practice's maturity explicitly and do not skip stages.</statement>
        <rationale>Requirements with placeholder baselines that nobody trusts fail faster than no requirements at all. Honesty about the stage builds trust.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="metric-definition-drift-prevention">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep a single metrics.md in the product repo before reaching for a metric layer. Always include n, as_of, and source_url next to every baseline.</statement>
        <rationale>Definition drift ("active user" means three different things in three dashboards) breaks downstream consistency. The discipline of writing definitions matters more than the tool.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-model-selection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Task allocation: Haiku for pattern matching and extraction. Sonnet for BA expertise and validation. Opus for complex business analysis and trade-off reasoning.</statement>
        <rationale>Sonnet is the efficient choice for most BA-core work. Opus adds value only when reasoning about competing business priorities or causal inference.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="example-data-driven-requirements-template">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Requirement: [ID] [Name]

## Business Context
- **Business Question:** [What problem are we solving?]
- **Current State Data:** [Baseline metrics]
- **Target State:** [Expected improvement]

## Evidence

### Data Sources
| Source | Metric | Current Value | Confidence |
|--------|--------|---------------|------------|
| [System] | [Metric] | [Value] | High/Med/Low |

### Analysis Summary
[Key findings from data analysis]

### Supporting Evidence
- [Link to dashboard]
- [Link to analysis]

## Requirement Specification
[Requirement statement]

## Success Metrics
| Metric | Baseline | Target | Measurement Method |
|--------|----------|--------|-------------------|
| [Primary] | [Value] | [Value] | [How measured] |
| [Secondary] | [Value] | [Value] | [How measured] |

## Validation Plan
- [ ] A/B test design defined
- [ ] Sample size calculated
- [ ] Success criteria documented
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <list>
        <item>BABOK Guide v3 — Strategy Analysis (§6) and Solution Evaluation (§8)</item>
        <item>Croll &amp; Yoskovitz — Lean Analytics (one-metric-that-matters, stage-appropriate KPIs)</item>
        <item>Davenport &amp; Harris — Competing on Analytics (analytics-first decision-making)</item>
        <item>DAMA-DMBOK 2 — Data Management Body of Knowledge</item>
        <item>https://posthog.com/docs/data — PostHog metrics + SQL data layer (OSS reference, BA-core friendly)</item>
        <item>https://www.metabase.com/learn/grow-your-data-skills/data-fundamentals — Metabase fundamentals</item>
        <item>https://docs.getdbt.com/docs/build/metrics — dbt semantic layer (step-up reference once at G3+)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </content>
</methodology>
