<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="process-mining-automation Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for process-mining-automation. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply process mining to reconstruct actual process flows from IT system event logs before documenting process requirements or selecting automation candidates. Do not rely on stakeholder interviews alone for process discovery — actual execution diverges from documented processes in the majority of cases.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stakeholder interviews capture the ideal process; event logs capture what actually happens. RPA initiatives built on interview-based process models fail because they automate the documented process, not the real one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Process mining follows four steps in sequence: (1) Event Log Extraction — extract case ID, activity, timestamp from IT systems; (2) Process Discovery — generate actual process model from event log; (3) Conformance Checking — compare discovered model to documented design, identify deviations and their frequency; (4) Enhancement — use deviation analysis to identify bottlenecks, rework loops, and automation candidates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping conformance checking (step 3) produces a "what is" model without identifying where and how often the process deviates from intent — the most actionable output for process improvement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score every automation candidate against six criteria: Volume (high = more than 100 transactions/day), Standardization (high = rule-based with few exceptions), Stability (medium = process unchanged more than 6 months), Digital Input (medium = structured data available), Error Rate (medium = high manual error frequency), ROI Potential (high = high labor cost with measurable payback). Total out of 30. Recommend: full automation above 24, partial automation 18-24, process improvement first 12-18, not suitable below 12.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a scoring matrix, automation selection is based on who has the loudest stakeholder voice. The matrix forces objective measurement across dimensions that predict automation success.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
