<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process-mining" title="Process Mining for Business Analysts">
  <summary>Process mining definition, BA competencies required, four-step workflow, and tool landscape.</summary>

  <section title="Definition and Purpose">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply process mining to reconstruct actual process flows from IT system event logs before documenting process requirements or selecting automation candidates. Do not rely on stakeholder interviews alone for process discovery — actual execution diverges from documented processes in the majority of cases.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholder interviews capture the ideal process; event logs capture what actually happens. RPA initiatives built on interview-based process models fail because they automate the documented process, not the real one.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Required BA Competencies">
    <list>
      <item>Technical: ProM, Disco, or Celonis (process mining tools), SQL for event log extraction, data visualization for conformance reports</item>
      <item>Process: BPMN 2.0 notation, process modeling, workflow variance analysis</item>
      <item>Analytical: statistics (frequency distributions, variant analysis), pattern recognition, root-cause analysis of process deviations</item>
      <item>Domain: industry-specific knowledge to interpret discovered process variants and regulatory understanding for compliance-sensitive processes</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Four-Step Mining Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Process mining follows four steps in sequence: (1) Event Log Extraction — extract case ID, activity, timestamp from IT systems; (2) Process Discovery — generate actual process model from event log; (3) Conformance Checking — compare discovered model to documented design, identify deviations and their frequency; (4) Enhancement — use deviation analysis to identify bottlenecks, rework loops, and automation candidates.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping conformance checking (step 3) produces a "what is" model without identifying where and how often the process deviates from intent — the most actionable output for process improvement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tool Landscape">
    <list>
      <item>Celonis: process mining market leader, enterprise SaaS, strong action orientation and EMS (execution management system) integration</item>
      <item>Disco (Fluxicon): desktop tool, fast for initial exploration, imports XES and CSV event logs</item>
      <item>ProM: open-source research platform, most algorithms, requires technical expertise</item>
      <item>Microsoft Power Automate Process Advisor: M365-integrated process mining for organizations already in the Microsoft ecosystem</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
