<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="seven-performance-domains">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>PMBOK 8 replaces 10 Knowledge Areas with seven performance domains for value delivery, systems thinking, and sustainability integration.</summary>
    <category>pmbok</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
    <tags>
      <tag>pmbok8</tag>
      <tag>domains</tag>
      <tag>performance</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Seven Performance Domains (PMBOK 8)</title>

    <summary>PMBOK 8 replaces the 10 Knowledge Areas with seven performance domains — Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk — as the primary PM rubric. Quality, Communications, and Procurement are absorbed into these domains rather than standing alone. The framework shifts emphasis from process compliance to value delivery, systems thinking, sustainability, and governance integration.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Domain-based framing produces more actionable health checks than process-group-based framing: each domain maps to one accountable person and produces a measurable RAG status rather than a checklist of artifacts. Agents can score a project against seven explicit axes and surface cross-domain cause/effect chains (e.g., Resources Red leads to Schedule Amber) that process-group audits routinely miss.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Greenfield PMO design where you would otherwise default to PMBOK 6 process groups.</item>
        <item>Project audits and health checks — domains give a structured rubric (one section per domain).</item>
        <item>Tailoring conversations: which domains apply to this project, with what intensity?</item>
        <item>PM certification alignment (PMP exam content since 2023+ leans on these domains).</item>
        <item>Coaching new PMs to think in outcomes rather than artifact production.</item>
        <item>Trigger words in user request: project health check, RAG status, PMO rubric, PMBOK 8, value realization audit, domain owner RACI.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Deep technical execution decisions — domains are PM-level abstractions, not engineering rubrics.</item>
        <item>Pure agile teams already running Scrum + product OKRs without a separate domain map.</item>
        <item>Teams committed to PMBOK 6 under a regulator's mandate — switching costs more than it returns.</item>
        <item>Day-to-day sprint operations — domains live at portfolio/program tempo, not stand-up tempo.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <step>Locate or create the project corpus root: charter, plan, risk register, last 4 status reports, sponsor decision log. If any artifact is missing, mark its domain as "not addressed" rather than guessing.</step>
      <step>Instantiate the manifest template at templates/domains.yaml in the project's PM folder (e.g. .product/pm/domains.yaml). One file per project.</step>
      <step>Assign one Accountable owner per domain in the manifest. No domain is left blank — if one person holds multiple, list the same name on each.</step>
      <step>Run the domain-health-checker prompt (see prompt block below) over the corpus. For each of the 7 domains, capture status (R/A/G), 2-3 evidence quotes with source path, and one top recommendation.</step>
      <step>Validate every Amber/Red rating with a quoted artifact line; reject ratings without evidence and re-score.</step>
      <step>Map cross-domain chains (Resources Red leads to Schedule Amber, etc.) and pick the single domain whose fix unblocks the most others — sequence remediation, do not parallelize.</step>
      <step>Compute the value realization rate (outcomes realized / outputs shipped) and record it alongside delivery metrics.</step>
      <step>Persist the manifest, commit it to the project repo, and schedule monthly re-scoring plus event triggers (incident, scope change, leadership change).</step>
      <step>Run the verify procedure below to confirm the manifest is complete and lint-clean before publishing the report.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="domain-map">
      <p>Seven domains replace the ten Knowledge Areas. Quality, Communications, and Procurement are absorbed — not removed — into the remaining domains. All domains operate concurrently; none is sequential to another.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign one accountable domain owner per domain on every project, even when one person holds multiple domains.</statement>
        <rationale>Domains with no named owner drift to green in status reports regardless of actual health; accountability produces honest reporting.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="governance">
      <p>Replaces Integration Management. Covers oversight, decision frameworks, and value realization tracking.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Establish project authority and decision rights</item>
        <item>Link project outcomes to portfolio value</item>
        <item>Manage change control and escalation paths</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="scope">
      <p>Enhanced definition over PMBOK 6 Scope Management. Requires explicit documented scope boundaries, not just a scope statement.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Define and baseline what is in scope and out of scope</item>
        <item>Control scope changes through the governance domain</item>
        <item>Validate deliverables against acceptance criteria</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="schedule">
      <p>Same focus as PMBOK 6 Time Management. Covers plan, sequence, estimate, and control timelines and dependencies.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Identify all activities and dependencies</item>
        <item>Develop schedule with critical path and resource constraints</item>
        <item>Monitor schedule performance and forecast completion</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="finance">
      <p>Replaces Cost Management. Broader financial lens including ROI, benefits realization, and financial risk.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Develop and baseline budget</item>
        <item>Track actual vs. planned expenditure (EVM optional)</item>
        <item>Forecast financial performance and report to sponsors</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="stakeholders">
      <p>Now absorbs Communications. Single domain for identifying, analyzing, engaging, and communicating with all stakeholders.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Build and maintain stakeholder register</item>
        <item>Develop engagement strategies per stakeholder segment</item>
        <item>Plan and execute communications — frequency, channel, tone</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating Communications as automatic once it is absorbed into Stakeholders.</description>
        <reason>Without an explicit comms plan, communications gets under-invested and stakeholder satisfaction drops regardless of delivery quality.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="resources">
      <p>Enhanced focus on both human and physical resources. Covers acquisition, development, and management.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Acquire team members and physical resources</item>
        <item>Develop team capability (see team-development methodology)</item>
        <item>Manage resource conflicts and availability</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="risk">
      <p>Same focus as PMBOK 6 Risk Management. Covers identify, analyze, respond to, and monitor uncertainties.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Identify risks and opportunities systematically</item>
        <item>Analyze probability and impact</item>
        <item>Implement responses and monitor risk register</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="new-emphases-in-pmbok-8">
      <p>Four critical shifts define PMBOK 8 philosophy:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Value Delivery over output delivery — outputs shipped vs. outcomes realized tracked separately</item>
        <item>Systems Thinking — understand project in broader organizational context</item>
        <item>Sustainability — environmental, social, and economic impact; requires measurable metrics</item>
        <item>Governance Integration — stronger portfolio/program/project linkage</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Track value realization rate (outcomes realized / outputs shipped) alongside delivery metrics.</statement>
        <rationale>A 100% delivery rate with 30% value realization rate is the most common trap; domains must surface it explicitly.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="rag-assessment-procedure">
      <rule>
        <statement>Anchor every domain color rating with a quoted artifact (retro line, incident, missed milestone); ratings without evidence are not valid inputs.</statement>
        <rationale>Unanchored RAG ratings default to Green due to politeness bias; evidence quotes force the assessor to confront actual data.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-score domain RAG monthly minimum AND on triggers: incident, scope change, leadership change.</statement>
        <rationale>The value of the framework is the trend line, not the snapshot; trigger-based re-scoring catches mid-cycle regressions that monthly cadence misses.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Green: domain performing as expected, no gaps requiring action</item>
        <item>Amber: domain has a documented gap with an active remediation plan</item>
        <item>Red: domain has a critical gap with no remediation plan, or remediation failing</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="domain-owner-raci">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign one Accountable owner per domain; one person can hold multiple domains, but no domain can be unowned.</statement>
        <rationale>Domains with no named owner drift to Green in status reports regardless of actual health; accountability produces honest reporting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Typical domain-owner assignment:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Governance: PM or PMO lead</item>
        <item>Scope: PM or Product Owner</item>
        <item>Schedule: PM</item>
        <item>Finance: Sponsor or Finance lead</item>
        <item>Stakeholders: PM (communications included)</item>
        <item>Resources: Line Manager or PM</item>
        <item>Risk: PM with risk register owner</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cross-domain-interaction-chains">
      <p>Domains are interdependent; a Red in one domain typically cascades to Amber or Red in others. Understanding these chains enables prioritized remediation.</p>
      <p>Common interaction chains:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Resources Red leads to Schedule Amber (capacity gap delays delivery)</item>
        <item>Stakeholders Red leads to Finance Amber (sponsor disengagement delays approvals)</item>
        <item>Governance Red leads to Scope Amber (unclear decision rights cause scope creep)</item>
        <item>Risk Red leads to all domains (unmitigated risk materializes everywhere simultaneously)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>When multiple domains are Red, identify which single domain improvement unblocks the most others; fix that first.</statement>
        <rationale>Parallel remediation across all Red domains spreads PM attention too thin and produces no completed fixes; sequenced priority maximizes recovery velocity.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-where-it-fails">
      <p>PMBOK 8 domains are powerful but not comprehensive. Understand these limitations:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Brief / generic by design — agents need concrete prompts to make outputs actionable.</item>
        <item>Quality integrated everywhere sounds nice but in practice means quality gets nobody's attention; teams must pin it to a domain owner.</item>
        <item>Communications absorbed into Stakeholders means comms plans get under-invested; bring them back explicitly.</item>
        <item>Procurement moved to appendix means vendors / contractors fall through the cracks unless an explicit owner is named.</item>
        <item>Sustainability emphasis without local metrics is greenwashing; require domain checklists with measurable items.</item>
        <item>Domains overlap (Resources, Schedule, Finance) — risk of double-counting work in dashboards.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A health-check agent ingests a project's docs (charter, plan, risk register, status reports) and produces a per-domain RAG status (Red/Amber/Green) with evidence quotes.</p>
      <p>A planning agent generates a tailored domain intensity matrix per project — which domains need full treatment, which can be light.</p>
      <p>A reviewer agent checks every status report or deliverable against the domain rubric and flags gaps (e.g., no Stakeholders section in last 4 status reports).</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>domain-health-checker — scores each of the 7 domains on a project corpus and outputs RAG with citations.</item>
        <item>tailoring-advisor — recommends which domains to apply heavily vs. lightly, given project type.</item>
        <item>domain-rubric-linter — verifies status reports / deliverables cover all required domains.</item>
        <item>value-delivery-coach — surfaces output vs. outcome misalignments (work shipped vs. value realized).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <checklist>
      <check>Manifest file domains.yaml exists at the agreed PM folder and is valid YAML.</check>
      <check>All 7 domains (governance, scope, schedule, finance, stakeholders, resources, risk) appear in the manifest exactly once.</check>
      <check>Each domain has a non-empty owner field (no TBD, no blank, no team-name placeholder).</check>
      <check>Each domain has a status field of exactly green | amber | red.</check>
      <check>Every amber/red domain carries at least one evidence entry with quote and source_path.</check>
      <check>Every amber/red domain carries a remediation field with a named owner and target re-score date.</check>
      <check>The manifest contains value_realization with outputs_shipped, outcomes_realized, and rate (decimal 0..1).</check>
      <check>Quality findings are surfaced in a top-level cross_cutting.quality block, not silently scattered.</check>
      <check>Communications plan is present under stakeholders.comms_plan with cadence, channels, and audience segments.</check>
      <check>Procurement / vendor owner is named under resources.procurement_owner if any third-party is involved.</check>
      <check>Sustainability metrics are numeric or carry an explicit not_applicable_reason string.</check>
      <check>Last_scored is within the last 30 days OR a trigger event is logged in scoring_history.</check>
      <check>One next remediation domain is selected (sequenced, not parallel) under priority.next_focus.</check>
    </checklist>

    <commands>
      <command name="validate-manifest">python3 -c "import yaml,sys; d=yaml.safe_load(open('templates/domains.yaml')); req={'governance','scope','schedule','finance','stakeholders','resources','risk'}; have=set(d.get('domains',{}).keys()); missing=req-have; extra=have-req; assert not missing, f'missing: {missing}'; assert not extra, f'unexpected: {extra}'; print('OK 7 domains')"</command>
      <command name="check-owners">python3 -c "import yaml; d=yaml.safe_load(open('templates/domains.yaml')); bad=[k for k,v in d['domains'].items() if not v.get('owner') or v['owner'].lower() in ('tbd','tba','')]; assert not bad, f'unowned domains: {bad}'; print('OK all owners assigned')"</command>
      <command name="check-evidence">python3 -c "import yaml; d=yaml.safe_load(open('templates/domains.yaml')); bad=[k for k,v in d['domains'].items() if v['status'] in ('amber','red') and not v.get('evidence')]; assert not bad, f'amber/red without evidence: {bad}'; print('OK evidence present')"</command>
      <command name="value-realization-rate">python3 -c "import yaml; d=yaml.safe_load(open('templates/domains.yaml'))['value_realization']; r=d['outcomes_realized']/max(d['outputs_shipped'],1); print(f'rate={r:.0%} ({d[\"outcomes_realized\"]}/{d[\"outputs_shipped\"]})'); assert r>=0.5, 'value realization below 50% — escalate'"</command>
      <command name="rag-summary">python3 -c "import yaml; d=yaml.safe_load(open('templates/domains.yaml'))['domains']; [print(f'{k:14s} {v[\"status\"].upper():5s} {v.get(\"owner\",\"?\")}') for k,v in d.items()]"</command>
    </commands>

    <prompt purpose="domain-health-checker"><![CDATA[
You are domain-health-checker (PMBOK 8 v1, not PMBOK 7).

Inputs:
- corpus: list of {path, content} project documents
  (charter, plan, risk register, last 4 status reports, sponsor log)

For EACH of the 7 domains in this exact order:
  1. governance
  2. scope
  3. schedule
  4. finance
  5. stakeholders
  6. resources
  7. risk

Output one YAML block per domain with these fields:
  status: green | amber | red
  evidence:
    - quote: "<verbatim ≤200-char excerpt>"
      source_path: "<path from corpus>"
  recommendation: "<one imperative sentence, ≤140 chars>"
  owner_role_suggestion: "<role, not a person name>"

Rules (hard):
- Do NOT invent quotes. If a domain is unaddressed in the corpus
  output: status: not_addressed, evidence: [], recommendation: "Add coverage in next status report".
- Do NOT default to green. Calibration: if no evidence is found,
  status MUST be amber (gap) or not_addressed — never green.
- Anonymize people: use roles (e.g. "Sponsor", "Tech Lead"), not names.
- One inference per domain — do not conflate.
- After the 7 domain blocks output a final block:
    cross_cutting:
      quality: "<one finding or 'no quality signal in corpus'>"
      sustainability_metric: "<numeric or not_applicable: <reason>>"
      value_realization:
        outputs_shipped: <int>
        outcomes_realized: <int>

Calibration example (one Red exemplar, mandatory to anchor):
  schedule:
    status: red
    evidence:
      - quote: "Milestone M3 slipped 3 weeks; no updated baseline."
        source_path: "status/2026-04-15.md"
    recommendation: "Re-baseline schedule and publish revised critical path within 5 working days."
    owner_role_suggestion: "PM"
]]></prompt>

    <template path="templates/domains.yaml" purpose="Per-project domain status manifest with owner, evidence, gap fields, and value-realization tracking."/>

    <verify>
      <step>Run: python3 scripts/validate-methodology-xml.py skills/faion/knowledge/pro/pm/pm-agile/seven-performance-domains/methodology.xml — must print PASS.</step>
      <step>Run validate-manifest command above against the project's domains.yaml — exits 0 with "OK 7 domains".</step>
      <step>Run check-owners command — exits 0 with "OK all owners assigned"; no TBD/TBA tokens.</step>
      <step>Run check-evidence command — every amber/red domain has at least one quoted source_path.</step>
      <step>Run value-realization-rate command — prints a percentage; flag if below 50% and escalate to sponsor.</step>
      <step>Run rag-summary command — visual confirmation that all 7 domains have R/A/G status and an owner.</step>
      <step>Confirm scoring_history shows a re-score within the last 30 days OR a logged trigger event (incident, scope change, leadership change).</step>
      <step>Confirm priority.next_focus names exactly one domain; reject manifests that list multiple parallel "fix everything" priorities.</step>
      <step>Cross-check: the per-domain status colors match the cited evidence — if quote text contradicts a Green rating (e.g. mentions slippage/incident), re-score before publishing.</step>
    </verify>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Force every status report to have a section per domain — even one line each. Missing sections become the early warning.</item>
        <item>Pair Value Delivery tracking with shipped output tracking; a 100% delivery rate with 30% value rate is the most common trap.</item>
        <item>When tailoring, drop a domain with deliberate documentation; never silently. "We are not tracking Finance because budget is fixed annual" is fine; ignoring it is not.</item>
        <item>Run a domain owner RACI: each of the 7 domains has one accountable person, even if the same person owns multiple.</item>
        <item>For agile/hybrid programs, map ceremonies to domains (PI Planning to Schedule + Resources, Demos to Stakeholders + Value).</item>
        <item>Re-score domain RAG monthly minimum; the value of the framework is the trend line, not the snapshot.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common failure modes when using agents with the PMBOK 8 domain framework:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Agents over-classify everything as Green if not given calibration examples; provide one explicit Red exemplar in the prompt (see prompt block above).</item>
        <item>Quality mentions tend to scatter across all 7 domains, making it invisible — explicitly ask the agent to surface quality-related findings as a cross-cutting section.</item>
        <item>Sustainability gets hand-waved; require numeric metrics or "not applicable, justification:" with a reason.</item>
        <item>LLMs invent PMBOK 7 vocabulary in PMBOK 8 contexts (and vice versa); pin the version in system prompt.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder domain tempts agents into people-name name-dropping without consent — anonymize roles in shared outputs.</item>
        <item>Long corpora cause domain conflation; chunk by domain (one inference per domain) for higher signal.</item>
      </list>
      <warning>If the agent emits all-Green ratings on first pass, treat the output as invalid and re-prompt with the calibration exemplar. All-Green from a real project is statistically suspect and almost always reflects politeness bias rather than reality.</warning>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/domains.yaml" purpose="Per-project domain status manifest with owner, evidence, gap fields, and value-realization tracking."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/disciplined-agile"/>
      <link href="https://www.scrum.org/resources/blog/scrum-and-pmbok"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
