<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="error-prevention">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Design out errors before they happen using constraints, defaults, validation, and dialogs.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>error-prevention</tag>
      <tag>validation</tag>
      <tag>forms</tag>
      <tag>ux-heuristics</tag>
      <tag>usability</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Error Prevention</title>

    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #5: design out error conditions before they occur. Apply constraints, defaults, inline validation, and confirmation dialogs instead of error messages.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Prevention costs less than recovery. A constraint on a date field eliminates an entire class of invalid-input errors at zero user effort. Inline validation surfaces problems while context is fresh, not after a multi-field form is submitted. Confirmation dialogs protect against irreversible actions — but overuse causes dialog fatigue that defeats the purpose.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing form specs for missing input constraints, absent real-time validation, or unguarded destructive actions</item>
        <item>Reviewing API endpoint contracts for inputs accepted without server-side constraints</item>
        <item>Drafting confirmation dialog copy for delete, cancel-subscription, or bulk operations</item>
        <item>Reviewing code PRs for validation gaps: fields that accept any string where a constrained type is appropriate</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Replacing QA — error prevention is a design heuristic, not a test suite</item>
        <item>Adding confirmations to routine, easily reversible actions — dialog fatigue reduces effectiveness for genuinely dangerous actions</item>
        <item>Very early concept stage where form fields are not yet defined</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="error-types">
      <p>Slips: right intention, wrong action (e.g., clicking Delete instead of Edit). Mistakes: wrong intention from misunderstanding (e.g., user thinks a required field is optional). Prevention strategy differs by type: slips require constraints and confirmation; mistakes require clearer information and guidance.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-1-constraints">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Replace open text fields with constrained inputs (pickers, selects, steppers) whenever the valid value set is finite or format-bound.</statement>
        <rationale>A date picker eliminates the entire class of invalid-date errors at zero user effort. A dropdown for country eliminates spelling variations, case differences, and unknown country codes.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Constrained date input">
        <note>Date input: date picker that allows only valid dates. Quantity: min 1, max 99, +/- buttons. Country: dropdown list, not free text.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Unconstrained date entry">
        <note>Text field for date entry — accepts "31/02/2024", "Feb 31", "tomorrow", all of which fail downstream validation.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-2-smart-defaults">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pre-fill fields with the most likely correct value; require confirmation rather than entry from scratch.</statement>
        <rationale>Recognition is more reliable than recall. A pre-filled field that the user confirms is faster and less error-prone than a blank field the user must populate.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-3-inline-validation">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Validate on blur for most fields; validate on change only for password strength indicators.</statement>
        <rationale>On-change validation for standard fields triggers error states before users finish typing, which is frustrating and counterproductive. On blur gives feedback when the user signals they are done with the field.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-4-confirmation-dialogs">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use confirmation dialogs for irreversible or high-consequence actions only; never for routine, easily reversible operations.</statement>
        <rationale>Dialog fatigue from overuse causes users to dismiss confirmations without reading them, defeating the purpose. Reserve dialogs for permanent delete, subscription cancellation, and bulk destructive operations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The confirmation button label must name the specific object and action, not a generic "OK" or "Confirm".</statement>
        <rationale>Specific labels ("Delete 47 files") force users to process what they are confirming. Generic labels ("OK") are dismissed as reflexively as ad popups.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-5-format-guidance">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Show format hints before the user enters data (placeholder or helper text), not only as error messages after incorrect input.</statement>
        <rationale>Error messages after entry waste user effort. Pre-entry guidance prevents the error from occurring. Provide examples: "(XXX) XXX-XXXX" for phone, "MM/DD/YYYY" for date.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="strategy-6-suggestions-and-autocomplete">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Provide autocomplete on search, email, and address fields; provide auto-formatting for phone and credit card fields.</statement>
        <rationale>Autocomplete reduces entry errors by completing from a validated set. Auto-formatting normalizes input format and gives real-time feedback that the field is interpreting input correctly.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="text-field-patterns">
      <list>
        <item>Character counter for fields with limits (visible, updates as user types)</item>
        <item>Format hints before entry (placeholder or helper text), not only as error messages</item>
        <item>Autocomplete suggestions for email, address, and known value sets</item>
        <item>Real-time validation on blur (not on change, which triggers errors mid-typing)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="numeric-field-patterns">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use a numeric keyboard on mobile for any numeric field; apply min/max constraints; provide increment/decrement buttons for bounded ranges.</statement>
        <rationale>Numeric keyboard prevents letters from entering numeric fields. Min/max constraints prevent out-of-range values. Stepper buttons make small adjustments faster and less error-prone than direct entry.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="date-field-patterns">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always use a date picker for date input; never use a free text field for dates.</statement>
        <rationale>Free text date fields accept invalid dates (31st of February), format variations (MM/DD vs DD/MM), and relative terms ("next week") that require complex parsing and still produce errors at downstream validation.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="confirmation-dialog-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use confirmation dialogs only for: permanent delete, subscription cancellation, bulk destructive operations. Never for: saving a file, moving to trash (reversible), logging out, or any routine action.</statement>
        <rationale>Dialog overuse trains users to dismiss confirmations reflexively, defeating the protection mechanism for genuinely dangerous actions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Effective confirmation dialog">
        <note>"Delete 47 items permanently? This action cannot be undone. All selected files will be permanently removed." [Cancel] [Delete 47 Items] — specific, consequence-clear, Cancel is prominent.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Generic confirmation">
        <note>"Are you sure?" [Cancel] [OK] — vague consequence, generic button label, user may dismiss without reading.</note>
      </example>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Position Cancel as the default focus in confirmation dialogs for destructive actions.</statement>
        <rationale>The default focus determines what happens if the user presses Enter or Space without reading. Default-to-Cancel prevents accidental destructive action via keyboard.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="inline-validation-timing">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Validate on blur for standard fields; validate on change only for password strength indicators.</statement>
        <rationale>On-change validation for email, name, and other fields triggers error states before users finish typing, creating jarring red error messages that are immediately proven wrong as typing continues. Password strength is the exception because users benefit from real-time feedback while choosing a password.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="good-examples">
      <example type="good" title="Gmail compose error prevention">
        <note>Gmail compose: "Did you mean to attach a file?" detects the word "attached" in body without an attachment. Warns about empty subject line. Undo send option for 30 seconds. Each is a targeted prevention for a specific, common error.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Google Forms validation">
        <note>Google Forms: required fields marked with asterisk before user begins. Real-time validation catches format errors per field. Field types (email, number, date) constrain input to valid values. No errors discovered only at submit.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Amazon checkout error prevention">
        <note>Amazon checkout: address validation with suggestions as user types. Payment validation before order placed. Estimated delivery date shown before confirming. Order review screen before final submit.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="bad-examples">
      <example type="bad" title="Submit-only validation">
        <note>Long form where user fills all fields and clicks Submit, then sees 5 error messages at the top of the page. User must scroll up to find the first error, then navigate back to each field. All errors could have been caught inline as the user typed.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Unvalidated email input">
        <note>Email field accepts invalid format on input. Confirmation email fails to send. User never discovers the email was wrong until they wonder why they received no confirmation.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Validation only on form submit.</description>
        <reason>User wastes effort filling subsequent fields after making an error in an early field. Inline validation catches errors while context is fresh and the field is still in focus.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding confirmation dialogs to every action.</description>
        <reason>Dialog fatigue causes users to dismiss confirmations without reading them, defeating protection for genuinely dangerous actions. Reserve confirmations for irreversible, high-consequence actions only.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A Claude agent reads a form spec or component definition and applies the Error Prevention Audit template: for each field it identifies the input type, constraints that should be applied, appropriate validation timing, smart default opportunities, and whether any associated action is destructive enough to require confirmation. The output is a prioritized remediation list. For code reviews, the agent scans form handler code for missing server-side validation and unguarded mutation endpoints.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent to check that each form field in a spec has a defined validation rule in the acceptance criteria before the feature moves to implementation.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Zod (TypeScript): Runtime schema validation; enforce field constraints at the boundary.</p>
      <p>Yup: Alternative schema validation for forms; integrates with Formik/React Hook Form.</p>
      <p>Pydantic (Python): Server-side input validation with type enforcement.</p>
      <p>Axe-cli: Catch missing required field indicators and unlabeled inputs.</p>
      <p>HTMLHint: Check HTML forms for missing required, type, and autocomplete attributes.</p>
      <p>Datadog / Sentry (SaaS, API): Query real form error rates and error types to identify highest-impact prevention targets.</p>
      <p>FullStory (SaaS): Rage-click and dead-click data reveals where users hit unexpected errors.</p>
      <p>LogRocket (SaaS, API): Session replay plus console errors correlated; surfaces validation failures at scale.</p>
      <p>Formspree / Typeform (SaaS): Built-in validation; limited custom constraint configuration.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent reviews only the frontend form without also reviewing the API handler.</description>
        <reason>Client-side validation alone is insufficient. A missing constraint in the API handler allows invalid data from any client (API, curl, other frontends). Always audit both layers in the same pass.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent generates Zod/Pydantic schemas that miss cross-field validation rules.</description>
        <reason>Schemas generated from field lists do not account for dependencies (end date must be after start date, password must match confirmation). Flag cross-field validations as needing manual implementation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Prefer constrained input types (date pickers, select dropdowns, numeric steppers) over open text fields whenever the valid value set is finite or format-bound</item>
        <item>Validate on blur for most fields, on change for password strength indicators only — on-change validation for other fields triggers error states before users finish typing</item>
        <item>For destructive actions: make the confirmation button label specific to the action ("Delete 47 files" not "OK") and position Cancel as the default focus</item>
        <item>Apply autocomplete attributes to all personal data fields — browser autofill is the cheapest recognition/recall aid for repeat data entry</item>
        <item>Surface format hints before the user enters data (placeholder or helper text), not only after they make an error</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/error-prevention-audit.md" purpose="Audit table: fields, constraints, validation timing, defaults, destructive actions"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/slips/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/user-errors/"/>
      <link href="https://formsthatwork.com/"/>
      <link href="https://zod.dev/"/>
      <link href="https://docs.pydantic.dev/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
