<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="On-Call Rotation Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every new on-call rotation must satisfy at launch. These prevent the standard burnout pattern that surfaces 6-9 months into a poorly-designed rotation.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-explicit-charter-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Publish a one-page On-Call Charter to the team wiki before the first shift. It states: shift length, shift boundaries (24h cutover time), participating engineers, acknowledgement SLA, escalation tree (primary + secondary + manager), comp policy, swap policy, and the named "rotation owner" (one engineer responsible for changes).</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Book Chapter 11; PagerDuty Operations Maturity Model">An undocumented rotation defaults to whatever the loudest engineer remembers from their last job. The charter is the contract that prevents the loudest-engineer drift. It is the first thing a new joiner reads on day one of their first shadow shift.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Charter shift specification">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# On-Call Charter — Platform Team (effective 2026-06-01)

Shift length: 7 days (Mon 09:00 → Mon 09:00 local).
Tiers: primary + secondary. Primary acks first; secondary escalation after 8 min.
Ack SLA: 5 min for sev-1, 15 min for sev-2, no SLA for sev-3.
Comp: 1h time-off-in-lieu per off-hours page; max 8h/shift, paid out as cash above ceiling.
Swap: any engineer can swap with another with 48h notice via PagerDuty override.
Rotation owner: tech lead (rotates yearly).
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-ack-sla-per-severity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define an acknowledgement SLA per severity level (sev-1 = 5 min, sev-2 = 15 min, sev-3 = no SLA, batched in next business hour). Escalation to secondary fires automatically when the primary misses the ack window. The SLA is enforced in the paging tool, not by social pressure.</statement>
      <rationale source="incident-response data; SRE workbook chapter on escalation">An on-call without a paging-tool-enforced escalation defaults to the primary handling everything alone, even when asleep. Tool-enforced escalation removes the cognitive load on the primary ("am I OK to go to sleep?") and protects the customer's MTTR.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-two-tier-rotation-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to a two-tier rotation: primary engineer + secondary engineer per shift. The secondary is a real escalation, not a manager-symbol; they cover primary unavailability, take over after 4 consecutive pages in a single shift, and are the second pair of eyes on sev-1. Single-engineer rotation is allowed ONLY for teams of 5-7 with an external SRE retainer as the de-facto secondary.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE workbook on cognitive load; common burnout postmortems">A single-engineer rotation under unbounded page load is the single highest-correlation cause of on-call resignations. The secondary tier doubles the rotation cost but reduces the burnout cost asymmetrically — the difference between "I will quit" and "this is sustainable".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-comp-time-policy-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Off-hours work during on-call (any time outside the engineer's normal working hours) accrues compensation: typically 1 hour of time-off-in-lieu per off-hours page-and-respond, capped per shift, with cash payout above the cap. Policy is documented in the HR handbook with signatures from engineering leader and HR. Comp accrues automatically from the paging tool's event log.</statement>
      <rationale source="research on burnout in on-call rotations; labour-law requirements in EU, UK, Brazil for after-hours work">Unpaid 3 AM pages are the single most-cited driver of on-call resignations. Comp must be (a) automatic, (b) defaulted-on, (c) explicit in the handbook. Cap exists to prevent abuse; cash above the cap prevents the cap from becoming exploitative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-on-call-load-red-line" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define red-line thresholds on the on-call-load metric: more than 2 off-hours pages per shift OR more than 3 weekend pages per quarter triggers a load-reduction action: alert tuning, runbook automation, additional headcount, or temporary external SRE coverage. The red-line is checked weekly and reported to the engineering leader monthly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Book on on-call sustainability; toil-budget concept">Without a red-line, on-call load drifts upward as alerts proliferate. The red-line forces an action when load crosses a quantitative threshold, replacing "the on-call engineer feels burnt out" with "the metric breached its threshold this month".</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Onboarding new rotation members">
    <list>
      <item>Shadow period: 2 full shifts as silent observer on the secondary tier</item>
      <item>Supervised solo: 2 shifts as primary with the previous primary as named safety-net</item>
      <item>Certification: a 30-minute walk-through of runbooks and the paging tool, signed off by the rotation owner</item>
      <item>First solo shift: scheduled during a low-volume week (no production releases that week)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
