<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="On-Call Rotation Bootstrap Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="single-engineer-large-team" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-engineer rotation in a team of 8+; burnout accumulates silently, surfaces as resignation 6-12 months in.</description>
      <reason>Team grew but rotation design was not revisited; the founding engineer remains de-facto on-call.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Add a secondary tier. Re-cut schedule. Apply comp policy to both tiers (secondary off-hours pages count).</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="alerts-as-rotation" severity="medium">
      <description>No charter, no paging tool, no schedule; on-call is whoever is in Slack and notices the alert.</description>
      <reason>Team postponed paging-tool setup; ad-hoc behaviour calcified.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Stand up the paging tool, commit schedule config to version control, route alerts through the tool. Publish the charter as prerequisite to any further alert tuning.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="aspirational-comp" severity="medium">
      <description>Engineers told 'we appreciate your off-hours work' with no actual time-off-in-lieu or cash compensation accruing.</description>
      <reason>Comp policy not formalised in HR handbook; no automatic accrual engine.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Draft and ship the comp policy. Backfill 90 days. Make comp accrual automatic from paging-tool events.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="noisy-alerts-swamp-rotation" severity="medium">
      <description>10+ pages per shift, most non-actionable; alert-blindness develops.</description>
      <reason>Alerts proliferate without runbooks; no noise budget.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Halt new rotation participation. Run an alert-tuning week. Re-open rotation when median pages/shift &lt; 3.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="new-joiner-solo-day-one" severity="medium">
      <description>New engineer's first shift is solo primary; first incident is sev-1; MTTR spikes.</description>
      <reason>Shadow-period rule not enforced in the scheduling tool.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Block solo primary assignment without shadow record. Enforce 2 shadow + 2 supervised solo before solo.</note>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
