<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Demo Hypothesis Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Demo Hypothesis Template application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="hypothesis-named-pre-demo" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each demo MUST have a named hypothesis (segment + job + price-sensitivity) filed BEFORE the call. No hypothesis = it&apos;s a sales pitch, not a discovery demo.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous-discovery research">Continuous-discovery research — anchors Demo Hypothesis Template rule `hypothesis-named-pre-demo`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="single-success-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each demo MUST declare exactly one success metric (observable prospect behaviour: &apos;asks about pricing within 15 min&apos;, &apos;requests another call within 48h&apos;). Multi-metric demos collapse into vibes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Goal-Question-Metric">Goal-Question-Metric — anchors Demo Hypothesis Template rule `single-success-metric`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-signal-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each demo MUST declare a kill signal (response that falsifies the hypothesis). No kill signal = hypothesis is unfalsifiable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability discipline">Falsifiability discipline — anchors Demo Hypothesis Template rule `kill-signal-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="follow-up-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Next demo for the same hypothesis MUST NOT be booked until the previous demo&apos;s artefact is filed + reviewed. Prevents stacking demos that all test the same wrong thing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Demo-discipline research">Demo-discipline research — anchors Demo Hypothesis Template rule `follow-up-gate`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="artefact-as-agenda" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The filled template IS the demo agenda. Demos without the artefact are skipped or rescheduled.</statement>
      <rationale source="Agenda-discipline practice">Agenda-discipline practice — anchors Demo Hypothesis Template rule `artefact-as-agenda`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
