<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Demo Hypothesis Template Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Demo Hypothesis Template must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every demo session declares one PRIMARY hypothesis in the form 'If we showed customers X, they would react Y because Z'. Demos without a primary hypothesis are deferred until one is written.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous discovery (Teresa Torres, 2021)">feature parades produce smile-and-nod feedback that is not signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define a falsifier upfront: 'we would update the roadmap if we observe ___'. If no falsifier can be written, the hypothesis is unfalsifiable and the demo is rebooked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Karl Popper's falsifiability / hypothesis-testing discipline">Karl Popper's falsifiability / hypothesis-testing discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture at least 3 verbatim reactions per customer. Paraphrased PM-notes do not count — the synthesizer needs raw quotes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-paraphrase rule from user-research literature (Erika Hall, Just Enough Rese">Anti-paraphrase rule from user-research literature (Erika Hall, Just Enough Research).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored application">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Trigger: Customer demo / sneak-peek session
Artefact: structured output meeting the contract in content/02-output-contract.xml
Evidence: ≥1 named source per rule (URL, ticket, transcript_id)
Decision: downstream consumer can act without re-deriving reasoning
]]></code>
      <note>Demonstrates the closed loop the methodology creates — trigger → artefact → decision — with auditability at each step.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored application">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Trigger: 'we should do this thing'
Artefact: prose paragraph, no schema
Evidence: 'industry best practice'
Decision: ambiguous — every reader interprets differently
]]></code>
      <note>Each ambiguity above is a failure mode catalogued in content/03-failure-modes.xml. The methodology exists to prevent exactly this shape.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
