<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gha-deployment-patterns Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gha-deployment-patterns. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production deploy jobs MUST use a GitHub Environment with required reviewers. Set cancel-in-progress: false on deploy concurrency groups so in-flight production deploys are never cancelled by a new commit.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">cancel-in-progress: true on a production deploy group kills an active rollout when a new commit is pushed — a partial deploy is worse than a delayed one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reusable workflows MUST pass only the secrets they need, not secrets: inherit. Each secret must be listed explicitly in the secrets: block with a description.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">secrets: inherit passes every secret in the calling repo's scope. Over-exposure of prod secrets to staging workflows violates least privilege and creates blast radius if the workflow is compromised.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every job in a CD workflow MUST declare timeout-minutes. Use 15-30 for tests, 60 for builds, 120 for deploys. The default 360-minute timeout is too long and leaves runners occupied during an outage.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A hung Kubernetes rollout will silently occupy a runner for 6 hours without a timeout. Explicit timeouts surface stuck deployments early and free runners for other work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reusable workflows MUST define outputs for any value downstream workflows need (e.g., deployment-url). Producing steps MUST have id: and the job MUST have an outputs: mapping.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents commonly miss one half of the output chain: a step with id: but no job-level outputs: produces empty string for consumers, causing silent failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
