<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitHub Actions — Deployment Patterns Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="environment-protection-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production environments MUST use `environment:` with required approvers + wait-timer + branch protection. Direct pushes to prod-deploy workflows from feature branches are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Environment protection docs">Without protection, any contributor can ship to prod; named approvers + branch gates restore the change-control surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="reusable-workflows-for-cd" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deployment logic MUST live in a reusable workflow (`uses: org/repo/.github/workflows/deploy.yml@vX`) tagged with semver. Inline duplicated deploy steps across repos are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="DRY + versioning">Duplicated deploy YAML drifts; centralised reusable workflows give one fix point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="canary-or-blue-green-for-prod" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production deploys MUST use canary (gradual traffic shift) or blue-green (swap-and-rollback) — never an in-place all-at-once update of &gt;25% of fleet.</statement>
      <rationale source="Risk reduction">In-place updates have no rollback fast path; canary/blue-green make rollback a button-press.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="automated-rollback-on-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each prod deploy MUST attach a metric-based rollback gate (error rate, P95 latency, success ratio) with explicit thresholds + automatic rollback action on breach.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE rollback discipline">Manual rollback is too slow during incidents; metric-bound automatic rollback caps blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="release-automation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Releases MUST be automated: tag, changelog generation from PRs, GitHub Release with artefacts. Manual tagging is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Release engineering">Manual releases drift in format; automation gives reproducible, audit-friendly artefacts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when single-env without progression, OR manual deploys cannot be automated, OR no health metrics for rollback gate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">Without progression/automation/metrics the methodology degrades to ceremony; fix the gaps first.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
