<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="modern-ba-framework Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for modern-ba-framework. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Declare one or more perspectives explicitly at project start. Default-Agile routing hides Business Architecture and BPM concerns until late in the project.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs default to the Agile perspective because it dominates training data; without explicit declaration the agent misses BI, BizArch, and BPM concerns that are equally important for the actual work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score competencies against SFIA v9 and certification curricula separately. Certifications signal coverage of a knowledge domain; SFIA scores actual skill capability level.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A CBAP holder has demonstrated BA knowledge breadth but not necessarily capability with LLMs, RAG, or eval design; conflating the two produces hiring decisions that miss AI-era requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a planner subagent that reads project context and emits ba-approach.json before any KA work starts. The planner routes; it does not execute BA work. Human PO/BA sign-off is mandatory before execution.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Auto-execution skips the only checkpoint where a real PO/BA can correct perspective bias and scope errors before they propagate through the entire pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock model selection per task in the ba-approach.json. Do not allow cost-driven downgrade at runtime.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cost regressions happen when orchestrators downgrade from opus to sonnet for gap analysis; the quality difference is significant and the cost saving is marginal relative to the rework cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
