<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-modern-application" title="Modern BA Framework — Application Table and Updated Perspectives">
  <summary>BABOK KA modern application by context, updated perspectives including AI-Product and Data-Product, and competency-based framework with 2025 additions.</summary>

  <section title="Knowledge Area Modern Application">
    <p>How each BABOK KA maps to modern delivery contexts in 2025-2026:</p>
    <list>
      <item>BA Planning and Monitoring — adaptive planning for iterative delivery; scaled agile frameworks; sprint-cadenced BA approach updates.</item>
      <item>Elicitation and Collaboration — virtual facilitation; AI-assisted transcript analysis; async observation via recorded walkthroughs.</item>
      <item>Requirements Lifecycle — agile backlog management; continuous refinement; content-hash IDs instead of manually assigned IDs for stable traceability.</item>
      <item>Strategy Analysis — digital transformation; AI strategy; platform economics; data-product thinking.</item>
      <item>Requirements Analysis and Design — data modeling for ML features; API design; prompt versioning as a requirement artifact; eval set as a test case.</item>
      <item>Solution Evaluation — continuous feedback loops; A/B testing as validation evidence; process-mining feeds for current-state baseline.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Updated Perspectives">
    <rule>
      <statement>Declare one or more perspectives explicitly at project start. Default-Agile routing hides Business Architecture and BPM concerns until late in the project.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to the Agile perspective because it dominates training data; without explicit declaration the agent misses BI, BizArch, and BPM concerns that are equally important for the actual work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Agile — extended to scaled frameworks (SAFe, LeSS), DevOps, and continuous delivery.</item>
      <item>Business Intelligence — expanded to AI/ML, advanced analytics, and data storytelling.</item>
      <item>Information Technology — cloud-native, microservices, API-first, platform engineering.</item>
      <item>Business Architecture — digital transformation, platform economics, capability mapping.</item>
      <item>Business Process Management — intelligent automation, process mining, RPA.</item>
      <item>Data-Product (2025 addition) — domain-owned data products, data mesh, data contracts, ML feature stores.</item>
      <item>AI-Product (2025 addition) — prompt engineering as requirements, eval-driven development, model version as a dependency, LLM-specific NFRs.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Competency-Based Framework — Modern Skills">
    <p>Competency categories and the modern skills added in 2025-2026 context:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Analytical Thinking — AI/ML literacy, data interpretation, eval design, prompt quality assessment.</item>
      <item>Behavioral — virtual collaboration, async facilitation, remote observation design.</item>
      <item>Business Knowledge — digital business models, platform economics, data-product ownership.</item>
      <item>Communication — data storytelling, dashboard annotation, decision brief writing.</item>
      <item>Interaction — cross-functional collaboration across data, ML, and product teams; DevOps integration.</item>
      <item>Tools and Technology — cloud data warehouses, LLM APIs, process-mining platforms, automation tools, data catalogs.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Certification Alignment 2025-2026">
    <list>
      <item>ECBA — entry-level BA; foundation for all contexts.</item>
      <item>CCBA — mid-level BA; practical application.</item>
      <item>CBAP — senior BA; strategic BA leadership.</item>
      <item>Agile Analysis Certification (AAC) — critical for agile and product teams.</item>
      <item>Business Data Analytics Certification (CBDA) — data-driven BA; analytics and BI perspective.</item>
      <item>Product Ownership Analysis Certification (CPOA) — product-focused BA; PO collaboration.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Score competencies against SFIA v9 and certification curricula separately. Certifications signal coverage of a knowledge domain; SFIA scores actual skill capability level.</statement>
      <rationale>A CBAP holder has demonstrated BA knowledge breadth but not necessarily capability with LLMs, RAG, or eval design; conflating the two produces hiring decisions that miss AI-era requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
