<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-integration" title="Modern BA Framework — Integration with Modern Frameworks and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>BABOK integration with modern frameworks, agentic workflow patterns, and prompt templates for the planner and competency-gap subagents.</summary>

  <section title="Framework Integration Table">
    <list>
      <item>SAFe/LeSS — BA competencies mapped to Program Increment planning; BA artifacts feed PI objectives and solution backlogs.</item>
      <item>DevOps — requirements in CI/CD pipelines; acceptance criteria as pipeline gates; RTM coverage as a merge check.</item>
      <item>Design Thinking — customer-centered requirements; empathy maps and jobs-to-be-done as elicitation outputs feeding BABOK KA-2.</item>
      <item>Lean Startup — hypothesis-driven requirements; build-measure-learn cycles as KA-6 evaluation loops.</item>
      <item>Data Mesh — domain-driven data requirements; data products as solution artifacts traced in KA-3.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow — Planner Subagent">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a planner subagent that reads project context and emits ba-approach.json before any KA work starts. The planner routes; it does not execute BA work. Human PO/BA sign-off is mandatory before execution.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-execution skips the only checkpoint where a real PO/BA can correct perspective bias and scope errors before they propagate through the entire pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Planner output schema: {perspectives[], knowledge_areas{ka: {include, methodologies[], rationale}}, competencies_needed[], model_routing{task: model}}.</p>
    <reference path="templates/ba-approach.json">Starter BA Approach JSON structure</reference>
    <reference path="templates/ba-approach-init.sh">Script scaffolding ba-approach.json for a feature</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Model Routing Per Task">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock model selection per task in the ba-approach.json. Do not allow cost-driven downgrade at runtime.</statement>
      <rationale>Cost regressions happen when orchestrators downgrade from opus to sonnet for gap analysis; the quality difference is significant and the cost saving is marginal relative to the rework cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Format requirements → haiku (mechanical template-fill).</item>
      <item>Write acceptance criteria → sonnet (requires testing perspective and detail).</item>
      <item>Validate requirements with stakeholders → sonnet (needs reasoning and communication planning).</item>
      <item>Gap analysis → opus (strategic analysis and trade-off evaluation).</item>
      <item>BPMN / process modeling → opus (architecture and complex modeling decisions).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the modern BA framework as a deliverable producer rather than a router.</description>
      <reason>The framework's output is ba-approach.json — a routing decision. Producing "a BA report from the modern framework" creates a document nobody asked for and skips the actual methodology execution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>KA included in ba-approach.json without a named executable sibling methodology.</description>
      <reason>A KA without a methodology is theatre; the planner must map every INCLUDE'd KA to at least one sibling methodology folder that the executor can load and run.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-execution from planner to executor without human sign-off on the BA approach.</description>
      <reason>Perspective bias introduced in the planner (e.g., defaulting to Agile for a BPM initiative) propagates through the entire pipeline and produces misaligned artifacts that cannot be corrected without starting over.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
