<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="modern-ba-framework Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for modern-ba-framework as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using the modern BA framework as a deliverable producer rather than a router.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The framework's output is ba-approach.json — a routing decision. Producing "a BA report from the modern framework" creates a document nobody asked for and skips the actual methodology execution.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>KA included in ba-approach.json without a named executable sibling methodology.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A KA without a methodology is theatre; the planner must map every INCLUDE'd KA to at least one sibling methodology folder that the executor can load and run.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-execution from planner to executor without human sign-off on the BA approach.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Perspective bias introduced in the planner (e.g., defaulting to Agile for a BPM initiative) propagates through the entire pipeline and produces misaligned artifacts that cannot be corrected without starting over.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Cost-driven downgrade of model_routing at runtime (opus → sonnet for gap analysis).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The savings are marginal compared to the rework cost when gap analysis quality degrades. Lock model selection in the JSON and reject runtime overrides.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Persisting competency-gap.md with individual names attached to gap scores.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The artifact contains performance-grade signals about specific people; storing it outside a private repo without scrubbing creates HR and GDPR exposure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
