<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Senior Promotion Case (Outsource Shop) Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules that distinguish an outsource-shop promotion case from a generic STAR write-up. Skipping any rule weakens the case against the tri-axis rubric.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-tri-axis-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The case MUST cover all three rubric axes — Technical Contribution, Revenue/Account Impact, Utilization — with explicit headed sections. Missing any axis = the committee will mark "incomplete" regardless of strength elsewhere.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Candidates over-index on the axis they're proud of (usually technical) and lose points on the others by silence. The committee scores per-axis; silence = zero.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-quantified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every claim MUST cite a numeric anchor: lines/PRs/design-docs, MRR/ARR/billable-revenue, billable utilization %. Adjective-only claims ("significantly improved", "led architecture") = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Outsource committees compare candidates head-to-head. Without numbers, the strongest narrative loses to the candidate with hard numbers in a weaker story.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-account-revenue-attributed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Revenue/Account section MUST attribute revenue impact with a defensible mechanism: scope-expansion won, contract-renewal saved, billable-rate raise justified, account-NPS uplift, escalation salvaged. Hand-wave revenue claims without a mechanism = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Outsource firms make money on billable hours and account expansion. "I delivered features" is table stakes; promotion happens when the firm earns more because of you.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-utilization-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Utilization section MUST report billable % over the window (typically 6 or 12 months), bench days, and any pre-sales / internal-tools time. Single-quarter snapshots = REJECT — the case window MUST match the firm's review window.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">A cherry-picked quarter mis-represents sustained performance. Window-matching is what auditors call "comparable basis."</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-anti-rubric-prep" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The case MUST include an "Objections &amp; Responses" appendix that anticipates the 3 most likely committee objections (per axis) and pre-rebuts them with evidence. Cases without anti-rubric prep get blindsided in the live review.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Outsource committees grill candidates on weaknesses; pre-rebutting flips the dynamic from defensive to confirmatory. This is the single highest-leverage section.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-manager-cosign" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The case MUST be cosigned by the candidate's direct manager AND at least one delivery / account lead from a major project. Self-only cases score worse — committee weights co-sign as social proof.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Manager-only co-sign reads as "boss is friendly"; adding an account lead from outside the candidate's reporting chain is the credibility multiplier.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example title="Case section header">
      <text>candidate: Olena V.  window: 2025-11 to 2026-05 (6mo)  axes: {Technical: senior architect on Account-X migration, 14 design docs, 0 P1 escalations | Revenue: scope expansion +$340k ARR, contract renewal saved on Account-Y | Utilization: 92% billable, 0 bench days, +20% pre-sales}  cosigners: @manager-lead @account-lead-X  objections_prep: 3 anticipated, all rebutted with evidence</text>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../hr-recruiter/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../executive-stakeholder-demo-narrative-frame/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
