<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="google-display-ads Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for google-display-ads. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set target_content_network=True and target_google_search=False when creating a Display campaign. The default allows search network exposure, which mixes display and search traffic in the same campaign.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Search and display have different CPCs, CTRs, and conversion rates. Mixing them in one campaign makes performance analysis unreliable and wastes budget on unintended placements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Layer at most 2 targeting types per ad group for the initial campaign. Over-constraining with 3+ layers severely limits reach and makes it impossible to diagnose which layer is blocking delivery.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multiple targeting layers apply AND logic — each additional layer reduces the eligible audience multiplicatively.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review the placement performance report weekly and add low-CTR or high-cost/no-conversion placements as negative placements.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Display campaigns without placement exclusions waste significant budget on app games, news aggregators, and parked domains with no purchase intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide the maximum asset count Google allows: 5 headlines, 5 descriptions, 15 marketing images, 5 logos. More assets give the algorithm more combinations to test, improving performance over time.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Google automatically tests asset combinations. Providing only the minimum (1 headline, 1 description, 1 image) eliminates the optimization surface and treats a responsive ad like a static ad.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Upload images as binary content (requests.get(image_url).content), not as URLs. The API does not accept external image URLs directly in the asset payload.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The Google Ads API requires binary image data in the asset creation request. Passing a URL causes a validation error without a clear error message.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
