<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="google-display-ads Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for google-display-ads as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using EXACT or PHRASE match types for display keyword targeting.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Display keyword targeting ignores match type qualifiers; only BROAD is effective. Setting other match types creates confusion without changing behavior.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents auto-generating ad copy often exceed the 30-char headline or 90-char description limit and the request fails server-side.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Character limits are strict; oversized strings are silently rejected with a generic validation error.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Image asset uploads send raw bytes; agents that pass URLs without fetching them first hit AssetError.INVALID_IMAGE.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The Google Ads API requires binary image data in the asset creation request. Passing a URL causes a validation error without a clear error message.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Models confuse placement (specific URL) with topic (Google's content category) — these are different criterion types.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Topics are Google's managed categories; placements are specific URLs or app IDs. Using the wrong type silently changes targeting.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Customer Match list upload requires SHA-256 of normalized lowercase email; LLMs frequently skip the lowercase or strip step.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Email normalization (lowercase, strip whitespace) is mandatory; skipping it results in 0% match rate with no error message.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents reading metrics.conversions may miss metrics.view_through_conversions; double-counting risk if both summed.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>View-through conversions are tracked separately; summing both inflates ROAS calculations. Use conversions only unless analyzing display-specific metrics.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
