<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="One Person Rollback Runbook Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of `One Person Rollback Runbook` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-three-layer-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The runbook MUST cover all three layers: app code, DB migrations, feature flags. Missing any layer = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo SaaS incident corpus 2024-2026">Rollbacks that only revert code leave broken migrations or stale flags; partial rollback is worse than no rollback because it hides the real state.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-verify-per-step" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every step MUST carry a `verify_cmd` (shell-runnable) and `expected` (string contained in stdout). Steps without verify are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-first ops">An unverifiable step is a hope; under pressure the operator skips it. Verifiable steps are auditable and survive panic-mode.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-named-runtime-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The runbook names the runtime owner (operator handle + role + escalation contact). No 'team' or 'we' as owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke">Anonymous runbooks rot. A named runtime owner is the only auditable backstop when the on-call alert fires.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-weekly-dry-run" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The runbook MUST be dry-run end-to-end weekly against staging. Unrehearsed runbooks (last_dry_run &gt; 14d) MUST be flagged as `needs-dry-run` before use.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reliability discipline">A runbook only works if the operator has hit the commands in muscle memory. Weekly drills are the cost of single-operator reliability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-smoke-after-revert" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>After each rollback, the smoke-check suite MUST be executed and pass before declaring 'rolled back'. Skipping smoke = REJECT.</statement>
      <rationale source="Incident post-mortem patterns">Rolling back to a green tag does not guarantee green prod — DNS, CDN cache, and config drift can keep it red. Smoke is the only honest signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
