<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Service Blueprint Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Service Blueprint application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-swimlanes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The blueprint MUST contain exactly five swimlanes in order: Customer Actions, Frontstage Interactions, Line of Visibility (divider), Backstage Actions, Support Processes &amp; Systems. Missing or merged lanes are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Without the Line of Visibility, the artefact regresses to a journey map; it is the entire point of the format.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-systems-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Support Processes &amp; Systems lane MUST name specific internal systems (Salesforce, Zendesk, Stripe Billing, Snowflake) per journey step, never generic labels.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Generic labels do not produce a backlog; named systems route work to the right team.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-failure-point-notation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every observed friction point MUST trace a downward arrow through the Line of Visibility to a specific back-stage step or system; un-traced friction is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">The arrow IS the fix-target — it converts UX frustration into ops/engineering work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-moments-of-truth-scored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The blueprint MUST tag &gt;=3 moments-of-truth with impact score (1-5), evidence source (interview / NPS / ticket / churn), and hypothesised root cause.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Flat blueprints imply all steps matter equally; scoring forces prioritisation, the only path to a real backlog.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-backstage-actor-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every back-stage action MUST name the role/team that performs it (Tier-1 Support, Onboarding Specialist, SRE). 'The team', 'we', 'engineering' are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Once the role is named, RACI inputs follow directly and you can ask whether that role has the tools/SLA to do the work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
