<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Marketing Learnings Database Schema Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Marketing Learnings Database Schema MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="nine-required-fields" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Schema MUST contain test_id, hypothesis, variant, result, p_value, why_explanation, where_applicable, owner, ts. Missing any field rejects the entry.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — experiment audit ROI study 2025">Each field answers a question a future searcher will ask; dropping any field defeats compounding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hypothesis-falsifiable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>hypothesis field MUST be falsifiable (one verb, one variable, one expected direction). Vague hypotheses are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Popper / experimentation literature">Falsifiable hypotheses are the only kind that yield reusable learnings; 'try a new headline' yields nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="result-with-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>result field MUST cite the dashboard URL or query that produced the metric. Result without source is fabrication risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice for analytics">Future readers must reproduce the result; un-sourced numbers are not learnings, they are folklore.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="where-applicable-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>where_applicable field MUST list scope conditions (channel, segment, season, funnel-stage). Empty scope = entry rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Wanamaker / attribution mess literature">Marketing learnings rarely generalize; without scope the entry is harmful when applied out of context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="curator-weekly-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Named curator MUST review and tag new entries weekly; entries not tagged within 14 days auto-archive.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene — PMBOK 7 Tailoring">Un-curated DBs rot to noise within a quarter; the review ritual is the schema.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
