<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Partnership Strategy Five-Stage Framework Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `ops-partnership-strategy` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-partnership-type-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name the partnership type explicitly: affiliate, co-marketing, integration, reseller, or white-label. Vague 'partnership' framing is forbidden in any deal record.</statement>
      <rationale source="Business-development practice (HubSpot Partner Programs, Salesforce AppExchange playbooks)">Vague partnership language hides misaligned expectations. Naming the type pins the operating motion (commission vs joint content vs technical integration).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-candidate-scoring-rubric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score every candidate partnership on five axes: reach, relevance, trust, effort, risk. Pursuing a partnership that scores low on any axis without written justification is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Partnership operations practice (Crossbeam, Reveal playbooks)">Unscored partnerships drift into vanity deals (big logo, no reach into ICP). The 5-axis rubric forces deliberate selection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-mutual-value-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The deal record explicitly states the value to BOTH sides — what the partner gets and what the operator gets. One-sided value statements ('this will be great for them') are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Partnership negotiation practice (Blair Enns, Patrick McKenzie)">Partnerships that lack explicit mutual value collapse at the first conflict. Writing both sides forces the operator to test whether the deal is real.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-partner-benefit-first-outreach" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outreach messages lead with the partner's benefit in the FIRST paragraph. Leading with self-benefit ('we'd love to partner with you') is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cold-outreach response-rate data (Reply.io, Lemlist benchmarks)">Partner-benefit-first outreach gets 3-5x the response rate of self-benefit-first. The constraint is the dominant variable in outreach performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-30-60-90-review-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Schedule 30 / 60 / 90 day reviews at deal signing with named outcomes per checkpoint (leads exchanged, integration shipped, revenue attributed). Partnerships without scheduled reviews are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Partnership operations practice">Most partnerships die from drift, not from explicit termination. Pre-scheduled reviews force a yes/no decision before drift becomes permanent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
