<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-discovery-and-scoring" title="Partnership Discovery and Scoring">
  <summary>Partnership type taxonomy, candidate discovery sources, and a five-factor scorecard for evaluating fit before outreach.</summary>

  <section title="Partnership Types">
    <p>Taxonomy: Affiliate (partner promotes to their audience, you pay commission per sale), Co-marketing (shared audience access and content creation), Integration (technical connection benefiting both user bases), Reseller (partner sells and supports your product for a margin), White-label (partner distributes an unbranded version), Strategic (resource, credential, or market-access exchange).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>For solopreneurs pre-scale: prioritize affiliates and co-marketing partnerships first. They require no technical integration and produce measurable results within 30–90 days.</statement>
      <rationale>Integration and reseller partnerships require months of setup and have higher failure rates when one party lacks dedicated partnership headcount. Affiliates and co-marketing can be tested with a single piece of co-created content or a webinar.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Partner Discovery">
    <p>Discovery sources: complementary products (same audience, different solution — signals: your customers mention them), influencers and content creators (bloggers, podcasters, YouTubers in your niche), adjacent communities (Slack groups, Discord, forums where your ICP gathers), adjacent businesses (same customer segment, non-competing offer).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate audience overlap before outreach: quote a specific data point ("their footer claims 12K customers") rather than asserting overlap. Agents and founders both overstate overlap from surface signals.</statement>
      <rationale>Partnership proposals based on fabricated overlap are discovered immediately by the partner and destroy credibility before any relationship starts. Data-grounded claims signal research investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Partner Scorecard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score every partner candidate on five factors (each 1–5): Reach, Relevance, Trust, Effort required (lower is better), Risk (lower is better). Total out of 25. Proceed only if score is 18 or above.</statement>
      <rationale>Partnerships below 18/25 consistently fail because one of the five dimensions is weak enough to doom execution: low reach means no ROI, low trust means poor conversion, high effort means neither side prioritizes it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/partner-score.py">Scorecard calculator: ranks candidates 0–25, flags proceed/no</reference>
  </section>
</text>
