<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-structuring-and-outreach" title="Partnership Structure, Outreach, and Maintenance">
  <summary>How to structure affiliate and co-marketing deals, write outreach that leads with partner value, and maintain relationships with a review cadence.</summary>

  <section title="Affiliate Structure">
    <p>Affiliate commission models: per sale 20–40% for digital products, per lead $5–50 for SaaS and services, recurring 10–20% monthly for subscriptions, tiered commission for high-volume partners. Set cookie duration (typically 30–90 days), payment on net-30 cycle, minimum payout threshold.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Instrument from day one: unique UTM per partner plus a dedicated landing page. Vague co-promotions without attribution infrastructure die in budget debates within the first quarter.</statement>
      <rationale>Without clear per-partner attribution, partners cannot see their results, you cannot rank partners by value, and neither party can justify continued investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Co-Marketing Structure">
    <p>Co-marketing options: joint webinar (you provide content and presentation, partner provides audience and promotion), bundle (both products offered together with shared pricing), co-authored content (article or guide with cross-distribution), launch support (product launch in exchange for testimonial and promotion).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Propose a small-bet first (joint blog post, single webinar) before pitching a multi-quarter integration. A successful small pilot creates proof points and builds trust for larger commitments.</statement>
      <rationale>Partners have competing priorities. A low-commitment pilot can be approved by one person without legal and exec review. Large proposals stall in approval chains.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Outreach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Put the partner's benefit in the first sentence of every outreach email. Founders and BD contacts scan for "what's in it for me" and discard anything that leads with the sender's company.</statement>
      <rationale>Cold outreach open rates are 20–30%; the first sentence determines whether the email gets read past the preview. Partner-benefit-first framing immediately answers the question that determines read/discard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Outreach opening: "I have a partnership idea that could generate 250 additional registrations for your next webinar, with zero additional prep from your team." Leads with partner outcome, specific and concrete. Compare to bad: "Hi, I'm the founder of [Company], we build [product]..." — leads with sender, partner must infer whether any benefit exists.</note>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/one-pager.md">Partnership proposal one-pager template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Maintenance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 30-60-90 review cadence for every active partnership. Partnerships decay in silence; explicit review prevents quiet disengagement from going unnoticed for a quarter.</statement>
      <rationale>Partnership champions change jobs; priorities shift. A cadenced review surfaces these changes while the relationship is still recoverable. Silent partnerships are vanity — they appear on a logo wall but generate no pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Cadence: weekly check on performance metrics, monthly partner update email, quarterly review and planning call, annual renewal discussion.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never auto-send partnership outreach via agent. Partner-network relationships are repeated-game interactions — one poorly-worded email from a batch run can burn goodwill across an entire industry vertical.</statement>
      <rationale>Unlike B2C marketing where individual-recipient mistakes are isolated, BD contacts share bad experiences with peers. A single batch-outreach incident can preclude relationships with all connected partners.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/tracker.md">Partnership pipeline tracker: active, in-discussion, target-list tables</reference>
  </section>
</text>
