<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples-and-gotchas" title="Partnership Examples and AI-Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>SaaS affiliate and co-marketing webinar examples with concrete results, and agent-specific limitations for partnership work.</summary>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS affiliate partnership: productivity blogger with 50K subscribers, 30% recurring commission, exclusive 20% discount code, co-created review content. Provided free account for testing + custom landing page + assets + monthly performance emails. Results: 25 signups in first month, $750 in recurring commissions, featured in year-end tool roundup.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Co-marketing webinar: complementary SaaS tool with overlapping ICP. Joint webinar "How to [combined value]", cross-promoted to both email lists, Zoom hosted jointly. Results: 500 registrations (250 each), 40% attendance rate, 30 new customers combined. Repeated quarterly — the key: repeating a successful format compounds without proportional effort.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Strategic" partnership: two logos appear on each other's websites, no joint plan, no named DRI on either side. No pipeline generated after 6 months. Classic vanity partnership — appeared valuable on paper, never executed because neither party owned it.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Models confidently invent partnership-team contact names and email addresses.</description>
      <reason>Always validate contacts via LinkedIn or company About page before any outreach. Never send to an email the agent generated without verification — sending to fabricated addresses creates CAN-SPAM and spam-filter issues.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Cold-outreach output drifts toward spammy templates with superlatives despite constraints.</description>
      <reason>Add hard constraints: "must reference [X]-specific recent action", "no superlatives", "under 150 words". Review every outreach before send regardless of constraint specification.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent asserts audience overlap without citing the source data point.</description>
      <reason>Require the agent to quote a specific number and source ("their pricing page says 8,000 customers"). Asserted overlap with no data source will be challenged by the partner immediately.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent auto-generates revenue-share math without showing the formula step by step.</description>
      <reason>LLMs flub multi-step financial calculations. Require explicit formula output ("30% of $99 MRR = $29.70/month x 12 = $356.40/year per referral") before any proposal is drafted.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent drafts contract terms or legal summaries without human review.</description>
      <reason>Partnership agreements that include integration rights, IP licensing, or data-sharing require legal review — especially if enterprise deals will reference the agreement for DPA/SCC compliance.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
