<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Cross-Channel CPA Rollup Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six antipatterns that make the rollup mislead budget allocation. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="double-counting" severity="high">
      <symptom>Sum of attributed_conversions across channels exceeds actual unique conversions in CRM.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Identity-resolution audit">Customer ID unstable across sessions, hashed inconsistently, or absent on key touchpoints.</root-cause>
      <fix>Audit identity stitching: stable ID across sessions, consistent hash, present on every touchpoint. Re-run rollup. Rule violated: dedup-id.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="missing-fees" severity="high">
      <symptom>gross_spend equals ad-platform billing only; agency invoices for the same period are not added.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Marketing-finance reconciliation gap">CPA looks artificially low because half the cost is missing.</root-cause>
      <fix>Add agency + production fees to gross_spend. Re-evaluate channel viability — some flip from "winning" to "losing". Rule violated: gross-spend.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="view-through-abuse" severity="high">
      <symptom>View-through count added to attributed_conversions to make Meta CPA look better.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Vendor narrative">View-through inflates the count without evidence.</root-cause>
      <fix>Keep view-through as a separate column. Report CPA with click-only attribution. Fund an incrementality test if view-through is critical. Rule violated: single-attribution-model.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="branded-cannibalization" severity="high">
      <symptom>Branded keywords drive ≥30% of Google paid conversions; pausing branded paid would shift them to organic with minimal loss.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Branded-paid cannibalization research">Paid claims credit for users who searched the brand directly.</root-cause>
      <fix>Split branded vs non-branded into separate rows. Apply incrementality lens. Consider pausing branded paid (geo-test if uncertain). Rule violated: organic-baseline.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="missing-cohort" severity="medium">
      <symptom>cohort_d30 column blank across ≥3 channels for cohorts older than 30 days.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — rollup audit">Channel allocation rewards low-quality acquisition because retention is invisible.</root-cause>
      <fix>Wire the cohort retention computation. Define minimum viable signal (login, action, purchase). Rule violated: cohort-lens.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="silent-policy-change" severity="medium">
      <symptom>attribution_policy.md modified more than once per quarter; historical rollup not re-run with new model.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Change-control gap">Quietly switching "last click within 7 days" to "linear across 30 days" invalidates historical comparison.</root-cause>
      <fix>Treat attribution changes like an experiment: version the model, re-run the last 90 days under both, document the delta, brief the team. Rule violated: single-attribution-model.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>Channel-vendor dashboards may include narrative ("Meta lifted incremental conversions by 30%") that is not evidence. The rollup uses raw spend/conversion data, not vendor narratives.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>Weekly review by growth lead + finance partner. The rollup is the artifact; the conversation is the gate. Budget shifts ≥ 20% across channels require two-week confirmation before commitment.</p>
  </section>
</text>
