<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitOps — Core Principles Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="git-single-source-of-truth" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All cluster-affecting changes MUST flow through Git. `kubectl apply` / UI changes by humans are rejected; emergency overrides require a documented break-glass procedure.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenGitOps Principle 1">Out-of-band changes destroy audit + reproducibility; the value of GitOps is exactly this discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="declarative-state-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cluster state MUST be declarative — desired-state YAML, never imperative scripts. `kubectl run`, ad-hoc Jobs, manual ConfigMap edits are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenGitOps Principle 2">Imperative state can't be diffed or reconciled; declarative is the only auditable shape.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="automated-reconciliation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An operator (ArgoCD / Flux) MUST continuously reconcile cluster state against Git within a bounded interval (default ≤3 minutes). Manual sync triggers are an audit hint, not the primary mechanism.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenGitOps Principle 3">Drift accumulates between manual syncs; bounded reconciliation catches drift quickly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="drift-and-health-observable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reconciliation status (synced / out-of-sync / health) MUST be exposed as metrics + dashboard. Silent drift is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="OpenGitOps Principle 4">Drift you can't see is drift you don't fix; metrics make GitOps observable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="tool-fits-team" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tool choice (ArgoCD vs Flux) MUST be documented with rationale: ArgoCD for UI-driven multi-tenant orgs, Flux for CRD-native automation-heavy orgs. Cargo-cult choice is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tool fit">Team-fit drives long-run success; the tool wars don't matter compared to operational fit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when (a) non-Kubernetes platform, (b) team workflow centred on imperative kubectl, or (c) single-dev cluster with no audit need.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">GitOps benefits are conditional on Kubernetes + declarative discipline + audit need; without them it's ceremony.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
