<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Segmentation Framework and Scoring Rubric">
  <summary>Four segmentation types, a five-step process, and a six-criterion weighted attractiveness rubric for scoring and selecting target segments.</summary>

  <section title="Segmentation types">
    <p>Use at most two or three dimensions per segmentation; denser matrices are unreadable in stakeholder conversations. Combine quantitative (firmographics, behavioural) and qualitative (needs, attitudes) dimensions — pure quant misses messaging insights.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Demographic: age, income, occupation, company size, industry. Best for B2B targeting and pricing tiers.</item>
      <item>Behavioural: usage frequency, purchase history, feature usage, engagement level, buying stage. Best for retention and product development.</item>
      <item>Psychographic: values, attitudes, lifestyle, motivations. Best for messaging and brand positioning.</item>
      <item>Needs-based: problem severity, current solution, budget, speed priority, support needs. Best for product tiers and pricing strategy.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-step process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Gather data from CRM, analytics, survey responses, and sales conversations; choose two to three dimensions that maximise inter-segment variance and minimise intra-segment variance.</statement>
      <rationale>Dimensions chosen without variance analysis produce segments that look different but behave the same — they do not guide distinct go-to-market or product decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate segment size against an addressable population (LinkedIn audience estimate, paid-ads reach, list-rental quote); theoretical size means nothing without addressability evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Segments that are not addressable via any channel are worthless regardless of their size on paper.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ensure mutually exclusive segments: every customer should fit one and only one segment after rules apply. Orphans signal definition gaps.</statement>
      <rationale>Overlapping segments prevent attribution and make channel and pricing decisions ambiguous.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a do-not-target segment with explicit reasoning (low LTV, high CAC, support-cost-heavy). Pair the top segment with one channel and one message.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an explicit do-not-target definition, teams waste acquisition budget on low-ROI users.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Attractiveness scoring rubric">
    <p>Score each segment 1-5 on six criteria; apply fixed weights to produce a weighted total. Re-score quarterly using the same rubric weights; weight changes must be flagged as a methodology change.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Size (20%): how many people or companies are in this segment?</item>
      <item>Growth (15%): is the segment growing as a share of the market?</item>
      <item>Reachability (20%): can we access them economically via existing channels?</item>
      <item>Profitability (20%): will they pay enough to sustain the business model?</item>
      <item>Fit (15%): do our strengths match this segment's needs?</item>
      <item>Competition (10%): how crowded is this segment currently?</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag any score with no evidence; do not accept agent-generated segment sizes ("estimated 200K SMBs in NYC") without a cited source.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs invent segment sizes that are decorative; unsupported numbers give false precision to strategic decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
