<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="cicd-tls-renewal-automation Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for cicd-tls-renewal-automation as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>HTTP-01 challenge selected when the pipeline later needs wildcard certificates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>HTTP-01 cannot issue wildcard certs. Flag wildcard requests early and force DNS-01 from the start — migrating mid-flight requires re-issuance and potential downtime.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Iterating on certificate issuance against the production LE endpoint during development.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Let's Encrypt rate limits: 50 certs/week per registered domain. Agents or pipelines iterating on issuance burn the quota fast. Always use the staging endpoint (https://acme-staging-v02.api.letsencrypt.org/directory) during development and testing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Defaulting to RSA-2048 key generation when ECDSA P-256 is available.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ECDSA P-256 is faster (smaller signatures, faster handshakes) and the modern standard. RSA-2048 provides 112-bit security while P-256 provides 128-bit security at a fraction of the computational cost.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>ARI (ACME Renewal Information) checks disabled or ignored.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>ARI lets the CA signal early renewal (e.g., due to mass revocation events). Ignoring ARI means your automation misses CA-recommended renewal windows and certs may expire unexpectedly during a CA incident.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
