<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ba-governance Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ba-governance. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define decision rights before any requirements work begins; document who can approve, who must be consulted, and who must be informed for each decision type.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without explicit decision rights, every scope change escalates to the highest available authority, creating steering-committee bottlenecks and delayed delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every change-control flow must have explicit terminal states: approve, reject with reason, and defer with owner and date; open-ended flows leave CRs in limbo.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLM-generated change-control flows frequently lack a "reject + reason" terminal state; unresolved CRs accumulate and make the requirements baseline untrustworthy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Bind change-control thresholds to objective signals (story points, dollar impact, regulatory flag), not to subjective severity assessments.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Subjective thresholds drift over time; every CR eventually qualifies as "XL / Steering" because teams learn that higher classification gets faster decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document tie-breaking rules before any prioritization conflict arises; do not defer tie-breaking to ad-hoc stakeholder negotiation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without explicit tie-breaking rules, priority conflicts become political; the loudest stakeholder wins rather than the most valuable requirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture every decision including rejections and defers; the audit trail is the deliverable, not the matrix.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Regulated industries require a complete decision log; even non-regulated projects benefit because rejected CRs contain the reasoning that prevents re-relitigating the same scope question next quarter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Re-validate the decision-authority matrix every 30 days; stale escalation paths are the leading cause of stuck CRs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Org charts change faster than governance documents; a matrix updated at kickoff is obsolete within 3 months on average for growing teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Map every communication channel to a feedback mechanism; a channel without a feedback mechanism is write-only and decays within weeks.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">"Email weekly digest" without a reply expectation or read-confirmation mechanism produces a false sense of stakeholder alignment; unresolved misunderstandings surface as surprise issues at sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define elicitation scope (what information is needed, what decisions will be made, what is out of scope) before scheduling any session.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Undefined scope turns sessions into open-ended discussions that produce inconsistent outputs and require rework to extract useful requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-commit the technique-selection table per session; agents otherwise default to "interview" for all information types.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each information type has an optimally matched technique; always interviewing leaves process gaps, current-state artifacts, and validation results under-covered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require three human-in-the-loop checkpoints: (1) sign-off on the decision-authority matrix before any requirements are baselined; (2) sponsor confirmation of comms cadence; (3) post-kickoff dry-run of the CR flow with one synthetic CR.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Governance integrity depends on human approval traces at critical junctures; agent-only setup produces a governance document that satisfies process checkers but fails the first real decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
