<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-governance-framework" title="BA Governance Framework">
  <summary>Decision rights definition, change control process, prioritization rules, and approval audit trail requirements for BA governance artifacts.</summary>

  <section title="Decision Rights">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define decision rights before any requirements work begins; document who can approve, who must be consulted, and who must be informed for each decision type.</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit decision rights, every scope change escalates to the highest available authority, creating steering-committee bottlenecks and delayed delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>New requirement: BA Lead authority, PM escalation.</item>
      <item>Scope change: Steering Committee authority, Sponsor escalation.</item>
      <item>Priority change: Product Owner authority, PM escalation.</item>
      <item>Baseline update: BA Lead + named approver, joint authority.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Escalation paths that use role titles without named individuals ("Director of Product" rather than a specific person).</description>
      <reason>Role titles become orphaned when people leave or org charts change; named individuals ensure the escalation path actually resolves in a crisis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Change Control Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every change-control flow must have explicit terminal states: approve, reject with reason, and defer with owner and date; open-ended flows leave CRs in limbo.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-generated change-control flows frequently lack a "reject + reason" terminal state; unresolved CRs accumulate and make the requirements baseline untrustworthy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Submit change request (CR) — link to affected requirements IDs.</item>
      <item>Step 2: Impact assessment — T-shirt sizing (S/M/L/XL) against scope, schedule, and cost. Mandatory; not optional for any CR severity.</item>
      <item>Step 3: Review by authority from decision matrix.</item>
      <item>Step 4: Decision — Approve / Reject (with reason) / Defer (with owner + date).</item>
      <item>Step 5: Update baseline; link CR → REQ in tracking system.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Bind change-control thresholds to objective signals (story points, dollar impact, regulatory flag), not to subjective severity assessments.</statement>
      <rationale>Subjective thresholds drift over time; every CR eventually qualifies as "XL / Steering" because teams learn that higher classification gets faster decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Prioritization Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document tie-breaking rules before any prioritization conflict arises; do not defer tie-breaking to ad-hoc stakeholder negotiation.</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit tie-breaking rules, priority conflicts become political; the loudest stakeholder wins rather than the most valuable requirement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Criteria: business value, regulatory compliance, strategic fit, implementation cost, risk.</item>
      <item>Weight assignment: use the same method as solution options scoring (AHP pairwise or 100-point swing); document the method and stakeholders who assigned weights.</item>
      <item>Tie-breaker: in a tie, the requirement with higher regulatory compliance score takes precedence; second tie-breaker is lower implementation cost.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Audit Trail">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture every decision including rejections and defers; the audit trail is the deliverable, not the matrix.</statement>
      <rationale>Regulated industries require a complete decision log; even non-regulated projects benefit because rejected CRs contain the reasoning that prevents re-relitigating the same scope question next quarter.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-validate the decision-authority matrix every 30 days; stale escalation paths are the leading cause of stuck CRs.</statement>
      <rationale>Org charts change faster than governance documents; a matrix updated at kickoff is obsolete within 3 months on average for growing teams.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/governance.md">Governance artifact with decision-authority matrix, change-control steps, and communication plan.</reference>
</text>
