<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-communication-and-elicitation" title="Communication Planning and Elicitation Preparation">
  <summary>Audience analysis, message design, channel selection with feedback mechanisms, and elicitation technique selection by information type.</summary>

  <section title="Communication Planning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Map every communication channel to a feedback mechanism; a channel without a feedback mechanism is write-only and decays within weeks.</statement>
      <rationale>"Email weekly digest" without a reply expectation or read-confirmation mechanism produces a false sense of stakeholder alignment; unresolved misunderstandings surface as surprise issues at sign-off.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Audience analysis: who needs what information, preferred format, preferred channel, frequency requirements.</item>
      <item>Message design: key points, level of detail appropriate for audience, supporting materials.</item>
      <item>Channel selection: formal vs informal, written vs verbal, synchronous vs asynchronous.</item>
      <item>Feedback mechanism: how to confirm understanding, follow-up process, issue resolution path.</item>
    </list>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Sponsor: weekly status summary by email, feedback mechanism = standing 15-minute review slot. Dev team: detailed requirements per sprint via Jira, feedback mechanism = refinement session questions log. Ops: release plan checklist pre-release via Slack, feedback mechanism = acknowledgment reaction + blockers thread.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Communication plan that defaults all channels to Slack regardless of audience or message formality.</description>
      <reason>Slack is appropriate for async informal communication; regulatory-track approvals, formal sign-offs, and sponsor status reports require traceable channels with retention guarantees.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Elicitation Preparation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define elicitation scope (what information is needed, what decisions will be made, what is out of scope) before scheduling any session.</statement>
      <rationale>Undefined scope turns sessions into open-ended discussions that produce inconsistent outputs and require rework to extract useful requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-commit the technique-selection table per session; agents otherwise default to "interview" for all information types.</statement>
      <rationale>Each information type has an optimally matched technique; always interviewing leaves process gaps, current-state artifacts, and validation results under-covered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Current state information: Observation, Document Analysis.</item>
      <item>Pain points and stakeholder needs: Interviews, Focus Groups.</item>
      <item>New requirements and consensus: Workshops, Prototyping.</item>
      <item>Validation of existing requirements: Reviews, Walkthroughs.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM-Specific Failures">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM generates a communication plan with a six-tier steering committee for a four-person project.</description>
      <reason>LLMs over-template governance artifacts for any project they perceive as "enterprise" regardless of actual team size. Pass team size and compliance flag explicitly in the system prompt to constrain output appropriately.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM auto-closes CRs when CI is green without requiring human approval.</description>
      <reason>Green CI indicates technical quality; governance integrity requires a human approval trace. Automating CR closure on CI signals removes the accountable human from the audit trail.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require three human-in-the-loop checkpoints: (1) sign-off on the decision-authority matrix before any requirements are baselined; (2) sponsor confirmation of comms cadence; (3) post-kickoff dry-run of the CR flow with one synthetic CR.</statement>
      <rationale>Governance integrity depends on human approval traces at critical junctures; agent-only setup produces a governance document that satisfies process checkers but fails the first real decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/scaffold-governance.sh">Bash script generating governance.md skeleton under .aidocs/in-progress/.</reference>
</text>
