<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ba-governance Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ba-governance as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Escalation paths that use role titles without named individuals ("Director of Product" rather than a specific person).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Role titles become orphaned when people leave or org charts change; named individuals ensure the escalation path actually resolves in a crisis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Communication plan that defaults all channels to Slack regardless of audience or message formality.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Slack is appropriate for async informal communication; regulatory-track approvals, formal sign-offs, and sponsor status reports require traceable channels with retention guarantees.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM generates a communication plan with a six-tier steering committee for a four-person project.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs over-template governance artifacts for any project they perceive as "enterprise" regardless of actual team size. Pass team size and compliance flag explicitly in the system prompt to constrain output appropriately.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM auto-closes CRs when CI is green without requiring human approval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Green CI indicates technical quality; governance integrity requires a human approval trace. Automating CR closure on CI signals removes the accountable human from the audit trail.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Matrix-vs-reality drift: the published matrix says "Steering Committee approves scope changes," but in reality the PM emails the sponsor and ships.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Symptom: audit findings during regulatory review. Fix: monthly sample of CRs vs matrix.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Approval-tier inflation: every CR escalates to "XL / Steering" because impact assessment is skipped.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Symptom: steering meetings with 30+ items. Fix: enforce T-shirt size with a checklist + mandatory link to impact analysis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Channel sprawl: comms plan starts with email + Jira; six weeks later there are five Slack channels, two Confluence spaces, and a shared Drive folder, none referenced in the plan.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fix: agent runs a quarterly comms-audit task that diffs declared channels vs actual.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Unowned artifacts: governance.md exists, no one updates it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fix: a single Owner: line + cron-triggered subagent that opens a "stale doc" issue at day 30.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
