<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ia-templates">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Reusable templates for IA deliverables: strategy documents, sitemaps, taxonomies, page inventories, and navigation specifications.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>information-architecture</tag>
      <tag>templates</tag>
      <tag>deliverables</tag>
      <tag>documentation</tag>
      <tag>navigation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-24</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Information Architecture - Templates</title>
    <summary>When producing IA deliverables for a new product, site redesign, or content migration, templates accelerate the output from research insights to structured documentation. IA strategy documents, sitemaps, taxonomy references, and page inventories are working artifacts that align stakeholders and govern content placement. Templates provide the structure; research data (card sorting, interviews, analytics) fills the content.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Research outputs (interview transcripts, card sort dendrograms, analytics events, support ticket themes) need to be translated into shared reference documents. Without templates, each deliverable is created from scratch, causing inconsistency and reinventing the same structure repeatedly across projects.</p>
      <p>Templates create a common language and structure that teams can quickly populate, review, and version-control. A filled-in sitemap or taxonomy document becomes a governance artifact — the single source of truth for where content belongs and how new items are classified.</p>
      <p>Documentation also serves onboarding: new team members and contributors understand the product's structure without tribal knowledge. Version-controlled templates prevent drift between the documented structure and the shipped product.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When producing IA deliverables for a new product, site redesign, or content migration project.</item>
        <item>When a sitemap, taxonomy, or navigation spec needs to go from research insights to structured document quickly.</item>
        <item>When onboarding a new team member who needs to understand the product's content structure.</item>
        <item>When multiple stakeholders need a shared IA reference that is version-controlled and updateable.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>As a substitute for user research informing the IA — templates structure the output; they do not replace card sorting or tree testing.</item>
        <item>When the information space is too small to warrant formal IA documentation (fewer than 20 pages/features — a simple outline suffices).</item>
        <item>When the taxonomy is actively contested between stakeholders — resolve the conflict before producing artifacts.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="ia-strategy-document">
      <p>The IA strategy document sets the direction and rationale before producing sitemaps and navigation designs. It answers: What organization scheme are we using and why? What are the user goals? How does content relate? What are scalability assumptions?</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Start with the IA strategy document before creating the sitemap — strategy defines the organization scheme; sitemap visualizes it.</statement>
        <rationale>Jumping to sitemap creation without strategy leads to arbitrary structure. Documenting the approach first ensures all stakeholders agree on whether the IA is topic-based, task-based, audience-based, or hybrid before design begins.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <template path="templates/ia-strategy-template.md" purpose="IA strategy document skeleton: overview, user insights, content insights, business requirements, organization approach, category structure, navigation design, labeling guidelines, search strategy, scalability plan, validation plan."/>
    </section>
    <section name="sitemap-and-page-inventory">
      <p>The sitemap is the visual hierarchy; the page inventory is the detailed catalog. Sitemaps show structure and relationships; page inventories track URLs, owners, templates, and priority.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep taxonomy document and sitemap in sync; they describe the same structure from different angles.</statement>
        <rationale>A sitemap that drifts from the taxonomy creates confusion when new content is added — contributors see a different structure in the two documents and make conflicting decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign a taxonomy owner responsible for approvals when new content types or categories are added — without governance, taxonomies become internally inconsistent within 6-12 months.</statement>
        <rationale>As teams add content independently, each interprets categories slightly differently. An owner with authority to approve new categories and enforce labeling standards prevents category drift and keeps the taxonomy navigable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <template path="templates/sitemap-template.md" purpose="Sitemap skeleton with legend, site structure tree, and page inventory table (URL, title, priority, template, owner)."/>
    </section>
    <section name="taxonomy-document">
      <p>The taxonomy document defines content types, categories, tags, and naming conventions. It is the governance reference for categorizing new content.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Document naming conventions with specific rules (sentence case, plain language, 2–4 words maximum, no jargon) and examples of good vs. bad labels.</statement>
        <rationale>Naming conventions prevent category label drift. "Resources" in one section might become "Tools" in another, confusing navigation. Documented conventions and examples help contributors make consistent choices.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <template path="templates/taxonomy-template.md" purpose="Taxonomy document skeleton: content types, primary categories and hierarchy, tags, naming conventions with examples of good/bad labels."/>
    </section>
    <section name="common-ia-patterns">
      <p>Common information architecture patterns solve recurring problems. The pattern choice depends on site type, content volume, and user tasks.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Mega Menu pattern (for large sites with many products): Use a two-dimensional grid showing categories (columns) with featured items (right column). Best for 30+ top-level items.</statement>
        <rationale>Mega menus surface secondary navigation without requiring a click, allowing power users to skip intermediate pages. Limits depth and supports large item counts within visual bounds.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Hub and Spoke pattern (for task-focused applications): A central hub page with links radiating to task-specific spoke pages. Each spoke is self-contained and returns to the hub.</statement>
        <rationale>Hub and spoke reduces navigation depth and clarifies task separation. Users do not get lost because each spoke has a clear purpose and visible return path.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Flat Structure pattern (for small sites and marketing pages): Home linking to top-level pages with limited nesting (max 2 levels). Best for fewer than 50 pages.</statement>
        <rationale>Flat structures minimize decision points and reduce cognitive load. No deep hierarchies means no users lose context. Best for simple marketing sites where users land deep and rarely navigate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use sentence case for all navigation labels; avoid title case (it reads as shouting) and ALL CAPS (inaccessible and outdated).</statement>
        <rationale>Sentence case is the standard for navigation labels and improves readability on small screens. Title case was common in desktop navigation but has fallen out of favor; ALL CAPS is actively hostile to screen readers and dyslexic readers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Limit primary navigation to 7 items maximum (Miller's Law); secondary items go in section nav or footer.</statement>
        <rationale>Humans comfortably hold 7 items in working memory while making a choice. Beyond 7, navigation becomes a search task. Use secondary navigation to provide depth without overloading primary items.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="validation-and-maintenance">
      <p>IA templates are starting points. Validation with users and regular maintenance keep them accurate.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Share the draft sitemap and taxonomy with 2–3 research participants for a member check before using them to drive decisions — they often correct assumptions that felt obvious internally.</statement>
        <rationale>Team members working inside a product are poor judges of label clarity and category groupings because they have internalized the structure. Research participants catch labels that are ambiguous or jargon-filled.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Date every IA artifact version — maps and taxonomies without dates get treated as current truth long after they are outdated.</statement>
        <rationale>Stale documentation is worse than no documentation because it actively misleads contributors. Dates and version numbers signal when the structure was last validated and guide when updates are due.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Review the IA annually against analytics: pages with no traffic despite good placement indicate label or discoverability problems; pages with high exit rates despite being the right destination indicate content problems, not IA problems.</statement>
        <rationale>Analytics reveal where the IA is failing in practice. High-traffic exits from a page might mean the content is poor (a content problem) or the page is hard to find (an IA problem). Low traffic to a well-placed page signals labeling or discoverability issues.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-workflow">
      <p>Agents can accelerate IA template production by generating first-draft sitemaps and taxonomies from content inventories or product descriptions. Humans then validate groupings against research and adjust labels for clarity.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents will produce plausible-looking groupings that reflect common web patterns, not your users' actual mental models — always validate generated taxonomies against card sort data.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs are trained on thousands of websites and will default to common patterns (Topic/Solutions/Resources sections) rather than your product's unique structure. Card sort results are ground truth; agent output is a starting point for revision.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>LLMs default to topic-based organization schemes; if your product needs task-based or audience-based IA, specify this explicitly in the prompt or the agent will not change defaults.</statement>
        <rationale>Topic-based organization (Products, Services, Resources) is the most common pattern in training data. Agents will reproduce this pattern by default unless explicitly instructed otherwise.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Generated taxonomy labels often include jargon or generic terms (Solutions, Resources); instruct the agent to flag any term users might not recognize.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents optimize for plausibility, not clarity. They will use common labels that sound professional but are vague to users. Explicit instructions to flag jargon help catch these in review.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents cannot know which content is high-priority for business goals — supply this explicitly or the agent will treat all content equally.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents have no access to business context and will create taxonomies that weight all content equally. Prioritization decisions (what goes in top-nav vs. footer, which content is featured) require human business judgment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For large content inventories (200+ items), break the agent task into sections; single-pass generation loses coherence and produces inconsistent category groupings.</statement>
        <rationale>Large taxonomies exceed the context window of a single agent pass. Breaking the task into sections (e.g., product pages, help articles, support resources) allows the agent to produce consistent categories within each section, which humans then reconcile at the top level.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>Templates are most powerful when combined with tools for creating, maintaining, and validating sitemaps and taxonomies.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>CLI tools for IA: markdown-toc to auto-generate table of contents for large IA docs, tree to generate directory-tree representations of file-based IA, csvkit to process page inventory CSVs for analysis and filtering.</statement>
        <rationale>Automation prevents manual maintenance errors. As sitemaps and page inventories grow, hand-maintained tables drift out of sync with reality. CLI tools allow version-controlled, scriptable management.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>SaaS services for IA: Optimal Workshop for card sorting and tree testing (partial API), Whimsical for quick sitemap diagramming (no API), Miro for collaborative IA work (REST API), Airtable for taxonomy and page inventory management (REST API), Notion for IA documentation (REST API).</statement>
        <rationale>Tool selection depends on team size and workflow. Optimal Workshop is purpose-built for IA research; Miro and Airtable excel at collaborative maintenance. API-enabled tools integrate with agent workflows for automated taxonomy updates.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices-and-gotchas">
      <p>IA templates are starting points. Several patterns and anti-patterns emerge in practice.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents will produce plausible-looking groupings that reflect common web patterns, not your users' actual mental models — always validate generated taxonomies against card sort data.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs are trained on thousands of websites and will default to common patterns (Topic/Solutions/Resources sections) rather than your product's unique structure. Card sort results are ground truth; agent output is a starting point for revision.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Generated taxonomy labels often include jargon or generic terms (Solutions, Resources); instruct the agent to flag any term users might not recognize.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents optimize for plausibility, not clarity. They will use common labels that sound professional but are vague to users. Explicit instructions to flag jargon help catch these in review before they reach the product.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Agents cannot know which content is high-priority for business goals — supply this explicitly or the agent will treat all content equally.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents have no access to business context and will create taxonomies that weight all content equally. Prioritization decisions (what goes in top-nav vs. footer, which content is featured) require human business judgment.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>For large content inventories (200+ items), break the agent task into sections; single-pass generation loses coherence and produces inconsistent category groupings.</statement>
        <rationale>Large taxonomies exceed the context window of a single agent pass. Breaking the task into sections (e.g., product pages, help articles, support resources) allows the agent to produce consistent categories within each section, which humans then reconcile at the top level.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/ia-deliverables/"/>
      <link href="https://alistapart.com/article/thedisciplineofcontentstrategy/"/>
      <link href="https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/information-architecture.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/information-architecture-deliverables"/>
      <link href="https://xd.adobe.com/ideas/process/information-architecture/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
