<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="data-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-modeling</domain>
    <summary>Structured approach to identifying, defining, and documenting data needs before system development, producing data dictionaries and requirements documents that guide architects and developers.</summary>
    <category>modeling</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>data-analysis</tag>
      <tag>data-modeling</tag>
      <tag>data-dictionary</tag>
      <tag>erd</tag>
      <tag>data-quality</tag>
    </tags>
    <applies-to>both</applies-to>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="database-design"/>
      <ref slug="business-process-analysis"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Data Analysis</title>

    <summary>A structured approach to identifying, defining, and documenting data needs before system development. Covers data requirements gathering, data element definition, conceptual/logical/physical modeling, data quality assessment across six dimensions, and data business rules. Produces a data dictionary and data requirements document that developers and architects use as authoritative data contracts.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Data exists in multiple systems with inconsistent definitions; reports show conflicting numbers; integration projects fail due to undiscovered schema mismatches. By mapping data entities, attributes, quality dimensions, and ownership before development, the BA prevents costly rework and ensures systems share a common data language.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Starting database or integration design and no shared data dictionary exists.</item>
        <item>Reports from different systems show conflicting figures for the same metric.</item>
        <item>Building ETL/integration layer between two or more systems.</item>
        <item>Assessing data migration scope before cutover.</item>
        <item>Data quality issues are causing operational problems and no baseline measurement exists.</item>
        <item>Compliance requires documented data ownership and classification (GDPR, HIPAA).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Exploratory analytics spike where the data model will be thrown away — just query and iterate.</item>
        <item>Event streaming architectures where schema-on-read is intentional; a rigid dictionary adds friction.</item>
        <item>Frontend-only features with no new data persistence.</item>
        <item>When an authoritative data dictionary already exists and is up to date — extend it, do not duplicate.</item>
        <item>Pure UI/UX research where the output is a prototype, not a data model.</item>
        <item>Greenfield prototypes pre-PMF where the schema changes weekly — formal data dictionaries become stale faster than written.</item>
        <item>Statistical / exploratory data analysis (EDA, pandas, notebooks) — that is data science, not BA Data Analysis.</item>
        <item>Pure ML feature engineering — features evolve through training pipelines, not through a BA-owned dictionary.</item>
        <item>Tiny CRUD apps with under 10 entities — the ceremony costs more than it saves.</item>
        <item>One-off ad-hoc reports where data lives only in a spreadsheet for a week.</item>
        <item>High-trust regulated domains (HIPAA, PCI, SOX) where data classification MUST be human-signed — agents may draft, humans must approve.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="five-step-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1 — Identify data needs: for each user role and system function, ask what information is displayed, captured, calculated, stored, and shared.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping need identification produces a data model that stores what developers guess rather than what the business requires.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2 — Define data elements: document each attribute with name, business definition, type, format, valid values, source, and owner.</statement>
        <rationale>Without business definitions, developers implement technical interpretations that conflict across systems and reports.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3 — Create data model at three levels: conceptual (high-level entities and relationships for business stakeholders), logical (detailed attributes and rules for BA and developers), physical (tables, columns, indexes for database developers).</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing levels produces models that are too abstract for developers or too technical for business review.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4 — Analyze data quality across six dimensions: accuracy, completeness, consistency, timeliness, validity, uniqueness. Measure each with a quantitative metric before defining improvement targets.</statement>
        <rationale>Unmeasured data quality produces subjective "bad data" complaints with no baseline to track improvement against.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5 — Define data rules: document validation rules, derivation formulas, default values, constraints, and uniqueness requirements as testable statements.</statement>
        <rationale>Business rules embedded in code without documentation become invisible and are lost when developers change; they must live in the data dictionary.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="data-quality-dimensions">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure accuracy as error rate (% of records with incorrect values vs. authoritative source), completeness as missing value %, consistency as conflict count across systems, timeliness as average data age, validity as % of records violating business rules, uniqueness as duplicate rate.</statement>
        <rationale>Each dimension requires a distinct metric; a single "data quality score" hides which dimension is failing and which remediation to apply.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Assign each data quality dimension a numeric score (1-5), a traffic-light status (Green/Yellow/Red), and a remediation priority (H/M/L) in the assessment report.</statement>
        <rationale>Qualitative assessments ("data is inconsistent") produce no remediation priority; numeric scores enable comparison across dimensions and tracking over time.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never declare a dimension "Green" without a measured sample from production data of at least 100 records or 10% of total volume, whichever is larger.</statement>
        <rationale>Small samples miss systemic issues; a 1% error rate on 10,000 records represents 100 corrupted records that will affect operations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="specific-use-cases-agentic">
      <p>Specific agentic-automation use cases for data analysis:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Greenfield feature spec needs a data dictionary: agent reads the spec + existing schema, emits new entities + attributes with types, validations, and ownership before DDL is written.</item>
        <item>Pre-migration data quality assessment: agent profiles a source table, fills the six-dimension scorecard (accuracy / completeness / consistency / timeliness / validity / uniqueness), and flags blockers per entity.</item>
        <item>Cross-system definition reconciliation: agent diffs customer.email semantics across CRM, billing, and product DBs and produces a canonical definition + mapping table.</item>
        <item>Conceptual → logical → physical drift check: agent compares data-dictionary.md against live schema (Postgres information_schema, dbt manifest) and opens issues per drift.</item>
        <item>ERD generation from spec: agent writes Mermaid / dbml ERD from the entity table, keeps it in git, regenerates on every dictionary change.</item>
        <item>Business-rule extraction from legacy code/SQL: agent reads stored procedures or app validators and reverse-engineers validation/derivation/constraint rule rows.</item>
        <item>Data-volume sizing for capacity planning: agent reads dictionary + traffic assumptions and produces volumes table (current / 1yr / 3yr).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="modeling-levels">
      <p>Conceptual: entities and relationships only, no attributes. Audience: business stakeholders. Purpose: confirm scope.</p>
      <p>Logical: entities with all attributes, data types, relationships with cardinality, business rules. Audience: BA, developers. Purpose: design contract.</p>
      <p>Physical: tables, columns, indexes, foreign keys, partitioning. Audience: database developers. Purpose: implementation spec.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="data-rule-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Document every business rule as one of: Validation (field-level constraint), Derivation (formula), Default (initial value), Constraint (cross-field or cross-entity), or Uniqueness (key definition).</statement>
        <rationale>Mixing rule types in a single list makes it impossible to generate validators, ETL transformations, and database constraints from the same document.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Validation: Email must contain @ and a domain with at least one dot</item>
        <item>Derivation: OrderTotal = sum(LineItem.Quantity * LineItem.Price) + ShippingCost - DiscountAmount</item>
        <item>Default: CustomerStatus defaults to "Prospect" on record creation</item>
        <item>Constraint: ShipDate must be on or after OrderDate</item>
        <item>Uniqueness: CustomerID is system-generated and immutable; Email is unique across all active customers</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="examples">
      <example type="good" title="Customer Entity Definition">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Entity: Customer
Owner: CRM Team
Source: Customer onboarding service

| Attribute    | Type       | Required | Validation                          |
|--------------|------------|----------|-------------------------------------|
| CustomerID   | Integer    | Yes      | Auto-generated, immutable, unique   |
| FirstName    | Text(50)   | Yes      | Not empty, no special characters    |
| LastName     | Text(50)   | Yes      | Not empty                           |
| Email        | Text(100)  | Yes      | Valid email format, unique (active) |
| Phone        | Text(20)   | No       | Valid E.164 format if provided      |
| Status       | Text(10)   | Yes      | Enum: Active, Inactive, Prospect    |
| CreatedDate  | DateTime   | Yes      | Auto-set on creation, immutable     |

Business Rules:
DR-01: CustomerID is system-generated and immutable
DR-02: Email must be unique across all active customers
DR-03: Status defaults to "Prospect" for new customers
DR-04: Inactive customers retain all records but cannot place orders
      ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Data Quality Assessment Example">
        <note>Product data assessment — shows how dimension scores drive prioritization.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Assessment: Product Catalog Data (n=5,000 records, sampled 10%)

| Dimension    | Score | Findings                                          | Priority |
|--------------|-------|---------------------------------------------------|----------|
| Accuracy     | 3/5   | 8% of prices incorrect vs. master catalog         | High     |
| Completeness | 4/5   | 2% missing product descriptions                   | Medium   |
| Consistency  | 2/5   | Product names differ between website and ERP      | High     |
| Timeliness   | 5/5   | Updated daily from supplier feed, acceptable      | Low      |
| Validity     | 4/5   | 1% records with invalid category codes            | Medium   |
| Uniqueness   | 3/5   | 5% duplicate SKUs from legacy import              | High     |

Priority issue: Consistency (score 2) — naming convention needed
  across all source systems before integration project proceeds.
Recommendation: define canonical product name field in data dictionary
  and ETL transformation rules before cutover.
      ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="ER Notation Reference">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
One customer has many orders:
Customer 1 ----< N Order

One order has one or more line items (mandatory):
Order 1 ----|| N LineItem

One product appears in zero or more line items (optional):
Product 1 --o-< N LineItem

Symbols:
  1    = exactly one
  N    = many (one or more)
  o    = zero (optional)
  |    = mandatory
  <    = crow's foot (many)
      ]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No data dictionary — every developer defines data elements independently.</description>
        <reason>Without shared definitions, integration and reporting produce conflicting numbers that erode trust in all data.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Skipping data quality assessment — assuming existing data is correct before migration.</description>
        <reason>Data quality issues discovered during migration cause project delays; assessing early allows remediation to run in parallel with development.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No data ownership defined — no one accountable for data accuracy or access.</description>
        <reason>Unowned data degrades over time; ownership assigns the accountability needed to maintain quality rules.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring historical data — modeling current state without considering how data changes over time.</description>
        <reason>Temporal requirements (audit trails, soft deletes, effective-date ranges) discovered after the physical model is built require schema rework.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Definition drift between systems: The same entity (Customer, Order, Product) is defined differently across 4-7 systems.</description>
        <reason>The methodology offers no reconciliation pattern. Force a reconciliation step requiring both sources cited before merge.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No lineage column: A data element without lineage (source system → transformations → consumers) is half-documented.</description>
        <reason>Agents and humans both omit it because the template does not require it. Lineage is mandatory; reject dictionaries lacking it.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Static quality scorecard: Six dimensions are point-in-time; quality decays.</description>
        <reason>Without recurring re-assessment, scorecard is outdated within a quarter. Schedule weekly.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>PII / classification handled as afterthought: "Data Security" is one row at the bottom.</description>
        <reason>Classification (Public / Internal / Confidential / Restricted) drives storage, retention, masking, access. Make it first-class.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Volume estimates without growth model: 1yr/3yr columns invite linear extrapolation.</description>
        <reason>Agents plug numbers without questioning the model. State the model explicitly (linear / exponential / seasonal).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No event / state-transition modelling: Entities have lifecycles (Order: created → paid → shipped).</description>
        <reason>Methodology models attributes but not state machines. Add status enum + transitions table.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Conflates relational with non-relational data: ERD assumes relational.</description>
        <reason>Document stores, event streams, and graph data need different primitives. Agents force everything into entity-attribute-relationship form.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Business rules in prose: Rule examples are English sentences, not executable.</description>
        <reason>Agents cannot verify them mechanically without a DSL (JSON Schema, OPA Rego, dbt tests). Use executable rules.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-prompt-patterns">
      <p>Prompt pattern for dictionary draft from spec:</p>
      <prompt purpose="data-dictionary-generation"><![CDATA[
You are a BA data modeller. Read the feature spec in <spec> and the canonical dictionary in <data-dictionary.md>. Output the diff: new entities, new attributes on existing entities, deprecated attributes.

For every attribute provide: name (PascalCase entity, snake_case attr), type, required (Y/N), valid values / range, validation rule (executable: regex, enum, FK), source system, owner (GitHub handle), classification (Public/Internal/Confidential/Restricted), lineage (source → transforms → consumers).

Reject any attribute lacking classification or owner. Output as the README's Data Dictionary table format plus a Mermaid ER diagram.
      ]]></prompt>

      <p>Prompt pattern for quality scorecard:</p>
      <prompt purpose="data-quality-assessment"><![CDATA[
You profiled <table> with sample size <n>. Fill the six-dimension scorecard (accuracy, completeness, consistency, timeliness, validity, uniqueness).

For each: state metric, finding, examples (redacted), score (1-5), priority (H/M/L). Use a 4-week rolling window for timeliness. For consistency, compare against <reference-system>.

No claim without a count + percentage. End with the top three remediation actions, each with owner and effort estimate.
      ]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Drive BA Data Analysis as a four-stage pipeline:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Extract — ingest the feature spec, existing dictionary, and live schema (information_schema, dbt manifest.json, Prisma schema.prisma).</item>
        <item>Draft — produce or update the data dictionary with attributes, validations, classification, lineage, and Mermaid/dbml ERD.</item>
        <item>Validate — run quality probes against sample data (Great Expectations / dbt tests / Soda checks) and fill the six-dimension scorecard.</item>
        <item>Govern — diff against canonical dictionary, open PRs per drift, request human sign-off for any classification change.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Persist data-dictionary.md, erd.mmd, and quality-scorecard.md in git so every run is a reviewable diff.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent (converts approved changes into SDD tasks), password-scrubber-agent (mandatory pre-step; SOPs contain credentials), a purpose-built data-modeller agent (canonical dictionary + classification rules; output JSON Schema for codegen), a schema-drift agent (cron, daily; diffs information_schema against data-dictionary.md), a data-quality agent (cron, weekly; runs quality suites and posts scorecard).</statement>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Data modeling and quality tools:</p>
      <list>
        <item>dbt (data build tool) — Logical/physical model + executable tests. (https://docs.getdbt.com)</item>
        <item>dbt-osmosis — Auto-propagates column descriptions and tests across dbt models.</item>
        <item>great_expectations — Data quality suites mapping to six dimensions. (https://docs.greatexpectations.io)</item>
        <item>soda-core — YAML-defined quality checks runnable in CI. (https://docs.soda.io)</item>
        <item>sqlfluff — Lint dictionary-bound SQL before agents run it. (https://docs.sqlfluff.com)</item>
        <item>schemaspy — Generates HTML + ERDs from any JDBC database. (https://schemaspy.org)</item>
        <item>tbls — CI-friendly DB documentation (markdown + Mermaid ERD) from live schema. (https://github.com/k1LoW/tbls)</item>
        <item>dbml-cli — Render ERDs from .dbml; round-trips to SQL. (https://dbml.dbdiagram.io/cli)</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli — Render erDiagram Mermaid blocks to SVG/PNG in CI.</item>
        <item>datacontract-cli — Lint and verify Data Contract YAML. (https://cli.datacontract.com)</item>
        <item>sqlglot — Parse + transpile SQL, extract column lineage. (https://github.com/tobymao/sqlglot)</item>
        <item>openlineage / marquez — Capture column-level lineage from dbt, Airflow, Spark. (https://openlineage.io)</item>
        <item>presidio (Microsoft) — PII detection/redaction before LLM ingestion. (https://microsoft.github.io/presidio)</item>
        <item>liquibase / flyway / alembic — Migrations as the executable physical model.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Platforms and services for data catalogs and governance:</p>
      <list>
        <item>dbt Cloud / dbt Core — SaaS / OSS. Canonical contract layer; agents read manifest.json for typed model graph.</item>
        <item>dbdiagram.io / dbdocs.io — SaaS. .dbml is plain text, git-versionable. Best-fit for reviewable ERD in PR.</item>
        <item>DataHub — OSS (LinkedIn). Catalog + lineage; agents push/pull definitions, classifications. (GraphQL + REST)</item>
        <item>OpenMetadata — OSS. Catalog with column-level lineage and quality test integration. (REST + Python SDK)</item>
        <item>Atlan / Alation / Collibra — SaaS. Enterprise catalogs; SSO + governance gates often slow agent loops.</item>
        <item>Monte Carlo / Bigeye / Anomalo — SaaS. Observability layer feeding timeliness dimension automatically.</item>
        <item>Soda Cloud — SaaS. Pairs with soda-core for quality reports.</item>
        <item>Great Expectations Cloud — SaaS. Hosted GX with API.</item>
        <item>Postgres / MySQL / SQL Server / Snowflake / BigQuery — DB. Agents introspect live schema via information_schema.</item>
        <item>Apache Atlas — OSS. Heavyweight; pick only if already running Hadoop ecosystem.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Classification is mandatory, not optional: Every attribute carries Public / Internal / Confidential / Restricted; downstream tooling keys off it.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Owner is a human handle, not a team: GitHub username or email; one per attribute.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Lineage column on every attribute: source_system → transforms → consumers. Without it the dictionary is a graveyard.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Executable rules, not English: Validation expressed as regex, enum, FK, or dbt/GX test ID. Prose rules drift; tests fail loudly.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Naming is an ADR: Pick snake_case columns + PascalCase entities + singular table names and write it down once.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Conceptual model first, in Mermaid, in git: Stakeholder review happens in PR comments, not Visio.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Reconcile before extending: When adding customer.email, search every system for existing email and document mapping.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Quality scorecard is recurring, not point-in-time: Schedule weekly; track trend, not snapshot.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>State machines for entities with lifecycles: Add status enum + transitions table; reject transitions outside table.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Retention + DPA columns for Confidential / Restricted: Tie to records-of-processing-activity (GDPR Article 30).</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Volumes assume explicit growth model: Linear / exponential / seasonal; cite assumption next to number.</statement>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Definitions are versioned: Definition change is semantic-versioned PR with deprecation notice; consumers get migration time.</statement>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated columns: Agents invent created_at / updated_at columns that live schema does not have.</description>
        <reason>Always pass introspected schema in prompt; reject any column not present without explicit ADD task.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Type-coercion blind spots: Agents map varchar(50) to text interchangeably.</description>
        <reason>In some warehouses (BigQuery STRING vs SQL Server NVARCHAR) the difference matters. Pin types to target dialect.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Silent classification downgrade: Agent re-emits attribute and drops Confidential tag.</description>
        <reason>Always include classification of every existing attribute in prompt; reject diffs lowering classification without ADR.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Definition collision: Two systems both define Customer; agent picks one and overwrites.</description>
        <reason>Force reconciliation step requiring both sources cited before merge.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>PII leakage in sample rows: "Show me 5 example rows" → real emails in prompt.</description>
        <reason>Always pre-redact via Presidio or use synthetic samples generated from schema.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Volume math fabrication: Agents produce confident 3-year numbers from single multiplier.</description>
        <reason>Require statement of model (linear / exp / seasonal) + assumption inputs; otherwise "needs human estimate".</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Cardinality misnaming: 1:N vs N:M confusion creates wrong ERDs.</description>
        <reason>Constrain agent to derive cardinality from FK + uniqueness constraints in information_schema, never prose.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Dropped historical context: Agents rewrite description, losing rationale.</description>
        <reason>Always require change-log row appended, never a description replacement.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No nullability invariants: Agents flag Required: Y but emit no NOT NULL constraint.</description>
        <reason>Bind the dictionary's Required column to migration generator (alembic / liquibase) so they cannot diverge.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Inferring meaning from name: is_active differs in CRM vs billing.</description>
        <reason>Force lineage + business definition on every Boolean.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Token bombs from full schema dumps: 400-table catalog blows context window.</description>
        <reason>Slice by feature scope; pass only entities the spec touches.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Dictionary becomes only source of truth, then rots: Agent updates dictionary but not migration.</description>
        <reason>Always pair dictionary PRs with migration + dbt tests in same commit, gated by tbls/schemaspy diff.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Mermaid ERD limits: Diagrams over 30 entities become unreadable.</description>
        <reason>Force per-bounded-context diagrams (one Mermaid file per domain).</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/data-dictionary.md" purpose="Per-entity template with attributes table, example records, relationships, and business rules."/>
      <template path="templates/data-requirements.md" purpose="Project-level data requirements: entities, attributes, derived data, quality thresholds, volumes, integration, security."/>
      <template path="templates/data-quality-assessment.md" purpose="Assessment report per quality dimension with scoring table and recommendations."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_modeling"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entity%E2%80%93relationship_model"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Database_design"/>
      <ref slug="database-design"/>
      <ref slug="business-process-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="specification-writing"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
