<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-triggers-and-timing" title="Expansion Triggers and Timing">
  <summary>Identifying upsell and cross-sell signals from product usage data, and choosing the right moment to present each offer.</summary>

  <section title="Upsell Triggers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Fire a upsell trigger when an account crosses 80% of a metered limit (subscribers, API calls, storage, seats). Present the offer at 80%, escalate at 90%, make it mandatory framing at 100%. Do not wait for 100% — the customer is already frustrated.</statement>
      <rationale>An 80%-limit trigger hits at the moment of high engagement and growing value, before frustration sets in. At 100%, the experience is broken and the offer feels like a barrier, not a benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Upsell signal inventory: hitting limits (highest-intent trigger), using advanced features on a lower tier (power-user signal), growing team size in a per-seat product, explicitly requesting gated features, high usage frequency (candidate for annual-plan upgrade to reduce churn risk).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Sell Opportunities">
    <p>Cross-sell signal mapping: project tool (communication add-on), course product (implementation coaching after course completion), single software product (integration or training), one product in a catalog (bundle offer to adjacent product).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cross-sell only after the customer has achieved a meaningful success milestone with the current product. Before first value is delivered, cross-sell offers register as premature upsell pressure and degrade trust.</statement>
      <rationale>First-success timing produces 2–3x higher cross-sell conversion than time-based campaigns. The customer is in a high-satisfaction state and is thinking about "what's next" — the cross-sell offer answers that question.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bad Timing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never present upsell or cross-sell offers during: active support escalation, within the first 7 days of signup (before first value), immediately after purchase (buyer's remorse window), or during payment failure resolution.</statement>
      <rationale>Upselling during negative experiences creates permanent price resistance and negative associations that persist even after the issue is resolved. The offer is associated with the frustrating moment, not the product value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set a maximum upsell cadence of one offer per quarter per account. More than one upsell per quarter trains users to filter out product emails entirely.</statement>
      <rationale>The metric to optimize is expansion MRR, not message send rate. Aggressive cadence accelerates list fatigue, which ultimately reduces both upsell conversion and regular product engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
