<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-offer-framing" title="Offer Framing and Friction Reduction">
  <summary>Value-based offer framing anchored to customer-specific data points, and eliminating upgrade friction to 2 clicks or fewer.</summary>

  <section title="Offer Framing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor every upsell offer to a customer-specific data point — their actual usage number, not a generic plan benefit. "You've used 900 of 1,000 subscribers" converts 3–5x better than "Upgrade to get more subscribers."</statement>
      <rationale>Customer-specific data proves the agent read their account, not a template list. It frames the upgrade as a response to the customer's proven behavior, not a sales attempt. Generic plan benefit copy is indistinguishable from spam.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Usage-anchored upsell: "Your list is growing — you've reached 900 of 1,000 subscribers. Upgrade to Growth ($49/mo) for 5,000 subscribers + advanced automation. [Upgrade Now — first month 50% off]"</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Generic upsell: "Want to upgrade to Pro? Get more features and better limits." No customer data, no specific benefit tied to their behavior. Reads as a marketing email, not a product notification.</note>
    </example>
    <p>Value framing approaches: ROI-based ("Pro saves you 10 hours/month = $500 value"), comparison ("for $20 more, you get 10x capacity"), social proof ("most teams your size use Pro"), risk reduction ("try Pro free for 14 days").</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Friction Reduction">
    <rule>
      <statement>Upgrade flow must complete in 2 clicks or fewer from the notification to the upgraded state. Every additional step costs 40–60% of remaining conversion intent.</statement>
      <rationale>Purchase intent degrades rapidly with friction. A customer who clicked "upgrade" and encountered a form with 4 fields + a confirmation email lost 80% of their upgrade intent by the time the email arrived.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Upgrade experience requirements: show clear value difference between tiers, highlight what they gain (not what they are missing), one-click upgrade button, automatic prorated billing, immediate access post-upgrade, confirmation message that validates the decision.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never offer a permanent discount in an upsell email. Once a 30% discount is offered, full-price conversion drops permanently because the customer's reference price is now the discounted price.</statement>
      <rationale>Discount anchoring is well-documented in behavioral economics. If discounts are used, use limited-time (e.g., "first month only") or one-use framing to prevent the reference-price shift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
