<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples-and-gotchas" title="Expansion Examples and AI-Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>SaaS usage-limit and course cross-sell case examples with measured results, and agent limitations for expansion messaging.</summary>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS email tool usage-limit upsell: in-app notification at 80% of 1,000-subscriber limit, email at 90%, hard upgrade prompt at 100%. Message: "Your list is growing! You've reached 900 of 1,000 subscribers. Upgrade to Growth ($49/mo) for 5,000 subscribers + advanced automation + priority delivery. [Upgrade Now — first month 50% off]." Results: 40% upgraded within 7 days of limit notification, 25% used discount, expansion MRR +15%.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Online course ($497) cross-sell to coaching program ($2,000): triggered at course completion milestone. Message: "Congratulations on finishing [Course]. You've learned the framework — now let's apply it. Join the Implementation Cohort (6 weeks group coaching + accountability). Course graduates get $500 off. [Apply Now]." Results: 5% course-buyer conversion to coaching, $1,500 net revenue per conversion, 50% increase in customer LTV.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs default to salesy, superlative-heavy tone in upsell copy.</description>
      <reason>Constrain with "no superlatives, no scarcity language, lead with the customer's specific data point." Review every draft for tone before sending. Salesy tone in product notifications reduces trust in the product itself.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent fabricates personalization when the data is not provided ("we saw you doubled your team!").</description>
      <reason>Require the agent to quote the source field for every data point used. Fabricated personalization is worse than generic — it signals that the system is making things up and damages trust.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent sends price-change or upgrade emails autonomously.</description>
      <reason>Pricing decisions require business owner sign-off. Auto-sent pricing emails create contractual and trust implications that cannot be undone.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates discount offers that exceed margin floor without rules-based constraints.</description>
      <reason>Codify discount caps in system rules (never more than X%), not prompts. LLMs will rationalize aggressive discounts to "close" hypothetical deals if discount logic is left to prompt reasoning.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Same trigger fires across email, in-app, and push notification to the same account on the same day.</description>
      <reason>Triple-channel simultaneous trigger reads as spam and creates negative brand association. Deduplicate by account-trigger-date with a minimum 72-hour window between channels for the same trigger.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent acts on stale CSV showing customer on Free tier after they already upgraded yesterday.</description>
      <reason>Pull live subscription state from Stripe/Chargebee API immediately before generating any upsell copy. Sending an upgrade offer to a paying Pro customer is an embarrassing failure that inflates churn risk.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Expansion Tracking">
    <p>Track expansion attribution by trigger type (usage threshold, feature signal, annual-plan offer) so bottom-quartile triggers can be eliminated and top triggers doubled down on. Expansion MRR without trigger attribution is unoptimizable.</p>
    <reference path="templates/expansion-dashboard.md">Monthly expansion MRR dashboard template by trigger type</reference>
    <reference path="templates/triggers.py">Expansion trigger detector: usage threshold and advanced feature signals</reference>
  </section>
</text>
