<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="north-star-metric">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Framework for identifying, validating, and operationalizing a single metric that captures core customer value and aligns all teams — includes selection process and validation tests.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>north-star</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>okr</tag>
      <tag>alignment</tag>
      <tag>value-delivery</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>North Star Metric</title>

    <summary>A framework for identifying, validating, and operationalizing a single metric that captures the core value a product delivers to customers — predicts long-term revenue, aligns all teams, and serves as the root of the OKR tree. Includes a 4-step selection process, validation test, real-product examples, and input-metrics tree pattern.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Teams tracking 50 metrics optimize in different directions. A North Star Metric (NSM) forces agreement on what "customer value delivered" means, makes trade-offs explicit, and converts disagreements about priorities into measurable hypotheses. Revenue and page views are explicitly disqualified — they measure company extraction or activity, not value delivery.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Teams are misaligned on what success looks like day-to-day.</item>
        <item>Marketing optimizes for clicks, product for features, sales for revenue — no shared growth lever.</item>
        <item>Setting up OKRs and need a root metric that team-level key results should roll up to.</item>
        <item>Scaling growth investment and need to validate that acquisition spend improves the right outcome.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch with no usage data — the NSM requires retention/revenue correlation to validate.</item>
        <item>Very early (solo, pre-PMF) stage — pick one proxy metric and iterate; formal NSM process adds overhead before it helps.</item>
        <item>When the product serves two fundamentally different user types with different value definitions — a single NSM will be dishonest for one group.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="definition-and-characteristics">
      <rule>
        <statement>The North Star Metric must measure customer value delivered, not company value extracted; it must be a leading indicator of revenue, not revenue itself.</statement>
        <rationale>Revenue as NSM causes teams to optimize for short-term extraction — discounts, forced upgrades, retention walls — at the expense of actual value delivery. When the NSM rises because customers are getting more value, revenue follows; when revenue is chased directly, product quality declines.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Five characteristics of a valid NSM: measures customer value (not company value), is a leading indicator of revenue, reflects the product vision, is actionable (specific teams can move it), is understandable by everyone in one sentence.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="disqualified-metrics">
      <p>Revenue: lags value delivery and causes extraction optimization. Sign-ups: no value exchange has occurred yet. Page views: activity without proven value. DAU/MAU alone: presence without value delivery. These are inputs or lagging outcomes, not NSM candidates.</p>
      <p>Real NSM examples by product: Airbnb — nights booked; Spotify — time spent listening; Slack — daily active users × messages sent; Uber — rides completed; Netflix — hours watched; Shopify — gross merchandise volume.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="four-step-selection-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run the four-step NSM selection: identify core value delivered, find the action that proves customers received that value, find the metric measuring that action, validate that improving the metric improves long-term revenue.</statement>
        <rationale>Without the validation step (step 4), teams adopt a plausible-sounding NSM that does not actually predict business outcomes. The validation test requires empirical correlation analysis between the candidate metric and retention or revenue growth.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="value-equation">
      <p>NSM = (action that delivers value) × frequency × number of users. This formula ensures the NSM captures breadth (users), depth (frequency), and quality (value action).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="product-examples">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Project management tool. Core value: helping teams complete work efficiently. NSM: weekly tasks completed per active team. Why: shows value delivery (work getting done), combines engagement with value, correlates with retention and revenue. Input metrics: number of active teams (growth), tasks created per team (adoption), task completion rate (product quality).</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>E-learning platform. NSM: lessons completed (not hours watched). Why lessons, not hours: watching is not learning; completion signals value delivery. Input metrics: new enrollments, enrollment-to-start rate, lesson completion rate, re-engagement rate (returning students).</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Freelance marketplace. NSM: projects completed with positive review. Why: shows successful value exchange for both sides; predicts repeat usage from both clients and freelancers. Input metrics: active freelancers, jobs posted, job-to-hire rate, delivery rate, satisfaction rate.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="validation-test">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run the NSM validation test quarterly: confirm that when the NSM goes up, retention goes up and revenue eventually follows; confirm that when the NSM goes down, churn increases.</statement>
        <rationale>Products evolve. An NSM that was valid at 1,000 users may become a vanity metric at 100,000 users if the product has shifted. Quarterly validation prevents teams from optimizing a stale metric for months before noticing the divergence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="nsm-and-okrs">
      <p>Relationship: NSM is what you optimize for — it rarely changes (quarterly at most). OKRs are quarterly goals that move the NSM. Structure: NSM at top → company-level objective → team-level key results (each owned by one team) → input metrics feeding into the NSM. Each team's KRs should be traceable to a specific NSM input metric.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-1-define">
      <list>
        <item>List the product's core value in one sentence.</item>
        <item>Brainstorm 5-10 candidate metrics that could represent that value.</item>
        <item>Test each candidate: Does it measure customer value? Is it a leading indicator? Is it actionable? Can it be explained in one sentence?</item>
        <item>Validate empirically: run correlation analysis between each candidate and retention/revenue growth.</item>
        <item>Choose one. Get leadership buy-in before proceeding.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-2-instrument">
      <list>
        <item>Write the exact calculation formula in a shared document — leave no ambiguity about what counts.</item>
        <item>Set up tracking so the metric updates at minimum weekly.</item>
        <item>Create a dashboard visible to all teams.</item>
        <item>Identify 3-5 input metrics and assign one team owner per input metric.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-3-operationalize">
      <list>
        <item>Include NSM in weekly leadership reviews.</item>
        <item>Set quarterly NSM targets and align OKRs to them.</item>
        <item>Run the validation test quarterly (retention and revenue correlation).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Choosing multiple North Star metrics ("we have two NSMs").</description>
        <reason>Two NSMs produce the same misalignment problem the NSM was designed to solve. Teams trade off between them differently; there is no single shared success definition. Use input metrics for team-level targets, not additional NSMs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>NSM that requires a paragraph to explain.</description>
        <reason>If the entire company cannot understand the metric from a one-sentence description, it will not align behavior. Simplify until it passes the "explain to a new hire in 10 seconds" test.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Setting the NSM and not reviewing the correlation for more than a quarter.</description>
        <reason>Products evolve; metrics that were predictive at one stage become vanity metrics at the next. A stale NSM silently misaligns the company for months before anyone notices.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/nsm-definition.md" purpose="North Star Metric definition card: metric, why, current state, input metrics, dashboard link."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="activation-tactics"/>
      <ref slug="retention-strategies"/>
      <ref slug="growth-loops"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
