<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Account Health Scoring Model Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five hard rules for a micro-agency account-health model with sub-20 clients.</summary>

  <section title="The six signals + scoring">
    <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
S1 Retainer utilization variance over 4 weeks:
   |actual - bought| / bought
   ≤ 15%   → 2
   16-30%  → 1
   &gt; 30%   → 0

S2 Decision-maker engagement (calls + replies):
   ≥ 1 substantive touch per 2 weeks → 2
   1 per 4 weeks                     → 1
   &lt; 1 per 4 weeks                   → 0

S3 Scope-creep delta vs. SOW (cumulative hours over scope):
   &lt; 10% over OR signed-off CO       → 2
   10-25% over, no CO                 → 1
   &gt; 25% over, no CO                  → 0

S4 Payment punctuality (last 3 invoices avg DSO):
   ≤ net terms                        → 2
   &lt; 15 days late                     → 1
   ≥ 15 days late OR open dispute     → 0

S5 Referral / advocacy signal:
   gave referral OR public testimonial in last 6 months → 2
   verbal positive in last 3 months                     → 1
   none                                                  → 0

S6 Executive sponsor stability:
   same sponsor &gt; 12 months           → 2
   same sponsor 3-12 months           → 1
   new sponsor in last 3 months       → 0

Total → Green (10-12), Yellow (5-9), Red (0-4).
    ]]></code>
  </section>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-six-signals-not-one" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Health score uses ALL six signals. Single-signal scoring (NPS-only, utilization-only) hides correlated risks. A client at 100% utilization with a brand-new sponsor and 30-day late payment is yellow, not green.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gainsight CS health-scoring data 2024; ChurnZero analyses">Single-signal scoring produced 35-50% false-positive "healthy" classifications in Gainsight's 2024 retention study. Multi-signal aggregation reduced false positives to 8-12%. At sub-20 scale, each false positive costs a meaningful % of revenue.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-observable-not-opinion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every signal is observable from data the agency already collects (timesheets, invoice records, calendar, Slack, CRM). "I feel like this client is unhappy" does not score. If a signal can't be measured, it's not in the model.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kahneman, Noise (2021)">Founder gut-feel scoring produces 30-50% week-on-week variance for the same account. Observable signals produce &lt; 5%. The model exists to remove noise from health assessment so trends are real, not founder mood.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-threshold-cutoffs-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The 0/1/2 thresholds per signal are fixed at quarter start and not adjusted mid-quarter. Moving cutoffs to "make the dashboard look better" destroys the model. Cutoffs are reviewed at quarter-end retro, not weekly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Statistical process control - SPC stability principle">Moving thresholds is the classic Goodhart's Law failure: the metric becomes the goal, the goal stops measuring health. Stability lets trend lines be meaningful across weeks; quarter-end review catches genuine threshold staleness.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-weekly-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score every account every week (Mondays). Skipping a week creates a perception gap that the model has nothing to say about (when in fact it has 0 changes to report — also valuable). Continuous cadence catches deterioration in 1-2 weeks vs. 6-8 weeks for quarterly-only review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer-success industry cadence research; Gainsight 2024 best-practices">Quarterly QBR alone catches problems at week 8-12; weekly health scoring catches them at week 1-2. The 4-6 week head start is the difference between save and churn.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-escalation-triggers-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Two trigger conditions force an account intervention: (a) score drops ≥ 2 points week-over-week, or (b) account sits Red for 2 consecutive weeks. Triggers produce a named action (call DM, scope-down conversation, internal post-mortem) within 48h.</statement>
      <rationale source="Voss "Never Split the Difference"; sales pipeline 30/60/90 retention rules">Without escalation triggers, the dashboard becomes wallpaper. Forcing a named action within 48h converts data into recovery. The 48h window aligns with research on intervention efficacy windows.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Account scored across 6 signals">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Acme Inc., 2026-05-20:
  S1 utilization variance 12%  → 2
  S2 DM engagement weekly      → 2
  S3 scope creep 18% no CO     → 1
  S4 last 3 invoices avg 8d late → 1
  S5 verbal positive Q1         → 1
  S6 sponsor stable 14 months   → 2
  Total: 9 (Yellow, trending down from 11 last week)
  Trigger: 2-point drop → action: 30-min call with DM by Wed, raise scope CO.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 (6 signals), r2 (observable), r5 (trigger fires).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="NPS-only false-positive">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Acme Inc.: NPS = 9 (last quarterly survey) → "healthy"

In reality: utilization at 20% (paying for hours not used), DM hasn't replied in 3 weeks,
2 invoices 30 days late. NPS lags by quarter; cancellation arrives 8 weeks later as a surprise.
Repair: score on the 6-signal model. Multi-signal would have flagged red at week 2.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Single-signal NPS health is the canonical false-positive pattern.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
