<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="design-critique Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for design-critique. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every piece of feedback must be connected to a stated design goal or usability principle.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Feedback not anchored to a goal is preference; preference-based feedback cannot be evaluated objectively and degrades into opinion battles.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The presenter decides what feedback to incorporate; it is their design, their call.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Removing designer agency from critique sessions destroys ownership and produces resentful implementation; the presenter's authority over their work must be explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>State the design stage before showing designs; polish feedback on exploration work is harmful.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Polish feedback on early exploration locks in a direction prematurely and wastes time debating details that may be discarded.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Limit major concerns to five items maximum per critique session.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Longer lists dilute priority and overwhelm the designer; five major concerns force prioritization and produce actionable output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ask clarifying questions before giving feedback; do not assume you understand the constraint space.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Feedback based on misunderstood constraints wastes the session and erodes trust; clarification first prevents this.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide at least two observations about what is working well, not only concerns.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Critique that identifies only problems gives the designer no signal about what to preserve; positive observations are as valuable as negative ones for iteration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide a list of decisions already made (not open for discussion) when requesting agent critique.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent may critique deliberate trade-offs it is unaware of; pre-specifying closed decisions prevents churn on settled questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require agent to steelman the current design before critiquing when used for solo work.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Steelmanning surfaces the designer's own rationale explicitly and produces more balanced critique output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agent critique output is a starting point for human review, not the final critique record.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent cannot replicate the back-and-forth clarification dynamic of real critique, and it may contradict design system rules it is unaware of.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
