<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Critique Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Design Critique. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-tied-to-goal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every feedback item references the design goal or a heuristic; bare 'I would do it differently' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-critique facilitation">Goal-anchored feedback turns opinion into decision input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-designer-drives" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Designer presents context, goal, and specific feedback ask; critique without an ask becomes a free-for-all.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-critique facilitation">Without a designer-set ask, the room defaults to taste.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-time-boxed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Session is time-boxed (45 to 90 minutes) with structure: context, walk-through, feedback per dimension, decisions, next actions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Facilitation practice">Unstructured sessions blow time and surface low-signal points.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-decisions-logged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decisions and follow-up actions are logged in a shared doc within 24 hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-ops practice">Unlogged decisions are re-argued the next sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-no-stealth-approval" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Critique is not a sign-off; approvals follow a separate decision review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Design-critique facilitation">Conflating critique and approval causes designers to avoid honest critique.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-design-critique.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
