<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Design Critique Process and Roles">
  <summary>Critique vs. criticism distinction, session roles, stage-appropriate feedback types, and five-step critique process.</summary>

  <section title="Critique vs. Criticism">
    <p>
      Critique: based on stated goals, specific and actionable, about the work, asks questions, improves design.
      Criticism: based on personal preference, vague, about the designer, makes judgments, hurts feelings.
    </p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every piece of feedback must be connected to a stated design goal or usability principle.</statement>
      <rationale>Feedback not anchored to a goal is preference; preference-based feedback cannot be evaluated objectively and degrades into opinion battles.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Roles">
    <p>
      Presenter — shows work, states goals and constraints, asks for specific feedback type.
      Facilitator — keeps discussion on track, ensures all voices are heard, redirects opinion to goals.
      Participants — ask clarifying questions before giving feedback, connect observations to goals.
      Note-taker — captures key feedback, questions raised, decisions made, action items.
    </p>
    <rule>
      <statement>The presenter decides what feedback to incorporate; it is their design, their call.</statement>
      <rationale>Removing designer agency from critique sessions destroys ownership and produces resentful implementation; the presenter's authority over their work must be explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage-Appropriate Feedback">
    <p>
      Directional feedback (Is this the right approach?) — for exploration stage; many options open.
      Refinement feedback (How can this be better?) — for iteration stage; one direction being developed.
      Polish feedback (Is this ready to ship?) — for final stage; micro-decisions and completeness.
    </p>
    <rule>
      <statement>State the design stage before showing designs; polish feedback on exploration work is harmful.</statement>
      <rationale>Polish feedback on early exploration locks in a direction prematurely and wastes time debating details that may be discarded.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Process">
    <p>Step 1: Set context — problem, user, constraints, stage, feedback type requested.</p>
    <p>Step 2: Present the work systematically — explain decisions made, point out areas of uncertainty, do not over-apologize.</p>
    <p>Step 3: Clarifying questions — participants ask to understand, not judge, before giving feedback.</p>
    <p>Step 4: Give structured feedback — Observation → Principle/Goal → Impact → (Optional suggestion).</p>
    <p>Step 5: Capture and prioritize — note-taker documents feedback, questions, decisions, and action items.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Observation: "The submit button is below the fold." Principle: "Users frequently miss below-fold CTAs on mobile." Impact: "This could hurt conversion on small screens." Suggestion: "What if we added a sticky footer button?"</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"I don't like the colors." — preference statement with no observation, no principle, no impact. Not actionable.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/critique-session.md">Full critique session document template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/feedback-framework.md">Observation → Principle → Impact format with worked example</reference>
</text>
