<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Design Critique Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Rules for giving and receiving feedback, facilitator responsibilities, async critique format, and agent limitations.</summary>

  <section title="Giving Feedback Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit major concerns to five items maximum per critique session.</statement>
      <rationale>Longer lists dilute priority and overwhelm the designer; five major concerns force prioritization and produce actionable output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask clarifying questions before giving feedback; do not assume you understand the constraint space.</statement>
      <rationale>Feedback based on misunderstood constraints wastes the session and erodes trust; clarification first prevents this.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide at least two observations about what is working well, not only concerns.</statement>
      <rationale>Critique that identifies only problems gives the designer no signal about what to preserve; positive observations are as valuable as negative ones for iteration.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No stated design goals before critique begins.</description>
      <reason>Feedback without criteria defaults to taste; the session degrades into preference-based debate with no resolution mechanism.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Solutioning instead of critiquing — redesigning the product in the meeting.</description>
      <reason>The critique session is for analysis and feedback, not real-time redesign; solutioning prevents the designer from incorporating multiple feedback sources into their own solution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Presenter defending every point instead of listening.</description>
      <reason>Defensive presenter blocks feedback reception; thanking participants for honest feedback is the appropriate response during the session.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Usage Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a list of decisions already made (not open for discussion) when requesting agent critique.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent may critique deliberate trade-offs it is unaware of; pre-specifying closed decisions prevents churn on settled questions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require agent to steelman the current design before critiquing when used for solo work.</statement>
      <rationale>Steelmanning surfaces the designer's own rationale explicitly and produces more balanced critique output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Agent critique output is a starting point for human review, not the final critique record.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent cannot replicate the back-and-forth clarification dynamic of real critique, and it may contradict design system rules it is unaware of.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/figma-elements.sh">Extract Figma frame element names via REST API for agent input</reference>
</text>
