<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design-principles" title="Dashboard Design Principles">
  <summary>Design principles for actionable dashboards, dashboard type taxonomy, and metric selection criteria.</summary>

  <section title="Core Design Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include 5-10 key metrics maximum on any single dashboard. A dashboard with 30 metrics is a report, not a decision tool.</statement>
      <rationale>Too many metrics dilute attention. A dashboard should answer the question "is my business healthy today?" in under 5 seconds. More than 10 metrics prevents this glance-level assessment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Glanceable: status visible in 5 seconds without analysis</item>
      <item>Focused: 5-10 key metrics maximum</item>
      <item>Current: real-time or daily updates (not monthly)</item>
      <item>Actionable: only metrics you can directly influence</item>
      <item>Comparative: show trend vs prior period, not just point-in-time value</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dashboard Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build separate dashboards for daily pulse, weekly review, and monthly report — each has a different audience, update frequency, and decision type.</statement>
      <rationale>A daily dashboard optimized for speed cannot serve monthly analysis. Combining them produces a hybrid that does neither well.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Daily pulse: quick health check, real-time or daily updates, 5-7 metrics</item>
      <item>Weekly review: trend analysis, weekly update, 10-12 metrics</item>
      <item>Monthly report: full analysis, monthly update, full metric set</item>
      <item>Real-time: live monitoring for time-sensitive operations</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Metric Selection Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include only metrics that pass the actionability test: if this metric changes 20% in the wrong direction, what specifically would you do differently?</statement>
      <rationale>Lagging vanity metrics (total pageviews, total followers) feel important but produce no decision. Actionable metrics (conversion rate, CAC, churn rate) map to specific interventions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
