<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Technical Debt Framework">
  <summary>Defines technical debt types, the deliberate/inadvertent quadrant, and the six-step process for making debt visible, quantified, and strategically paid down.</summary>

  <section title="Debt Types">
    <p>Technical debt is the implied cost of additional rework caused by choosing easy solutions now instead of better approaches that take longer — borrowing against future productivity.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Deliberate: conscious shortcut, e.g. "ship now, refactor later."</item>
      <item>Accidental: discovered a better pattern after the fact.</item>
      <item>Bit rot: environment changed around stable code — outdated dependencies.</item>
      <item>Design debt: architecture that cannot scale to the next requirement.</item>
      <item>Documentation debt: missing docs mean only one person can maintain the system.</item>
      <item>Test debt: missing tests prevent safe changes to production code.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Deliberate prudent debt is acceptable; deliberate reckless debt is not. Inadvertent debt must be discovered and registered as soon as identified.</statement>
      <rationale>Reckless debt accumulates compounding interest; prudent debt is a conscious trade-off with a planned repayment date.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Six-Step Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — Make debt visible: tag every known item in the issue tracker with a tech-debt label; capture what, why, time tax, and fix cost per item.</statement>
      <rationale>Invisible debt cannot be prioritized; registration is the prerequisite for all downstream steps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Quantify impact: measure interest as (development slowdown × frequency) + risk cost. Require at least one evidence source (build-time graph, incident post-mortem, PR cycle time delta).</statement>
      <rationale>Without instrumented data the interest score is political; evidence anchors the number to reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Prioritize: score each item on interest rate (40%), contagion (20%), effort to fix (20%), alignment with planned work (20%). Priority = Impact × Alignment / Effort.</statement>
      <rationale>Alignment-weighted scoring ensures the lowest marginal cost paydown happens during adjacent feature work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Allocate capacity: reserve 15-20% of every sprint continuously plus one focused quarterly debt sprint. Maintain a separate, visible budget line — never let it merge with the feature backlog.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a hard, visible budget line the allocation evaporates under feature pressure every sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Pay down strategically: fix during related features (lowest marginal cost), fix highest-interest first, fix blocking debt, batch related items for efficiency.</statement>
      <rationale>Batching related debt reduces context switching cost; fixing during related work amortizes setup overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6 — Prevent new debt: Definition of Done must include "no new unregistered debt"; code review catches it; architectural decisions are documented.</statement>
      <rationale>Prevention cost is always lower than remediation cost; gate at the point of creation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Tracking debt item count instead of interest reduction — closing 20 cheap items while leaving the one item that causes 40% of PR delay.</description>
      <reason>Item count is a vanity metric; the business impact is in interest rate reduction (build time, MTTR, PR cycle time).</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>A 6-month-old register with 30-50% stale entries — items fixed silently, descriptions outdated, owners departed.</description>
      <reason>Stale registers destroy credibility; teams stop trusting and stop maintaining them. Re-baseline quarterly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Registering automatable bit-rot (dependency upgrades, formatter violations) as debt items.</description>
      <reason>Machine-fixable items waste PM prioritization bandwidth; automate via Renovate/Dependabot and remove from the register.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Debt items deferred 4+ quarters with no decision — zombie entries that destroy register credibility.</description>
      <reason>Every zombie must become either "done next quarter" or "accepted debt" — a positive, explicit choice.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/debt-hotspots.sh">Bash script generating JSONL candidate list (churn x complexity) to seed the scanner subagent.</reference>
</text>
