<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Technical Debt Examples">
  <summary>Two worked examples — legacy API dual-maintenance and missing test coverage — demonstrating how to apply the scoring formula to reach a concrete paydown decision.</summary>

  <section title="Example: Legacy API Dual-Maintenance">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Old API v1 still maintained alongside v2 with 20 remaining users.</note>
      <note>Interest: 3 hours/sprint maintaining both + risk of v1 bugs affecting v2 users + cannot deprecate without a migration plan.</note>
      <note>Interest rate: High (ongoing time tax). Effort: Medium (migration path for 20 users). Alignment: High (API work planned next quarter).</note>
      <note>Decision: Score = High × High / Medium = prioritize in Q2 alongside planned API improvements. Lowest marginal cost because the team is already context-loaded on the API surface.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Missing Test Coverage on Billing Module">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Billing module has 10% test coverage. Impact: 2 hours extra manual testing per release, fear of changing billing code, a previous billing bug cost $5K.</note>
      <note>Interest: Medium-High. Effort: High (complex business logic requires deep domain understanding). Alignment: Medium (billing feature planned but not next sprint).</note>
      <note>Decision: Add tests as part of billing feature work — Boy Scout approach. Not standalone because alignment is medium; standalone effort is high without feature context.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring debt entirely — no register, no allocation, no visibility.</description>
      <reason>Without registration, debt is invisible to stakeholders and can never be prioritized against features.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>All-or-nothing approach: waiting for a "debt sprint" that never gets scheduled because features always win.</description>
      <reason>Continuous small allocation (15-20% per sprint) is more durable than periodic large allocations that are always displaced by roadmap pressure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No business case for debt items — technical language only, no $ or hours quantification.</description>
      <reason>Non-technical stakeholders cannot prioritize an item described only in technical terms. Every item needs a business-impact statement (hours/sprint lost, incidents caused, features blocked).</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
