<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-examples" title="Roadmap Design Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>B2B SaaS and solo product Now-Next-Later roadmap examples, and common roadmap antipatterns with fixes.</summary>

  <section title="B2B SaaS Roadmap">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Now (Q1): onboarding improvements (reduce time to value), API v2 launch (enterprise requirement), performance optimization (load times). Each tied to objective: "Improve activation rate to 40%".</note>
      <note>Next (Q2): team collaboration features (confidence: High), Slack integration (confidence: Medium), advanced permissions (confidence: Medium). Depends on: API v2 stable.</note>
      <note>Later: mobile app (pending user research validation), AI-powered insights (exploring, no commitment). Explicitly not doing: custom themes, white-labelling — not on enterprise ICP roadmap this year.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Solo Product Roadmap">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Now: core feature polish toward MLP, payment integration, basic analytics.</note>
      <note>Next: email automation, template library, referral program.</note>
      <note>Later: mobile app, team features, marketplace. Not doing: multi-language support — insufficient international user demand to justify.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Feature list with specific dates for every item.</description>
      <reason>Dates imply commitment. When any date slips, stakeholder trust erodes. Use confidence levels instead of dates for everything beyond "Now".</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>No strategic connection — initiatives not linked to objectives.</description>
      <reason>Orphaned initiatives accumulate and eventually dominate the roadmap without anyone being able to justify why. Every initiative must have an objective ID.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>"Later" column becoming a permanent graveyard.</description>
      <reason>If items never graduate from Later to Next, stakeholders stop believing the roadmap is real. Review Later quarterly and either promote, archive, or move to not-doing with a reason.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Same roadmap shared with engineering, exec, and customers.</description>
      <reason>Each audience needs a different abstraction level. Engineering needs initiative detail; exec needs theme-level strategy; customers need benefit language with no internal jargon.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
