<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Newsletter Growth Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Newsletter Growth application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-positioning-in-one-sentence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The newsletter MUST be positionable in one sentence naming audience + outcome + frequency. Without it, growth tactics are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Unfocused newsletters churn faster than they grow; positioning is the prerequisite, not an optimisation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-lead-magnet-exists" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Signup form MUST be paired with a concrete lead magnet (asset / template / cheatsheet). Email-only signup is rejected for tier 1 growth.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Bare email forms convert at 1-2%; lead-magnet forms convert at 5-15%.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-signup-above-fold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary signup form MUST be above the fold on every newsletter-relevant page (homepage + posts). Footer-only signup is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Above-fold placement triples capture rate vs footer-only on identical traffic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-confirmed-opt-in" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Signup MUST use double opt-in. Single opt-in is rejected; complaint risk is too high.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Double opt-in protects deliverability and produces a more engaged baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-referral-loop" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Plan MUST include one referral mechanism (built-in referral program OR share-to-unlock OR forwarding ask). Pure paid acquisition is rejected as the only growth lever.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Compounding referral beats paid acquisition on solo budgets.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
