<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Card Sorting Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Card Sorting application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-participant-count" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Open sort MUST have ≥15 participants; closed sort MUST have ≥30. Lower counts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Below threshold the similarity matrix is too noisy to identify confident groupings.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-user-language-cards" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cards MUST be written in user language (the words users use), not the team's internal product taxonomy.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Internal-language cards bias the sort toward the existing taxonomy and defeat the purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-similarity-matrix-computed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Analysis MUST include a similarity matrix and an agreement score per grouping. Eyeballed groupings without quantification are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Eyeballed groupings reflect researcher mental models, not participant ones.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-ambiguous-flagged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Items with &lt;60% agreement MUST be flagged for re-test, not silently assigned.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Forcing weak-agreement items into a category degrades the IA in a way that re-testing would reveal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-named-recommendation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The artefact MUST emit a recommended structure (category names + item membership) with one-sentence rationale per category. Result-only dumps without recommendation are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">The recommendation is the actionable output; the matrix is the evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
