<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="recruiting-process Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for recruiting-process. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use at least three sourcing channels per role; over-reliance on a single channel (e.g., job boards) caps the addressable candidate pool and biases toward active seekers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LinkedIn data shows 70% of the global workforce is passively open to opportunities; job boards only reach active seekers, typically 30% of the market.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Remove degree requirements that are not job-essential; replace with skills assessments or portfolio evaluation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">76% of organizations report successful hires from candidates previously excluded by degree requirements (LinkedIn). Degree proxies exclude qualified candidates from under-resourced educational backgrounds without improving quality-of-hire.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each outreach message must reference the candidate's specific work; generic "exciting opportunity" subject lines achieve less than 10% open rate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Passive candidates receive multiple generic outreach messages weekly. A specific reference to a project, article, or contribution they produced proves the sender did research and respects their time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build and maintain warm candidate lists for critical roles before those roles open; reactive hiring from a cold start adds 2-4 weeks to time-to-fill.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pipeline building converts recruiting from a reactive sprint into an ongoing relationship. When a role opens, the first outreach goes to candidates who already know the company.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post all roles internally before external sourcing begins; an internal hire closes 50-70% faster and retains institutional knowledge.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Internal candidates require less ramp time, already understand culture, and their move opens a backfill at a more junior level — cheaper to fill. Skipping internal posting destroys trust in career development commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Limit must-have requirements to 5-7 items and nice-to-have to 3-4; JDs listing 15+ requirements reduce qualified applicant volume without improving hire quality.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Research (LinkedIn, Textio) shows that long requirement lists disproportionately deter underrepresented candidates who self-screen out if they don't meet every requirement. Reducing to true requirements increases qualified applicant volume.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define the target candidate persona before writing the JD or opening sourcing channels; without a profile, sourcing generates noise and screening becomes subjective.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A persona converts the hiring manager's vague "someone like our best performer" into specific, sourceable attributes: experience range, current role, motivations, channels. This makes sourcing targeted and screening criteria explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report six core metrics weekly or monthly; any metric without a defined target and owner degrades into a vanity number.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Metrics without targets drive reporting behavior, not improvement. Assigning ownership (recruiter for time-to-fill, compensation for offer acceptance) creates accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Application process must complete in under 5 minutes and render correctly on mobile; test with a real resume before publishing every role.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">ATS default forms often include non-essential fields (graduation year, GPA, references before interview) that extend application time and reduce conversion. Mobile rendering issues silently drop applicants who don't self-report the problem.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit every AI sourcing or screening tool for demographic bias before deployment; document the audit and review annually.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI tools trained on historical hiring data replicate historical bias patterns. EEOC and EU AI Act require explainability for decisions affecting employment; undocumented AI use creates legal exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Extend the offer within 48 hours of the hiring decision; every additional day increases competing-offer risk by a measurable margin.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Top candidates in active searches often have multiple processes running in parallel. A 5-day lag between decision and offer letter loses 20-30% of candidates in competitive markets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
