<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-sourcing-methods" title="Sourcing Channels and Pipeline Building">
  <summary>Multi-channel sourcing strategy, skills-based hiring, passive candidate outreach, and talent pipeline building to reduce reactive, channel-dependent hiring.</summary>

  <section title="Multi-Channel Sourcing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use at least three sourcing channels per role; over-reliance on a single channel (e.g., job boards) caps the addressable candidate pool and biases toward active seekers.</statement>
      <rationale>LinkedIn data shows 70% of the global workforce is passively open to opportunities; job boards only reach active seekers, typically 30% of the market.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Channel Selection by Use Case">
      <p>LinkedIn: passive candidates, highest effort, highest yield for experienced roles. Employee referrals: culture-fit signal, lowest sourcing cost, fastest time-to-screen. Job boards: active seekers, medium effort, works for high-volume or well-known roles. University partnerships: entry-level pipeline, medium effort, requires relationship investment. Niche communities and Slack groups: specialized roles (e.g., ML engineers, security researchers). Agencies: hard-to-fill or time-sensitive roles; significant cost premium.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Skills-Based Hiring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Remove degree requirements that are not job-essential; replace with skills assessments or portfolio evaluation.</statement>
      <rationale>76% of organizations report successful hires from candidates previously excluded by degree requirements (LinkedIn). Degree proxies exclude qualified candidates from under-resourced educational backgrounds without improving quality-of-hire.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Identify the 5-7 essential skills for the role (not proxies).</item>
      <item>Remove degree requirements that are not legally mandated.</item>
      <item>Create or source skills assessments tied to actual job tasks.</item>
      <item>Evaluate portfolio, open-source contributions, or past projects as evidence.</item>
      <item>Use structured interviews to assess skills not visible in the portfolio.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Passive Candidate Outreach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each outreach message must reference the candidate's specific work; generic "exciting opportunity" subject lines achieve less than 10% open rate.</statement>
      <rationale>Passive candidates receive multiple generic outreach messages weekly. A specific reference to a project, article, or contribution they produced proves the sender did research and respects their time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Target response rate: 25-40%. Outreach structure: personalized subject (no "job opportunity"), opening referencing their specific work, value proposition framed for what they gain, low-commitment CTA (a conversation, not an application). Follow-up: 3 touches with different angles, then stop.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Talent Pipeline Building">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build and maintain warm candidate lists for critical roles before those roles open; reactive hiring from a cold start adds 2-4 weeks to time-to-fill.</statement>
      <rationale>Pipeline building converts recruiting from a reactive sprint into an ongoing relationship. When a role opens, the first outreach goes to candidates who already know the company.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Identify 3-5 roles most likely to open in the next 2 quarters.</item>
      <item>Build a warm list of 20-50 candidates per role.</item>
      <item>Nurture with content, company updates, and event invitations — not job postings.</item>
      <item>Track engagement (opens, replies, event attendance).</item>
      <item>Activate the warm list within 24 hours of role opening.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Internal Mobility">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post all roles internally before external sourcing begins; an internal hire closes 50-70% faster and retains institutional knowledge.</statement>
      <rationale>Internal candidates require less ramp time, already understand culture, and their move opens a backfill at a more junior level — cheaper to fill. Skipping internal posting destroys trust in career development commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
