<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-jd-and-personas" title="Job Description Writing and Candidate Personas">
  <summary>Frameworks for writing JDs that attract qualified candidates and developing candidate personas that define the target profile before sourcing begins.</summary>

  <section title="Job Description Writing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit must-have requirements to 5-7 items and nice-to-have to 3-4; JDs listing 15+ requirements reduce qualified applicant volume without improving hire quality.</statement>
      <rationale>Research (LinkedIn, Textio) shows that long requirement lists disproportionately deter underrepresented candidates who self-screen out if they don't meet every requirement. Reducing to true requirements increases qualified applicant volume.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="JD Structure">
      <p>Hook: why this role matters to the company and the market (2-3 sentences). Impact: what the hire will accomplish in the first year (concrete outcomes, not job duties). Requirements: 5-7 must-have skills or experiences, each grounded in actual job tasks. Nice-to-have: 3-4 bonus qualifications that differentiate candidates. Benefits: compensation range (required in many jurisdictions), equity, perks. Culture: team size, working style, decision-making norms.</p>
    </section>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Publishing a JD copied from a prior job posting without updating requirements to reflect the current role.</description>
      <reason>Stale JDs attract candidates for the previous role, not the current one. Misalignment surfaces in screening and wastes recruiter and candidate time.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Candidate Persona Development">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the target candidate persona before writing the JD or opening sourcing channels; without a profile, sourcing generates noise and screening becomes subjective.</statement>
      <rationale>A persona converts the hiring manager's vague "someone like our best performer" into specific, sourceable attributes: experience range, current role, motivations, channels. This makes sourcing targeted and screening criteria explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Persona Components">
      <p>Demographics: experience range (years), current title or adjacent titles, industries with transferable background.</p>
      <p>Motivations: what career goal does this role advance? What values must the company demonstrate? What are their deal-breakers (e.g., no remote, no equity)?</p>
      <p>Channels: where do they spend time online? How do they search for roles (referrals, LinkedIn, community)? What content do they consume?</p>
      <p>Messaging: what value proposition resonates (growth, mission, compensation, flexibility)? What objections must the JD or outreach preempt?</p>
    </section>

    <example type="good">
      <note>Persona: "Senior Software Engineer, 5-8 years, current role at a Series B-C startup or scaleup. Motivated by technical autonomy and ownership. Searches via LinkedIn and engineering community newsletters. Objection: will we have greenfield work or inherit legacy code? Messaging: lead on new infra stack, no approval layers for architectural decisions."</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
