<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-metrics-and-ats" title="Recruiting Metrics, ATS Optimization, and Offer Management">
  <summary>Metrics dashboard targets, ATS configuration for candidate experience, AI tooling ethics, and offer-stage close tactics.</summary>

  <section title="Recruitment Metrics Dashboard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Report six core metrics weekly or monthly; any metric without a defined target and owner degrades into a vanity number.</statement>
      <rationale>Metrics without targets drive reporting behavior, not improvement. Assigning ownership (recruiter for time-to-fill, compensation for offer acceptance) creates accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Core Metrics">
      <p>Time-to-fill: date hired minus date posted; target under 45 days; review weekly. Cost-per-hire: total recruiting cost divided by hires; target under $4,000; review monthly. Offer acceptance rate: accepts divided by offers extended; target above 85%; review weekly. Quality of hire: percentage meeting or exceeding expectations at 1-year review; target above 80%; review quarterly. Source effectiveness: application and hire volume by channel; review monthly. Candidate NPS: post-process survey; target above 50; measure continuously.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="ATS Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Application process must complete in under 5 minutes and render correctly on mobile; test with a real resume before publishing every role.</statement>
      <rationale>ATS default forms often include non-essential fields (graduation year, GPA, references before interview) that extend application time and reduce conversion. Mobile rendering issues silently drop applicants who don't self-report the problem.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="ATS Configuration Areas">
      <p>Application form: remove non-essential fields; keep under 10 required inputs; test on a mobile device. Resume parsing: validate with 10 real resumes from target pool; identify and correct misparse patterns. Automation: set up auto-acknowledgment within 24 hours; auto-reject only for hard knockout criteria. Communication: templatize rejection emails with enough specificity to not feel generic; automate scheduling prompts. Analytics: configure stage-by-stage conversion tracking for the funnel dashboard.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="AI Recruiting Tools">
    <rule>
      <statement>Audit every AI sourcing or screening tool for demographic bias before deployment; document the audit and review annually.</statement>
      <rationale>AI tools trained on historical hiring data replicate historical bias patterns. EEOC and EU AI Act require explainability for decisions affecting employment; undocumented AI use creates legal exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Tool Categories and Use Cases">
      <p>AI sourcing: finds passive candidates matching a persona; high value for specialized roles. Resume screening: matches skills to JD; must be audited for false-negative rate by demographic. Chatbots: answer FAQs and schedule screens; frees recruiter time; do not use for evaluation decisions. Video interviewing: async first rounds for high-volume roles; ensure candidates with slow connections can rerecord. Skills assessments: validated, job-related tests; avoid general cognitive tests without validity data for the specific role.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Offer Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Extend the offer within 48 hours of the hiring decision; every additional day increases competing-offer risk by a measurable margin.</statement>
      <rationale>Top candidates in active searches often have multiple processes running in parallel. A 5-day lag between decision and offer letter loses 20-30% of candidates in competitive markets.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Offer Close Process">
      <p>Pre-offer: verbal commitment call from the hiring manager before the written offer; surface objections early while there is still room to address them. Offer call: personal call from hiring manager, not just an email; explains the offer and invites questions. Negotiation: know the band ceiling and what non-cash levers are available (signing bonus, extra PTO, equity refresh, start-date flexibility) before the call. Counter-offer handling: if the candidate signals a competing offer, ask what it would take to close; don't assume the competing package is better — often they prefer this role if the gap is small.</p>
    </section>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending the offer letter via email with no follow-up call and waiting for the candidate to respond.</description>
      <reason>An unaccompanied offer letter communicates low enthusiasm. Candidates who are on the fence read the absence of a personal call as a signal that the organization does not really want them.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
