<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Competitive UX Analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Competitive UX Analysis. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-rubric-locked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rubric criteria and weights are agreed before evaluation begins; ad-hoc rubric changes during evaluation invalidate the comparison.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Locked rubric prevents post-hoc cherry-picking of criteria that favour a result.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-real-account-tested" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Evaluation uses a real or sandbox account with realistic data, not landing-page screenshots.</statement>
      <rationale source="UX-research practice">Landing-page reviews miss in-product friction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-three-to-seven-competitors" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Three to seven competitors are evaluated; below three the picture is anecdotal, above seven the rubric becomes unmaintainable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Outside this range the report either lacks coverage or drowns in detail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-evidence-screenshots" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every rubric score cites at least one screenshot or recording timestamp; bare scores are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Defensible-research practice">Bare scores cannot survive cross-team scrutiny.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-positioning-output" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output ends with a positioning recommendation (gap to exploit / parity to maintain / table-stakes to copy), not raw scores.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Score tables without recommendations rarely drive decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-competitive-analysis.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
