<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Competitive Analysis Process and Dimensions">
  <summary>Six-step process for structured competitive UX analysis: scope definition, competitor selection, data collection, documentation, pattern analysis, and insight generation.</summary>

  <section title="Competitor Taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Analyze a minimum of 3-5 direct competitors, 2-3 indirect competitors, and 1-2 aspirational examples outside the direct category. Do not limit analysis to direct competitors only.</statement>
      <rationale>Direct competitors reveal table stakes and parity requirements. Indirect competitors show alternative approaches to the same user problem. Aspirational examples outside the category (e.g., studying Airbnb's onboarding for a B2B SaaS) produce the most differentiated ideas.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Direct: same problem, same target user (Uber vs Lyft)</item>
      <item>Indirect: same problem, different approach (Uber vs public transit apps)</item>
      <item>Partial: overlapping features (Google Maps vs Waze)</item>
      <item>Aspirational: best-in-class for a specific pattern, not a direct competitor</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Six-Step Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1: Define scope. Identify the specific product or feature being analyzed, which competitors to include and why, which dimensions matter most, and how findings will be used.</statement>
      <rationale>Undefined scope produces unfocused analysis. "Analyze the market" yields a report too broad to act on. "Analyze checkout flow across 5 direct competitors" yields actionable findings for a specific design decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2: Create evaluation criteria before gathering data. Criteria must be based on research questions, not what is easy to observe. Rate each criterion consistently using a fixed scale (Excellent/Good/Fair/Poor) before writing narrative.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc criteria selection introduces confirmation bias — you find evidence for what you already believe. Consistent ratings prevent rationalization: if you score before writing narrative, the data leads the conclusion, not the conclusion the data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3: Gather data by actually using each product. Create accounts, complete full user flows, try edge cases, contact support, test on mobile. Do not rely on screenshots of marketing pages.</statement>
      <rationale>Marketing pages show the product's best-case presentation. Real usage reveals friction, error handling quality, mobile experience, and edge-case behavior — the factors that differentiate good UX from poor UX.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4: Document with screenshots and annotations immediately during research. Competitor UIs change; documentation is the historical record.</statement>
      <rationale>Memory of observed UIs decays and blurs. Annotated screenshots capture exact wording, layout, interaction patterns, and the date of observation. Without them, analysis findings cannot be reproduced or compared to later versions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5: Analyze patterns across competitors to find: baseline (what all do), best practices (what top performers do), common problems (what to avoid), and gaps (what none do).</statement>
      <rationale>Pattern analysis across multiple products reveals market consensus vs differentiation opportunities. A feature present in all competitors is table stakes; a feature no competitor does well is an opportunity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6: Generate insights as actionable recommendations in three buckets: "We should..." (adopt), "We could differentiate by..." (opportunity), and "We should avoid..." (competitor failures).</statement>
      <rationale>Observations without recommendations are notes, not insights. The three-bucket structure maps directly to roadmap prioritization: must-have, opportunity, and anti-patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Analysis Dimensions">
    <list>
      <item>Features: what can users do?</item>
      <item>User flows: how do users accomplish key goals? Count steps, measure time to value</item>
      <item>UI patterns: navigation, forms, error handling, empty states</item>
      <item>Information architecture: how is content organized?</item>
      <item>Content and tone: messaging strategy, voice</item>
      <item>Accessibility: WCAG compliance level, screen reader behavior</item>
      <item>Mobile experience: mobile-first or responsive-degraded?</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
