<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Competitive Analysis Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Worked examples showing insight generation from competitive data, and antipatterns that produce useless or misleading analysis.</summary>

  <section title="Worked Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>E-commerce checkout analysis — table stakes finding</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Finding: All 5 direct competitors offer guest checkout.
Insight: Guest checkout is table stakes.
         Not having it is a competitive disadvantage.
Action:  Must have → add to P0 backlog.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>E-commerce checkout analysis — differentiation opportunity</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Finding: Only 1 of 5 competitors shows estimated delivery
         on the product page. Others show it only at checkout.
Insight: Opportunity to differentiate by showing delivery
         estimate earlier in the purchase funnel.
Action:  Could differentiate → test in next sprint.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS onboarding analysis — data-driven priority finding</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Competitor | Onboarding Steps | Time to Value | App Store Rating
A          | 8 steps          | 15 min        | 3.8
B          | 3 steps          | 2 min         | 4.7
C          | 5 steps          | 8 min         | 4.2

Insight: Competitor B's minimal onboarding correlates with
         highest ratings. Reducing our 7-step flow is a priority.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Priority Buckets">
    <rule>
      <statement>Categorize all competitive findings into three priority buckets: Must Have (table stakes — competitors all have it), Should Have (parity — match the best), and Could Differentiate (opportunity — nobody does it well).</statement>
      <rationale>These three buckets map directly to roadmap prioritization. Table stakes go to P0; parity goes to the next cycle; differentiation opportunities go to experimentation or innovation tracks. Avoid mixing all findings in a flat list — stakeholders cannot prioritize a flat list.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only analyzing direct competitors — missing inspiration from adjacent industries</description>
      <reason>Cross-industry patterns produce the most differentiated ideas. A fintech product studying Airbnb's trust signals or Duolingo's onboarding may find patterns no direct competitor has tried.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Copying competitor features without understanding why they made that design decision</description>
      <reason>A competitor's feature may exist due to legacy technical constraints, regulatory requirements, or past A/B test results that no longer apply. Copying without context means inheriting their tradeoffs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-time analysis treated as permanent truth</description>
      <reason>Competitor products update continuously. An analysis from 6 months ago may reflect a product that no longer exists. Schedule quarterly lightweight checks and annual deep analyses.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating industry consensus as validated best practice</description>
      <reason>If all competitors share a bad pattern, the analysis surfaces a shared bad practice, not a best practice. App store reviews and user research are needed to determine whether the consensus pattern actually works for users.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
