<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="competitive-analysis Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for competitive-analysis as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Only analyzing direct competitors — missing inspiration from adjacent industries</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-industry patterns produce the most differentiated ideas. A fintech product studying Airbnb's trust signals or Duolingo's onboarding may find patterns no direct competitor has tried.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Copying competitor features without understanding why they made that design decision</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A competitor's feature may exist due to legacy technical constraints, regulatory requirements, or past A/B test results that no longer apply. Copying without context means inheriting their tradeoffs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>One-time analysis treated as permanent truth</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Competitor products update continuously. An analysis from 6 months ago may reflect a product that no longer exists. Schedule quarterly lightweight checks and annual deep analyses.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating industry consensus as validated best practice</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If all competitors share a bad pattern, the analysis surfaces a shared bad practice, not a best practice. App store reviews and user research are needed to determine whether the consensus pattern actually works for users.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents analyzing competitor public pages via screenshots cannot access gated features requiring accounts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The most important flows (checkout, settings, admin) are invisible to the agent. The deepest user flows remain inaccessible without human research participation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>App Store reviews are biased toward extreme experiences (1-star and 5-star).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent-extracted patterns may overrepresent edge cases. Combine review extraction with direct product usage for balanced insight.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Competitor feature presence detected from marketing pages may not reflect actual implementation quality.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"AI-powered search" on a landing page means nothing about UX quality. Feature presence alone does not validate whether it works well for users.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Feature comparison matrices generated by agents from web content frequently contain outdated information.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every cell needs a human spot-check date. Competitor products update faster than manual analysis can track.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>An agent identifying "what most competitors do" as best practice may be identifying a shared bad practice.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Industry consensus is not the same as user-validated design. Combine competitive findings with app store reviews and user research.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
