<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Reference Program Playbook Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Reference Program Playbook` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="ask-at-peak-not-end" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference asks MUST happen at peak satisfaction moment (mid-engagement win, public outcome) NOT at engagement end. End-of-engagement asks have &lt;= 30% yes rate; peak-moment asks &gt;= 70%.</statement>
      <rationale source="Win Without Pitching reference workflow; agency casework">End of engagement is the worst moment — client is in transition, mind already on next thing. Peak-moment asks capture maximum emotional credit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="tier-references-by-strength" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference roster MUST tier requests: Tier-1 (named in case study + on-call), Tier-2 (named, no calls), Tier-3 (anonymous case study). Each client picked for the tier they will sustain.</statement>
      <rationale source="B2B reference operations playbook">Single-tier (all-or-nothing) reference asks lose moderately-happy clients. Tiered asks let lukewarm clients say yes to something instead of no to everything.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="case-study-outcome-not-process" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Case studies MUST lead with the outcome metric (revenue lift, time saved, churn reduced), not the process. Process-led studies read like SOWs, outcome-led read like proof.</statement>
      <rationale source="ConvertKit / Wynter B2B case-study analysis">Buyers scanning case studies care about &apos;will this work for me&apos;. Process leads with &apos;how&apos; (irrelevant to prospect); outcome leads with &apos;what changed&apos; (the relevant signal).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="peer-call-script-prepped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference calls MUST come with a 3-question script that the reference reviews + approves before any prospect call. Unscripted calls leak negative or off-topic content.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reference-selling field manual; agency interview corpus">Unscripted reference calls go off-rails — reference mentions a billing dispute, an out-of-scope ask, an old version of the product. Scripted = predictable + reuseable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="warm-intro-double-opt-in" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Warm intro asks MUST use double opt-in (separate intro to reference first, get green light, then intro to prospect). Single-step intros forbidden — burns reference goodwill.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patrick Collison double-opt-in intro pattern">Single-step intros impose on reference&apos;s time + risk reputation. Double opt-in respects both sides + signals professionalism. References give more intros to founders who run it this way.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
