<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Reference Program — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every reference program must enforce. Violating any one of these leaks goodwill, burns clients, or produces unconvincing social proof.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-asymmetric-value-exchange" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every reference request MUST offer the client a concrete value in return — peer introduction, training credit, public co-marketing slot, charity donation, or commercial discount. Pure-ask is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reichheld — The Ultimate Question 2.0; Bain customer-loyalty research">References that are asked without an offer produce one-shot compliance and resentment. References that are exchanged become a recurring relationship asset. The exchange does not have to be expensive — a peer intro to a senior contact in the client's own target market is high-value at near-zero cost.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-fatigue-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No single reference is contacted more than 2 times per quarter (peer calls, case-study updates, podcast asks combined). Hard cap; no exceptions for must-win deals.</statement>
      <rationale source="Forrester reference-selling research; field interviews with B2B sales leaders">Reference fatigue is the silent killer of programs. Clients stop returning calls after the 3rd ask; the relationship turns from advocacy into chore. The cap forces the program to maintain ≥3-deep reference depth per archetype rather than burning a single star reference.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-archetype-matched-routing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A reference MUST be matched to the prospect by buyer-archetype (industry, company-size band, role of decision-maker, deal-shape). Generic "any happy client" routing is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="GTM playbook canon (Winning by Design, Force Management)">Cross-archetype references convert at &lt;30% the rate of matched references because the prospect cannot self-identify. A SaaS founder talking to a manufacturing CIO does not move the deal. The registry MUST tag every reference with at least industry, headcount band, and decision-maker title.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-consent-on-record" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every reference asset (logo, quote, case study, peer-call availability) MUST have an explicit written consent record dated within the last 12 months, with a `permitted_uses` list (website, deck, peer-call, podcast, paid ads, etc.).</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR / CCPA practice for B2B endorsements; case law on unauthorised logo use">Implicit consent ("they didn't object") fails at the worst moment. Logo on a paid ad without consent triggers cease-and-desist letters from procurement at large clients. The consent record turns "I think they're fine with it" into a date-stamped, scoped permission.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-asset-expiry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference assets carry an explicit `expires_on` (12 months from consent unless renewed) AND a `freshness_check` cadence. Expired assets MUST be removed from sales decks and website within 30 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field practice; legal risk of unauthorised use">Clients churn, sponsors leave, products change. A 4-year-old logo on the homepage when the company is now using a competitor is embarrassing at best and legally actionable at worst. Expiry forces deliberate renewal.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Value-exchange offer in the ask">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Hi Maria, we're closing a deal with a fintech that looks a lot like
where you were 18 months ago. Would you be open to a 20-min peer call
with their CTO next week? In exchange, I'd like to introduce you to
Sasha, who runs platform-engineering at <bigger fintech> — she's the
exact persona you said you wanted to meet last quarter. No pressure
either way."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 (concrete value-exchange), r3 (archetype match between Maria's company and the prospect), r4 (peer-call as the asset, easy to consent).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Reference burn pattern">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Q1: Maria does a peer call with prospect A.
Q1: Maria's quote used in new case study without renewed consent.
Q1: Maria asked for a podcast appearance.
Q1: Maria asked to speak at user conference.
→ Maria stops returning emails by Q2.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r2 violation (≥4 asks in one quarter), r4 violation (quote reused without renewed consent). The relationship is now worth zero references.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
