<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="Prometheus Core Concepts">
  <summary>Metric types, naming conventions, and label cardinality rules — the foundation of a maintainable Prometheus setup.</summary>

  <section title="Metric Types">
    <p>Prometheus has four metric types. Choose based on what the value represents, not how you want to display it.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Counter: monotonically increasing value; never decreases except on process restart. Use for request count, errors, bytes sent. Always suffix with _total.</item>
      <item>Gauge: value that can go up and down. Use for queue size, active connections, temperature, memory usage.</item>
      <item>Histogram: samples observations into configurable buckets. Use for request duration and response sizes. Exposes _bucket, _sum, _count series. Required for histogram_quantile().</item>
      <item>Summary: client-side quantile calculation over a sliding window. Prefer Histogram — Summaries cannot be aggregated across instances.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer Histogram over Summary for latency metrics in distributed systems.</statement>
      <rationale>Histograms are aggregatable across replicas with sum(rate(...)) by (le). Summary quantiles are calculated per-instance and cannot be meaningfully combined across multiple pods.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Naming Conventions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow the pattern: namespace_name_unit_suffix. Use snake_case. Suffix counters with _total; histograms with _seconds or _bytes.</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent naming allows tooling (Grafana, alerting) to auto-discover metrics and enables teams to understand a metric's purpose without documentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
http_requests_total                   # Counter
http_request_duration_seconds_bucket  # Histogram bucket
db_connections_active                 # Gauge
process_memory_bytes                  # Gauge
job:http_requests:rate5m              # Recording rule (level:metric:operation)
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
httpRequests          # camelCase, no unit, no suffix
request_count_total   # 'count' is redundant; just _total
latency               # No unit, no namespace
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Label Cardinality Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use unbounded values as labels: no user IDs, request IDs, email addresses, or UUIDs. Each unique label combination creates a new time series.</statement>
      <rationale>High cardinality causes Prometheus OOM crashes. 1M users × 10 endpoints = 10M time series from a single metric. Labels must have bounded value sets: HTTP methods, status code classes, service names.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep label count per metric at or below 10. Add only labels needed for meaningful aggregation or filtering in dashboards and alerts.</statement>
      <rationale>Each additional label multiplies the number of time series exponentially. Labels that are never used in queries waste memory and slow down scrapes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# Good: bounded labels (method has ~5 values, status ~10, endpoint ~50)
REQUEST_COUNT = Counter(
    'http_requests_total',
    'Total HTTP requests',
    ['method', 'endpoint', 'status']
)
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# Bad: unbounded labels — user_id creates millions of time series
REQUEST_COUNT = Counter(
    'http_requests_total',
    'Total HTTP requests',
    ['method', 'user_id', 'request_id']  # Never do this
)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
