<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-configuration" title="Prometheus Configuration">
  <summary>Scrape intervals, ServiceMonitor and PodMonitor CRDs, recording rules, and alerting philosophy.</summary>

  <section title="Scrape Intervals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set global scrape interval to 15s. Override to 10s only for critical systems. Use 30–60s for low-priority metrics. Never scrape faster than the metric changes.</statement>
      <rationale>10s scrape doubles storage and CPU load compared to 15s with minimal benefit for most metrics. Scrape interval below 10s is unsupported in practice — Prometheus needs time to complete each scrape cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
global:
  scrape_interval:     15s
  evaluation_interval: 15s
  scrape_timeout:      10s

scrape_configs:
  - job_name: 'kubernetes-pods'
    kubernetes_sd_configs:
      - role: pod
    relabel_configs:
      - source_labels: [__meta_kubernetes_pod_annotation_prometheus_io_scrape]
        action: keep
        regex: 'true'
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Kubernetes Operator CRDs">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use ServiceMonitor for scraping services by label selector. Use PodMonitor only when pods do not have a backing Service. Define PrometheusRule for all recording rules and alerts.</statement>
      <rationale>ServiceMonitor is the standard Prometheus Operator CRD for service-level scraping. It is self-service — teams can add a ServiceMonitor to their namespace without touching prometheus.yaml. PrometheusRule keeps alerts version-controlled alongside the application.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: monitoring.coreos.com/v1
kind: ServiceMonitor
metadata:
  name: myapp
  namespace: monitoring
  labels:
    prometheus: main
spec:
  selector:
    matchLabels:
      app: myapp
  namespaceSelector:
    matchNames: [production]
  endpoints:
    - port: metrics
      interval: 15s
      path: /metrics
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Recording Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-compute expensive queries used in dashboards as recording rules. Follow the naming format: level:metric:operation (e.g., job:http_requests:rate5m).</statement>
      <rationale>Dashboard queries running on every panel refresh under load multiply Prometheus CPU usage. Recording rules run once per evaluation interval and store the result as a new time series, making dashboards fast regardless of cardinality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: monitoring.coreos.com/v1
kind: PrometheusRule
metadata:
  name: http-recording-rules
  labels:
    prometheus: main
spec:
  groups:
    - name: http.rules
      interval: 30s
      rules:
        - record: job:http_requests:rate5m
          expr: sum(rate(http_requests_total[5m])) by (job)
        - record: job:http_request_duration_seconds:p99
          expr: |
            histogram_quantile(0.99,
              sum(rate(http_request_duration_seconds_bucket[5m])) by (job, le)
            )
        - record: job:sli_availability:rate5m
          expr: |
            sum(rate(http_requests_total{status!~"5.."}[5m])) by (job)
            / sum(rate(http_requests_total[5m])) by (job)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Alerting Philosophy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Alert on symptoms, not causes. Alert on error rate exceeding threshold, not on individual pod failures. Every alert must have a runbook_url annotation.</statement>
      <rationale>Symptom-based alerts (high error rate, high latency) are actionable and describe user impact. Cause-based alerts (pod crashed) create alert fatigue — a pod may crash and restart with no user impact. Runbook URLs eliminate information lookup time during incidents.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the for: duration to require alerts to persist before firing. Set at least 2m for critical alerts and 5–15m for warning alerts.</statement>
      <rationale>Transient spikes lasting seconds should not page on-call engineers. A minimum for: duration filters out flapping alerts caused by temporary metric anomalies during deployments or garbage collection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- alert: HighErrorRate
  expr: job:http_requests:error_rate5m > 0.05
  for: 5m
  labels:
    severity: critical
  annotations:
    summary: "High error rate for {{ $labels.job }}"
    description: "Error rate {{ $value | humanizePercentage }} exceeds 5%"
    runbook_url: "https://runbooks.example.com/high-error-rate"
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
