<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Decision Analysis Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the decision-analysis methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 1 (define decision): Write outcome-shaped statement; include status quo in option set.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the define decision gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 2 (generate options): Divergence pass; minimum 3 options including status quo.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the generate options gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 3 (elicit weights): Individual weight elicitation; emit per-stakeholder vector.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the elicit weights gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 4 (reconcile and score): Reconcile to group weights; score each option × criterion by SME.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the reconcile and score gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 5 (sensitivity and document): One-at-a-time perturbation; document recommendation + dissent + traceability.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the sensitivity and document gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 6 (review and sign off): Governance review; capture dissent; tag and archive.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the review and sign off gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for decision-analysis do not hold, do not apply this methodology; route to an alternative as the decision tree suggests.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Methodologies misapplied to wrong contexts create overhead without value; explicit skip preserves the agent's budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
