<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="decision-analysis Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for decision-analysis. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write the decision statement in 25 words or fewer with an outcome shape ("select platform to reduce manual data entry by X%"); reject decision statements that are solution-shaped ("buy Salesforce").</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Solution-shaped decision statements pre-select the answer before the analysis begins, turning the matrix into theater. Outcome-shaped statements keep the option space open for the evaluation to close it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include a "do nothing / status quo" option; without it, the matrix is a coronation of the best available alternative, not a defense of changing at all.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Some decision analyses will conclude that the cost and risk of change exceed the benefit; excluding the status quo prevents this correct conclusion from being reached.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run brainstorm for a divergence pass before locking the option set; skipping this is the most common failure mode (the matrix only compares three obvious vendors).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs and stakeholders both anchor on salient options; a structured divergence pass surfaces alternatives that would otherwise be excluded without consideration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap the criteria set at 5-7; more than 7 and stakeholders cannot hold the matrix in working memory and weights become arbitrary noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Beyond 7 criteria, cognitive load produces inconsistent weighting; the matrix loses analytical validity even if it retains formal completeness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trace every criterion to at least one requirement (REQ-XXX) before locking the criteria list. Criteria with no trace must either become new requirements (then return) or be dropped. This kills the "we evaluated on features the business never asked for" failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Criteria invented at decision time instead of traced from the requirements catalog lead to decisions that look defensible but do not serve the actual stakeholder needs documented during elicitation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Elicit weights individually from each stakeholder before any group session; aggregate, compute σ per criterion, and reconcile only rows where σ &gt; 0.05 or range &gt; 0.20.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Group elicitation lets the loudest voice anchor the room; functions with legitimate interests (security, accessibility, operations) get under-weighted without individual-first elicitation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock weights before any scoring begins; record weight_locked_at and weight_setter on every criterion row. Retroactive weight editing to support a preferred outcome invalidates the analysis.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without timestamp locking, weight manipulation is undetectable; the audit trail collapses and the Decision Analysis Document cannot answer "why this option?" authoritatively.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Route scoring by stakeholder expertise: Security criteria scored by Security, Finance criteria by Finance, UX criteria by UX research. Define a 1-3-5 rubric per criterion before scoring begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">One BA scoring all options against all criteria inherits one person's biases across the entire matrix. Domain-routed scoring distributes both expertise and accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stamp retrieved_at on every fact cited as evidence; refuse to reuse evidence older than 90 days without re-fetching (pricing and capabilities go stale fast).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A recommendation based on pricing data from a previous quarter may be factually wrong; stale evidence invalidates the analysis without any party being aware.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define the scoring rubric per criterion *before* scoring begins. "Ease of use = 5" must mean the same thing to Security and Sales. Write the 1-3-5 anchors in the matrix header before any cell is filled.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a shared rubric, stakeholders score from different reference points; the column becomes noise rather than signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run sensitivity analysis at ±20% on every criterion weight; if small weight changes flip the recommendation, declare the decision sensitive and require a second stakeholder reconciliation session before sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A recommendation that changes when weights shift 10% indicates the matrix is measuring noise, not signal; forcing a reconciliation session uncovers the real disagreement hidden by averaged weights.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Link the decision both ways: each impacted requirement gets decisions: [DEC-XXX]; each decision document lists traces_to: [REQ-XXX]. This creates a queryable traceability chain (git grep DEC-XXX).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Decisions not traced to requirements cannot be audited by a business case review; requirements not linked to decisions cannot be scoped to the chosen option's implementation boundaries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Schedule a 6-month post-implementation review. Compare predicted scores to actual outcomes; log the calibration error in `.aidocs/memory/patterns.md`. This is what turns the matrix from theater into learning.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without post-hoc review, teams never learn how well their weighting predictions match reality; the same calibration errors repeat on the next decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Frame** — BA + sonnet agent extract the decision frame from elicitation transcripts (interviews, RFP responses, steering minutes). Output: {decision_statement, objectives[], constraints[], decision_maker, stakeholders[]} in JSON. The agent flags ambiguity ("decision_maker not stated") instead of guessing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Explicit frame extraction prevents agents from inventing missing decision-maker context and ensures all stakeholders agree on what is being decided before weighting begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Trace criteria to requirements** — opus agent walks the requirements catalog (BRD, FRDs, NFRs) and proposes criteria *that map to existing requirements*. Each criterion gets a `traces_to: [REQ-XXX, REQ-YYY]` field. Criteria with no requirements link must either be added to the requirements catalog or dropped — this kills the "we evaluated on features the business never asked for" failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tracing criteria to requirements at this stage prevents the most common post-decision complaint: "we optimized for features the business never asked for."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Elicit weights — individually, then reconcile.** Each stakeholder weights criteria privately (a Notion form, an Airtable view, a 1000minds PAPRIKA round). The BA agent aggregates and shows the variance per criterion. Where σ &gt; 20%, the BA convenes a reconciliation call. Lock weights before any scoring begins; record `weight_setter`, `weight_locked_at` on every row.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Individual elicitation followed by aggregation and selective reconciliation balances speed with stakeholder alignment; only high-variance rows consume reconciliation time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r17" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Score with role-routing.** Per matrix cell, an agent picks the *right rater* (Security cells → security stakeholder, Cost cells → finance, UX cells → UX research) instead of one BA scoring everything. Each cell gets an evidence URL and a rubric reference. A second agent runs collinearity / direction checks on the assembled matrix.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Role-routed scoring produces more credible scores and distributes accountability; a secondary collinearity check surfaces both duplicate criteria and contradictory scoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r18" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>**Memo + sensitivity + sign-off.** A final opus agent generates the Decision Analysis Document (template in templates/), runs sensitivity ±20% on weights, and produces a recommendation. The BA presents to the decision-maker; signature goes in the document; the matrix + rationale is committed to the project's `.aidocs/` and linked from each impacted requirement (forward + backward traceability).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The written decision document and signed commitment create the audit trail; commitment to `.aidocs/` makes the decision part of the permanent project record.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r19" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The BA always remains in the loop at three mandatory checkpoints: weights lock, recommendation review, and post-implementation calibration. Agents prepare; humans sign.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mandatory human checkpoints prevent agents from optimizing for a pre-determined outcome and ensure accountability lies with named decision-makers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
