<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-decision-steps" title="Decision Analysis: Six-Step Procedure">
  <summary>Six-step decision analysis procedure, criteria weighting, scoring scale, sensitivity analysis, and documentation requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define the Decision">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write the decision statement in 25 words or fewer with an outcome shape ("select platform to reduce manual data entry by X%"); reject decision statements that are solution-shaped ("buy Salesforce").</statement>
      <rationale>Solution-shaped decision statements pre-select the answer before the analysis begins, turning the matrix into theater. Outcome-shaped statements keep the option space open for the evaluation to close it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Decision statement — what specifically is being decided (outcome-shaped, 25 words max).</item>
      <item>Objectives — what success looks like for each stakeholder group.</item>
      <item>Constraints — non-negotiable limitations (budget ceiling, technology standard, regulatory requirement).</item>
      <item>Decision maker — the single named human with authority to sign off.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Generate Options">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a "do nothing / status quo" option; without it, the matrix is a coronation of the best available alternative, not a defense of changing at all.</statement>
      <rationale>Some decision analyses will conclude that the cost and risk of change exceed the benefit; excluding the status quo prevents this correct conclusion from being reached.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run faion-brainstorm for a divergence pass before locking the option set; skipping this is the most common failure mode (the matrix only compares three obvious vendors).</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and stakeholders both anchor on salient options; a structured divergence pass surfaces alternatives that would otherwise be excluded without consideration.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Define and Weight Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap the criteria set at 5-7; more than 7 and stakeholders cannot hold the matrix in working memory and weights become arbitrary noise.</statement>
      <rationale>Beyond 7 criteria, cognitive load produces inconsistent weighting; the matrix loses analytical validity even if it retains formal completeness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Elicit weights individually from each stakeholder before any group session; aggregate, compute σ per criterion, and reconcile only rows where σ &gt; 0.05 or range &gt; 0.20.</statement>
      <rationale>Group elicitation lets the loudest voice anchor the room; functions with legitimate interests (security, accessibility, operations) get under-weighted without individual-first elicitation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock weights before any scoring begins; record weight_locked_at and weight_setter on every criterion row. Retroactive weight editing to support a preferred outcome invalidates the analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>Without timestamp locking, weight manipulation is undetectable; the audit trail collapses and the Decision Analysis Document cannot answer "why this option?" authoritatively.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Evaluate Options">
    <rule>
      <statement>Route scoring by stakeholder expertise: Security criteria scored by Security, Finance criteria by Finance, UX criteria by UX research. Define a 1-3-5 rubric per criterion before scoring begins.</statement>
      <rationale>One BA scoring all options against all criteria inherits one person's biases across the entire matrix. Domain-routed scoring distributes both expertise and accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stamp retrieved_at on every fact cited as evidence; refuse to reuse evidence older than 90 days without re-fetching (pricing and capabilities go stale fast).</statement>
      <rationale>A recommendation based on pricing data from a previous quarter may be factually wrong; stale evidence invalidates the analysis without any party being aware.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Sensitivity Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run sensitivity analysis at ±20% on every criterion weight; if small weight changes flip the recommendation, declare the decision sensitive and require a second stakeholder reconciliation session before sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale>A recommendation that changes when weights shift 10% indicates the matrix is measuring noise, not signal; forcing a reconciliation session uncovers the real disagreement hidden by averaged weights.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Document and Trace">
    <rule>
      <statement>Link the decision both ways: each impacted requirement gets decisions: [DEC-XXX]; each decision document lists traces_to: [REQ-XXX]. This creates a queryable traceability chain (git grep DEC-XXX).</statement>
      <rationale>Decisions not traced to requirements cannot be audited by a business case review; requirements not linked to decisions cannot be scoped to the chosen option's implementation boundaries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/decision-analysis-document.md">Full Decision Analysis Document template with all seven sections</reference>
    <reference path="templates/decision-matrix.md">Simple decision matrix for fast evaluations</reference>
    <reference path="templates/weight-reconcile.py">Aggregates per-stakeholder weight CSVs and flags high-variance criteria</reference>
  </section>
</text>
