<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="error-recovery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Plain language error messages with three components: what happened, why, how to fix it.</summary>
    <category>error-handling</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>error-recovery</tag>
      <tag>error-messages</tag>
      <tag>user-guidance</tag>
      <tag>microcopy</tag>
      <tag>heuristic-9</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Error Recovery — Nielsen Heuristic #9</title>

    <summary>Plain language error messages with three components: what happened, why, how to fix it.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Cryptic or generic error messages (Error 403, "Something went wrong") abandon users at the moment they most need guidance. Users who cannot diagnose or fix an error abandon the task, generate support tickets, or lose trust in the product. Well-formed error messages with concrete recovery paths eliminate the support escalation path for the most common failure modes and keep users moving forward without external help.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing any form, API response surface, or system state where errors can occur.</item>
        <item>Writing microcopy for validation errors, system failures, 404 pages, network errors.</item>
        <item>During a design review for any new feature that has failure states.</item>
        <item>When support ticket analysis reveals recurring user confusion about a specific error.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Do not conflate error recovery with error prevention — prevention (Heuristic #5) eliminates errors before they occur; this methodology handles errors that do occur. Apply both, not one instead of the other.</item>
        <item>Do not use for success or informational states — the three-component structure (what/why/fix) is specific to failure states.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="the-heuristic">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every error message must contain three components: what happened (problem statement), why it happened (context), and how to fix it (concrete action).</statement>
        <rationale>An error message missing any of the three components creates a dead end. Without "what happened," users do not understand the failure. Without "why," they cannot prevent recurrence. Without "how to fix," they cannot continue.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Full three-component message: "You don't have permission to view this page. [What] Your account requires administrator access for this section. [Why] Contact your administrator to request access. [How]"</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>"Error 403" — provides the technical code only. Users cannot act on this. Maps to none of the three components.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="five-message-principles">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write error messages in plain language: no error codes, no technical jargon, no system-facing terminology.</statement>
        <rationale>Error codes are meaningful to engineers, not users. A user who sees ECONNREFUSED cannot diagnose or fix a network issue; "Cannot connect — check your internet connection" can.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Be specific: name the exact field or element that caused the error, not a generic summary.</statement>
        <rationale>"Invalid input" forces users to guess which field is wrong. "This email address is missing the @ symbol" points directly to the problem and its solution.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never write error messages that blame the user for the error.</statement>
        <rationale>Blame language ("You entered invalid data") increases frustration and damages trust. The error message is a recovery tool, not a judgment. Passive or system-focused framing ("This email address doesn't match our records") is always preferable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always provide at least one recovery action — a button, link, or explicit instruction — never a dead-end OK button.</statement>
        <rationale>An error message without a recovery path traps users. If the only button is [OK], users return to a state with no guidance on what to do next. Every error should offer [Retry], [Go back], [Contact support], or an explicit instruction.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Place error messages immediately adjacent to the element that caused them — inline for form fields, banner for page-level errors, modal only for system failures requiring full attention.</statement>
        <rationale>An error shown at the top of the page while the problem field is at the bottom forces users to scroll and cross-reference. Proximity makes the relationship between error and fix obvious.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="error-type-placement-rules">
      <p>Validation errors: inline, next to the field; show on blur or submit, not on every keystroke. Recovery: user corrects input.</p>
      <p>System errors: modal or banner when the operation has failed; recovery path: Retry, alternative action, support contact.</p>
      <p>404 Not Found: full page; message explains page not found plus navigation suggestions; recovery: links to home, search, common pages.</p>
      <p>Network errors: banner or non-blocking modal; recovery: Retry, Offline mode, Check connection instruction.</p>
      <p>Form with multiple errors: show count summary at top ("Please fix 3 errors") plus inline error at each field; both are required — summary alone forces scrolling, inline alone loses overview.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="good-examples">
      <example type="good">
        <note>Stripe payment error: "Your card was declined. Your card number is incorrect. Please check the number and try again." [Try a different card] — all three components present, plain language, specific cause, recovery action provided.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>GitHub 404: "This is not the web page you are looking for. The page you requested doesn't exist. You may have typed the address incorrectly or the page may have moved." [Go to GitHub.com] [Search GitHub] — human tone, two recovery paths offered.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Form password validation: "Password must contain: checkmark At least 8 characters / X One uppercase letter (add one) / X One number (add one)" — live checklist format shows both what is satisfied and what remains; users can see progress without re-reading requirements.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="anti-patterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Showing only a technical error code: "Error: ECONNREFUSED" or "Error 403".</description>
        <reason>Technical codes are meaningless to users. They cannot diagnose the problem or take any corrective action. Even "Connection refused" is better than the raw code.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Generic error message: "Something went wrong."</description>
        <reason>Tells users nothing about what failed, why, or what to do. Generates immediate support escalation because users have no information to self-serve.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Blame framing: "You entered invalid data" or "You did not complete the form correctly."</description>
        <reason>Accusatory language increases frustration without adding information. Replace with passive or system-focused framing: "This field requires a valid date" rather than "You entered an invalid date."</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Dead-end error with only an [OK] button and no recovery path.</description>
        <reason>Users who dismiss an [OK] dialog are returned to an unchanged state with no guidance. They will either repeat the same action (same failure) or abandon. Always offer at least one forward path.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not communicate errors by color change alone — always include an icon or text label alongside color.</statement>
        <rationale>Color-only error indication fails for users with color vision deficiency. Red borders without an error icon or text are invisible to approximately 8% of male users.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use ARIA live regions or role="alert" to announce errors to screen reader users; move focus to the error message or the first invalid field on form submission.</statement>
        <rationale>Screen reader users do not perceive visual error indicators. Without ARIA announcements and focus management, they may be unaware an error occurred at all.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-prompts">
      <prompt purpose="Generate improved error messages from existing ones">
You are a UX writer specializing in error message design. For each error condition below, write an improved user-facing error message following this structure:
- Title: 5–8 words, plain language, no technical terms
- Body: 1–2 sentences explaining what happened and why (if known), in second person
- Suggested action: specific step the user can take now
- Primary button label: action verb + object (e.g., "Try Again", "Go to Home", "Update Payment Method")
- Secondary button label (optional): alternative path

Rules:
- Never use error codes in the user-facing message (log them separately)
- Never blame the user
- Always suggest a concrete next step
- If the cause is a server error outside user control, acknowledge uncertainty ("Something went wrong on our end")

Error conditions: [list with technical cause and context]
Platform: [web | iOS | Android]
Product tone: [formal | conversational | playful]
      </prompt>
      <prompt purpose="Audit existing error messages for quality">
You are auditing error messages for UX quality. For each message below, score it on:
- clarity: 1–5 (is the problem understandable to a non-technical user?)
- specificity: 1–5 (does it identify the exact problem, not just "something went wrong"?)
- actionability: 1–5 (does it tell the user what to do next?)
- tone: 1–5 (is it non-blaming and helpful?)

Then provide an improved version for any message scoring below 4 in any category.

Messages: [list]
      </prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-resources">
      <p>Accessibility auditing: axe-core for automated accessibility audit including error state accessibility (ARIA, color contrast), pa11y CLI for accessibility checking, Storybook to build and review all error states in isolation across component library, i18next for managing error message strings across locales. Error tracking: Sentry API for querying most frequent error events to prioritize message fixes, Datadog API for error rate monitoring and user impact correlation, Lokalise API for translation management, Contentful API for storing error messages as content entries, BugSnag API for error monitoring and prioritization by user impact. Script example: bash script to extract user-facing error strings from TypeScript/React codebase using grep patterns for common error display components.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/error-message.md" purpose="Per-error design doc: trigger, technical cause, user impact, message content, visual design, actions"/>
      <template path="templates/error-audit.md" purpose="Audit table: error, current message, issues, improved message, placement, recovery options"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/error-message-guidelines/"/>
      <link href="https://uxdesign.cc/how-to-write-better-error-messages-b0fdc07e60dc"/>
      <link href="https://www.microcopybook.com/"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/components/dialogs/guidelines"/>
      <link href="https://dequeuniversity.com/rules/axe/4.9"/>
      <ref slug="error-prevention"/>
      <ref slug="heuristic-evaluation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>