<text id="health-concepts" title="Health Checks and Auto-Heal: Concepts">

  <summary>
    Three monitoring layers: systemd liveness (process alive via Restart=always), HTTP health endpoints (application responds correctly), auto-heal watcher (application logic is healthy — e.g. Celery processes tasks). Liveness vs readiness: liveness = process responds, readiness = all dependencies accessible.
  </summary>

  <section title="Liveness vs Readiness">
    <list>
      <item>Liveness — is the process alive and responding? `systemctl is-active` or `/health/live` (returns 200 with no body)</item>
      <item>Readiness — can the service handle requests? `/health` checks all dependencies: DB, Redis, message queue. Returns 200 if all OK, 503 if degraded.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always return 503 when any critical dependency is unhealthy, not 200 with an error body.</statement>
      <rationale>Load balancers and health check scripts check HTTP status codes, not body content. A 200 with {"status":"error"} will be treated as healthy.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="systemd Watchdog">
    <p>Type=notify + WatchdogSec=30s: the application must send WATCHDOG=1 to the NOTIFY_SOCKET every 15s (half the interval). If it stops sending, systemd kills and restarts the process — catching hung states that still pass `is-active`.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Send watchdog notification at WatchdogSec/2 interval, not WatchdogSec. This provides a safety margin before systemd triggers the kill.</statement>
      <rationale>If the notification thread hangs right after sending at exactly WatchdogSec, the next cycle may be too late. Sending at half the interval provides one missed cycle before restart.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Auto-Heal Watcher">
    <p>A long-running watcher process polls all services every 60s. On failure: 5-minute cooldown between restart attempts, max 3 restarts per hour per service. Prevents restart storms.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Check methods: HTTP /health, systemctl is-active, Celery inspect ping</item>
      <item>Restart command: `systemctl --user restart service-name`</item>
      <item>Restart count decays: subtract 1 per successful check cycle</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-implementations.xml">FastAPI health endpoint, watchdog notify, watcher class</link>
    <link path="templates/watcher.py">Full auto-heal watcher implementation</link>
  </see-also>

</text>
