<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="modern-ba-framework">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Meta-framework routing BABOK KAs to modern delivery (agile, AI/ML, cloud, BPM). Emits ba-approach.json with perspective, KA-to-methodology map, model tiers, and PO sign-off gate.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>ba-framework</tag>
      <tag>meta-framework</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>perspective-routing</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Modern BA Framework: BABOK for Agile, AI/ML, Cloud, and Platform Delivery</title>
    <summary>A meta-framework for applying the six BABOK Knowledge Areas to modern delivery contexts: agile, AI/ML, cloud-native, platform engineering, and process-mining. The deliverable for an agent is not "do BA" but a routing decision — a ba-approach.json that picks methodologies per KA, declares delivery perspective (Agile/BI/IT/BizArch/BPM/Data-Product/AI-Product), maps per-task model tiers, and requires human PO sign-off before execution. The framework also maps team competencies against ECBA/CCBA/CBAP/AAC/CBDA/CPOA and SFIA v9.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>BABOK was published in 2015. Without a modern interpretation layer, agents default to waterfall-shaped artifacts (BRD/SRS/RTM) even on agile projects, miss AI/ML-specific concerns (prompt versioning, eval traceability, model selection), and apply a single Agile perspective when the work actually spans Business Architecture and BPM. The framework forces explicit perspective declaration and maps each KA to a concrete sibling methodology, preventing KAs with no executable output.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Onboarding a new BA or PO: agent reads project context and emits a tailored BA approach that selects methodologies per KA and perspective.</item>
        <item>Migration audits: shifting from waterfall BABOK artifacts to agile/lean BA equivalents.</item>
        <item>Certification-aligned skill assessment: scoring a team against BABOK certifications and SFIA v9.</item>
        <item>Multi-perspective discovery: work spanning Agile + BI + Business Architecture simultaneously.</item>
        <item>Model selection routing: assigning haiku/sonnet/opus per task type (format → haiku, AC → sonnet, gap analysis → opus).</item>
        <item>Trigger phrases from the user: "design a BA approach", "how should we run BA on this", "modernize our BA process", "set up BA for an AI project", "competency gap analysis".</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A specific BA task is already scoped — load the concrete sibling methodology directly (acceptance-criteria, elicitation-techniques, business-process-analysis).</item>
        <item>Pure non-BA work (code refactor, infra hardening) — the framework manufactures BA scaffolding nobody asked for.</item>
        <item>Solo founders with no enterprise team — the routing value collapses to a single perspective.</item>
        <item>Greenfield product discovery before stakeholders or a problem statement exist — use continuous-discovery first.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="knowledge-area-modern-application">
      <p>How each BABOK KA maps to modern delivery contexts in 2025-2026:</p>
      <list>
        <item>BA Planning and Monitoring — adaptive planning for iterative delivery; scaled agile frameworks; sprint-cadenced BA approach updates.</item>
        <item>Elicitation and Collaboration — virtual facilitation; AI-assisted transcript analysis; async observation via recorded walkthroughs.</item>
        <item>Requirements Lifecycle — agile backlog management; continuous refinement; content-hash IDs instead of manually assigned IDs for stable traceability.</item>
        <item>Strategy Analysis — digital transformation; AI strategy; platform economics; data-product thinking.</item>
        <item>Requirements Analysis and Design — data modeling for ML features; API design; prompt versioning as a requirement artifact; eval set as a test case.</item>
        <item>Solution Evaluation — continuous feedback loops; A/B testing as validation evidence; process-mining feeds for current-state baseline.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="updated-perspectives">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Declare one or more perspectives explicitly at project start. Default-Agile routing hides Business Architecture and BPM concerns until late in the project.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to the Agile perspective because it dominates training data; without explicit declaration the agent misses BI, BizArch, and BPM concerns that are equally important for the actual work.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Agile — extended to scaled frameworks (SAFe, LeSS), DevOps, and continuous delivery.</item>
        <item>Business Intelligence — expanded to AI/ML, advanced analytics, and data storytelling.</item>
        <item>Information Technology — cloud-native, microservices, API-first, platform engineering.</item>
        <item>Business Architecture — digital transformation, platform economics, capability mapping.</item>
        <item>Business Process Management — intelligent automation, process mining, RPA.</item>
        <item>Data-Product (2025 addition) — domain-owned data products, data mesh, data contracts, ML feature stores.</item>
        <item>AI-Product (2025 addition) — prompt engineering as requirements, eval-driven development, model version as a dependency, LLM-specific NFRs.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="competency-based-framework">
      <p>Competency categories and the modern skills added in 2025-2026 context:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Analytical Thinking — AI/ML literacy, data interpretation, eval design, prompt quality assessment.</item>
        <item>Behavioral — virtual collaboration, async facilitation, remote observation design.</item>
        <item>Business Knowledge — digital business models, platform economics, data-product ownership.</item>
        <item>Communication — data storytelling, dashboard annotation, decision brief writing.</item>
        <item>Interaction — cross-functional collaboration across data, ML, and product teams; DevOps integration.</item>
        <item>Tools and Technology — cloud data warehouses, LLM APIs, process-mining platforms, automation tools, data catalogs.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="certification-alignment">
      <list>
        <item>ECBA — entry-level BA; foundation for all contexts.</item>
        <item>CCBA — mid-level BA; practical application.</item>
        <item>CBAP — senior BA; strategic BA leadership.</item>
        <item>Agile Analysis Certification (AAC) — critical for agile and product teams.</item>
        <item>Business Data Analytics Certification (CBDA) — data-driven BA; analytics and BI perspective.</item>
        <item>Product Ownership Analysis Certification (CPOA) — product-focused BA; PO collaboration.</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score competencies against SFIA v9 and certification curricula separately. Certifications signal coverage of a knowledge domain; SFIA scores actual skill capability level.</statement>
        <rationale>A CBAP holder has demonstrated BA knowledge breadth but not necessarily capability with LLMs, RAG, or eval design; conflating the two produces hiring decisions that miss AI-era requirements.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="framework-integration">
      <list>
        <item>SAFe/LeSS — BA competencies mapped to Program Increment planning; BA artifacts feed PI objectives and solution backlogs.</item>
        <item>DevOps — requirements in CI/CD pipelines; acceptance criteria as pipeline gates; RTM coverage as a merge check.</item>
        <item>Design Thinking — customer-centered requirements; empathy maps and jobs-to-be-done as elicitation outputs feeding BAKOK KA-2.</item>
        <item>Lean Startup — hypothesis-driven requirements; build-measure-learn cycles as KA-6 evaluation loops.</item>
        <item>Data Mesh — domain-driven data requirements; data products as solution artifacts traced in KA-3.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run a planner subagent that reads project context and emits ba-approach.json before any KA work starts. The planner routes; it does not execute BA work. Human PO/BA sign-off is mandatory before execution.</statement>
        <rationale>Auto-execution skips the only checkpoint where a real PO/BA can correct perspective bias and scope errors before they propagate through the entire pipeline.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Planner output schema: {perspectives[], knowledge_areas{ka: {include, methodologies[], rationale}}, competencies_needed[], model_routing{task: model}}.</p>
      <reference path="templates/ba-approach.json">Starter BA Approach JSON structure</reference>
      <reference path="templates/ba-approach-init.sh">Script scaffolding ba-approach.json for a feature</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="model-routing-per-task">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Lock model selection per task in the ba-approach.json. Do not allow cost-driven downgrade at runtime.</statement>
        <rationale>Cost regressions happen when orchestrators downgrade from opus to sonnet for gap analysis; the quality difference is significant and the cost saving is marginal relative to the rework cost.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Format requirements → haiku (mechanical template-fill).</item>
        <item>Write acceptance criteria → sonnet (requires testing perspective and detail).</item>
        <item>Validate requirements with stakeholders → sonnet (needs reasoning and communication planning).</item>
        <item>Gap analysis → opus (strategic analysis and trade-off evaluation).</item>
        <item>BPMN / process modeling → opus (architecture and complex modeling decisions).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <how-to>
      <p>Apply the framework in this exact order. Each step has a defined input, output artifact, and verification anchor.</p>
      <step>Confirm trigger fits when-to-use. If the task is already scoped to a single KA (e.g. "write acceptance criteria"), STOP and load the matching sibling methodology directly.</step>
      <step>Resolve feature slug: read repo context for the active feature folder under .aidocs/ or .product/. If none, ask the user for one, then create .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/.</step>
      <step>Run templates/ba-approach-init.sh &lt;feature-slug&gt; to scaffold .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json from templates/ba-approach.json.</step>
      <step>Gather planner inputs: project-brief (1-paragraph problem statement), stakeholder-list (roles, not names where possible), repo-tree (top 2 levels), existing-tickets (Jira/Linear/GitHub Issues sample of 10).</step>
      <step>Run the Planner Pass prompt (see prompt block) with model=opus. Constrain output to the JSON schema in section agentic-workflow. Save to .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json.</step>
      <step>For every INCLUDE'd KA, list at least one sibling methodology slug under skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/. If a KA has zero matches, mark it SKIP with rationale instead of leaving it empty.</step>
      <step>Lock model_routing per task using the table in section model-routing-per-task. No "auto" values.</step>
      <step>Run the Competency-Gap Pass prompt with team roster + skill self-assessments as input. Save to .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/competency-gap.md. Run password-scrubber-agent before persisting if names are present.</step>
      <step>Validate ba-approach.json with the verify section commands. Fix all issues before requesting sign-off.</step>
      <step>Request human PO sign-off by writing approval_status="pending" and emitting a one-page summary. WAIT. Do not proceed to execution while approval_status != "approved".</step>
      <step>On approval, dispatch the executor pass: one subagent per INCLUDE'd KA, loading the chosen sibling methodology files as context.</step>
      <step>Re-run the Planner Pass on every sprint boundary or whenever stakeholders, perspective, or delivery model changes. Diff old vs new ba-approach.json and surface drift to the PO.</step>
    </how-to>
    <checklist>
      <check>Feature slug exists under .aidocs/ and is kebab-case.</check>
      <check>ba-approach.json exists at .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json.</check>
      <check>perspectives[] has 1-3 entries from the closed list (Agile, BI, IT, BizArch, BPM, Data-Product, AI-Product).</check>
      <check>Each of the six BABOK KAs is present in knowledge_areas with include=true|false.</check>
      <check>Every include=true KA has at least one entry in methodologies[] and a one-sentence rationale.</check>
      <check>Every include=false KA has a one-sentence rationale explaining why it is skipped.</check>
      <check>model_routing maps each task type (format, ac, validate, gap, bpmn) to one of haiku|sonnet|opus — no "auto" or empty values.</check>
      <check>competencies_needed[] is populated and references the six categories (Analytical, Behavioral, BizKnowledge, Communication, Interaction, ToolsTech).</check>
      <check>approval_status is one of pending|approved|rejected.</check>
      <check>JSON parses with jq and matches schema with yq eval validation.</check>
      <check>No invented IIBA clause numbers or BABOK section IDs without a citation file path.</check>
      <check>Names of individuals removed from competency-gap.md or run through password-scrubber-agent first.</check>
      <check>Every methodology slug listed under a KA actually resolves to an existing folder under skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/.</check>
    </checklist>
    <prompt purpose="planner-pass"><![CDATA[
You are a BA Planner. Read the inputs below and emit ba-approach.json
that conforms to the schema in <schema/>. Do not execute BA work — route only.

<inputs>
  <project-brief>{{ PROJECT_BRIEF }}</project-brief>
  <stakeholder-list>{{ STAKEHOLDERS }}</stakeholder-list>
  <repo-tree>{{ REPO_TREE_TWO_LEVELS }}</repo-tree>
  <existing-tickets>{{ TICKETS_JSON }}</existing-tickets>
</inputs>

<rules>
  - Pick 1-3 perspectives from: Agile, BI, IT, BizArch, BPM, Data-Product, AI-Product.
  - For each of the six BABOK KAs decide INCLUDE or SKIP with a one-sentence rationale.
  - For each INCLUDE'd KA name 1-2 sibling methodology slugs under
    skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/. Verify each slug exists.
  - Lock model_routing: format=haiku, ac=sonnet, validate=sonnet, gap=opus, bpmn=opus.
  - Set approval_status="pending". Halt for human PO sign-off after emitting JSON.
  - Cite IIBA references by file path only (cached BABOK ToC). Do not invent clause numbers.
</rules>

<schema>
{
  "feature_slug": "<kebab-case>",
  "perspectives": ["..."],
  "knowledge_areas": {
    "ba_planning":            {"include": true, "methodologies": ["..."], "rationale": "..."},
    "elicitation":            {"include": true, "methodologies": ["..."], "rationale": "..."},
    "requirements_lifecycle": {"include": true, "methodologies": ["..."], "rationale": "..."},
    "strategy_analysis":      {"include": true, "methodologies": ["..."], "rationale": "..."},
    "requirements_analysis":  {"include": true, "methodologies": ["..."], "rationale": "..."},
    "solution_evaluation":    {"include": true, "methodologies": ["..."], "rationale": "..."}
  },
  "competencies_needed": ["analytical","behavioral","biz_knowledge","communication","interaction","tools_tech"],
  "model_routing": {"format":"haiku","ac":"sonnet","validate":"sonnet","gap":"opus","bpmn":"opus"},
  "approval_status": "pending",
  "approver": null,
  "approved_at": null
}
</schema>

Output: a single JSON object, no prose around it.
]]></prompt>
    <prompt purpose="competency-gap-pass"><![CDATA[
You are a BA Competency Auditor. Score the team against BABOK + SFIA v9.
Inputs: team-roster (roles only), skill-self-assessments, ba-approach.json.

For each competency category (Analytical, Behavioral, BizKnowledge, Communication,
Interaction, ToolsTech): record Have / Need / Gap on a 0-5 scale.
Map each Gap to ECBA/CCBA/CBAP/AAC/CBDA/CPOA training tracks AND to an SFIA v9 level.
Cross-reference PMI-PBA, BCS, Scrum.org product-owner tracks before recommending.
Emit competency-gap.md with sections: Summary, Per-Category Table, Ranked Recommendations.
Strip individual names. If names appear in input, refuse and request anonymized roster.
]]></prompt>
    <commands>
      <command name="scaffold">bash templates/ba-approach-init.sh &lt;feature-slug&gt;</command>
      <command name="parse-check">jq . .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json &gt; /dev/null</command>
      <command name="schema-keys">jq -e '.feature_slug and .perspectives and .knowledge_areas and .model_routing and .approval_status' .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json</command>
      <command name="all-kas-present">jq -e '.knowledge_areas | keys == ["ba_planning","elicitation","requirements_analysis","requirements_lifecycle","solution_evaluation","strategy_analysis"]' .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json</command>
      <command name="every-included-has-methodology">jq -e '[.knowledge_areas[] | select(.include==true) | (.methodologies | length &gt; 0)] | all' .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json</command>
      <command name="model-routing-locked">jq -e '.model_routing | (.format=="haiku" and .ac=="sonnet" and .validate=="sonnet" and .gap=="opus" and .bpmn=="opus")' .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json</command>
      <command name="perspectives-bounded">jq -e '.perspectives | length &gt; 0 and length &lt;= 3' .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json</command>
      <command name="approval-status-valid">jq -e '.approval_status | IN("pending","approved","rejected")' .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json</command>
      <command name="render-for-review">glow .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.md</command>
      <command name="diff-drift">git diff HEAD~1 -- .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json</command>
      <command name="resolve-methodology-slugs">jq -r '.knowledge_areas[].methodologies[]?' .aidocs/&lt;feature-slug&gt;/ba-approach.json | xargs -I{} test -d skills/faion/knowledge/pro/ba/business-analyst/{}</command>
    </commands>
    <verify>
      <step>Run command "parse-check" — must exit 0; otherwise the JSON is malformed.</step>
      <step>Run command "schema-keys" — must exit 0; missing required top-level keys is a hard fail.</step>
      <step>Run command "all-kas-present" — all six BABOK KAs must be keys in knowledge_areas.</step>
      <step>Run command "every-included-has-methodology" — no INCLUDE'd KA may have an empty methodologies[].</step>
      <step>Run command "model-routing-locked" — model_routing values must match the locked table exactly.</step>
      <step>Run command "perspectives-bounded" — perspectives must contain 1 to 3 entries.</step>
      <step>Run command "approval-status-valid" — approval_status must be pending|approved|rejected.</step>
      <step>Run command "resolve-methodology-slugs" — every named slug must resolve to an existing folder.</step>
      <step>Grep competency-gap.md for typical first/last name patterns; refuse to commit if any match.</step>
      <step>If approval_status != "approved", refuse to dispatch the executor pass.</step>
    </verify>
    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using the modern BA framework as a deliverable producer rather than a router.</description>
        <reason>The framework's output is ba-approach.json — a routing decision. Producing "a BA report from the modern framework" creates a document nobody asked for and skips the actual methodology execution.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>KA included in ba-approach.json without a named executable sibling methodology.</description>
        <reason>A KA without a methodology is theatre; the planner must map every INCLUDE'd KA to at least one sibling methodology folder that the executor can load and run.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-execution from planner to executor without human sign-off on the BA approach.</description>
        <reason>Perspective bias introduced in the planner (e.g., defaulting to Agile for a BPM initiative) propagates through the entire pipeline and produces misaligned artifacts that cannot be corrected without starting over.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cost-driven downgrade of model_routing at runtime (opus → sonnet for gap analysis).</description>
        <reason>The savings are marginal compared to the rework cost when gap analysis quality degrades. Lock model selection in the JSON and reject runtime overrides.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Persisting competency-gap.md with individual names attached to gap scores.</description>
        <reason>The artifact contains performance-grade signals about specific people; storing it outside a private repo without scrubbing creates HR and GDPR exposure.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="where-it-fails-limitations">
      <p>Not executable on its own. Without sibling methodologies wired in, the framework is descriptive only and an agent applying it produces hand-wavy plans.</p>
      <p>Companion files can drift. checklist, templates, examples, and prompts must stay in sync with the JSON schema; treat schema changes as breaking and bump the version field.</p>
      <p>Static perspective list. Five BABOK perspectives miss data-product, AI-product, and platform-engineering perspectives now common in 2025-2026. The agent must extend the table or risk routing AI/ML work into a stale Agile/BI bucket.</p>
      <p>Certification-to-real-skill drift. ECBA/CCBA/CBAP signal coverage, not capability with LLMs, RAG, prompt design, or evals. Do not treat the cert table as a hiring filter for AI-era BA.</p>
      <p>No KPI surface. Framework gives no measurable output by itself — pair it with an SLO doc that tracks cycle time, defect rate, and stakeholder NPS to prove modernization actually moved a number.</p>
      <p>Recency risk. "BA Standard (2025)" wording will go stale; the agent must check current IIBA publications before quoting versions to humans.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Treat the framework as a router, not a deliverable. Output is ba-approach.json, not "a BA report".</item>
        <item>Force perspective declaration up front. Default-Agile routing hides BizArch and BPM concerns until late.</item>
        <item>Persist the approach under .aidocs/feature-slug/ and diff it sprint-over-sprint to catch silent scope shifts.</item>
        <item>Map every INCLUDE'd KA to at least one executable sibling methodology — a KA without a methodology is theatre.</item>
        <item>Score competencies against SFIA v9 and certification curricula separately; certs do not equal skills.</item>
        <item>Re-run the planner whenever stakeholders, perspective, or delivery model changes (e.g., team adopts SAFe, or product pivots to data-product).</item>
        <item>Cache IIBA PDFs locally; the agent must not invent BABOK clause numbers under hallucination pressure.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow-details">
      <p>Run a planner-style subagent that takes a work brief + repo context and emits a BA Approach JSON. The planner does not execute BA work — it routes. A second pass (executor) loads each chosen sibling methodology (stakeholder-analysis, requirements-validation, etc.) and runs the actual analysis. State lives in .aidocs/feature-slug/ba-approach.md and is re-read on every sprint or milestone for drift detection. Human PO/BA approves the approach before any execution starts; otherwise the agent will self-justify a default plan.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: brainstorm (diverge across perspectives before converging), /faion (consumes the BA Approach plan and runs each KA's chosen methodology in order with quality gates), faion-sdd-executor-agent (wraps BA approach inside SDD feature so requirements get traced into code), improver (periodic audit of BA Approach drift), General Task subagent (one per KA with KA's sibling methodology files as context).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern — Planner pass inputs: project-brief, stakeholder-list, repo-tree, existing-tickets. Pick 1-3 BABOK perspectives (Agile, BI, IT, BizArch, BPM, +Data-Product, +AI-Product). For each KA decide INCLUDE/SKIP with one-sentence rationale. For each INCLUDE'd KA name 1-2 sibling methodologies. Emit JSON to .aidocs/feature-slug/ba-approach.json. Halt for human PO sign-off. Competency-gap pass inputs team roster + skill self-assessments, BA approach JSON. For each competency (Analytical, Behavioral, BizKnowledge, Communication, Interaction, ToolsTech) score Have / Need / Gap. Map gaps to ECBA/CCBA/CBAP/AAC/CBDA/CPOA training tracks and SFIA v9 levels. Emit competency-gap.md with ranked hiring/training recommendations.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: iiba-bakok (fetch from IIBA member portal for authoritative BABOK/BA Standard text), acli/jira-cli (pull tickets to feed planner with real project context), gh + gh project (read GitHub Issues/Projects v2 backlog as input), glow/mdcat (render BA Approach markdown for human review), mermaid-cli (render KA dependency/perspective diagrams from generated mermaid), pandoc (convert ba-approach.md to DOCX/PDF for non-technical stakeholders), yq/jq (validate/transform BA Approach JSON in CI), pre-commit (reject commits to .aidocs/feature-slug/ lacking required KA sections), sfia-mapper (map competencies to SFIA v9 levels).</p>
      <p>Services: IIBA KnowledgeHub (SaaS, no public API, source of truth for BABOK), Jira/Jira Align (REST + acli, ingest backlog for planner), Linear (GraphQL SDK, smaller teams), Azure DevOps (az boards CLI), Lucid/Miro (REST for perspective workshops), Confluence/Notion (persist BA Approach + competency-gap docs), Camunda/Signavio (REST + BPMN XML for BPM perspective), Power BI/Tableau/Metabase (BI-perspective deliverables), GitHub Projects v2 (lightweight backlog source), n8n/Airflow (schedule planner re-runs on sprint cadence).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs over-fit to the Agile perspective. Force a structured perspective-selection step or you'll never see BizArch / BPM picks.</item>
        <item>The model often confabulates IIBA version numbers. Pin a fact-source file (cached BABOK ToC + BA Standard ToC) and require citations.</item>
        <item>Agent Selection table in README is advisory. Cost regressions happen when the planner downgrades opus to sonnet for "gap analysis"; lock model per task in the JSON.</item>
        <item>Human-in-the-loop checkpoint is mandatory between planner and executor. Auto-execution skips the only place a real PO/BA can correct perspective bias.</item>
        <item>Competency-gap output is sensitive PII when it names individuals. Run password-scrubber-agent and remove names before persisting outside private repos.</item>
        <item>Do not let the agent edit the README's tables; it tends to "modernize" them every run, churning git history. Confine edits to agent-integration.md and .aidocs/feature-slug/.</item>
        <item>Certification recommendations leak vendor bias (IIBA-only). Cross-reference PMI-PBA, BCS, and Scrum.org product-owner tracks before presenting to the user.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ba-approach.json" purpose="Starter BA Approach JSON: perspectives, KA include/rationale, methodologies, model routing, human sign-off flag."/>
      <template path="templates/ba-approach-init.sh" purpose="Script scaffolding a ba-approach.json for a feature under .aidocs/feature-slug/."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/professional-development/knowledge-centre/agile-extension/"/>
      <link href="https://sfia-online.org/en/sfia-9"/>
      <link href="https://scaledagileframework.com"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/business-analysis-certifications/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
