<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="AWS Architecture Services Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules every application of `AWS Architecture Services` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="lambda-vs-containers" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Lambda for variable / spiky traffic, execution &lt; 15min, cold-start tolerance, no GPU. Use containers (ECS Fargate / EKS) for steady ≥ 1M req/day, GPU, persistent websockets, K8s ecosystem. Document the boundary in an ADR.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected; internal cost reviews 2025">A binary choice is wrong for most teams; the hybrid boundary is the actual decision.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="event-routing-by-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use EventBridge for cross-service decoupled routing, Step Functions for stateful orchestration ≥ 2 sequential steps, SQS for async buffering + retry, SNS for fan-out. Mixing roles (SQS for routing, SNS for state) is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Application Integration docs; SaaS architecture postmortems">Service mis-selection creates invisible retry loops + observability holes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="well-architected-six-pillars" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every architecture review MUST cover all six Well-Architected pillars (Operational Excellence, Security, Reliability, Performance Efficiency, Cost Optimization, Sustainability). Skipping any pillar is rejected at review.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected Framework">Skipping a pillar creates technical debt: missing Security → breaches; missing Cost → uncontrolled spend; missing Sustainability → audit gap.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="graviton-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to Graviton (ARM64) compute for all new resources; require an explicit comment to justify x86. Audit Graviton coverage quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Graviton2/3 benchmarks; FinOps reports 2025">Graviton delivers ~20% lower cost + comparable / better perf for most workloads; x86 default is unjustified waste.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="eks-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>EKS clusters MUST be deployed in private subnets, IRSA enabled, secrets encryption via KMS, managed node groups on Graviton, and CoreDNS / kube-proxy / VPC CNI / EBS CSI as managed add-ons.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS EKS Best Practices">Public-subnet workers + IAM-keys-on-nodes is the most common EKS misconfiguration class.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="aurora-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Aurora production deployments MUST run Multi-AZ (≥ 2 instances), KMS-encrypted at rest, IAM authentication enabled, deletion protection on, retention ≥ 30 days, Performance Insights + Enhanced Monitoring (60s) on.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Aurora Best Practices; SOC2 audit findings">Single-AZ Aurora has no automatic failover; deletion-protection-off has cost teams entire databases.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="alb-tls-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ALB MUST redirect HTTP → HTTPS, use SSL policy `ELBSecurityPolicy-TLS13-1-2-2021-06` minimum, and ship access logs to S3 with ≥ 90d lifecycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS ALB security guide; PCI-DSS 4.0">Default ALB security policies allow weak ciphers; TLS 1.3 policy is the defensible baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="eventbridge-dlq-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every EventBridge rule target MUST have a DLQ + retry policy configured; use a custom event bus for application events with 30-day event-archive retention.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS EventBridge ops guide; event-driven postmortems">Without DLQ, EventBridge silently drops events after 24h of retries; archive enables replay during outages.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>