<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-kubernetes" title="Kubernetes Secrets Integration">
  <summary>External Secrets Operator setup, Vault Secrets Operator, IRSA and Workload Identity auth, and secure injection patterns.</summary>

  <section title="External Secrets Operator">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use External Secrets Operator (ESO) as the standard Kubernetes integration layer — it supports all major backends (AWS SM, GCP SM, Azure KV, Vault) with a unified API.</statement>
      <rationale>Native Kubernetes Secrets are base64-encoded, not encrypted at rest by default. ESO syncs from an encrypted backend and recreates the K8s Secret automatically on rotation, without restarting pods.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# ClusterSecretStore — backend connection
apiVersion: external-secrets.io/v1beta1
kind: ClusterSecretStore
metadata:
  name: aws-secrets-manager
spec:
  provider:
    aws:
      service: SecretsManager
      region: us-east-1
      auth:
        jwt:
          serviceAccountRef:
            name: external-secrets-sa
            namespace: external-secrets
---
# ExternalSecret — specific secret sync
apiVersion: external-secrets.io/v1beta1
kind: ExternalSecret
metadata:
  name: db-credentials
  namespace: production
spec:
  refreshInterval: 1h
  secretStoreRef:
    name: aws-secrets-manager
    kind: ClusterSecretStore
  target:
    name: db-credentials
    creationPolicy: Owner
  data:
    - secretKey: password
      remoteRef:
        key: prod/app/db
        property: password
]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/eso-secret-store.yaml">Complete ESO ClusterSecretStore + ExternalSecret example</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="IRSA and Workload Identity">
    <rule>
      <statement>On AWS EKS, use IRSA (IAM Roles for Service Accounts) to bind a Kubernetes ServiceAccount to an AWS IAM role — no AWS credentials in pods or Secrets.</statement>
      <rationale>IRSA uses OIDC token exchange: the pod presents a K8s JWT, AWS STS exchanges it for temporary credentials scoped to the IAM role. Credentials auto-rotate every hour.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: v1
kind: ServiceAccount
metadata:
  name: app-sa
  namespace: production
  annotations:
    eks.amazonaws.com/role-arn: arn:aws:iam::123456789012:role/app-prod-role
]]></code>
      <note>The IAM role trust policy must allow sts:AssumeRoleWithWebIdentity from the OIDC provider and restrict the sub claim to the specific namespace:serviceaccount.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Hardening">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable envelope encryption for etcd using a KMS provider key — base64 encoding in native Secrets is not encryption.</statement>
      <rationale>Without envelope encryption, anyone with etcd access (backup files, etcd snapshots) can read all Kubernetes Secrets in plaintext after a simple base64 decode.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never log secrets: ensure application code masks credential values in logs and that Kubernetes audit logs do not capture Secret data.</statement>
      <rationale>Secrets in logs are effectively unencrypted and distributed — logs go to ELK/Loki, S3, and potentially third-party log aggregators.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Storing secrets in ConfigMaps because they are easier to manage.</description>
      <reason>ConfigMaps have no access control differentiation from regular config. Any pod that can read ConfigMaps in a namespace can read all secrets stored there.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/vault-policy.hcl">Vault policy template with least-privilege path scoping</reference>
  </section>
</text>
