<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Secrets Management Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="static-keys-in-ci" severity="medium">
      <description>GitHub repo contains AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID + AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY in repo secrets; rotation manual.</description>
      <reason>Team set up CI/CD before OIDC trust was available; static keys grandfathered in.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Configure OIDC trust between GitHub and AWS IAM. Replace static keys with role assumption via id-token. Delete the IAM access keys.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="kubectl-create-secret-in-prod" severity="medium">
      <description>Production cluster has 50+ Secrets created via kubectl create secret; no rotation; manifests in private git.</description>
      <reason>ESO not installed; team uses imperative kubectl.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Install ESO + the backend ClusterSecretStore. Replace plaintext Secrets with ExternalSecret manifests. Delete the plaintext Secrets after migration.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="wildcard-iam-policy" severity="medium">
      <description>Application can read every secret in the backend; security review flags it.</description>
      <reason>Initial policy used 'secrets/*' to unblock the team.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Replace with explicit paths: prod/api/* for the api role, prod/worker/* for the worker role. Audit logs surface the actual paths used.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="manual-rotation-overdue" severity="medium">
      <description>Audit shows a database password not rotated in 18 months; engineer who knew the rotation procedure left.</description>
      <reason>Rotation never automated; documented as a quarterly manual task that nobody owned.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Configure backend's dynamic-credentials engine for the database. Rotation becomes automatic on lease expiry.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="secret-baked-into-image" severity="medium">
      <description>Old image layer contains hardcoded API key; image still pullable from registry.</description>
      <reason>Dockerfile had ENV API_KEY=... during a hotfix.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Remove ENV. Mount via secret volume or fetch at runtime via SDK. Rotate the leaked key. Audit registry for other contaminated images.</note>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
