<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-tactics" title="Seven Activation Tactics">
  <summary>Concrete techniques to reduce time-to-value and increase the percentage of signups that reach the Aha moment.</summary>

  <section title="Progressive Onboarding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show value before requiring setup; defer configuration to the moment it becomes relevant.</statement>
      <rationale>Front-loaded setup screens increase cognitive load before the user has experienced any value. Show a sample project first, then guide them to create their own.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>5 setup screens → empty product. User quits before seeing any value.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Skip setup → show sample project → guide "try editing this task" → after Aha: "now create your own project".</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Templates and Presets">
    <rule>
      <statement>Offer 3-5 use-case templates at first login; users who pick a template activate at ~65% vs ~35% for blank-start.</statement>
      <rationale>Templates reduce the blank-page problem and immediately anchor the product to the user's specific use case, accelerating time to value.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Activation Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show a visible progress checklist (2-5 steps) with a marked activation event; remove it once the user activates.</statement>
      <rationale>Progress visibility triggers the Zeigarnik effect — users feel motivated to complete partial sequences. Expected lift: +10-25% activation rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/activation-checklist.yaml">YAML config for in-product checklist with activation_event flag</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Empty State Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Replace generic empty states with personalized prompts that surface the highest-converting first action.</statement>
      <rationale>An empty state is a decision point: without guidance, the user faces choice paralysis. A personalized CTA with a template shortcut doubles conversion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Time-to-Value Optimization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure time from signup to Aha moment; if it exceeds 5 minutes for the core use case, remove steps until it does not.</statement>
      <rationale>Each additional minute increases dropout probability. Remove optional fields, pre-fill defaults, skip to core action. Target: signup to value in under 3 minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Activation Emails">
    <rule>
      <statement>Send a 4-email sequence (Day 0, 1, 3, 7) to users who have not activated; each email has a single CTA linked to the next blocking step.</statement>
      <rationale>Re-engagement emails targeting non-activated users recover 5-10% of them on Day 7. Each email should have one goal — not a product tour.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/email-sequence.md">4-email activation sequence copy templates</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="In-App Guidance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deploy tooltips at the first visit to each key feature; use coach marks for multi-step processes; use chat prompts only when session recordings show users stuck for 30+ seconds.</statement>
      <rationale>Contextual help shown at the right moment adds guidance without overwhelming the interface. Poorly timed tooltips (shown every visit) are dismissed and create noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
