<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ba-governance">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>Establishes decision rights, change control, and communication planning for BA requirements work.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>governance</tag>
      <tag>ba</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>decision-rights</tag>
      <tag>change-control</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>BA Governance</title>

    <summary>Establishes decision rights, change control, and communication planning for requirements work. Includes governance framework, communication planning, and elicitation preparation.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Requirements processes without explicit governance produce stuck change requests, scope drift, and sign-off ambiguity. A decision-authority matrix with explicit escalation paths prevents the most common failure mode: every change escalating to steering committee because impact thresholds are undefined. Communication plans without feedback mechanisms become write-only channels within weeks.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Setting up decision rights, change control, and approval workflow for a new product or squad before requirements work starts.</item>
        <item>Projects crossing three or more stakeholder groups (sponsor, dev, ops, legal/compliance) that need a communication plan.</item>
        <item>Preparing elicitation logistics and technique selection before interviews or workshops begin.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing requirements process where rework, scope drift, or sign-off ambiguity has been observed.</item>
        <item>Regulated builds (SOX, HIPAA, GDPR) where a decision audit trail is mandatory.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founder / single-team early MVP — formal governance burns time you do not have; use lightweight requirements-prioritization instead.</item>
        <item>Pure engineering refactors with no external stakeholders — governance overhead is waste; rely on PR review.</item>
        <item>Research spikes and discovery sprints where the goal is learning, not committing scope.</item>
        <item>Crisis incidents — use incident command, not governance workflow.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="decision-rights">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define decision rights before any requirements work begins; document who can approve, who must be consulted, and who must be informed for each decision type.</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit decision rights, every scope change escalates to the highest available authority, creating steering-committee bottlenecks and delayed delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>New requirement: BA Lead authority, PM escalation.</item>
        <item>Scope change: Steering Committee authority, Sponsor escalation.</item>
        <item>Priority change: Product Owner authority, PM escalation.</item>
        <item>Baseline update: BA Lead + named approver, joint authority.</item>
      </list>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Escalation paths that use role titles without named individuals ("Director of Product" rather than a specific person).</description>
        <reason>Role titles become orphaned when people leave or org charts change; named individuals ensure the escalation path actually resolves in a crisis.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="change-control-process">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every change-control flow must have explicit terminal states: approve, reject with reason, and defer with owner and date; open-ended flows leave CRs in limbo.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM-generated change-control flows frequently lack a "reject + reason" terminal state; unresolved CRs accumulate and make the requirements baseline untrustworthy.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Step 1: Submit change request (CR) — link to affected requirements IDs.</item>
        <item>Step 2: Impact assessment — T-shirt sizing (S/M/L/XL) against scope, schedule, and cost. Mandatory; not optional for any CR severity.</item>
        <item>Step 3: Review by authority from decision matrix.</item>
        <item>Step 4: Decision — Approve / Reject (with reason) / Defer (with owner + date).</item>
        <item>Step 5: Update baseline; link CR → REQ in tracking system.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Bind change-control thresholds to objective signals (story points, dollar impact, regulatory flag), not to subjective severity assessments.</statement>
        <rationale>Subjective thresholds drift over time; every CR eventually qualifies as "XL / Steering" because teams learn that higher classification gets faster decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prioritization-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Document tie-breaking rules before any prioritization conflict arises; do not defer tie-breaking to ad-hoc stakeholder negotiation.</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit tie-breaking rules, priority conflicts become political; the loudest stakeholder wins rather than the most valuable requirement.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Criteria: business value, regulatory compliance, strategic fit, implementation cost, risk.</item>
        <item>Weight assignment: use the same method as solution options scoring (AHP pairwise or 100-point swing); document the method and stakeholders who assigned weights.</item>
        <item>Tie-breaker: in a tie, the requirement with higher regulatory compliance score takes precedence; second tie-breaker is lower implementation cost.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="audit-trail">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Capture every decision including rejections and defers; the audit trail is the deliverable, not the matrix.</statement>
        <rationale>Regulated industries require a complete decision log; even non-regulated projects benefit because rejected CRs contain the reasoning that prevents re-relitigating the same scope question next quarter.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Re-validate the decision-authority matrix every 30 days; stale escalation paths are the leading cause of stuck CRs.</statement>
        <rationale>Org charts change faster than governance documents; a matrix updated at kickoff is obsolete within 3 months on average for growing teams.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="communication-planning">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Map every communication channel to a feedback mechanism; a channel without a feedback mechanism is write-only and decays within weeks.</statement>
        <rationale>"Email weekly digest" without a reply expectation or read-confirmation mechanism produces a false sense of stakeholder alignment; unresolved misunderstandings surface as surprise issues at sign-off.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Audience analysis: who needs what information, preferred format, preferred channel, frequency requirements.</item>
        <item>Message design: key points, level of detail appropriate for audience, supporting materials.</item>
        <item>Channel selection: formal vs informal, written vs verbal, synchronous vs asynchronous.</item>
        <item>Feedback mechanism: how to confirm understanding, follow-up process, issue resolution path.</item>
      </list>

      <example type="good" title="Audience-specific communication plan">
        <note>Sponsor: weekly status summary by email, feedback mechanism = standing 15-minute review slot. Dev team: detailed requirements per sprint via Jira, feedback mechanism = refinement session questions log. Ops: release plan checklist pre-release via Slack, feedback mechanism = acknowledgment reaction + blockers thread.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Communication plan that defaults all channels to Slack regardless of audience or message formality.</description>
        <reason>Slack is appropriate for async informal communication; regulatory-track approvals, formal sign-offs, and sponsor status reports require traceable channels with retention guarantees.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="elicitation-preparation">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define elicitation scope (what information is needed, what decisions will be made, what is out of scope) before scheduling any session.</statement>
        <rationale>Undefined scope turns sessions into open-ended discussions that produce inconsistent outputs and require rework to extract useful requirements.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pre-commit the technique-selection table per session; agents otherwise default to "interview" for all information types.</statement>
        <rationale>Each information type has an optimally matched technique; always interviewing leaves process gaps, current-state artifacts, and validation results under-covered.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Current state information: Observation, Document Analysis.</item>
        <item>Pain points and stakeholder needs: Interviews, Focus Groups.</item>
        <item>New requirements and consensus: Workshops, Prototyping.</item>
        <item>Validation of existing requirements: Reviews, Walkthroughs.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-specific-failures">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM generates a communication plan with a six-tier steering committee for a four-person project.</description>
        <reason>LLMs over-template governance artifacts for any project they perceive as "enterprise" regardless of actual team size. Pass team size and compliance flag explicitly in the system prompt to constrain output appropriately.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM auto-closes CRs when CI is green without requiring human approval.</description>
        <reason>Green CI indicates technical quality; governance integrity requires a human approval trace. Automating CR closure on CI signals removes the accountable human from the audit trail.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require three human-in-the-loop checkpoints: (1) sign-off on the decision-authority matrix before any requirements are baselined; (2) sponsor confirmation of comms cadence; (3) post-kickoff dry-run of the CR flow with one synthetic CR.</statement>
        <rationale>Governance integrity depends on human approval traces at critical junctures; agent-only setup produces a governance document that satisfies process checkers but fails the first real decision.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Treat the decision-authority matrix as code: keep it in Git next to governance.md, review changes via PR, never edit Confluence in place.</item>
        <item>Re-validate the matrix on a fixed cadence (30 days). Stale escalation paths are the #1 cause of stuck CRs.</item>
        <item>Map every comms channel to a feedback mechanism — "email weekly digest" without a reply expectation is a write-only channel and decays in 3 weeks.</item>
        <item>Bind change-control thresholds to objective signals (story points, $ impact, regulatory flag), not vibes; otherwise the threshold drifts.</item>
        <item>Co-locate governance.md with stakeholder-analysis.md and requirements-lifecycle.md in .aidocs/, then cross-link — the three documents only work together.</item>
        <item>For elicitation prep, pre-commit the technique-selection table (README §3) per session. Agents otherwise default to "interview" for everything.</item>
        <item>Capture every decision (including rejections and defers) — the audit trail is the deliverable, not the matrix.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="failure-modes-in-practice">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Matrix-vs-reality drift: the published matrix says "Steering Committee approves scope changes," but in reality the PM emails the sponsor and ships.</description>
        <reason>Symptom: audit findings during regulatory review. Fix: monthly sample of CRs vs matrix.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Approval-tier inflation: every CR escalates to "XL / Steering" because impact assessment is skipped.</description>
        <reason>Symptom: steering meetings with 30+ items. Fix: enforce T-shirt size with a checklist + mandatory link to impact analysis.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Channel sprawl: comms plan starts with email + Jira; six weeks later there are five Slack channels, two Confluence spaces, and a shared Drive folder, none referenced in the plan.</description>
        <reason>Fix: agent runs a quarterly comms-audit task that diffs declared channels vs actual.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Unowned artifacts: governance.md exists, no one updates it.</description>
        <reason>Fix: a single Owner: line + cron-triggered subagent that opens a "stale doc" issue at day 30.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="integration-with-sibling-methodologies">
      <list>
        <item>stakeholder-analysis feeds the audience matrix in communication-planning section — never draft comms without it.</item>
        <item>requirements-prioritization consumes the priority-change authority row from decision-rights section — keep them in sync.</item>
        <item>requirements-traceability depends on the change-control flow defining stable IDs (REQ-NNN, CR-NNN) before any baseline.</item>
        <item>elicitation-techniques is the runtime counterpart of elicitation-preparation section — governance plans the session, elicitation runs it.</item>
        <item>requirements-validation reuses the approval thresholds from decision-rights to decide which artifacts need sponsor sign-off vs reviewer-only.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="stakeholder-inventory">
      <p>Before defining governance, inventory all stakeholders: identify sponsors, decision makers, approvers, reviewers, and affected parties. Map each to the decision-authority matrix so no stakeholder is surprised by the approval flow. Missing stakeholders from the inventory are the leading cause of governance breakdown—someone always has veto power that was not reflected in the matrix.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-agent-constraints">
      <p>When using LLM agents to generate governance artifacts, enforce explicit constraints: cap team size, specify compliance requirements, define primary async communication channel, require placeholders for unknown authorities instead of invented role names. Governance artifacts are legal documents in regulated contexts; auto-generation must pass human review before publishing.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Pass team size + regulatory flag (SOX/HIPAA/GDPR/none) explicitly in system prompt.</item>
        <item>Declare primary async channel (Slack/Email/Jira) before generating communication plan.</item>
        <item>Force TBD placeholders for unknown decision authorities; never invent role names.</item>
        <item>Require explicit sign-off on decision-authority matrix before requirements are baselined.</item>
        <item>Run a dry-run CR flow with one synthetic change request post-kickoff before relying on the process.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder rosters in generated artifacts must not include real email addresses or phone numbers — use 1Password references or TBD for contact info until shared in a separate secure channel.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/governance.md" purpose="Governance artifact skeleton with decision-authority matrix, change-control steps, and communication audience matrix."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/agile-extension/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/career-resources/a-business-analysis-professionals-foundation-for-success/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://docs.github.com/en/repositories/managing-your-repositorys-settings-and-features/customizing-your-repository/about-code-owners"/>
      <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/confluence/templates/decision"/>
      <link href="https://camunda.com/bpmn/reference/"/>
      <link href="https://hbr.org/2006/06/decision-rights"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
