<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="viral-metrics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>growth-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Measure and optimize viral coefficient K = i * c; track invites per user and conversion rate separately; benchmark by product type and project exponential growth.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>viral</tag>
      <tag>k-factor</tag>
      <tag>referrals</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>sharing</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Viral Metrics and K-factor</title>
    <summary>The viral coefficient K = i * c, where i is average invites sent per user and c is the conversion rate of those invites. K greater than 1 produces exponential growth; K = 0.5-1.0 amplifies other channels. Measure i, c, and viral cycle time weekly; optimize both independently.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Paid acquisition costs compound; viral growth does not. K-factor quantifies self-sustaining growth: each user with K=1.2 brings 1.2 more users, doubling the cohort every cycle. Most products target K=0.3-0.7 as a meaningful supplement to paid channels — K greater than 1 is rare and reserved for inherently collaborative or content-based products.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or auditing a referral/sharing mechanism for an existing product.</item>
        <item>Building a weekly viral dashboard to track i, c, and K by loop type and channel.</item>
        <item>Projecting growth to determine whether viral alone can hit a user target within N cycles.</item>
        <item>Identifying which factor (i or c) has the most improvement headroom.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-retention: if D30 retention is below 20%, increasing K just cycles more users through a leaky bucket.</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise with 6-month sales cycles — K compounds too slowly to matter for pipeline.</item>
        <item>When invite event tracking is not yet in place — computing K from incomplete data is misleading.</item>
        <item>Regulated products where incentivized referrals trigger disclosure requirements.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="K-factor Formula and Growth Projection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Compute K = i * c, where i = total invites / active referrers and c = referral signups / total invites sent. Track both factors separately so you know which to optimize.</statement>
        <rationale>K conflates two independent levers. If K drops, diagnosing whether i or c fell determines the correct fix (UX change for i, landing page for c).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="K-factor Computation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Active referrers: 850
Invites sent: 4,200   -> i = 4,200 / 850 = 4.94
Referral signups: 630  -> c = 630 / 4,200 = 0.15
K = 4.94 * 0.15 = 0.74  (near-viral, strong amplifier)]]></code>
      </example>
      <p>K interpretation: K less than 0.5 is weak virality — supplement only, not a growth strategy. K = 0.5-1.0 is a good amplifier — each cohort grows 50-100% via referrals. K = 1.0 is break-even — each user replaces themselves. K greater than 1.0 is viral — exponential growth without ad spend. K greater than 2.0 is highly viral — rare; Slack, WhatsApp, early Wordle territory.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>For B2B SaaS target K=0.1-0.3 baseline, K=0.5+ as "great". For consumer apps K=0.2-0.5 baseline, K=1.0+ as "great". Do not benchmark against outliers.</statement>
        <rationale>Most benchmarks are survivorship-biased toward exceptional cases. Realistic targets by product type avoid chasing K greater than 1 at the expense of other channels.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Growth Projection">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Starting users: 1,000 | K = 1.2 | Viral cycle: 7 days

Cycle 0: 1,000
Cycle 1: 1,000 + (1,000 * 1.2) = 2,200
Cycle 2: 2,200 + (2,200 * 1.2) = 4,840
Cycle 3: 4,840 + (4,840 * 1.2) = 10,648
Cycle 4: 10,648 + (10,648 * 1.2) = 23,426]]></code>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>Optimize viral cycle time (days from signup to successful referral conversion) as aggressively as K — halving cycle time approximately equals doubling K in compounding terms.</statement>
        <rationale>K amplifies per cycle, not per day. A K=0.6 product with a 3-day cycle outgrows a K=0.8 product with a 14-day cycle over 60 days.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Improving i and c — Viral Optimization Levers">
      <section name="Increasing i (Invites per User)">
        <list>
          <item>Natural share moments: prompt sharing at the instant of an achievement or result — not on first login</item>
          <item>Referral incentives: reward referrers; double-sided (both parties rewarded) converts better than single-sided</item>
          <item>Multi-channel sharing: email, SMS, copy-link, social — users have channel preferences</item>
          <item>Contact import: allow bulk invite from address book to lower per-invite friction</item>
          <item>Viral content: shareable artifacts (results page, badge, score) that embed product branding</item>
          <item>Team/collaboration features: product that requires others to use inherently drives invites</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Increasing c (Invite Conversion Rate)">
        <list>
          <item>Personal invitation copy: "John invited you to [Product]" vs generic blast — high impact</item>
          <item>Social proof: "5 of your colleagues already use this" — high impact</item>
          <item>Clear value proposition on landing page: one sentence, no jargon</item>
          <item>Low-friction signup: one-click social auth, minimal fields — high impact</item>
          <item>Incentive for invitee: "$10 when you join" — medium impact, verify margin allows it</item>
          <item>Preview of value before signup: show what they will get, not just marketing copy</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Measurement Checklist">
        <list>
          <item>Track: invite_sent event with loop_type and share_channel properties</item>
          <item>Track: invite_clicked, referral_signup, referral_activated events</item>
          <item>Compute i, c, K weekly; flag K drops greater than 20% week-over-week</item>
          <item>Segment K by acquisition channel and user cohort to find viral power users</item>
          <item>Do not report K computed on fewer than 500 invites — noise dominates at small samples</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Over-incentivizing referrals (50%+ reward to hit K=1).</description>
        <reason>Attracts fraud and low-quality users who joined for the reward. Sets unsustainable cost expectations. K plateaus quickly; agents optimizing reward size erode margin without meaningful K lift.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using a single invite channel (email only).</description>
        <reason>Users have strong channel preferences. Email-only sharing misses SMS and social invites that convert at 25% vs email's 12-15% in many consumer apps.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sending generic invite blasts from the product (outbreak/spam virality).</description>
        <reason>Modern email filters and OS protections block automated contact imports. Damages brand NPS and can trigger CAN-SPAM violations.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
  </content>
</methodology>
