<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-computing-overview">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Spatial computing platforms, terminology, and market context. AR/VR/MR distinctions, platform landscape (Vision Pro, Quest, Android XR, HoloLens, Magic Leap), and per-platform design implications.</summary>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-computing</tag>
      <tag>ar-vr-mr</tag>
      <tag>platform-overview</tag>
      <tag>xr-design</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Spatial Computing Overview</title>

    <summary>Reference overview of spatial computing platforms, terminology, and market context for designers entering AR/VR/MR work. Covers the distinction between AR, VR, and MR; the current platform landscape (Apple Vision Pro, Meta Quest, Android XR, HoloLens, Magic Leap); and the design implications of 3D-space interfaces versus rectangular screens.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Designers coming from 2D backgrounds often conflate AR, VR, and MR, leading to wrong platform assumptions, incorrect interaction model selection, and deliverables that do not match the target device's capabilities. A shared vocabulary and platform map prevents misaligned design decisions early in a project.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Onboarding to a spatial computing project with no prior XR design experience</item>
        <item>Choosing which XR platform to target for a given use case</item>
        <item>Writing briefs or technical specs that need precise AR/VR/MR terminology</item>
        <item>Evaluating market context and platform maturity before committing to a platform</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Deep-dive on specific interaction patterns — use the spatial-interaction-patterns methodology instead</item>
        <item>Tooling decisions — use the spatial-design-tools methodology instead</item>
        <item>Enterprise XR requirements — use the enterprise-xr-applications methodology instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="terminology">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use precise XR terminology in all design documentation: AR (digital overlay on real world, passthrough camera or optical), VR (fully immersive synthetic environment), MR (real and digital objects interact in real time), XR (umbrella term for all three).</statement>
        <rationale>Conflating AR and VR leads to wrong platform selection, incorrect interaction model assumptions, and deliverables that cannot be implemented on the target device.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-comparison">
      <list>
        <item>Apple Vision Pro: spatial computing (MR), premium UX, enterprise-ready, visionOS, primary input via eye+hand+voice, no controllers</item>
        <item>Meta Quest 3/Pro: VR and color passthrough MR, largest consumer install base, controller and hand tracking, Android XR SDK</item>
        <item>Android XR: open platform for Android ecosystem devices, largest potential scale, early maturity in 2026</item>
        <item>Microsoft HoloLens 2: AR headset, enterprise and industrial focus, spatial mapping, gaze+hand tracking, Windows Mixed Reality</item>
        <item>Magic Leap 2: AR for industrial applications, high brightness for factory floors, enterprise-only</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="2026-market-context">
      <list>
        <item>AR/VR headset market: 87% projected growth in 2026</item>
        <item>40% of Global 2000 manufacturers have deployed digital twin initiatives</item>
        <item>Enterprise is the primary revenue driver; consumer adoption lags but accelerating with Quest and Android XR</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="design-implications-by-platform">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For Apple Vision Pro: design eye-gaze + pinch as the primary interaction; no physical controller grip states; use visionOS window and volume primitives; assume high rendering quality and precision eye tracking.</statement>
        <rationale>visionOS was designed around eye+hand input from the ground up; controller-centric patterns from other platforms do not translate and will feel unnatural.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For Meta Quest: design for both hand tracking and controller input as parallel paths; assume color passthrough for MR use cases; test comfort for the larger consumer user base including non-technical users.</statement>
        <rationale>Quest's broad consumer install base includes users unfamiliar with 3D interfaces; simpler interaction models and robust onboarding are required.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For HoloLens and Magic Leap: design for factory and field use — glove compatibility, outdoor brightness, short interaction sequences between physical work tasks, voice as primary input when hands are occupied.</statement>
        <rationale>Industrial XR users are performing physical tasks concurrently; interaction must be minimal and glove-compatible; content must be visible in high-ambient-light environments.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use this overview to seed a scoping conversation, then route to specific methodologies. Agents help with: platform-comparison matrix, market-context-2026 fact-check, AR-vs-VR-vs-MR decision tree from a use case, deck/document drafts. Agents do NOT replace: hands-on device evaluation, user interviews, ergonomic testing.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>`faion-sdd-executor-agent` — translate scoping decisions into SDD spec/design tasks per platform target.</item>
        <item>Platform-decision subagent — given use case + constraints (mobile/seated/social/industrial), recommend AR / VR / MR + specific device.</item>
        <item>Market-fact subagent — when README cites figures, verify against current sources and replace stale data; flag when sources older than 6 months.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>Platform decision from use case:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Given this use case: "{{description}}", recommend AR vs VR vs MR plus a
device shortlist (Vision Pro / Quest 3 / Quest 3S / HoloLens / Magic Leap 2 /
Android XR / WebXR / Pico). For each, give one-sentence rationale and one
constraint that could disqualify. End with a single primary recommendation
and a fallback.
      ]]></code>
      <p>Landscape brief generation:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Build a 2026 spatial-computing landscape brief (≤500 words):
- AR / VR / MR definitions with examples.
- Top 5 platforms with strengths and one weakness each.
- Two trends to watch (e.g., smart glasses, generative content).
- Cite at least three sources from the last 6 months.
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Overview-only: ≈40 lines, no implementation detail.</item>
        <item>Market figures (87% growth) age fast; verify before quoting.</item>
        <item>Platform list is incomplete — Pico, Lynx, Varjo (industrial), Bigscreen Beyond, Samsung's headset all relevant in 2026.</item>
        <item>Doesn't cover WebXR, smart glasses (Ray-Ban Meta, Halliday, Brilliant Labs Frame), or mobile AR.</item>
        <item>"Spatial computing" is contested terminology — Apple's framing vs. Meta's "MR" vs. Microsoft's "MR" differ.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-sdks">
      <list>
        <item>Unity XR Interaction Toolkit — Cross-platform XR. Docs: https://docs.unity3d.com/Packages/com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit</item>
        <item>Unreal OpenXR — Cross-platform. Docs: https://docs.unrealengine.com/5.0/en-US/openxr-in-unreal-engine/</item>
        <item>MRTK3 — Microsoft mixed-reality toolkit. Repo: https://github.com/MixedRealityToolkit/MixedRealityToolkit-Unity</item>
        <item>visionOS SDK / RealityKit / Reality Composer Pro — Vision Pro native. Docs: https://developer.apple.com/visionos/</item>
        <item>Meta XR SDK + Presence Platform — Quest features. Docs: https://developer.oculus.com</item>
        <item>ARKit / RealityKit (iOS) — Mobile AR. Docs: https://developer.apple.com/augmented-reality/</item>
        <item>ARCore — Android AR. Docs: https://developers.google.com/ar</item>
        <item>WebXR — Browser XR. Spec: https://immersive-web.github.io/webxr/</item>
        <item>Babylon.js / Three.js + WebXR — OSS web XR. Sites: https://www.babylonjs.com / https://threejs.org</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-platforms">
      <list>
        <item>Apple App Store / Reality Composer — Vision Pro distribution (manual).</item>
        <item>Meta Quest Store / App Lab / Quest for Business — Consumer + enterprise channels (manual + API).</item>
        <item>Microsoft Store on HoloLens / Intune — Enterprise distribution (API).</item>
        <item>Niantic Lightship — Real-world AR (geo, semantic). Website: https://lightship.dev</item>
        <item>8thWall (Niantic) — Web AR, no-app-required. SaaS with SDK.</item>
        <item>Snap Lens Studio + Spectacles — AR glasses (Spectacles 5). Platform with SDK.</item>
        <item>Sketchfab / Polycam / Luma AI — 3D asset capture and library. SaaS with API.</item>
        <item>NVIDIA Omniverse / USD — Industrial 3D collaboration. SaaS with API.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Stale facts: market growth rates, install bases, and platform roadmaps change quarterly. Agents quoting README numbers without verification will mislead stakeholders.</item>
        <item>LLM tends to over-recommend Vision Pro for premium use cases; balance with cost and install-base realities (Vision Pro install base remains small in 2026).</item>
        <item>Confusion between "MR" terms — Apple "passthrough", Meta "MR", Microsoft "MR" are not equivalent. Agent must specify which.</item>
        <item>Agents may suggest WebXR as a universal answer; acknowledge platform-specific limits (no Vision Pro WebXR full feature parity, no advanced hand tracking on iOS Safari).</item>
        <item>Don't let agent design specific interactions from this overview alone — it lacks the depth.</item>
        <item>Agents may forget about smart glasses, treating "spatial" = headsets only; Ray-Ban Meta and similar need consideration in 2026.</item>
        <item>Treat as a router: when an agent reaches a decision point, dispatch to the deeper methodology rather than answering inline.</item>
        <item>Agents may underweight ergonomics and battery — flag both as scoping checks.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Start every spatial project with this overview, then immediately go deeper — do not stay at this level for design decisions.</item>
        <item>Pick OpenXR-aligned tooling for forward portability across vendors.</item>
        <item>Validate against actual hardware early — emulators lie about ergonomics, FOV, and tracking quality.</item>
        <item>Match interaction model to platform strengths: hand-eye on Vision Pro, controllers + hands on Quest, hands + voice on HoloLens.</item>
        <item>Cover accessibility (`spatial-accessibility`) from the start — retrofitting is expensive in XR.</item>
        <item>Plan content distribution (App Store, Quest Store, Intune) and revenue/licensing model in scoping, not post-build.</item>
        <item>Beware "spatial computing" hype-claims; ground decisions in measurable user value.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/designing-for-visionos"/>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/"/>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/mixed-reality/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.magicleap.cloud"/>
      <link href="https://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=spatial-computing"/>
      <link href="https://lightship.dev"/>
      <link href="https://ar.snap.com/lens-studio"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
