<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Research Repo Naming — Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes when applying the convention. Each has a detector and a repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>PII in filename: a real name or email leaks via the filename, becomes visible in screenshots, sync logs, and search indexes.</description>
      <detector>regex match for `[A-Z][a-z]+` (capitalised word) at the participant slot OR `@.*\.` (email pattern) anywhere in filename</detector>
      <repair>Stop. Rename via the participant-id map. Rotate the leaked artefact (replace with anonymised copy). If the original was synced to cloud storage, audit history for exposure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Filename collision: two artefacts get the same name (often `notes.md`, `transcript.vtt`) in different folders, breaking flat indexes.</description>
      <detector>scripts/lint produces COLLISION for identical basenames across the tree</detector>
      <repair>Re-name per grammar; the filename should be unique by construction. Add a descriptor segment if needed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Lost language: mixed UK/EN repo, files lack `.&lt;lang&gt;.` suffix; RAG retrieves wrong-language quotes for synthesis.</description>
      <detector>repo has files with `lang == auto-detect-uk` AND files with `lang == auto-detect-en` AND any filename lacks the lang suffix</detector>
      <repair>Run `scripts/extract_metadata_from_transcript` to auto-detect, then rename. Backfill from the body language; if uncertain, escalate to manual.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Synthesis without source citations: `synth/2026-05-themes.md` is created with no frontmatter pointing to the raw files. Cannot audit which quotes drove the theme.</description>
      <detector>file in `synth/` with frontmatter missing `sources: [...]` OR sources contain filenames not in manifest</detector>
      <repair>Block publication of the synthesis. Re-author with explicit source list. Synthesis is only credible when its sources are auditable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Drifting study-type tags: researcher uses `int` for some interviews and `interview` or `conversation` for others.</description>
      <detector>manifest.type_counts contains any key not in the closed enum</detector>
      <repair>Mass-rename to the canonical tag. Update lint script to fail-closed when a non-enum type appears.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="low">
      <description>Participant renumbering: P001 becomes P008 after a "cleanup" pass; published synthesis citations break.</description>
      <detector>participants/map.json has entries where original_id != current_id AND any synth/ file references original_id</detector>
      <repair>Revert. Renumbering after publication is forbidden by r3 enforcement. New participants get the next free P###.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>
      Filenames are sometimes constructed by an LLM tagger (the researcher pastes a
      transcript and asks for a filename). The tagger MUST refuse to emit a filename
      that contains real names found in the body, even if asked. Anonymisation is
      not optional and is the user's downstream legal exposure.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>
      Every rename and re-numbering operation runs through `scripts/lint-research-repo.py`
      before commit. The lint script is the human's external memory; the researcher
      reviews any violation rather than auto-fix.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
