<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-usage-guide" title="Using the Cart Example as a Few-Shot Reference">
  <summary>How to use this worked example when generating or reviewing specs, including key reusable patterns and AI-agent failure modes specific to this example.</summary>

  <section title="Reusable Patterns">
    <list>
      <item>FR → US traceability table: every FR row has a Traces To column pointing to US-X</item>
      <item>NFR measurement format: requirement + target + measurement method + validation load test</item>
      <item>AC Given/When/Then with specific values: "$25.00" not "valid price", "2 days later" not "some time"</item>
      <item>Out of Scope with "When" column: Phase 2 / Phase 3 / v2.0 / Not planned</item>
      <item>AC coverage matrix with explicit unchecked items as documented risks</item>
      <item>Open Questions as a forcing function — minimum 3 per complex feature</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Prompt Patterns">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Few-shot generation prompt: "Use the following completed spec as a reference for structure and quality. Reference spec: [paste content/01-full-spec.xml]. Now write a spec for: [new feature name]. Problem: [problem statement]. User types: [list]. Key constraints: [list]. Follow the same section structure. Replace all domain-specific content. NFRs must use [MEASURE_NEEDED] where targets are unknown."</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Gap analysis prompt: "Compare this draft spec against the e-commerce cart example. Identify: (1) sections present in example but missing from draft, (2) AC scenarios (error, edge case, persistence) missing from draft, (3) traceability gaps (FR with no AC, US with no FR). Output: gap list only."</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent copies story-point estimates (5 pts, 3 pts) from this example into new specs.</description>
      <reason>SDD replaces story points with token estimates. Explicitly instruct agents to remove story points and replace with token estimates per the 100k rule.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent treats the TypeScript interface in the Appendix as the canonical data model.</description>
      <reason>The interface is labeled preliminary. Without this label, agents use it in design.md as approved, bypassing the architectural decision process.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent copies NFR targets (200ms p95, 50k concurrent) verbatim into new specs.</description>
      <reason>These values have no measurement source. Add a required [SOURCE] tag next to each NFR target when adapting to force replacement with real measurements.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent expands personas (Busy Parent Sarah, Deal Hunter Mike) with hallucinated pain points.</description>
      <reason>Persona pain points must come from real user research. Agents generate plausible-sounding but fabricated persona context. Provide real research or use placeholder text explicitly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/check-coverage.sh">Extract all unchecked AC coverage items from a spec file</reference>
</text>
