<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Jira Workflow Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Jira Workflow Management. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="workflow-as-yaml-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Workflow definitions MUST live as version-controlled YAML in the project repo; UI-only edits forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian — Jira workflow as code">UI-only workflow edits drift between projects and break on cloud migrations; versioned YAML is reviewable and re-applicable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="transition-condition-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every workflow transition MUST declare its conditions (role / status / custom-field) and validators. Implicit 'open' transitions forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian — Workflow conditions docs">Implicit transitions allow anyone to change status; conditions enforce business rules at the workflow boundary.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="jql-saved-not-ad-hoc" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recurring queries MUST be saved as named JQL filters, not pasted into search each time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian — JQL best practices">Ad-hoc JQL drifts: contributors recreate near-duplicates with subtle bugs. Saved filters become a documented inventory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="automation-throttled" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Jira automation rules MUST declare rate limits and rule-execution scope (project / global) to prevent recursion loops.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian — Automation pitfalls docs">Unscoped automation has caused mass-update incidents (10k issues in 10 minutes); throttling contains blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="token-scope-minimal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>API tokens used by agents MUST scope to read:jira-work + write:jira-work minimum. Admin tokens forbidden in automation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atlassian — API token security">Admin tokens expose project administration; minimum-scope tokens contain blast radius on leak.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Jira Workflow Management fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Jira Workflow Management outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
