<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-workflow-design" title="Jira Workflow Design">
  <summary>Rules for configuring Jira issue types, workflow states/transitions, and board setup to create maintainable, scalable project structures.</summary>

  <section title="Issue Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use one workflow scheme per issue type before creating project-scoped variants.</statement>
      <rationale>Workflow schemes are shared across projects; a per-project variant multiplies maintenance cost and risks breaking sibling projects when schemes are edited.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Standard issue types and their required fields:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Epic — Summary, Description, Start/End Date; groups related Stories</item>
      <item>Story — Story Points, Acceptance Criteria; user-facing functionality</item>
      <item>Task — Estimate, Component; technical work with no user story framing</item>
      <item>Bug — Severity, Steps to Reproduce; defect with reproduction path</item>
      <item>Sub-task — linked to parent; used only when a Story exceeds 1-day granularity</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow States">
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit workflow statuses to 5-7 maximum per issue type.</statement>
      <rationale>More statuses increase cognitive load and transition errors without improving visibility. Reflect actual team process, not an ideal one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
statuses:
  - name: "To Do"
    category: "To Do"
  - name: "In Progress"
    category: "In Progress"
  - name: "Code Review"
    category: "In Progress"
  - name: "QA Testing"
    category: "In Progress"
  - name: "Done"
    category: "Done"

transitions:
  - from: "To Do"
    to: "In Progress"
    trigger: "Start Work"
  - from: "In Progress"
    to: "Code Review"
    trigger: "Submit for Review"
    condition: "Branch linked"
  - from: "Code Review"
    to: "QA Testing"
    trigger: "Approve"
  - from: "QA Testing"
    to: "Done"
    trigger: "Pass QA"
]]></code>
      <note>Transitions use validators (e.g., "Branch linked") to enforce process gates without extra communication overhead.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add required-field validators on transitions, not on issue creation.</statement>
      <rationale>Requiring fields at creation time increases friction for bulk imports and bot-driven flows. Gate fields at the transition where they become meaningful (e.g., Code Reviewer at "Submit for Review").</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Board Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set WIP limits on Kanban columns; use swimlanes to group by epic or priority on Scrum boards.</statement>
      <rationale>WIP limits make overload visible. Swimlanes reduce context switching by grouping related work during daily standups.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Scrum board: backlog + active sprint + burndown chart + velocity chart</item>
      <item>Kanban board: WIP limits per column + cumulative flow diagram + cycle time tracking</item>
      <item>Quick filters: "My Issues", "Blocked", "No Assignee" — accessible in one click</item>
      <item>Backlog grooming target: keep under 2 sprints worth of refined stories</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Share custom fields via Global context; avoid project-scoped contexts where possible.</statement>
      <rationale>Project-scoped custom fields compound across projects and hit Jira's 200-field issue-view cap, slowing the entire site for all users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/custom-fields.yaml">Custom field definitions with type and screen placement</reference>
  </section>
</text>
