<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Risk Threshold Policy — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every risk threshold policy must satisfy. The rules exist so the policy can be read at 11pm and produce the right routing decision without judgement calls.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-explicit-severity-bands" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The policy MUST partition the severity scale into 3-5 explicit bands (e.g. green ≤6, amber 7-15, red 16-25). Continuous-score "use judgement" routing is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBOK 7 risk governance; APM Body of Knowledge">Bands convert continuous scores into discrete escalation decisions. A PM looking at "score 14" should see "amber band → notify sponsor by EOD Friday" without re-evaluating. The bands are the policy's primary user interface.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-named-target-per-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each band routes to a NAMED individual (role + person), not a group inbox or committee. "Notify the steering committee" without a named chair is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI clarity; field experience">Named targets are accountable; groups diffuse. The named target may delegate to a group, but the policy's contract is with the person. If the named person is unavailable, the policy specifies a fallback (deputy) by name.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-sla-per-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each band has an explicit SLA: a maximum time from "PM identifies the risk crossed the threshold" to "named target receives the escalation". Red ≤2h, amber ≤24h, green = weekly digest. Bands without SLA are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Incident-management best practice; APM escalation guidance">SLAs convert "I'll escalate when I get to it" into a binding promise. The SLA is what makes the policy a contract; sponsors who agree to be the named target for red also agree to be reachable within the SLA.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-de-escalation-criteria" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each band defines explicit de-escalation criteria: what must change for the risk to move down. Without criteria, risks ratchet upward and never close.</statement>
      <rationale source="ITIL incident lifecycle; project-management postmortem analysis">A risk register without de-escalation rules becomes a museum of past worries. The criteria force the PM to define what good looks like — mitigations applied, probability reduced, sponsor briefed, etc. — and the named target signs off on the descent.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-co-signed-policy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The policy is co-signed by sponsor + delivery lead + PMO (or equivalent governance) at engagement kickoff. Refresh required at every milestone (e.g. phase gate) OR every 12 weeks, whichever first.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI standards; field experience with mid-project escalation disputes">When a red risk arrives, the sponsor must not be able to claim they did not know they were the escalation target. Co-signature pre-commits the relationship. Periodic refresh keeps the policy in sync with team changes.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical band table">
    <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
green  (1-6):   PM logs in risk register; weekly digest to delivery lead; no real-time notification
amber  (7-15):  PM pings delivery lead within 24h; delivery lead briefs sponsor at next standup
red    (16-20): PM emails sponsor within 4h with mitigation proposal; sponsor acknowledges within 24h
black  (21-25): PM phone calls sponsor within 2h; emergency steering call within 24h; PMO informed
    ]]></code>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Policy in action">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tuesday 14:30 — PM scores newly-discovered vendor-delay risk at 4×4=16 (red).
Tuesday 14:35 — PM pulls policy: red → email sponsor within 4h with mitigation proposal.
Tuesday 16:10 — Email sent with: risk, mitigation A/B, recommendation, decision deadline Friday.
Tuesday 17:42 — Sponsor acknowledges within SLA.
Friday 11:00 — Decision: option B. Risk re-scored at 3×3=9 (amber). De-escalation criteria met
                (signed contract with backup vendor). Risk closed at next standup.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r5. PM did not invent the routing; the policy did.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="No policy, all-or-nothing escalation">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
PM identifies red risk Monday morning.
PM hesitates because "the sponsor is in a board meeting all day".
PM raises in steering committee Thursday.
Sponsor: "Why didn't you tell me sooner?" — relationship damaged.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r3 violation (no SLA), r2 violation (no named target with reachability commitment). The fault is structural, not personal.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
