<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="work-breakdown-structure">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Deliverable-oriented hierarchical decomposition of project scope into work packages with noun-based nodes, 100% rule, and Dictionary entries for acceptance criteria, ownership, and dependencies.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>wbs</tag>
      <tag>scope</tag>
      <tag>project-planning</tag>
      <tag>deliverables</tag>
      <tag>estimation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Work Breakdown Structure</title>
    <summary>A deliverable-oriented hierarchical decomposition of project scope into work packages — noun-based nodes (outputs), not verbs (activities). Each level represents 100% of its parent (100% rule). Leaf nodes (work packages) satisfy the 8-80 hour rule and carry a Dictionary entry with acceptance criteria, owner, and dependencies. The WBS is the scope baseline; schedule and cost are derived from it, not contained in it.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without a WBS, scope is ambiguous: team members build different things, estimates are guesses, and hidden dependencies surface too late. The deliverable orientation (nouns not verbs) keeps the structure stable when implementation changes. The 100% rule forces completeness — it eliminates forgotten work packages before scheduling or costing begins.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Translating an approved scope statement or SOW into an estimable, assignable work-package tree before scheduling and costing</item>
        <item>Bidding on fixed-scope work requiring bottom-up estimation</item>
        <item>Validating the 100% rule on a hand-drafted plan: diff WBS against scope statement</item>
        <item>Re-baselining after a change request — mutate only the affected branch</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure Scrum or Kanban teams where the product backlog is the decomposition — an extra WBS creates two sources of truth</item>
        <item>Discovery or research projects where less than 30% of scope is known — the WBS below level 2 will be fabricated</item>
        <item>Solo work on a feature under 2 weeks — a checklist is simpler</item>
        <item>Projects with emergent deliverables (innovation, R&amp;D, platform exploration) — use rolling-wave planning instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="deliverable-orientation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every WBS node must be a noun phrase describing an output — never a verb phrase describing an activity.</statement>
        <rationale>Deliverable names survive implementation changes; activity names do not. A WBS structured around activities must be rewritten every time the approach changes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Activity-based — breaks when technology or approach changes.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[2.1 Design user authentication
2.2 Build user authentication
2.3 Test user authentication]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Deliverable-based — stable across implementation changes.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[2.1 User Authentication Module
    2.1.1 Registration System
    2.1.2 Login / Logout
    2.1.3 Password Reset]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="100-percent-rule">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every parent node must represent exactly 100% of the scope in its children — no gaps, no overlaps. Verify by asking: "If all children are complete, is the parent complete?"</statement>
        <rationale>Gaps produce forgotten work packages that surface during execution. Overlaps produce double-counted effort and budget disputes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include these overhead branches; if any are missing, the WBS is incomplete: Project Management, QA, Deployment, Documentation, Training, Transition.</statement>
        <rationale>Overhead is 15-25% of real project effort. Agents and manual drafters systematically omit it, creating a structural budget gap that cannot be recovered during execution.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="work-package-sizing">
      <rule>
        <statement>Leaf nodes must have effort estimates between 8 and 80 hours. Leaves outside this range must be split (too large) or merged (too small).</statement>
        <rationale>Below 8 hours, tracking overhead exceeds value. Above 80 hours, the estimate is a guess and internal dependencies are invisible. Calibrate bounds to match your tracking unit.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Stop decomposing when the 8/80 rule is satisfied. Maximum 4 levels for human readability; deeper decomposition belongs in the Dictionary, not the tree.</statement>
        <rationale>Vanity depth gives a false sense of precision without improving schedule or cost predictability. Level 5+ trees are unmaintainable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="id-stability">
      <rule>
        <statement>WBS IDs are append-only. Once assigned, a numeric ID never changes or is reused, even if the node is deleted or scope is reduced.</statement>
        <rationale>Change requests, risk entries, and task files reference WBS IDs. Renumbering breaks traceability across the entire project record.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="wbs-dictionary">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every leaf work package must have a Dictionary entry with all of these fields: ID, Name, Description (what is included AND explicitly excluded), Deliverable (the tangible output), Acceptance Criteria (observable and testable), Owner (one accountable person or named team), Effort Estimate (hours, 8-80), Dependencies (predecessor WBS IDs).</statement>
        <rationale>Missing acceptance criteria make sign-off subjective. Missing exclusions cause scope creep. Missing ownership causes handoff gaps. A WBS tree without a Dictionary is an outline, not a scope baseline.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>MVP launch WBS with PM branch and balanced depth.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[MVP Launch
1.0 Project Management
    1.1 Planning Documentation
    1.2 Status Reporting
    1.3 Risk Management
2.0 Core Features
    2.1 User Authentication
    2.2 Main Dashboard
    2.3 Core Workflow
3.0 Quality
    3.1 Test Suite
    3.2 Bug Fix Cycle
4.0 Deployment
    4.1 Production Deploy
    4.2 Monitoring Setup
5.0 Transition
    5.1 Handover Documentation
    5.2 Support Handover]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Dictionary entry for a single leaf work package.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[## WBS 2.1.1 — Interview 10 Users

| Field               | Value                                                            |
|---------------------|------------------------------------------------------------------|
| Parent              | 2.1 User Research                                                |
| Description         | 30-min structured interviews; excludes survey analysis           |
| Deliverable         | Interview transcripts + synthesis report                         |
| Acceptance Criteria | 10 interviews completed; notes documented and reviewed           |
| Owner               | UX Researcher                                                    |
| Effort Estimate     | 20 hours                                                         |
| Dependencies        | 2.1.0 Interview guide approved                                   |]]></code>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>WBS tree without a Dictionary — just numbered labels.</description>
        <reason>Numbered labels without definitions leave ownership, acceptance criteria, and scope boundaries undefined. The PM interprets everything; the team guesses.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Dates or assignees in the WBS tree structure.</description>
        <reason>The WBS answers "what"; the schedule answers "when"; the RACI answers "who". Mixing them forces WBS changes every time the schedule shifts.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Two-phase: (1) decomposition agent reads the scope statement + glossary and emits a tree YAML with leaves at work-package granularity (8-80h rule); (2) WBS-dictionary agent expands each leaf into a card (description, AC, owner, estimate, deps, deliverable). Human review between phases is mandatory — never let phase 2 run on an unvalidated tree. Re-runs only mutate the diff branch.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>wbs-decomposer (define inline) — input: scope.md + glossary.yaml; output: wbs.yaml tree validated against 100% rule.</item>
        <item>wbs-dictionary-writer (define inline) — input: wbs.yaml leaf; output: wbs-dict-ID.md card.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor — once a leaf becomes a TASK, drives implementation through quality gates.</item>
        <item>brainstorm — for the first level-1 decomposition when phase boundaries are not obvious.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <p>Decompose &lt;project&gt; into a noun-based deliverable tree.</p>
      <p>Rules:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Leaves obey the 8-80 hour rule.</item>
        <item>Each level represents 100% of its parent (no gaps, no overlap).</item>
        <item>Include "1.0 Project Management" as the first branch.</item>
        <item>Use stable IDs (1, 1.1, 1.1.1 …); re-runs MUST keep existing IDs and only append.</item>
        <item>Do NOT include dates, durations, or assignees — those are schedule/resource artefacts.</item>
        <item>If a deliverable is not in &lt;scope.md&gt;, do not invent it; emit "OUT_OF_SCOPE" instead.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Output: YAML</p>
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[items:
  - id: "1"
    name: "Project Management"
    children: [...]]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — Render WBS as a tree diagram (mindmap or flowchart). https://github.com/mermaid-js/mermaid-cli</item>
        <item>graphviz (dot) — Render WBS as a hierarchical diagram. https://graphviz.org/</item>
        <item>yq — Validate / mutate WBS YAML in CI. https://github.com/mikefarah/yq</item>
        <item>xmlstarlet — Edit WBS in PMI-standard WBS-XML format. http://xmlstar.sourceforge.net/</item>
        <item>pandoc — WBS markdown → DOCX / PDF for sponsor packs. https://pandoc.org/</item>
        <item>gh / jira-cli — Sync WBS leaves into issues / epics. https://cli.github.com/</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <list>
        <item>MS Project / Project for the Web (SaaS) — Native WBS support, dictionary as task notes. Graph API + MPP/XML import. Agent-friendly.</item>
        <item>Smartsheet (SaaS) — WBS as hierarchical sheet. REST API. Agent-friendly.</item>
        <item>Asana / ClickUp / Monday (SaaS) — Tasks + subtasks ≈ WBS branches. REST API. Agent-friendly.</item>
        <item>MindMeister / Whimsical (SaaS) — WBS as mindmap, export OPML. REST + export. Partial agent support.</item>
        <item>WBS Schedule Pro (Desktop) — Industry-standard WBS app, MPP I/O. No agent support due to file format.</item>
        <item>Lucidspark / Miro (SaaS) — Collaborative WBS workshops. REST API. Agent-friendly.</item>
        <item>Jira (Advanced Roadmaps / Plans) (SaaS) — Initiative → epic → story ≈ WBS levels 1-3. REST + JQL. Agent-friendly.</item>
        <item>Notion / Confluence (SaaS) — WBS dictionary cards live here. REST API. Agent-friendly.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Lock the scope baseline before decomposing; a moving scope makes WBS regeneration meaningless.</item>
        <item>Always include the "Project Management" branch (charter, status, risk, change control) — usually 8-15% of total effort.</item>
        <item>Numbering: 1, 1.1, 1.1.1; never go past four levels for human readability — go deeper only in the dictionary.</item>
        <item>Pair WBS with the responsibility matrix (RACI) so each leaf has exactly one A.</item>
        <item>Tag leaves with development-approach (predictive vs agile) — drives downstream estimation method.</item>
        <item>Keep WBS dictionary cards in version control alongside the tree; treat as code, review via PR.</item>
        <item>Do not put dates in the WBS — schedule lives in the schedule artefact; mixing them creates churn.</item>
        <item>Re-baseline triggers: scope change, sponsor change, &gt; 10% effort variance per branch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs love verbs ("Design dashboard"); enforce noun phrasing in the prompt and post-validate via regex (^[A-Z][a-z]+ [A-Z]? is a smell).</item>
        <item>Agents skip the 100% rule because it sounds tautological; require explicit weight_pct per child and validate sum.</item>
        <item>ID stability across regenerations is broken by default; pass the previous WBS in context and instruct "keep IDs, append only".</item>
        <item>Agents inflate level depth on confident topics and under-decompose on unfamiliar ones; cap depth at 4 and require justification for any sibling with more than 5 items.</item>
        <item>Cross-cutting work (security, documentation) gets duplicated across branches; name a single owning branch and reference from others.</item>
        <item>Agents emit fake estimates ("4 hours") to satisfy the 8-80 rule; force them to mark effort_hours: TBD when unknown.</item>
        <item>For very large projects (with more than 200 leaves), an LLM context window cannot hold the full tree; decompose level-by-level with separate calls and stitch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/wbs-template.md" purpose="Hierarchical WBS outline with PM + all major branches"/>
      <template path="templates/wbs-dict-entry.md" purpose="Single work-package Dictionary card"/>
      <template path="templates/wbs-validate.py" purpose="Validator: weight_pct 100% rule + 8-80h leaf rule against wbs.yaml"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/work-breakdown-structures">PMI — Practice Standard for Work Breakdown Structures (3rd ed.)</link>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/pmbok">PMI — A Guide to the PMBOK 7th Edition, Planning Performance Domain</link>
      <link href="https://www.acq.osd.mil/asda/dpc/cp/policy/mil-std-881.html">DoD MIL-STD-881F — WBS for defense materiel items (industry reference)</link>
      <link href="https://www.criticaltools.com/wbs-schedule-pro-tutorials.html">WBS Schedule Pro tutorials</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
