<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enforce WIP limits as a first-class column setting with a hard block (Jira Premium / Linear Cycles); soft warnings are ignored under pressure.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WIP limits without enforcement become aspirational. Teams blow past them under pressure without visible feedback; hard blocks force the conversation about priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Throughput + 85th-percentile cycle time beats velocity for forecasting; use Monte Carlo simulation on these metrics for date predictions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Velocity is a Scrum artifact dependent on sprint length and planning accuracy. Kanban teams deliver on a sliding window; cycle-time percentiles are more stable and actionable for forecasting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the PI Planning agenda exactly the day before; teams that "tweak" it lose 30+ minutes to confusion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">PI Planning thrives on predictability. Late agenda changes ripple through breakout groups and reduce decision quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track I&amp;A actions in the same backlog as features with owners and due dates; otherwise they get prioritized to zero and re-surface every PI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Improvements without tracking disappear into noise. Make them first-class work items.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Kanban metrics (cycle time, throughput) need ≥6 weeks of clean data before they are trustworthy for forecasting.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Short windows capture noise (one slow item, holiday week). Six-week minimum smooths anomalies and reveals true process stability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
