<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-kanban-cadences" title="Kanban Cadences: Five Recurring Events">
  <summary>The five Kanban cadences that replace Scrum sprint ceremonies for continuous-flow teams, with format, participants, and outputs for each.</summary>

  <section title="Daily Standup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Walk the board right-to-left during the daily standup — start with items nearest Done and work backward — to focus attention on completing work over starting new work.</statement>
      <rationale>Left-to-right (backlog-first) standups focus on what people are starting; right-to-left surfaces what is close to completion and what is blocked, which is the more actionable signal for flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Focus: blocked items (highest priority), items close to completion, WIP vs limit, any capacity to pull new work.</item>
      <item>Duration: 15 minutes maximum.</item>
      <item>Key metrics reviewed: current WIP count vs limits, active blockers, aging items.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Replenishment Meeting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run replenishment with the PO and tech lead only; opening it to all interested parties turns a 30-minute meeting into 90 minutes of negotiation.</statement>
      <rationale>Replenishment is a prioritization decision, not a discovery session. Broad attendance creates stakeholder pressure that overrides technical capacity signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Frequency: weekly.</item>
      <item>Duration: 30 minutes.</item>
      <item>Participants: Product Owner (required), tech lead (required), stakeholders (optional observer).</item>
      <item>Output: Ready queue filled to capacity, priorities confirmed, team capacity considered.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Service Delivery Review">
    <rule>
      <statement>Drive every service delivery review with metrics — throughput, cycle time, lead time, WIP vs limits, SLA performance — and produce at least one concrete policy change or experiment as output.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a policy-change output, the service delivery review devolves into status theater. The meeting exists to change how the team works, not to report how it worked.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Frequency: weekly.</item>
      <item>Duration: 30 minutes.</item>
      <item>Participants: team (required), stakeholders (required), customers (optional).</item>
      <item>Agenda: 10 min metrics, 10 min trends, 10 min improvement discussion.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Retrospective and Strategy Review">
    <list>
      <item>Retrospective: bi-weekly, 60 min. Focus: process policies, WIP limit effectiveness, flow efficiency, blocker patterns. Output: policy changes documented, WIP limit adjustments, experiments defined.</item>
      <item>Strategy review: monthly, 60 min. Focus: align work with business goals, review roadmap fit, long-term policy decisions.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="WIP Limits">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce WIP limits as a hard column setting (Jira Premium column limit, Linear cycle WIP); soft warnings get ignored under pressure.</statement>
      <rationale>Soft WIP warnings are bypassed during busy periods — exactly when WIP limits matter most. Hard blocks require an explicit exception that surfaces the conversation about trade-offs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/kanban-metrics.md">Weekly service-delivery review dashboard template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/cycle-stats.py">Throughput and cycle-time percentile computation from issue JSONL</reference>
</text>
