<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-scaled-agile" title="SAFe Events: PI Planning, Scrum-of-Scrums, PO Sync, Inspect-and-Adapt">
  <summary>Structure and rules for the four SAFe program-level events used in multi-team agile programs.</summary>

  <section title="PI Planning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the PI Planning agenda exactly; teams that improvise the structure lose 30 minutes per ceremony to confusion and shortchange team breakout time.</statement>
      <rationale>PI Planning is the highest-value SAFe ceremony per hour. Agenda deviations compound across all teams simultaneously, creating schedule pressure that degrades plan quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-build the program board the day before remote PI Planning; live-building the board during the ceremony kills momentum.</statement>
      <rationale>Remote PI Planning with real-time board construction causes technical delays that disrupt the flow and reduce breakout time in which teams actually plan.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Frequency: every 8-12 weeks (typically 10-week PIs).</item>
      <item>Duration: 2 days.</item>
      <item>Day 1: business context (30 min), product vision (30 min), architecture vision (30 min), planning context (30 min), team breakouts (4 hrs), draft plan review (1 hr).</item>
      <item>Day 2: planning adjustments (1 hr), team breakouts (2 hrs), final plan review (2 hrs), confidence vote (15 min), planning retrospective (30 min).</item>
      <item>Outputs: committed PI objectives per team, program board with dependencies, identified risks, confidence vote recorded.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Scrum-of-Scrums">
    <rule>
      <statement>Focus Scrum-of-Scrums on cross-team dependency resolution, not status reporting; teams that turn it into a round-robin get no value from it.</statement>
      <rationale>Status reporting belongs in individual team standups. Scrum-of-Scrums is the only forum specifically for inter-team blockers and integration issues — use it exclusively for that.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Frequency: daily or every other day.</item>
      <item>Duration: 15 minutes.</item>
      <item>Participants: one Scrum Master per team, Release Train Engineer as facilitator.</item>
      <item>Questions: what did your team accomplish since last, what will they do before next, what impediments are they facing, what dependencies exist with other teams.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="PO Sync">
    <list>
      <item>Frequency: weekly.</item>
      <item>Duration: 30 minutes.</item>
      <item>Participants: all Product Owners, Product Manager as facilitator.</item>
      <item>Agenda: feature priorities (10 min), dependency coordination (10 min), roadmap updates (5 min), impediments (5 min).</item>
      <item>Output: aligned priorities across teams, dependencies managed, roadmap updates communicated.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Inspect and Adapt">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track Inspect-and-Adapt action items in the same program backlog as features; items tracked separately get prioritized to zero and disappear.</statement>
      <rationale>I&amp;A actions without formal backlog entries have no owner or sprint assignment. They exist only in the retro notes, which no one reads between PIs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Frequency: end of each PI.</item>
      <item>Duration: 3 hours.</item>
      <item>Agenda: PI system demo (45 min), quantitative measurement review (30 min), retrospective workshop (90 min), action planning (15 min).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="ScrumBan Hybrid">
    <p>ScrumBan combines sprint planning for steering (from Scrum) with WIP limits and continuous flow (from Kanban). Timeboxing becomes flexible; commitment is to WIP capacity, not sprint content. Metrics: cycle time plus velocity reported together.</p>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/kanban-metrics.md">Kanban metrics dashboard and PI Planning board scaffold</reference>
  <reference path="templates/cycle-stats.py">Throughput and cycle-time stats for flow-based forecasting</reference>
</text>
