<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>WIP limits without leadership backing become aspirational; teams blow past them under pressure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without visible enforcement and leadership support for pushing back on demand, WIP limits are ignored.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Service-delivery review devolves into status theater unless metrics drive concrete policy changes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SDR without decisions becomes a data dump. Tie every metric to an action (WIP adjustment, priority re-rank, process change).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>PI Planning quality drops sharply when run remote-only with poor tooling (Miro lag, audio chaos).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PI Planning depends on real-time cross-team problem-solving. Remote logistics must match in-person (clear tool, low latency, breakout rooms).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Scrum-of-Scrums turns into a status round-robin instead of a dependency-resolution forum.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SoS without focused agenda becomes theater. Set rule: only discuss cross-team dependencies and escalations; status updates happen in team standups.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents trained on Scrum default to sprint-thinking; explicitly tell them "this team uses Kanban, no sprints, WIP-limited."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLM training data skews Scrum-heavy. Without explicit constraint, agents suggest sprint boundaries and velocity tracking.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Cycle-time math: define "started" precisely (entered "In Progress" vs. assignee set). LLMs guess inconsistently.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Ambiguous definition leads to inconsistent calculations. Pin the definition in the system prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>SAFe terminology overlap (PI vs. Iteration, Feature vs. Story) — pin definitions in the system prompt or get garbage outputs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SAFe reuses Scrum terms with slightly different meanings. Agents hallucinate without explicit vocabulary.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>An agent generating retro themes from comments often surfaces venting, not actionable signal — filter for verbs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Comments capture emotion. Themes need to be actionable improvement statements with owners and due dates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidence-vote scores look like data but are social signals; do not feed raw to forecasting models.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confidence votes reflect team optimism at PI Planning; they are not predictive of actual delivery. Use historical cycle-time data instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Time-zone math for distributed PI Planning: pass explicit IANA TZ strings, never "PST" / "EST".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Daylight saving time rules vary. Agents miscount hours without explicit timezone.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
