<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="benefits-realization">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Identify, quantify, assign ownership for, and track business value delivered post-launch via Benefits Register with metrics, baselines, targets, and named owners accountable post-delivery.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>benefits</tag>
      <tag>roi</tag>
      <tag>outcomes</tag>
      <tag>measurement</tag>
      <tag>attribution</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>benefits</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Benefits Realization</title>

    <summary>Identify, quantify, assign ownership for, and track the business value that a project is expected to deliver after go-live. A Benefits Register stores each benefit with metric, baseline (frozen before launch), target, owner, and source system. The rule: every benefit must have a quantified target and a named owner before project approval — "soft benefits" without a metric do not count.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Projects routinely complete on time and on budget while delivering zero measurable business value. The gap is that outputs (a CRM system) do not automatically become outcomes (sales team adoption) or benefits (20% more deals closed). Benefits realization closes this loop by making post-delivery measurement a first-class project artefact, accountable to a business owner who survives project close.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Business case approval requiring quantified ROI and a tracking plan.</item>
        <item>Post-launch benefits review (3, 6, 12 months) across a project portfolio.</item>
        <item>Investment committee asking "did the last N projects pay back?"</item>
        <item>Programs spanning years where outputs precede outcomes by 6-18 months.</item>
        <item>PMO maturity step: adopting outcome-based metrics over output-based.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-revenue startup pre-PMF — benefits are speculative; track learning milestones instead.</item>
        <item>Compliance-driven projects where the benefit is "stay legal" (binary, not quantifiable).</item>
        <item>Internal tooling with weak baseline data (no measurable "before" state).</item>
        <item>Crisis incident response — the benefit is "stopped bleeding", not a trackable KPI.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="benefits-framework">
      <title>Benefits Realization Framework</title>

      <section name="output-outcome-benefit">
        <title>Output vs Outcome vs Benefit</title>
        <list>
          <item>Output — what the project delivers (a new CRM system).</item>
          <item>Outcome — behavioral change that the output enables (sales team uses the CRM daily).</item>
          <item>Benefit — measurable value from the outcome (20% more deals closed per quarter).</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Every benefit must have a quantified target and a named owner before project approval.</statement>
          <rationale>"Soft benefits" without a metric cannot be tracked or disputed. Requiring quantification at approval time forces honest benefit claims and creates accountability before work begins.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="six-step-process">
        <title>Six-Step Process</title>
        <list>
          <item>Step 1 — Identify: answer "why are we doing this?" and "how will success be measured?" for each stakeholder group.</item>
          <item>Step 2 — Quantify: for each benefit, define metric, baseline value (pre-project), target value, and expected realization date.</item>
          <item>Step 3 — Assign Owner: benefit owner is a business stakeholder, NOT the project manager; PM hands off at go-live.</item>
          <item>Step 4 — Plan: document prerequisites, enablers (training, process changes, adoption activities), measurement method, and data source.</item>
          <item>Step 5 — Track: pull actual values from source systems post-launch; compare to target; compute % realized.</item>
          <item>Step 6 — Report: executive-ready status with trend, barriers, recommendations; escalate at-risk benefits to sponsor.</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Freeze baseline values in writing with date and source query before launch — agents can re-pull but not redefine.</statement>
          <rationale>A baseline that can be redefined post-hoc makes the benefit un-measurable. Lock the T-0 values in the register; subsequent measurements are compared against them.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="attribution">
        <title>Attribution</title>
        <rule>
          <statement>Pre-register a control cohort or comparator before launch for any benefit where attribution is contested.</statement>
          <rationale>Post-hoc attribution ("revenue grew, but was it the project or seasonality?") is unresolvable without a pre-planned counterfactual. Difference-in-differences requires a control group defined before intervention.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Lead indicators: adoption rate, NPS — track monthly; early signal of benefit trajectory.</item>
          <item>Lag indicators: revenue, cost reduction — track quarterly; realize 6-18 months post-launch.</item>
          <item>Cap claimable benefits at portfolio level to prevent double-counting across projects.</item>
          <item>Sunset the benefits register at 24 months unless extended — long tails distort portfolio metrics.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="benefits-antipatterns">
      <title>Benefits Realization Antipatterns and Agent Gotchas</title>

      <section name="structural-antipatterns">
        <title>Structural Antipatterns</title>
        <antipattern>
          <description>PM owns benefits after go-live instead of business stakeholder.</description>
          <reason>PMs move to the next project. Benefits that outlast the PM's tenure need a business owner who is accountable for adoption and process change — the two primary enablers of realization.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Benefits register ignored after project closes ("fire and forget").</description>
          <reason>Most benefits realize 6-18 months post-launch. A register reviewed only at go-live misses the window where corrective action (change management, re-training) can still save the benefit.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Benefits overstated in the business case to secure project approval.</description>
          <reason>Inflated benefits create a credibility trap: if realized benefits are 40% of promised, the next project from the same team faces funding skepticism regardless of merit.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Double-counting the same revenue lift across two projects in the same portfolio.</description>
          <reason>Each claimed benefit inflates the portfolio ROI. Cap total claimable benefit at portfolio level and require attribution sign-off from the CFO or PMO for any benefit over a materiality threshold.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>

      <section name="agent-gotchas">
        <title>Agent Gotchas</title>
        <rule>
          <statement>Require the agent to fail closed when baseline data is missing — never allow "industry average" substitution.</statement>
          <rationale>Agents fabricate baselines from benchmarks when the actual pre-launch value is absent. A fabricated baseline makes the benefit permanently unmeasurable; better to block the benefit claim and demand the real data.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Counterfactual analysis: require pre-registered DiD/synthetic control plan; do not let the agent pick a model post-hoc (p-hacking).</item>
          <item>Adoption metrics from telemetry can be inflated by bots; segment human vs automated traffic before computing realization %.</item>
          <item>ROI calculations: agents ignore time-value-of-money; require NPV, not raw nominal sum.</item>
          <item>Benefit ownership decays silently when owners leave; build a cron check that the owner's email still resolves to an active employee.</item>
          <item>Currency and inflation: agents must use the same deflator for baseline and actual measurements.</item>
          <item>"AI productivity gain" is the most over-claimed benefit category; require independent validation and a documented measurement method.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <title>Agentic Workflow and Integration</title>
      <p>A benefits-cataloger subagent extracts benefit statements from business cases, normalizes them into a Benefits Register with metric, baseline, target, owner, and measurement method. A baseline-collector pulls the actual baseline values from source systems before launch. A measurement-runner queries the same sources monthly post-launch, computes % realized vs target, and produces variance analysis. A counterfactual agent estimates attribution (intervention vs market). PM/PO reviews; sponsor signs.</p>

      <section name="recommended-subagents">
        <title>Recommended Subagents</title>
        <list>
          <item>benefits-cataloger — turns prose business cases into structured Benefits Register.</item>
          <item>baseline-collector — pulls T-0 metric values from analytics/CRM/ERP, freezes them.</item>
          <item>measurement-runner — periodic pulls vs target, drift detection.</item>
          <item>counterfactual-analyzer — applies diff-in-diff or synthetic control for attribution.</item>
          <item>benefits-reporter — exec-ready report with status, trend, recommendations.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="cli-tools">
        <title>CLI Tools</title>
        <list>
          <item>dbt — Transform analytics data into benefit metric tables (https://docs.getdbt.com).</item>
          <item>metabase-cli (community) — Pull dashboards / metrics for tracking (https://github.com/metabase/metabase).</item>
          <item>gcp / aws CLIs — Pull telemetry, BigQuery / Redshift / Athena (gcloud, aws).</item>
          <item>python (pandas, statsmodels) — Diff-in-differences, synthetic control (pip).</item>
          <item>r — Causal inference packages (CausalImpact, MatchIt) (https://cran.r-project.org).</item>
          <item>jq — Parse JSON benefit registers (https://jqlang.github.io/jq/).</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="services-apps">
        <title>Services and Apps</title>
        <list>
          <item>Salesforce — SaaS, CRM revenue benefit baseline + realization, REST/SOAP.</item>
          <item>HubSpot — SaaS, Marketing/sales benefit data.</item>
          <item>Mixpanel / Amplitude — SaaS, Product analytics for adoption + KPI.</item>
          <item>Looker / Looker Studio — SaaS, Dashboards via API.</item>
          <item>Tableau — SaaS / desktop, REST API, embed.</item>
          <item>Power BI — SaaS, REST API, AAD auth.</item>
          <item>Productboard — SaaS, Outcome-based roadmap, partial benefits track.</item>
          <item>Aha! — SaaS, Strategy → benefits link, REST API.</item>
          <item>ProductPlan — SaaS, Lighter.</item>
          <item>Apptio Targetprocess — SaaS, Portfolio benefits + spend.</item>
          <item>Anaplan — SaaS, Financial benefit modeling.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="best-practices">
        <title>Best Practices</title>
        <list>
          <item>Quantify before approval; "soft benefits" without metric do not count.</item>
          <item>Freeze baseline in writing with date and source query — agents can re-pull but not redefine.</item>
          <item>Benefit owner ≠ project manager; PM hands off at go-live.</item>
          <item>Track leading indicators (adoption, NPS) monthly; lagging (revenue, cost) quarterly.</item>
          <item>Build attribution intentionally — pre-register a control cohort or comparator before launch.</item>
          <item>Cap claimable benefits at portfolio level to prevent double-counting.</item>
          <item>Sunset benefits register at 24 months unless extended — long tails distort portfolio metrics.</item>
          <item>Treat under-realization as learning, not blame; publish post-mortems.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
        <title>AI Agent Gotchas</title>
        <list>
          <item>Agents will fabricate baselines from "industry averages" if the actual baseline is missing — fail closed, demand source.</item>
          <item>Counterfactual analysis is easy to do badly; require pre-registered DiD/synth-control plan, do not let agent pick model post-hoc.</item>
          <item>Benefit ownership decays silently when owners leave; cron-check that owner email still resolves and projects still active.</item>
          <item>Currency, FX, and inflation: agents must use the same deflator for baseline and actual.</item>
          <item>Adoption metrics from telemetry can be inflated by bots/automation; segment human vs bot traffic.</item>
          <item>ROI calculations: agents tend to ignore time-value-of-money; use NPV, not raw sum.</item>
          <item>"Productivity gain from AI" benefit is the most over-claimed category in 2024-2026; require independent validation.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="references">
      <title>References</title>
      <list>
        <item>PMI, Benefits Realization Management Framework.</item>
        <item>Bradley &amp; Cantwell, Benefits Realization Management (Routledge).</item>
        <item>John Thorp, The Information Paradox — benefits realization origins.</item>
        <item>Office of Government Commerce (UK), MSP — managing successful programmes.</item>
        <item>Counterfactual analysis: Brodersen et al., CausalImpact (Google).</item>
        <item>McKinsey, Measuring the impact of digital transformations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/benefits-register.md" purpose="Register table: ID, benefit, category, owner, metric, baseline, target, status."/>
      <template path="templates/benefits-report.md" purpose="Post-launch report: executive summary, status per benefit, barriers, forecast."/>
      <template path="templates/business-case-benefits.md" purpose="Business case section: financial table (3-year), non-financial table, ROI/NPV."/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/benefits-track.py" purpose="Pull current metric values vs target from Looker/CSV, emit JSON status and % realized."/>
      <script path="scripts/diff-in-diff.py" purpose="Quick difference-in-differences for benefit attribution (ATT estimation)."/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/devops/report/extend-analytics/"/>
      <link href="https://www.mckinseydigital.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
