<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="30-60-90-day-plan">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Three-phase new-hire ramp framework (Learn/Contribute/Execute) with observable milestones anchored to real team work, not generic verbs, enabling defensible day-30, day-60, and day-90 reviews.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>onboarding</tag>
      <tag>new-hire</tag>
      <tag>ramp</tag>
      <tag>performance-management</tag>
      <tag>structured-hiring</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>onboarding</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>30-60-90 Day Plan</title>

    <summary>A three-phase new-hire ramp framework based on Michael Watkins's Learn / Contribute / Execute cadence. Each phase has observable milestones anchored to real team work (a release, a quota slice, a shipped doc), not generic verbs like "understand". The plan is co-authored with the hiring manager and the new hire on Day 1; plans written by HR alone become checkboxes nobody reads.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a structured ramp plan, new hires and managers operate on implicit, mismatched expectations. The 30-day review is the first moment misalignment surfaces — too late for easy correction. Observable artifacts per phase (PR merged, deal closed, doc published) give the manager a defensible basis for the day-30, day-60, and day-90 reviews and give the hire a clear contract for what success looks like.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>New hire onboarding for any role with measurable project deliverables (engineer, sales rep, PM, marketer).</item>
        <item>Internal transfers and promotions where role scope changes substantially.</item>
        <item>Re-orgs where leaders need a structured first quarter against new mandates.</item>
        <item>Drafting role-specific milestones during offer close to set explicit expectations.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Hourly or shift roles where competency comes from training scripts, not project ownership.</item>
        <item>Sub-30-day contracts where the three-phase cadence does not fit.</item>
        <item>Roles where outcomes depend wholly on team output — use team-level OKRs instead.</item>
        <item>Externally mandated apprenticeship curricula (medical residency, regulated trades).</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="core-principles">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every milestone in a 30-60-90 plan must be anchored to a concrete, observable artifact; never use the verbs "understand", "be familiar with", or "learn about" as milestone criteria.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague verbs cannot be verified at the day-30 review; the manager and hire will disagree on whether the milestone is complete. Observable artifacts (PR merged, doc written, customer call completed, deal proposed) have a clear binary: done or not done.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Co-author the plan with the hiring manager and the new hire on Day 1; plans written by HR alone become checkboxes nobody reads after week 2.</statement>
        <rationale>Ownership of the plan predicts adherence. When the new hire participates in setting the milestones, they internalize them as personal commitments rather than corporate requirements.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-1-days-1-30-learn">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Days 1-30 are a learning phase; do not assign project ownership or execution pressure in the first 30 days unless the role explicitly requires immediate delivery (e.g., revenue-critical backfill).</statement>
        <rationale>Pushing delivery into the learn phase causes early burnout, poor-quality output, and missed context that creates technical or relationship debt. The day-30 review is the correct gate for confirming readiness to contribute.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="day-30-success-criteria">
        <list>
          <item>Can describe the team's current quarter goals and how this role contributes to them.</item>
          <item>Has met all key stakeholders within and adjacent to the team.</item>
          <item>Has read and can locate all critical documentation for the role.</item>
          <item>Has identified one area of friction, risk, or opportunity (written 1-pager observation).</item>
          <item>Has documented goals for days 31-60 in a shared artifact with the manager.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-2-days-31-60-contribute">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Phase 2 ends with ownership of at least one completed project, however small; a completed project is a stronger signal than partial progress on a large one.</statement>
        <rationale>Completing a scoped project demonstrates the full delivery cycle (planning, execution, communication, handoff) at whatever scale is appropriate. A partial large project reveals nothing about completion behavior.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="day-60-success-criteria">
        <list>
          <item>Has owned and completed at least one project end-to-end (scope appropriate to role and level).</item>
          <item>Has received and acted on feedback from at least two sources (manager and peer or stakeholder).</item>
          <item>Works with minimal supervision on familiar tasks.</item>
          <item>Has proposed at least one improvement to a team process, tool, or practice.</item>
          <item>Has documented goals for days 61-90 in a shared artifact.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="phase-3-days-61-90-execute">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>By day 90, the hire must work independently on 80%+ of their responsibilities; anything below this threshold triggers a formal performance conversation, not an extension of the onboarding period.</statement>
        <rationale>Extending the onboarding frame past 90 days without a performance conversation obscures underperformance and delays the manager's decision. The 90-day review is the formal transition from onboarding to standard performance management.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="day-90-success-criteria">
        <list>
          <item>Meets or exceeds performance expectations on primary job responsibilities.</item>
          <item>Works autonomously on 80%+ of tasks without requiring guidance.</item>
          <item>Has contributed to team goals in a measurable, visible way.</item>
          <item>Has a documented development plan for the next quarter.</item>
          <item>Is integrated into team culture (included in social and professional rituals).</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="check-in-cadence">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run the day-30 review at day 25 to leave 5 days of correction opportunity before the formal milestone; never use the review as the first signal of problems.</statement>
        <rationale>If issues surface first at the day-30 review, the correction window is zero. Running at day 25 gives 5 days to course-correct before the formal gate, converting the review from a verdict into a coaching tool.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Check-in schedule: day 7 (early pulse, informal), day 25-30 (30-day review), day 45 (skip-level: hire meets manager's manager, removes reporting-chain blind spot), day 60 (60-day review), day 90 (formal performance review).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="role-specific-examples">
      <section name="software-engineer-example">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Engineering 30-60-90 plans must anchor milestones to code artifacts: merged PR, deployed feature, published doc, completed code review — not "learned the codebase".</statement>
          <rationale>Learning the codebase is a means, not a milestone. The day-30 deliverable should be a first commit, however small, that demonstrates the environment is set up and the engineer can work in the team's workflow.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <example type="good" title="Software Engineer 30-day milestone">
          <note>Development environment fully set up, first small PR (bug fix or doc update) merged, all team workflows (CI/CD, code review, deployment) completed at least once, key stakeholders introduced.</note>
        </example>

        <example type="good" title="Software Engineer 60-day milestone">
          <note>Owns and delivers a scoped feature independently — from technical design review through merge and monitoring for one week post-deploy. Participates in sprint planning and owns at least 2 code reviews per sprint.</note>
        </example>

        <example type="good" title="Software Engineer 90-day milestone">
          <note>Recognized as a productive team member by the team (peer feedback). Owns a medium-complexity feature. Has contributed to at least one architectural discussion with a documented position. Leads or presents in one team sync.</note>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="sales-representative-example">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Sales 30-60-90 plans must anchor to pipeline metrics, not activity counts; "made 50 calls" is not a milestone — "built a qualified pipeline of $X" is.</statement>
          <rationale>Activity counts measure effort, not output. A sales representative can make 100 calls to unqualified prospects and have zero qualified pipeline. Pipeline value and deal stage distribution are the leading indicators of ramp performance.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <example type="good" title="Sales Representative 30-day milestone">
          <note>Product certified (passed internal product test), completed 5 ride-along calls with senior reps, built first territory plan, run first 3 discovery calls independently.</note>
        </example>

        <example type="good" title="Sales Representative 60-day milestone">
          <note>50% of full-quota pipeline built in the CRM with stage-correct opportunities. Has presented at least 5 demos. Has submitted at least 2 proposals. Has developed a territory account map.</note>
        </example>

        <example type="good" title="Sales Representative 90-day milestone">
          <note>Hit ramp quota (50-75% of full quota). Has closed at least 1 deal independently. Manages full sales cycle without manager shadowing. Has a territory strategy for Q2 documented.</note>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="role-antipatterns">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Using the same plan template for engineering and sales roles without role-specific adaptation.</description>
          <reason>A Sales 60-day milestone (50% pipeline) is fundamentally unlike an engineering one (feature delivered). Generic templates produce milestones that don't match either role's actual delivery cycle, making the review a formality.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Setting stretch goals in the Learn phase (days 1-30) to signal high expectations.</description>
          <reason>Stretch goals in the first 30 days reward speed over quality, incentivize the hire to skip context-building, and produce poor output that creates downstream debt. The manager signals expectations through the day-60 and day-90 milestones, not by front-loading delivery.</reason>
        </antipattern>

        <antipattern>
          <description>Plans written solely by HR using a generic template, then handed to the hire on Day 1 as a done document.</description>
          <reason>Plans the hire did not co-author become external checklists with no ownership. Drift starts in week 2; by day 30, nobody references them. Thirty minutes of co-authoring on Day 1 produces a plan the hire treats as a personal commitment.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/plan-scaffold.sh" purpose="Bash scaffold: given a role slug and JD file, generates a markdown plan skeleton with the three phases."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.bcg.com/en-us/capabilities/authors/michael-d-watkins"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
