<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-model" title="Blurred Roles Team Model">
  <summary>Overlapping Venn diagram team structure where each role holds fluency in adjacent disciplines, replacing relay-race handoffs.</summary>

  <section title="The Core Shift">
    <p>Traditional product teams pass work in sequence: PM writes spec, designer designs, engineer builds, QA tests. AI-era teams operate as overlapping Venn diagrams. Each discipline participates earlier and across more phases. The overlap is intentional — it is the operating model.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Every Venn-overlap zone must have exactly one human DRI. Agents fill the zone but never own the decision.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a DRI, parallel role-persona agents on the same problem produce contradictions and the team ships the loudest recommendation rather than the right one.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="New PM Skillset">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require PMs to hold fluency in design, data, model behavior, distribution, and pricing — not just spec writing and roadmap ownership.</statement>
      <rationale>As engineering throughput scales with AI, the bottleneck shifts to discovery, evaluation, and judgment. PMs without adjacent fluency become the constraint.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <note>PM who can write SQL to validate a hypothesis, read a confusion matrix, and articulate a pricing model trade-off participates in all three overlap zones without creating handoffs.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <note>PM who writes a spec and hands it to design, then waits for a handoff from engineering to review, is operating as a relay runner — creating latency at every baton pass.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Functional Expectations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every "PM speaks design" expectation with a symmetric expectation on the other side. One-sided blurring breeds resentment.</statement>
      <rationale>If PMs are expected to give design feedback but designers are not expected to track metrics, the blurring is extractive, not collaborative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Keep one depth specialist per critical discipline (security, ML eval, accessibility). Full-blurring is an anti-pattern in deep domains.</statement>
      <rationale>T-shaped fluency scales well; eliminating specialization entirely creates a team that is mediocre at everything and expert at nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PM:Engineer Ratio">
    <p>Andrew Ng observed at Sequoia AI Ascent 2024 that AI-augmented teams invert the traditional ratio: 2 PMs per 1 Engineer replaces the traditional 1 PM per 4–8 Engineers. This holds when engineering throughput is heavily agent-assisted and the real bottleneck is discovery, evals, and prioritization — not coding.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the 2:1 PM:Engineer ratio as a hypothesis per team, not a universal target. Measure agent-assisted velocity separately from baseline engineering throughput.</statement>
      <rationale>The inversion only holds when the engineer is heavily AI-augmented. Measuring on baseline throughput leads to over-hiring PMs and under-building.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Re-Audit Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-audit role overlap quarterly using commit/PR-author distribution as the truth signal, not self-reported role descriptions.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-reported role splits in surveys are systematically wrong by ~30%. Git shortlog surfaces who actually touches which areas of the codebase.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Blurred roles defined in a Notion page but not reflected in actual work assignment or code ownership.</description>
      <reason>Blurred roles drift back to silos under deadline pressure. The quarterly audit is the forcing function that prevents reversion.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/role-overlap.sh">Emit per-author file-area distribution from git history to surface actual role boundaries</reference>
</text>
