<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Blended CAC Model Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Blended CAC Model application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them. Plus a skip-methodology rule for decision-tree leaves that exit the methodology.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-bound-scope" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply to a single paid-spend window (campaign, month, or quarter). Do not batch multiple windows in one record.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-conflation">Each window has its own attribution decisions; batching destroys reproducibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-typed-input" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every channel row carries spend (USD), customers acquired (int), source path. Free-form prose without typed values is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-first">Typed inputs make the readout falsifiable; untyped values hide hallucinations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output names a single accountable owner. No &apos;growth team&apos; or &apos;we&apos; as owner.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI">Plural ownership equals none; future readers need a named human.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-versioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output carries semver + last_reviewed date. Re-run on material spend changes; do not silently overwrite.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay">Blended CAC drifts with channel mix; old records must be flagged.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-conversion-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Attribution window (e.g. 7-day click, 1-day view) is declared up front and frozen for the duration of the test.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-window-shopping bias">Post-hoc window adjustment manufactures wins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-incremental-lift" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Subtract platform-claimed conversions by an incremental-lift estimate (geo-test, holdout, or default 30% haircut documented in the record).</statement>
      <rationale source="MMM-lite">Without lift adjustment, platform CAC double-counts across channels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the decision tree resolves to a skip branch — preconditions are not met OR an adjacent methodology fits better.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-tree discipline">Skipping cleanly preserves the integrity of the rubric; misapplied methodologies produce false positives downstream.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
