<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>Kanban and SAFe ceremonies: daily standup, weekly replenishment/SDR, bi-weekly retro, monthly strategy. Use throughput + cycle time for forecasting instead of velocity.</summary>
    <category>ceremonies</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>kanban</tag>
      <tag>safe</tag>
      <tag>ceremonies</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>continuous-flow</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Kanban and Scaled Agile Ceremonies</title>

    <summary>Alternative agile cadences for continuous-flow teams (Kanban) and multi-team programs (SAFe). Kanban replaces fixed sprints with five cadences: daily standup (walk-the-board right-to-left), weekly replenishment, weekly service-delivery review, bi-weekly retrospective, and monthly strategy review. SAFe adds PI Planning (2-day, every 8-12 weeks), Scrum-of-Scrums (daily), PO Sync (weekly), and Inspect-and-Adapt (end of PI). The rule: throughput plus 85th-percentile cycle time beats velocity for forecasting; use Monte Carlo on these for date predictions.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Sprint boundaries break down for ops, platform, and support teams with high mid-sprint volatility. Kanban cadences decouple commitment from timebox, making WIP limits the primary flow-control mechanism. At scale (3+ Scrum teams), PI Planning provides the cross-team dependency surface that individual standups cannot — it is the SAFe ceremony that delivers the most value per hour spent.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Continuous-flow teams (support, ops, data engineering) with no natural sprint boundary.</item>
        <item>Multi-team programs needing PI Planning and Scrum-of-Scrums coordination.</item>
        <item>Teams with high mid-sprint volatility (incident-heavy ops, content production).</item>
        <item>Platform teams serving many internal customers where replenishment fits better than sprint commitment.</item>
        <item>Hybrid ScrumBan setups: sprint planning kept for steering, WIP limits enforced for flow.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A single team of fewer than 8 people with stable feature work — Scrum's ceremonies suffice.</item>
        <item>Pure project work with fixed end date and known scope — predictive cadences fit better.</item>
        <item>Organizations drowning in ceremonies; adding SAFe events without removing others causes revolt.</item>
        <item>Discovery-heavy product work where dual-track agile maps better than SAFe.</item>
        <item>Solopreneur or 2-person teams — overhead exceeds value; a personal Kanban board is enough.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="kanban-cadences">
      <p>Kanban ceremonies focus on flow, WIP management, and continuous improvement rather than time-boxed iterations.</p>

      <term name="Daily Standup">Daily walk-the-board meeting, right-to-left. Start with blocked/at-risk items, then move blockers. Owners speak only for their work. 15 minutes max. Uses WIP visualization to discuss flow constraints.</term>

      <term name="Weekly Replenishment">PO + tech lead select top-N "Ready" items from the backlog (prioritized by value × age × dependency). Ordered list becomes the next week's pull sequence. 30 minutes. No "anyone interested" — focus is selection, not discussion.</term>

      <term name="Service-Delivery Review (SDR)">Weekly metrics review: throughput (items/week, last 4 weeks), cycle time (avg and 85th percentile per state), WIP vs limits, list of aged items (>2x median), blockers. Data-driven, not status theater. Drives policy changes (WIP limit adjustments, priority re-ranking, process updates). 45 minutes.</term>

      <term name="Bi-weekly Retrospective">Discuss impediments, WIP limit breaches, outdated process steps, and team growth. Owners: process improvements and people development. Output: 2-3 actions with owners and due dates. Not a complaint session.</term>

      <term name="Monthly Strategy Review">Leadership alignment: roadmap progress vs plan, new strategic direction (if any), resource constraints, customer feedback themes. Drives replenishment priority for the next month. 60 minutes.</term>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Enforce WIP limits as a first-class column setting with a hard block (Jira Premium / Linear Cycles); soft warnings are ignored under pressure.</statement>
        <rationale>WIP limits without enforcement become aspirational. Teams blow past them under pressure without visible feedback; hard blocks force the conversation about priority.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Throughput + 85th-percentile cycle time beats velocity for forecasting; use Monte Carlo simulation on these metrics for date predictions.</statement>
        <rationale>Velocity is a Scrum artifact dependent on sprint length and planning accuracy. Kanban teams deliver on a sliding window; cycle-time percentiles are more stable and actionable for forecasting.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scaled-agile-framework">
      <p>SAFe (Scaled Agile Framework) layers Kanban+Scrum ceremonies with Program Increment (PI) planning and cross-team synchronization.</p>

      <term name="Program Increment (PI)">8-12 week planning cycle. Each PI is split into 2 iterations (each ~2 weeks). Starts with PI Planning, ends with Inspect-and-Adapt.</term>

      <term name="PI Planning">2-day, in-person (preferred) quarterly event. All teams (3+) attend with their PO and tech lead. Day 1: Product vision, capacity planning, team breakouts (each team plans stories into iterations). Day 2: cross-team dependency board (identify and resolve blockers), confidence vote. Output: PI roadmap, capacity sheet, dependency board.</term>

      <term name="Scrum-of-Scrums">Daily 15-min standup of team representatives to discuss cross-team dependencies, risks, escalations. Not a status round-robin — focus is dependency resolution.</term>

      <term name="PO Sync">Weekly 1-hour sync of all POs to align on priority, roadmap, and customer feedback. Feeds into next replenishment.</term>

      <term name="Inspect-and-Adapt (I&amp;A)">End-of-PI meeting (~90 min). Program-level retrospective: measure objectives + key results (OKRs) achieved, systemic impediments, process improvements. Output: action items with owners + due dates for next PI. Items tracked in the program backlog.</term>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Lock the PI Planning agenda exactly the day before; teams that "tweak" it lose 30+ minutes to confusion.</statement>
        <rationale>PI Planning thrives on predictability. Late agenda changes ripple through breakout groups and reduce decision quality.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track I&amp;A actions in the same backlog as features with owners and due dates; otherwise they get prioritized to zero and re-surface every PI.</statement>
        <rationale>Improvements without tracking disappear into noise. Make them first-class work items.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>WIP limits without leadership backing become aspirational; teams blow past them under pressure.</description>
        <reason>Without visible enforcement and leadership support for pushing back on demand, WIP limits are ignored.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Service-delivery review devolves into status theater unless metrics drive concrete policy changes.</description>
        <reason>SDR without decisions becomes a data dump. Tie every metric to an action (WIP adjustment, priority re-rank, process change).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>PI Planning quality drops sharply when run remote-only with poor tooling (Miro lag, audio chaos).</description>
        <reason>PI Planning depends on real-time cross-team problem-solving. Remote logistics must match in-person (clear tool, low latency, breakout rooms).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Scrum-of-Scrums turns into a status round-robin instead of a dependency-resolution forum.</description>
        <reason>SoS without focused agenda becomes theater. Set rule: only discuss cross-team dependencies and escalations; status updates happen in team standups.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="metrics-and-flow">
      <p>Kanban metrics provide visibility into flow and enable data-driven process changes.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Kanban metrics (cycle time, throughput) need ≥6 weeks of clean data before they are trustworthy for forecasting.</statement>
        <rationale>Short windows capture noise (one slow item, holiday week). Six-week minimum smooths anomalies and reveals true process stability.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <term name="Cycle Time">Time from "In Progress" to "Done" per issue. Median and 85th percentile tell the whole story. Use for forecasting and SLA promises.</term>

      <term name="Lead Time">Time from "Created" to "Done". Includes waiting in backlog. Use for customer communication ("how long until my request is done?").</term>

      <term name="Throughput">Items completed per week (or per sprint). Stable measure of team capacity. Use for roadmap planning and Monte Carlo forecasting.</term>

      <example type="good" title="Service-delivery review dashboard">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[## Service Delivery Review — Week of 2026-04-28

### Flow Metrics
- Throughput (28d): 18 items
- Weekly avg: 4.5 items/week
- Cycle time (median): 3.2 days
- Cycle time (p85): 7.1 days

### WIP Status
| Column      | WIP Limit | Current | Status |
|-------------|-----------|---------|--------|
| Backlog     | ∞         | 42      | OK     |
| Ready       | 10        | 8       | OK     |
| In Progress | 5         | 5       | AT CAP |
| Code Review | 3         | 2       | OK     |
| QA          | 3         | 3       | AT CAP |
| Done        | —         | —       | —      |

### Aged Items (>2x median cycle time = >6.4 days)
- PROJ-204: Bug, "In Progress" since Apr 20 — owner: @alice
- PROJ-198: Feature, "Code Review" since Apr 19 — blocker: waiting for 3rd reviewer

### Actions
1. (@alice) Unblock PROJ-204 by EOD Thursday or escalate.
2. (@bob) Hire code-review signal for PROJ-198 or adjust reviewer rota.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflows">
      <p>Agent-driven ceremony support automates agenda prep, metrics calculation, action tracking, and facilitation.</p>

      <list>
        <item>kanban-flow-analyst — pulls cycle/lead time, throughput, WIP from API; flags outliers, aging items.</item>
        <item>replenishment-prepper — orders the "Ready" queue by priority × age × dependency, returns top-N picks.</item>
        <item>pi-planning-facilitator — generates the PI agenda, capacity sheet, dependency board template per team.</item>
        <item>inspect-adapt-tracker — captures I&amp;A action items into the program backlog with owners + due dates.</item>
        <item>/faion — already in repo; can be invoked to walk SDD tasks once they are committed in PI plan.</item>
      </list>

      <example type="good" title="Flow analyst prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are kanban-flow-analyst. Inputs: JSON list of issues with state, entered_state_at,
exited_state_at, wip_limit per column. Output: Markdown brief with throughput
(items/week, last 4 weeks), avg cycle time per state, WIP vs limit, list of items aged > 2x
median cycle time. Do not infer reasons — only report numbers.]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents trained on Scrum default to sprint-thinking; explicitly tell them "this team uses Kanban, no sprints, WIP-limited."</description>
        <reason>LLM training data skews Scrum-heavy. Without explicit constraint, agents suggest sprint boundaries and velocity tracking.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Cycle-time math: define "started" precisely (entered "In Progress" vs. assignee set). LLMs guess inconsistently.</description>
        <reason>Ambiguous definition leads to inconsistent calculations. Pin the definition in the system prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>SAFe terminology overlap (PI vs. Iteration, Feature vs. Story) — pin definitions in the system prompt or get garbage outputs.</description>
        <reason>SAFe reuses Scrum terms with slightly different meanings. Agents hallucinate without explicit vocabulary.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>An agent generating retro themes from comments often surfaces venting, not actionable signal — filter for verbs.</description>
        <reason>Comments capture emotion. Themes need to be actionable improvement statements with owners and due dates.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Confidence-vote scores look like data but are social signals; do not feed raw to forecasting models.</description>
        <reason>Confidence votes reflect team optimism at PI Planning; they are not predictive of actual delivery. Use historical cycle-time data instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Time-zone math for distributed PI Planning: pass explicit IANA TZ strings, never "PST" / "EST".</description>
        <reason>Daylight saving time rules vary. Agents miscount hours without explicit timezone.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Throughput + 85th-percentile cycle time beats velocity for forecasting; use Monte Carlo on these for date predictions.</item>
        <item>For PI Planning, lock the agenda exactly; teams that "tweak" it lose 30 minutes per ceremony to confusion.</item>
        <item>Run replenishment with the PO + tech lead only; opening it to "anyone interested" turns a 30-min meeting into 90.</item>
        <item>Make WIP limits a first-class column setting with a hard block (Jira Premium / Linear Cycles) — soft warnings get ignored.</item>
        <item>Track I&amp;A actions in the same backlog as features; otherwise they get prioritized to zero.</item>
        <item>For remote PI Planning, pre-build the program board the day before; live-creation kills momentum.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/kanban-metrics.md" purpose="Weekly service-delivery review dashboard: throughput, cycle time, WIP vs limits, blockers, aging items."/>
      <template path="templates/cycle-stats.py" purpose="Compute throughput and cycle-time percentiles from a JSONL of issues with state timestamps."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.kanban.university/kanban-guide/"/>
      <link href="https://scaledagileframework.com/pi-planning/"/>
      <link href="https://www.atlassian.com/agile/kanban/metrics"/>
      <ref slug="scrum-ceremonies"/>
      <ref slug="jira-workflow-management"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
