<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="user-story-mapping Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for user-story-mapping. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build the backbone first with verbs in user-journey order; then add tasks. Reverse order produces noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Backbone-first approach ensures the context exists for meaningful task prioritization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Walking skeleton is non-negotiable: exactly one task per backbone activity and end-to-end working flow.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The skeleton is the minimum viable release contract; without it, Release 1 becomes a feature soup.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each release slice must span the full backbone, not just one column. Otherwise users can't complete the journey.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Partial-backbone releases are broken by definition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include error/edge tasks in the columns, not just happy path.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Error handling determines user retention; happy path alone is incomplete.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Update the map at every quarterly review; treat it as living, not a deliverable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Maps drift; periodic sync with roadmap reality keeps them useful.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair the map with the spec: each release-bound task gets a story-card with acceptance criteria.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Maps are a planning tool; acceptance criteria drive implementation and testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For solo dev work, drop the workshop ceremony but keep the structure: backbone + skeleton + 2 release slices.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Structure applies even without cross-functional teams; it forces clarity on priority and scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
