<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="Story Map Structure">
  <summary>The four layers of a user story map — backbone, tasks, walking skeleton, and release slices — with rules for building each layer correctly.</summary>

  <section title="Backbone">
    <rule>
      <statement>The backbone is a left-to-right sequence of 5–10 verb-phrase user activities that represent the user's journey. Use verb phrases ("Create Project"), never nouns ("Project").</statement>
      <rationale>Nouns hide the action and make it impossible to see whether the user can actually accomplish anything. Verb phrases make activities testable: you can verify whether a user can "Create Project."</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tasks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Under each backbone activity, list specific user tasks ordered vertically by importance (higher = more important). Cap at 6 tasks per column.</statement>
      <rationale>Vertical ordering is the priority signal. More than 6 tasks per column makes the map unreadable and usually means the backbone activity needs to be split.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include at least one error path or empty-state task per activity — not just the happy path.</statement>
      <rationale>Happy-path-only maps produce releases that break on the first edge case. Error paths are where users abandon products.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Walking Skeleton">
    <rule>
      <statement>The walking skeleton is exactly one task per backbone activity — the minimum set that forms an end-to-end working flow. Every backbone activity must have exactly one skeleton task; the flow must be completeable end-to-end.</statement>
      <rationale>Without the walking skeleton constraint, Release 1 becomes a maximalist feature dump. The skeleton forces the team to ask "what is the thinnest possible flow that works?"</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Release Slices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each release slice is a horizontal cut that spans the full backbone. A release that covers only 2 of 5 activities means users cannot complete the journey.</statement>
      <rationale>Partial-backbone releases ship an incomplete experience. Users who reach the edge of the covered activities are blocked and churn. Every slice must be shippable value — something a user can accomplish end-to-end.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/story-map.md">Tabular story map with all layers</reference>
  <reference path="templates/storymap-check.py">Validator: skeleton coverage and release-spans-backbone check</reference>
</text>
