<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Story Mapping Process">
  <summary>Five-step mapping process: frame the journey, build backbone, add tasks, identify walking skeleton, slice releases. Each step has concrete outputs and a verification question.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1 — Frame the Journey">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before writing any activities, define: who is the user, what is their big goal, and where does the journey start and end.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a journey frame the backbone drifts into product-internal activities instead of user-facing ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2 — Build the Backbone">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write activities as verb phrases on cards, arrange left-to-right in journey order, then verify the sequence by reading it aloud as a user narrative.</statement>
      <rationale>The read-aloud test catches activities in the wrong order and reveals missing steps before you add tasks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3 — Add Tasks">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each activity: list what the user does there, place tasks in the activity column, arrange vertically by importance (top = most important). Do not write tasks before the backbone is complete.</statement>
      <rationale>Writing tasks before the backbone produces task lists, not a story map. The backbone provides the grouping context that gives vertical ordering its meaning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4 — Identify the Walking Skeleton">
    <rule>
      <statement>Draw a line separating the walking skeleton (one task per activity, end-to-end flow) from all remaining tasks. The skeleton must not skip any backbone activity.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping an activity in the skeleton means the user cannot complete the journey — the skeleton is broken by definition.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5 — Slice Releases">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each release: define the value it delivers, draw a horizontal line, name the release goal, and verify the slice spans all backbone activities.</statement>
      <rationale>Naming the release goal forces the team to ask "what can a user do after this release that they could not do before?" If the answer is unclear, the slice is not ready.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not run backbone, task, and release-slicing in one pass. Run as three sequential steps; quality drops sharply when combined.</statement>
      <rationale>Each step requires a different thinking mode. Combined passes produce noise-rich maps with undisciplined priority ordering.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
