<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="user-story-mapping Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for user-story-mapping as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Backbone activities written as nouns ("Dashboard", "Reports") instead of verb phrases ("View Dashboard", "Generate Report").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Nouns hide the user action and make priority ordering arbitrary. Verb phrases are testable: you can verify whether a user can accomplish the activity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Walking skeleton skips one or more backbone activities.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A skeleton with gaps means the user cannot complete the end-to-end journey. Releases built on a broken skeleton ship an incomplete experience by design.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Release slice covers only 1–2 activities out of the full backbone.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users hit a wall at the edge of the covered activities and cannot complete their goal. Every release must span the full backbone — even if each column gets only one task in that release.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Map built once at project start and never updated.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A static map loses fidelity within one sprint cycle as scope changes. Treat it as a living artifact tied to quarterly roadmap reviews.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Only happy-path tasks in each activity column.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Error paths, empty states, and failure recovery are where users abandon products. Missing them from the map means they are never prioritized into a release.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
