<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="swap-memory-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for swap-memory-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For a server with 16–32 GB RAM, create a 4 GB swap file. Swap is a safety net — it prevents OOM kills under burst conditions but should rarely be used during normal operation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Large swap on a RAM-rich server does not improve performance. With swappiness=10, the kernel will only start using swap when RAM is nearly exhausted, so 4 GB covers burst situations without wasting disk on idle swap space.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use fallocate to create the swap file; set chmod 600 before mkswap; add to /etc/fstab; verify with findmnt --verify to guard against a typo that prevents boot.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A swap file with world-readable permissions leaks RAM content to unprivileged users. An invalid /etc/fstab entry can render the server unbootable. findmnt --verify catches syntax errors before reboot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set vm.swappiness = 10 on servers with 8 GB+ RAM. Never set it to 0 — value 0 means the kernel will not swap at all and may OOM-kill instead of using the swap safety net.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Default swappiness=60 causes the kernel to start swapping when 40% of RAM is used, creating latency spikes during LLM API calls. Value 10 delays swapping until RAM is almost full while still keeping the swap safety valve functional.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pair swappiness tuning with vm.dirty_ratio=15, vm.dirty_background_ratio=5, and vm.vfs_cache_pressure=50 for stable I/O behavior and longer inode/dentry cache retention.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">dirty_background_ratio=5 starts background writeback early, preventing a sudden I/O spike when dirty_ratio=15 is reached. vfs_cache_pressure=50 tells the kernel to reclaim page cache before dentry/inode caches, keeping filesystem metadata resident.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set OOMScoreAdjust in systemd unit files to control kill order. Databases: −900. Core API: −300. Celery workers: 0. Static file servers: +100. Never set −1000 for application services — reserve that for kernel threads.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without explicit OOM priorities the kernel picks victims by memory usage alone, often killing the database instead of a worker. Explicit priorities ensure that if OOM must kill something, it kills the least critical service first, in a deterministic order.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set MemoryMax (hard kill limit) and MemoryHigh (soft throttle limit) on every service. Without limits, a Celery worker processing a large context window grows unbounded and triggers the kernel OOM killer against the wrong process.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">MemoryHigh causes the kernel to throttle the cgroup and activate memory reclaim before hitting MemoryMax. This gives the service a chance to release memory gracefully. MemoryMax is the hard backstop — the process receives SIGKILL when it exceeds this.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monitor cgroup memory usage via systemctl status and the cgroup fs at /sys/fs/cgroup/. Use systemd-cgtop for a live overview of all services.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">High-water-mark memory usage is not visible in free -h — it is scoped to the cgroup. Checking memory.peak (if available) or watching memory.current reveals whether a service is regularly approaching its MemoryHigh limit and needs an increase.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
