<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Creational Design Patterns Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every creational-patterns application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to Dependency Injection for any component with dependencies. Never reach for Singleton unless the dependency is truly process-global, read-only, and stateless.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DI reduces maintenance bugs by ~27%, improves testability (70% of high-performing teams rely on mocking), enables modularity, and accelerates refactoring. DI frameworks exist in every mainstream language.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Builder when a constructor has more than 3 parameters or any optional parameter, instead of overloading constructors or passing positional `None`/`null` placeholders.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Telescoping constructors are unreadable and break call-site refactoring. Builders make required vs optional explicit and produce immutable results.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Factory Method when the concrete subclass to instantiate depends on runtime input (config, env, request payload). Do not litter `if/elif` constructor switches across business logic.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Centralizing the switch in one factory keeps domain code closed against new variants and makes it possible to add a new variant by registering it once.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r1-construction-justified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Adoption of any creational pattern MUST be justified by a construction-hotspot record (location + reason). Patterns without a hotspot are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="GoF; refactoring discipline">Pattern overhead is justified by construction-complexity removal; without that the pattern is pure indirection.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-no-default-singleton" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Singleton MUST NOT be the default choice. Singletons need a documented invariant that genuinely requires a single instance.</statement>
      <rationale source="Refactoring; 'Singletons are the new globals'">Singletons hide shared mutable state and break test isolation; the default is module/request/app-scoped DI.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-builder-threshold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Builder pattern adopted only when the target type has ≥4 construction params OR ≥1 invariant validated mid-construction.</statement>
      <rationale source="GoF; pragmatism">Below the threshold, plain dataclass with defaults is simpler and equally clear.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-factory-needs-variants" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Factory Method / Abstract Factory adopted only when ≥2 concrete products exist or are imminent. Single-product factories are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="GoF; YAGNI">Single-product factory is indirection without variance; remove until a second variant appears.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-di-scope-documented" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every DI registration MUST declare its scope (request / app / singleton / transient). Implicit defaults are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="DI best practice">Scope ambiguity is the leading cause of subtle leak / shared-state bugs in DI-heavy codebases.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-23 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
