<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="token-organization Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for token-organization. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Organize all tokens into exactly three tiers; never reference a primitive token directly from a component.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Skipping the semantic layer collapses theming into a global search-and-replace; the semantic tier is the only place where "meaning" lives and can be swapped per theme.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Name tokens using the pattern `{category}.{property}.{variant}.{state}` with all segments in kebab-case.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Self-documenting names eliminate the need for external lookup; `color.surface.primary.hover` conveys category, property, variant, and state without a legend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start with the minimum token set required to implement the design system; add tokens only when a genuine gap exists, not speculatively.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Token bloat reduces discoverability and defeats the systematization purpose; every token without a consumer is maintenance debt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require at least one designer and one engineer to approve any new token before it enters the source-of-truth file.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Token conventions collapse into forks when individual contributors add tokens unilaterally; dual approval enforces naming and tier discipline without a bottleneck.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide a deprecation alias for any renamed token for at least one release cycle before removal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Instant removal of renamed tokens breaks builds silently across every consuming codebase; deprecation aliases give teams time to migrate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before any global token rename, produce a migration plan with codemods — do not do a bulk rename mid-flight when engineers are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mass rename without codemod support destroys team velocity and erodes trust in the design system.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When auditing an existing token set, output a diff plan (rename map + deprecation aliases) for human approval before making any bulk writes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automated bulk renames without human review risk breaking all consuming codebases; the diff plan separates analysis from execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When classifying tokens into tiers, flag tokens that share the same value but appear in different tiers as candidates for deduplication.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Duplicate values across tiers indicate missing aliases; the tier system only works when primitives are referenced by aliases, not duplicated.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
