<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-hierarchy" title="Token Organization Hierarchy and Naming Convention">
  <summary>The three-tier token model (primitives, semantic, component) with a naming convention and examples.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Tier Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Organize all tokens into exactly three tiers; never reference a primitive token directly from a component.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping the semantic layer collapses theming into a global search-and-replace; the semantic tier is the only place where "meaning" lives and can be swapped per theme.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Primitives — raw values with no semantic meaning: `color.primitive.blue-500`, `spacing.4`, `font-size.16`. Never consumed directly by components.</item>
      <item>Semantic — role-based aliases that point to primitives: `color.surface.primary`, `color.text.danger`, `spacing.component.button`. Used in component styles.</item>
      <item>Component — scoped overrides for components that genuinely deviate from the semantic layer: `button.padding.vertical`. Use sparingly; most components should consume only semantic tokens.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Naming Convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name tokens using the pattern `{category}.{property}.{variant}.{state}` with all segments in kebab-case.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-documenting names eliminate the need for external lookup; `color.surface.primary.hover` conveys category, property, variant, and state without a legend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[color.background.primary
color.background.primary.hover
color.text.danger
spacing.component.button
typography.heading.xl]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[blue-1
btn-bg
hoverState
16px-text
primaryBtnPaddingLeftHoverLarge]]></code>
      <note>Raw-value names and camelCase break discovery and theming; component-plus-property-plus-state names in a single token cause component-token bloat.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Lean Token Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with the minimum token set required to implement the design system; add tokens only when a genuine gap exists, not speculatively.</statement>
      <rationale>Token bloat reduces discoverability and defeats the systematization purpose; every token without a consumer is maintenance debt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Audit for duplicates before adding: does a token with the same value and role already exist?</item>
      <item>Document why each token exists in its `$description`; tokens without documented purpose are candidates for deletion.</item>
      <item>Version-control token changes and communicate renames with deprecation aliases before removal.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
