<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Token Organization Rules, Governance, and Agent Guidance">
  <summary>Governance rules to prevent token bloat and cross-team drift, with agent-specific guidance for audits and migrations.</summary>

  <section title="Governance Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require at least one designer and one engineer to approve any new token before it enters the source-of-truth file.</statement>
      <rationale>Token conventions collapse into forks when individual contributors add tokens unilaterally; dual approval enforces naming and tier discipline without a bottleneck.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a deprecation alias for any renamed token for at least one release cycle before removal.</statement>
      <rationale>Instant removal of renamed tokens breaks builds silently across every consuming codebase; deprecation aliases give teams time to migrate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Before any global token rename, produce a migration plan with codemods — do not do a bulk rename mid-flight when engineers are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale>Mass rename without codemod support destroys team velocity and erodes trust in the design system.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tooling Drift Risk">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Tailwind config and CSS custom properties maintained separately from the JSON token source-of-truth.</description>
      <reason>Manual synchronization drifts silently; a pipeline from JSON → Tailwind config → CSS variables must be automated or the three will diverge.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Component tokens created for every component property variation without governance review.</description>
      <reason>Ungoverned component tokens explode; `button.primary.padding.left.hover.large` is a canonical failure mode that signals the semantic layer was bypassed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-Specific Guidance">
    <rule>
      <statement>When auditing an existing token set, output a diff plan (rename map + deprecation aliases) for human approval before making any bulk writes.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated bulk renames without human review risk breaking all consuming codebases; the diff plan separates analysis from execution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>When classifying tokens into tiers, flag tokens that share the same value but appear in different tiers as candidates for deduplication.</statement>
      <rationale>Duplicate values across tiers indicate missing aliases; the tier system only works when primitives are referenced by aliases, not duplicated.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
