<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gha-caching-artifacts Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gha-caching-artifacts. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cache keys MUST include hashFiles('**/lockfile') so the cache is invalidated when dependencies change. Never use a bare runner.os key without a content hash.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A cache key without a lockfile hash will restore a stale node_modules or site-packages that does not match the current lockfile, causing hard-to-diagnose test failures and version drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set retention-days: 7 on intermediate build artifacts. Reserve the 90-day default only for release artifacts that must be downloadable post-deployment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Every run's artifacts consume storage billed to the org. 7-day retention for intermediate outputs keeps storage costs proportional to actual usage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use actions/cache@v4 (not v3). The v4 service was rewritten in Feb 2025; v3 silently fails to restore on new runner images. Verify cache hits in the job log after upgrading.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The v3 → v4 API change broke existing restore logic silently. You lose the entire performance benefit of caching without any error to diagnose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For Docker Buildx: use cache-from: type=gha and cache-to: type=gha,mode=max. Do not use a manual actions/cache step for Docker layers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">type=gha is the native GHA cache backend for Buildx; it handles layer deduplication correctly. Manual cache steps for Docker layers corrupt layer ordering.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
