<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-company-practices" title="Design Doc Practices by Company">
  <summary>How Google, Amazon, Uber, Spotify, Stripe, Meta, and Microsoft structure design documents, reviews, and decision records — with key distinguishing features per company.</summary>

  <section title="Company Overview">
    <p>Design documents serve four universal purposes: early issue identification (cheap to fix on paper), consensus building, knowledge sharing, and onboarding. Each company developed its own format based on culture and scale.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Google: informal Google Doc, inline comments, emphasis on "why" and trade-offs, always include "do nothing" alternative</item>
      <item>Amazon: 6-Pager (narrative prose, no bullets, max 6 pages) + PR-FAQ (press release first, then FAQ); silent 20-25 min read at meeting start; "working backwards" from customer</item>
      <item>Uber: RFC evolved to tiered ERD — Lightweight (team), Standard (cross-team), Heavyweight (org-wide); mailing list circulation with named approvers</item>
      <item>Spotify: two-stage — RFC for consensus (1-3 weeks open), ADR for recording the decision; break large RFCs into big-picture + focused sub-RFCs</item>
      <item>Stripe: strong written culture; RFCs for any decision needing cross-team alignment; high-bar async review; mentorship integrated</item>
      <item>Meta/Facebook: notably less formal — no company-wide RFC process; 1-pagers optional; compensates with high talent bar and long tenures. Not recommended for most teams.</item>
      <item>Microsoft: FDD (functional) + TDD (technical) integrated with Security Development Lifecycle (SDL); security is first-class, not afterthought</item>
      <item>Shopify: GitHub PR-based RFC with explicit review deadline; deadline-driven consensus works well with agent-drafted PRs</item>
      <item>Atlassian: Confluence-based, triad model (eng/PM/design), validated against architecture principles</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Google Design Docs">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include "do nothing" as Alternative 1 in the alternatives section.</statement>
      <rationale>Sometimes the best decision is not to build. Forcing this option ensures the author justifies why building is worth the cost and risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Process: author writes → shares with close collaborators → wider review → optional formal meeting → doc becomes historical artifact. No strict format, but common structure has emerged: Context and Scope, Goals and Non-Goals, Overview, Detailed Design, Alternatives Considered, Cross-cutting Concerns.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Amazon 6-Pager and PR-FAQ">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write in narrative prose, no bullet points, maximum 6 pages; supporting data goes in an unlimited appendix.</statement>
      <rationale>Dense prose forces the author to synthesize; bullets permit loose thinking. Every word must carry information.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>PR-FAQ starts with a hypothetical press release announcing the finished product, then a FAQ document adding detail. This forces customer-centric thinking from day one. Meeting process: printed copies distributed, 20-25 minutes silent reading, discussion, printouts with handwritten notes returned to author.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Uber Tiered ERD">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the lightest template that fits the change scope; do not over-engineer the process.</statement>
      <rationale>Uber evolved from simple RFCs to tiered ERDs precisely because heavyweight process for lightweight changes slows teams without adding value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Lightweight: team-only changes, mini RFC, team lead approver</item>
      <item>Standard: cross-team impact, full RFC, multiple team approvers</item>
      <item>Heavyweight: org/company-wide, detailed ERD, principal engineers</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Spotify RFC + ADR Two-Stage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate the RFC (consensus-reaching) from the ADR (decision-recording); do not conflate the two jobs in one document.</statement>
      <rationale>An RFC trying to reach consensus and record the decision simultaneously produces a document that does neither well. The RFC is collaborative and iterative; the ADR is the immutable record.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
