<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-template-rules" title="Design Document Template: Rules and Fill Order">
  <summary>Rules for correctly filling the design.md template: section fill order, AD format requirements, FR coverage reconciliation, and anti-patterns that produce incomplete designs.</summary>

  <section title="Required Sections">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every design.md must contain all nine required sections: Reference Documents, Overview, Architecture Decisions, Components, Data Flow, Files, Testing Strategy, Risks, and FR Coverage.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing sections cause executor agents to make ungrounded implementation decisions. The FR Coverage table in particular must be generated last as a completeness check.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Reference Documents — links to spec.md, constitution.md, contracts.md</item>
      <item>Overview — 2-3 sentences of technical approach (write LAST, after all sections are complete)</item>
      <item>Architecture Decisions — AD-X in ADR format (minimum 3, maximum 7 for typical features)</item>
      <item>Components — component name, purpose, location, dependencies</item>
      <item>Data Flow — Component A to B to C with validation, transformation, persistence steps</item>
      <item>Files — CREATE/MODIFY/DELETE table with Action, File, Description, FR, AD columns</item>
      <item>Testing Strategy — unit tests table and integration tests table</item>
      <item>Risks — Impact, Probability, Mitigation for each risk</item>
      <item>FR Coverage — every FR-X from spec mapped to AD-X and file entries</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="AD Format Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each AD must include Context, Options (minimum 2 alternatives), Decision, Rationale, and Traces to FR-X. Omitting any field makes the AD unusable for future agents making related decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Future agents reading a design.md need to understand why a path was NOT taken, not just what was chosen. Consequences and rejection reasons are the most valuable fields.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Minimal correct AD structure</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AD-1: {Decision Name}

**Context:** {Problem being solved and relevant context}

**Options:**
- **A: {Option}** — Pros: {benefits}. Cons: {drawbacks}.
- **B: {Option}** — Pros: {benefits}. Cons: {drawbacks}.

**Decision:** {Chosen solution}

**Rationale:** {Why this solution; which constraints drove the choice}

**Traces to:** FR-001, NFR-002
]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>AD with straw-man alternatives — obviously inferior options listed to justify the pre-decided choice.</description>
      <reason>Agents reviewing the design cannot trust the alternatives analysis and will re-open closed decisions during implementation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Fill Order">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write Overview last, after all other sections are complete. Fill FR Coverage as the final reconciliation step.</statement>
      <rationale>Overview written first becomes a summary of assumptions. Overview written last summarizes actual decisions. FR Coverage generated last catches any FR that was not assigned to an AD or file during drafting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1. Reference Documents</item>
      <item>2. Architecture Decisions</item>
      <item>3. Components</item>
      <item>4. Data Flow</item>
      <item>5. Data Models</item>
      <item>6. API Endpoints (reference contracts.md — do not redefine)</item>
      <item>7. Files table</item>
      <item>8. Testing Strategy</item>
      <item>9. Risks</item>
      <item>10. FR Coverage (reconciliation)</item>
      <item>11. Overview (summary of actual decisions)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="API Endpoints Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>If contracts.md exists, the API Endpoints section must say "See contracts.md section X" and must not redefine endpoints.</statement>
      <rationale>Redefining endpoints in design.md creates two sources of truth that drift apart. Executor agents implement from design.md and produce code that diverges from the actual contract.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Writing Overview before Architecture Decisions.</description>
      <reason>Overview becomes a summary of intentions, not decisions. Write it last.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Data Models section omits constraints column.</description>
      <reason>Missing constraints cause migration failures when the executor agent implements the schema.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Files table missing test files.</description>
      <reason>Agents stop after source files. Tests must be explicit CREATE entries or they will not be implemented.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/design.md">Complete design.md template with all required sections</reference>
  <reference path="templates/design-section-check.py">Verifies required sections present and counts ADs and FR traces</reference>
</text>
