<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="Pattern Memory Concepts">
  <summary>What a pattern is vs a code snippet, confidence levels, capture triggers, and hierarchical memory architecture.</summary>

  <section title="Pattern vs Code Snippet">
    <rule>
      <statement>A pattern must include the problem context, when to apply, and when NOT to apply — not just the code example.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents conflate "pattern" with "code snippet." A pattern applied in the wrong context is worse than no pattern. The problem context is what enables correct routing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pattern: high abstraction (problem + context + solution), cross-project reusability, metadata (validation, provenance), evolves over time</item>
      <item>Code snippet: low abstraction (just code), project-specific, no metadata, static</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Pattern Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Code patterns: error handling, data management, API design, testing approaches</item>
      <item>Architecture patterns: structural (component org, module boundaries), behavioral (event handling, pub-sub), integration (service communication)</item>
      <item>Workflow patterns: planning (estimation, decomposition), execution (implementation order, debugging), review (quality gates, code review practices)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Confidence Levels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start every new pattern at confidence 0.5; do not promote to patterns.md until at least 2 uses in distinct contexts.</statement>
      <rationale>Confidence scores are self-assessed by agents and inflate over time without external validation. Requiring 2+ distinct-context uses before promotion prevents premature standardization of single-use fixes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Initial (0.5): first successful use — capture as candidate</item>
      <item>Validated (0.6-0.7): 2-3 successful uses in similar contexts</item>
      <item>Established (0.8-0.9): 5+ uses, verified across different contexts — sync to CLAUDE.md</item>
      <item>Proven (0.9+): 10+ uses, adopted as standard practice</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Capture Triggers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture a pattern when: the solution works in 2+ different contexts, solves a problem seen before, includes a non-obvious insight, or prevents a common mistake.</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit extraction at task completion, agents never capture patterns. The extraction must be built into the task completion checklist, not left as an optional afterthought.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Do capture: solutions to recurring problems, non-obvious approaches, cross-context generalizations, mistake preventers</item>
      <item>Do not capture: one-off fixes, well-known best practices (already in docs), project-specific configurations, trivial implementations</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Hierarchical Memory Architecture">
    <list>
      <item>Working memory (current task): always loaded, session scope</item>
      <item>Session memory (current feature): on-demand, conversation scope</item>
      <item>Project memory (.aidocs/memory/patterns.md): persistent, queried by relevance</item>
      <item>Global memory: permanent, cross-project — used sparingly</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Filter patterns.md by relevance to the current task domain before injecting into task context.</statement>
      <rationale>Loading all patterns into every task context wastes tokens. A payment feature task does not need auth patterns injected unless they share a mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
