<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Disagree-and-Commit Protocol Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that convert post-decision dissent into an auditable commitment with a defined revisit trigger.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Dissent MUST be recorded by named stakeholder (full name + role) with a one-sentence statement of grounds. Anonymised dissent ("some stakeholders objected") is rejected from the decision register.</statement>
      <rationale>Anonymous dissent travels and grows; named dissent is bounded and reviewable. Naming also forces the dissenter to take responsibility for the grounds, which raises the quality of objections that get logged.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Within 48 hours of the decision, the dissenting stakeholder MUST sign exactly one of: (a) `commit-with-revisit` — agrees to work the decided direction until the revisit trigger fires, or (b) `escalate-now` — invokes the named threshold owner for an immediate review. No third option ("commit but reserve the right to re-raise") is accepted.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a binary choice, "I commit, but..." becomes permission to lobby quietly. The binary forces the dissenter to either run the experiment honestly or formally escalate where the conflict can be resolved at the right level.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every `commit-with-revisit` entry MUST carry an explicit, falsifiable trigger: either a date OR a metric threshold (e.g., "revisit by 2026-09-01" OR "revisit if quarterly churn >5%"). Vague triggers ("if it doesn't work out") are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>A trigger that cannot be falsified guarantees the dissenter can re-raise at any time, which defeats the whole point. Falsifiable triggers give the team a clean signal of "experiment running, hands off" until the trigger fires.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>An `escalate-now` choice MUST be routed to the pre-named threshold owner within 5 working days, with the decision register entry attached. The PM is responsible for booking the escalation review even if the dissenter does not follow up.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-driven escalation often stalls because the dissenter has already lost political appetite; the PM closing the loop preserves the integrity of the protocol regardless. 5-day SLA prevents indefinite limbo.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Until the revisit trigger fires (for `commit-with-revisit`) or the escalation completes (for `escalate-now`), the dissenter MUST NOT lobby individual engineers, designers, or other stakeholders to alter the decision through side channels. The PM has explicit license to call out side-channel lobbying as a protocol breach.</statement>
      <rationale>Side-channel lobbying is the dominant failure mode this protocol exists to stop. Encoding "PM may call it out" as a rule shifts the social cost from the PM to the dissenter, which is what makes the protocol actually hold.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Decision: 2026-05-20 — Q3 roadmap prioritisation

## Decision
Build "team workspace" feature in Q3. Defer "API webhooks v2" to Q4.

## Dissent
- **Tomás Silva (CFO)** — grounds: "API webhooks delay risks enterprise
  renewal with Acme."
  - Choice (signed 2026-05-21): commit-with-revisit
  - Revisit trigger: "if Acme renewal at risk before 2026-08-15 OR
    weekly enterprise pipeline drops below $400k"

## Threshold owner for any escalation
Pedro Costa (VP Product)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Named dissent, binary choice signed, falsifiable trigger, threshold owner identified. Auditable artefact.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Q3 Planning Notes

We decided to do "team workspace" first. Finance had some concerns but
agreed to revisit later if needed.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Anonymised dissent ("Finance"), no signed choice, no trigger, no threshold owner. Functionally identical to no protocol at all.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
