<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Helm Chart Authoring Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the helm-charts methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="chart-yaml-v2-strict" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set apiVersion: v2, include kubeVersion, list maintainers and use SemVer 2 versioning; never publish a chart without these fields.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">v2 + kubeVersion is the gate between published charts and unusable scratch directories.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="required-template-files" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every chart MUST include templates/NOTES.txt, templates/_helpers.tpl and templates/tests/test-connection.yaml.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">NOTES + helpers + test stub is the documented minimum for a chart that survives upgrade and a CI test step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="values-schema-json" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide values.schema.json (JSON Schema draft-07) to validate user values at helm install / upgrade time.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Schema validation catches typos and missing values before they reach the cluster — orders of magnitude cheaper than runtime debugging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pinned-dependencies" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pin every dependency to an exact SemVer (never *), commit Chart.lock and gate on helm dependency update + helm lint in CI.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Wildcards break reproducible builds the day upstream cuts a major; pinned + lock is the single safe pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="values-driven-templates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All configurable values MUST be in values.yaml with comments; no hardcoded values inside templates other than constants documented in NOTES.txt.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Hard-coded values create branches in the template that cannot be overridden — defeating the chart pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
