<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Release Planning Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Cross-team release bundling, scheduling, and communication discipline (release-train cadence, readiness matrix, deprecation comms, change-control artefacts) for paying-customer products.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="release-train-cadence-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Release cadence (weekly / biweekly / monthly) MUST be fixed and published 1 quarter ahead. Ad-hoc release dates are forbidden once the train is announced.</statement>
      <rationale source="SAFe / Spotify release-train patterns">Ad-hoc dates break downstream prep; the train sets the heartbeat.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="readiness-matrix-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each release MUST publish a readiness matrix at T-7d: engineering / QA / support / sales / marketing / legal each with status (green/yellow/red). Any red blocks the release.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — release readiness audits">Without a published matrix, late-Friday surprises kill the release.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="deprecation-comms-90d-min" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Breaking changes and deprecations MUST be announced &gt;=90 days before removal. Affected customers receive direct comms plus migration tooling where feasible.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stripe / Twilio API deprecation playbooks">&lt;90 day deprecations damage trust and trigger contractual breach.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="release-notes-customer-facing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Release notes MUST be customer-facing: behaviour-change framing, not commit-log framing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Open-source / SaaS release-notes best practice">Commit-log notes degrade the customer experience.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="post-release-monitor-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each release MUST name a post-release monitor (on-call PM/eng) for T+24h with explicit rollback triggers.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE post-release ownership patterns">Hand-off ambiguity in T+24h is the most common source of slow incident response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — internal tooling; pre-PMF daily releases; one-shot launches (use launch-readiness-review); single-team product without coordination need), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
