<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Technology Stack Selection Decision Tree Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the decision-tree-tech-stack methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale; the final rule is the skip-this-methodology gate referenced by the decision tree.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-team-expertise-dominates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When team expertise in a candidate stack is concentrated (≥70% of engineers have ≥1 year hands-on), that stack MUST be the default unless a specific workload disqualifies it.</statement>
      <rationale source="ThoughtWorks Tech Radar 2024; team-velocity studies.">Hiring + ramp-up cost dwarfs language-feature differences; ignoring team expertise produces 6-12 month productivity dips.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-workload-niche-overrides-tie" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When team expertise is neutral, route by workload niche: real-time / numeric → Go / Rust, AI / data → Python, browser / SSR → TypeScript, JVM-shop / regulated → Java / Kotlin. Niche routing MUST follow r1, never override it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stack Overflow 2025 dev survey; language-by-niche capability matrix.">Each language retains a workload niche where standard-library + ecosystem alignment shortens delivery by months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-bleeding-edge-requires-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Adopting a bleeding-edge framework (&lt; 2 years GA, &lt; 1k production case studies) MUST carry an explicit risk budget (engineering weeks reserved for upstream-blocking bugs) and a fallback plan.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — bleeding-edge adoption postmortems.">Bleeding-edge frameworks burn engineering time on bugs the user community has not yet flushed out; teams without budget burn out.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-datastore-fits-data-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Datastore choice MUST follow data shape (relational entities → Postgres, document/JSON-heavy → Postgres-JSONB or Mongo, time-series → TimescaleDB / ClickHouse, vector → pgvector / Qdrant). Datastore picked for popularity instead of data shape is a defect.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — data-modelling audits.">Datastore-data-shape mismatch produces 10× query complexity and 3-5× operational cost; the data shape is the determinant.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-record-rejected-and-trigger" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stack ADR MUST list rejected alternatives with reasons, MUST include a review trigger (hiring failure rate, perf miss, ecosystem shift), and MUST be reviewed annually.</statement>
      <rationale source="MADR practice.">Without rejected-alternatives + trigger, the next architect cannot reconstruct the reasoning; review is the safety net for shifting markets.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When prerequisites hold (expertise, performance target, hiring data, ecosystem deps), walk r1 → r4 → r2 → r3 → r5 and emit the ADR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology design — gate rule.">Out-of-order evaluation produces team-incompatible picks; the order encodes risk reduction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do NOT use when (a) platform mandate exists, (b) it is a library swap inside a service, (c) the project is throwaway. Note the constraint and exit.</statement>
      <rationale source="Preconditions — skip gate.">Stack ceremony for constrained or short-lived choices wastes review time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
