<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Anti Roadmap Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Anti Roadmap Template application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="rationale-per-entry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every anti-roadmap entry MUST carry a one-sentence rationale citing a specific input (data, customer quote, constraint). &apos;Not now&apos; alone is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder-management research">Stakeholder-management research — anchors Anti Roadmap Template rule `rationale-per-entry`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="revisit-trigger-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each entry MUST name a revisit trigger — either a measurable threshold (&apos;revenue from segment ≥ $5k MRR&apos;) or a dated event (&apos;post-launch retrospective&apos;). Open-ended &apos;maybe later&apos; is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Falsifiability discipline">Falsifiability discipline — anchors Anti Roadmap Template rule `revisit-trigger-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sponsor-sign-off" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The anti-roadmap MUST be signed by the PM AND the top sponsoring stakeholder. Single-signature anti-roadmaps lack the political coverage they were designed to provide.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stakeholder governance">Stakeholder governance — anchors Anti Roadmap Template rule `sponsor-sign-off`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="expiration-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each entry MUST carry an expiration date (≤90 days). Past-expiration entries trigger a fresh review, not silent renewal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Anti-decay practice — anchors Anti Roadmap Template rule `expiration-date`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="paired-with-roadmap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The anti-roadmap MUST be published alongside the roadmap (same page, same review cadence). Standalone anti-roadmaps are not read.</statement>
      <rationale source="Publication-discipline research">Publication-discipline research — anchors Anti Roadmap Template rule `paired-with-roadmap`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
