<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-adhd-autism-dyslexia" title="Design Patterns for ADHD, Autism, and Dyslexia">
  <summary>Concrete design interventions for ADHD (auto-save, progress, reduced motion), autism (predictability, literal language, sensory palette), and dyslexia (typography, spacing, text-to-speech).</summary>

  <section title="ADHD-Friendly Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Auto-save all form progress every 15-30 seconds and display an explicit "All changes saved" indicator — never rely on browser memory or session state.</statement>
      <rationale>ADHD users are frequently interrupted or switch tasks mid-flow. Lost progress from distraction is the leading cause of task abandonment for this group. Auto-save to server storage (not localStorage) prevents data loss on shared devices.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Show step-and-total progress indicator on multi-step tasks (e.g., "Step 2 of 5").</item>
      <item>Provide "Save and continue later" with email magic link on any form longer than 3 steps.</item>
      <item>Respect prefers-reduced-motion: disable auto-playing animations, make carousels pauseable, offer static alternatives.</item>
      <item>Focus mode: hide non-essential UI elements and reduce notifications on demand.</item>
      <item>Remember scroll position on return to in-progress items.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-save data to localStorage without scoping to authenticated session.</description>
      <reason>Shared devices expose draft data to other users. Scope auto-save to the authenticated user's server-side session.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Autism-Friendly Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use only literal language in UI copy — no idioms, no metaphors, no ambiguous phrases. Pair every icon with a text label.</statement>
      <rationale>Autistic users often process language literally. Icons without labels are ambiguous for autism and aphasia users. Idiomatic error messages ("Something went wrong") convey no actionable information.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Piece of cake!" (ambiguous success message)
"Click here" (where is here?)
"Think outside the box" (non-literal instruction)
"Something went wrong" (no actionable guidance)
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Your file was saved."
"Submit your application"
"Consider alternative solutions"
"Your payment failed. Please check your card number and try again."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <list>
      <item>Consistent button and navigation placement across all pages — same action always in the same position.</item>
      <item>No unexpected popups or auto-redirects without user confirmation.</item>
      <item>Clear visual boundaries between sections (defined borders, whitespace).</item>
      <item>Show a "You will leave this page" warning before external links or session changes.</item>
      <item>Sensory-friendly color palettes: muted, no harsh color combinations; provide high-contrast mode as opt-in.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dyslexia-Friendly Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use left-aligned, sans-serif body text at minimum 16px with at least 1.5 line-height, 0.12em letter-spacing, and no justified alignment.</statement>
      <rationale>Justified text creates variable word spacing ("rivers") that disrupts tracking for dyslexic readers. Ragged right edges and extra spacing reduce word reversal errors and improve reading speed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="css"><![CDATA[
/* Dyslexia-friendly typography */
body {
  font-family: Arial, Verdana, sans-serif; /* clean sans-serif */
  font-size: 16px;
  line-height: 1.5;
  letter-spacing: 0.12em;
  word-spacing: 0.16em;
  text-align: left; /* never justify */
}

p {
  max-width: 70ch; /* optimal line length */
  margin-bottom: 2em;
}
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <list>
      <item>Avoid serif and decorative fonts for body text.</item>
      <item>OpenDyslexic font as opt-in (not forced — preference varies; some studies show no universal benefit).</item>
      <item>High contrast: black on white or cream/beige; never gray-on-gray.</item>
      <item>Text-to-speech: built-in read-aloud with synchronized text highlighting and adjustable speed.</item>
      <item>Never use color alone as the only indicator of meaning.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
