<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="cognitive-inclusion-design Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for cognitive-inclusion-design. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto-save all form progress every 15-30 seconds and display an explicit "All changes saved" indicator — never rely on browser memory or session state.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">ADHD users are frequently interrupted or switch tasks mid-flow. Lost progress from distraction is the leading cause of task abandonment for this group. Auto-save to server storage (not localStorage) prevents data loss on shared devices.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use only literal language in UI copy — no idioms, no metaphors, no ambiguous phrases. Pair every icon with a text label.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Autistic users often process language literally. Icons without labels are ambiguous for autism and aphasia users. Idiomatic error messages ("Something went wrong") convey no actionable information.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use left-aligned, sans-serif body text at minimum 16px with at least 1.5 line-height, 0.12em letter-spacing, and no justified alignment.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Justified text creates variable word spacing ("rivers") that disrupts tracking for dyslexic readers. Ragged right edges and extra spacing reduce word reversal errors and improve reading speed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use inline validation with positive confirmation — never wait until form submit to reveal all errors at once, and never use blaming language in error messages.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Submit-time error dumps overwhelm anxious users. Blame-language ("You entered an invalid value") triggers avoidance. Immediate, calm, actionable feedback reduces cognitive load and builds trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Test readability with textstat (Flesch &gt;= 60) and vale (Microsoft Writing Style) in CI; test copy with alex for insensitive or blame language.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual copy review is inconsistent; automated gates catch most instances of jargon, over-complexity, and blaming language before they reach production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include at least one moderated testing session with neurodiverse participants (ADHD, autism, dyslexia, anxiety) per major release; automated tools cannot substitute for real cognitive usability testing.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cognitive inclusion cannot be fully verified by code analysis. Flesch scores miss domain jargon. "Sensory-friendly" palette choices vary by individual. Real user testing reveals the actual burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
