<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-anxiety-and-checklists" title="Anxiety-Friendly Design, Learning Support, and Implementation Checklist">
  <summary>Design patterns for anxiety and learning disabilities, a comprehensive implementation checklist, and user testing guidance for neurodiverse panels.</summary>

  <section title="Anxiety-Friendly Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use inline validation with positive confirmation — never wait until form submit to reveal all errors at once, and never use blaming language in error messages.</statement>
      <rationale>Submit-time error dumps overwhelm anxious users. Blame-language ("You entered an invalid value") triggers avoidance. Immediate, calm, actionable feedback reduces cognitive load and builds trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"You failed to enter a valid email address."
"Error: Invalid input detected."
"Your session has expired. All data lost."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Please enter a valid email, for example: name@example.com"
"Your draft was saved. You can continue later."
"Your password is strong."
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <list>
      <item>Provide undo functionality and confirmation before any destructive action.</item>
      <item>Show progress and completion indicators ("You're almost done! Step 4 of 5").</item>
      <item>Include obvious "Cancel" or "Go back" buttons — no dead ends or traps.</item>
      <item>Breadcrumb navigation so users always know where they are and how to go back.</item>
      <item>Avoid overcrowding choices — chunk options into groups of 5-7 maximum.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Over-apologetic copy: "We're so sorry this happened!" on every error.</description>
      <reason>Excessive apology language is itself anxiety-inducing for many users; aim for calm, neutral, factual tone.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Learning Disability Support">
    <list>
      <item>Multi-modal content: text + images + video; audio alternatives to reading; visual diagrams for concepts.</item>
      <item>Scaffolding: break complex tasks into numbered simple steps; provide worked examples and templates.</item>
      <item>Flexible pacing: no time limits on learning; unlimited task repetition; progress saved automatically.</item>
      <item>Hints and tips available on demand without cluttering the main UI.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Implementation Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Test readability with textstat (Flesch >= 60) and vale (Microsoft Writing Style) in CI; test copy with alex for insensitive or blame language.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual copy review is inconsistent; automated gates catch most instances of jargon, over-complexity, and blaming language before they reach production.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/readability-gate.py">Python CI script failing the build if Flesch reading ease falls below 60 for any UI string</reference>
    <list>
      <item>Content: heading hierarchy; short paragraphs (3-4 sentences max); bullet points for lists; visual breaks; plain language.</item>
      <item>Interaction: predictable navigation; consistent patterns; auto-save; undo/redo; confirmation for destructive actions.</item>
      <item>Visual: adequate spacing; readable fonts (16px minimum); high contrast; color not sole indicator; reduced-motion option; visible focus.</item>
      <item>Timing: no time limits or adjustable; timeout warnings; auto-save prevents data loss; pauseable media.</item>
      <item>Feedback: non-blaming error messages; positive reinforcement; progress indicators; loading states; success confirmations.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Testing with Neurodiverse Users">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include at least one moderated testing session with neurodiverse participants (ADHD, autism, dyslexia, anxiety) per major release; automated tools cannot substitute for real cognitive usability testing.</statement>
      <rationale>Cognitive inclusion cannot be fully verified by code analysis. Flesch scores miss domain jargon. "Sensory-friendly" palette choices vary by individual. Real user testing reveals the actual burden.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Test metrics: task completion rate, error rate, time on task, user confidence, stress (self-reported).</item>
      <item>Recruiting: Fable, UserTesting with neurodiverse screener filters, community organizations.</item>
      <item>Dyslexia font swap (OpenDyslexic) must be opt-in — offer as a user preference, not as the default.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
