<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="agile-ba-frameworks">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>Maps BA competencies to agile frameworks (Scrum, SAFe, Disciplined Agile, IIBA Agile Extension) so an analyst can choose a canonical framework, audit adherence against the IIBA seven principles, and generate a framework-fit report.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>framework</tag>
      <tag>ba</tag>
      <tag>scrum</tag>
      <tag>safe</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Agile BA Frameworks</title>

    <summary>Maps BA competencies to agile frameworks (Scrum, SAFe, Disciplined Agile, IIBA Agile Extension) so an analyst can choose a canonical framework, audit adherence against the IIBA seven principles, and generate a framework-fit report. Distinct from the operational sprint-cadence BA work; this layer covers framework selection and constitution-level decisions.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>71% of BAs practice agile yet scaled agile frameworks do not define an explicit BA role. Without a principled framework selection, teams conflate ceremonies with practices and organisations repeatedly litigate the same "where does the BA fit?" question. IIBA Agile Extension v2's seven principles provide an auditable checklist; Disciplined Agile supplies lifecycle-choice tooling; both are testable against project evidence.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Picking an agile BA framework for a new initiative before the team commits to Scrum/SAFe/DA.</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing delivery against IIBA Agile Extension's seven principles to produce a gap report.</item>
        <item>Mapping BABOK v3 knowledge areas onto an agile horizon when a BA function migrates from waterfall.</item>
        <item>Choosing between Disciplined Agile lifecycles using the DA "Way of Working" decision tree.</item>
        <item>Writing a constitution or playbook section that codifies "how we do agile BA" with official source references.</item>
        <item>Preparing IIBA Agile Analysis Certification (AAC) study material or competency self-assessment.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Day-to-day backlog refinement and sprint-cadence artifact generation — use the business-analyst variant.</item>
        <item>Single-team Scrum with no scaling concern and no regulatory traceability need — overhead is not justified.</item>
        <item>Greenfield product discovery — use continuous-discovery, user-story-mapping, strategy-analysis instead.</item>
        <item>Non-software domains (marketing ops, HR change) — frameworks lean software; misapplied vocabulary creates false precision.</item>
        <item>Pure tooling questions (Jira API, Linear webhooks) — frameworks here are vendor-neutral.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="ba-in-scrum">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assign specific BA deliverables to each Scrum phase; do not treat BA work as a single undifferentiated "refinement" activity.</statement>
        <rationale>BA activities that are not assigned to a ceremony are skipped or performed ad-hoc, causing acceptance-criteria defects to surface only at Sprint Review.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="BA activities mapped to Scrum ceremonies">
        <note>Sprint 0: vision, roadmap, initial backlog creation. Refinement: user story elaboration, acceptance criteria, models. Planning: story clarification, dependency identification. Execution: ad-hoc clarification under 30 min response target. Review: solution validation, feedback capture. Retrospective: BA process improvement.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ba-in-safe">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Map the BA role to the SAFe level before the PI Planning ceremony; do not assume a single BA role covers all levels.</statement>
        <rationale>SAFe does not define an explicit BA role; without explicit mapping the BA defaults to Team Level tasks even when the initiative requires Program or Portfolio BA work.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="BA role mapping across SAFe levels">
        <note>Team Level: Product Owner duties — user stories, acceptance criteria, backlog management. Program Level: Senior BA / System Architect — domain modeling, feature analysis, dependency analysis. Large Solution: Solution Analyst — cross-ART coordination, capability definition. Portfolio Level: Enterprise BA — portfolio backlog grooming, strategic alignment.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="five-key-ba-responsibilities">
      <list>
        <item>Bridge business and IT: translate business needs to technical requirements.</item>
        <item>Facilitate communication: enable collaboration among stakeholders across cadences.</item>
        <item>Prioritize by value: support value-based feature prioritization at each level.</item>
        <item>Define vision and roadmap: support Product Management in strategic direction.</item>
        <item>Ensure alignment: verify agile delivery aligns with business goals at each PI.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agile-ba-techniques">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select agile BA technique by purpose, not by familiarity; each technique has a distinct trigger.</statement>
        <rationale>Using a single technique (e.g. user stories) for all purposes leaves discovery gaps that surface as missed requirements after Sprint Review.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Agile BA techniques and their purpose">
        <note>User Story Mapping: release planning, feature prioritization. Example Mapping: acceptance criteria clarification. Story Splitting: breaking epics into implementable stories. Impact Mapping: connecting features to business goals. Event Storming: domain discovery and process modeling.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="iiba-agile-extension-principles">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Score each of the seven IIBA Agile Extension principles with a quoted evidence line; reject any score row that lacks an evidence quote.</statement>
        <rationale>Principle scoring without evidence reduces to opinion; only cited artefacts survive a CCBA/CBAP audit and provide actionable gap data.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>See the Whole</item>
        <item>Think as a Customer</item>
        <item>Analyze to Determine What is Valuable</item>
        <item>Get Real Using Examples</item>
        <item>Understand What is Doable</item>
        <item>Stimulate Collaboration and Continuous Improvement</item>
        <item>Avoid Waste</item>
      </list>

      <example type="bad" title="Scoring without evidence">
        <note>Scoring "Principle 4: 4/5" with no quoted evidence. Agents routinely produce scores without source anchors, making the audit unverifiable.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="framework-comparison">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Choose one canonical framework as the anchor and label techniques borrowed from others explicitly; do not mix IIBA AE + DA + SAFe vocabulary without declaring the anchor.</statement>
        <rationale>Mixed vocabulary creates false precision and forces future BAs to relitigate framework choices every sprint.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Framework selection by team scale">
        <note>IIBA Agile Extension: scope single team to 2-3 teams, low adoption cost, principles-based. Disciplined Agile: mid-org mixed cadences, 6 lifecycle options, explicit BA roles. SAFe: large enterprise 50+ people, highest adoption cost, strongest scaling guidance. Do not propose SAFe for teams under 50 people.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating ceremony coverage as principle adherence — "we run stand-ups therefore we Stimulate Collaboration."</description>
        <reason>Ceremonies are necessary but not sufficient; principle adherence requires evidence of behaviour change, not attendance records.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="disciplined-agile-lifecycle-selection">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select a single DA primary lifecycle and at most one alternative; reject "all lifecycles apply" outputs.</statement>
        <rationale>DA documents 6 lifecycles; an agent given all options will select all, making the choice useless for team planning.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Agile — iterative, team-scoped, low process weight.</item>
        <item>Lean — flow-optimised, WIP-limited, continuous improvement.</item>
        <item>Continuous Delivery: Agile — CD pipeline required, assumes mature DevOps.</item>
        <item>Continuous Delivery: Lean — CD + Lean, highest DevOps maturity bar.</item>
        <item>Exploratory — R&amp;D, proof-of-concept, unknown solution space.</item>
        <item>Program — multi-team coordination, large solution scope.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="framework-fit-agent-workflow">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run the framework fit as a knowledge-retrieval and synthesis pipeline, not a periodic cron; trigger is one-shot on initiative setup or after a major team/scope change.</statement>
        <rationale>Framework choices are not daily tasks; automating them on a schedule produces stale recommendations that erode trust in the analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Step 1: Ingest team state (constitution, roadmap, sample backlog, retro notes, regulatory profile).</item>
        <item>Step 2: Score IIBA AE seven principles (1-5, with one quoted evidence line per score).</item>
        <item>Step 3: Run DA lifecycle fit scoring against team context dimensions (size, DevOps maturity, discovery maturity).</item>
        <item>Step 4: Emit framework-fit.md: primary framework, secondary alternative, top 3 principle gaps with concrete remediation actions.</item>
        <item>Step 5: Hand off operational work (story refinement, AC generation) to the business-analyst variant agent.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pin framework versions in the constitution; refresh the framework-fit report after major team or scope changes.</statement>
        <rationale>Without version pins, agent output drifts as upstream content updates; without refresh triggers, recommendations become stale after M&amp;A, new regulatory load, or team size doubling.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pin framework versions in the constitution. "IIBA Agile Extension v2 (2017), Disciplined Agile via PMI Browser as of &lt;quarter&gt;." Without pin, agent output drifts as upstream content updates.</item>
        <item>Treat the seven IIBA principles as audit checklist, not aspiration. Score quarterly with quoted evidence; principle scores &lt; 3 become explicit backlog items, not "we'll do better."</item>
        <item>Choose one canonical framework, supplement with techniques from others. Mixing DA + SAFe + IIBA AE without an anchor produces vocabulary chaos. Pick the anchor, label the borrowed techniques.</item>
        <item>Cite primary sources, never blog summaries. Agents trained on aggregator content reproduce errors. Prompt explicitly: "cite IIBA, PMI, Scaled Agile only."</item>
        <item>Decouple framework selection from tooling selection. Choosing DA does not pick Jira; choosing Linear does not pick Scrum. Agents that conflate them produce false constraints.</item>
        <item>Run principle audit before framework switch, not after. Switching frameworks to fix a principle gap usually fails — the gap is cultural. Address principles first; framework follows.</item>
        <item>Document explicit non-adoptions. "We do not adopt SAFe Portfolio level — we have one product." Saves future agents from re-litigating.</item>
        <item>Refresh the framework-fit report after major team or scope changes. Triggers: team size doubles, new regulatory load, M&amp;A, new product line.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hallucinated DA process goals.</description>
        <reason>Disciplined Agile has ~24 process goals; agents under context pressure invent plausible-sounding extras. Force the agent to enumerate from a vetted list — fail closed if it can't.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>BABOK v3 quoted into agile contexts verbatim.</description>
        <reason>Knowledge-area definitions are waterfall-tinted; quoting them as agile guidance misleads. Always cross-reference with the Agile Extension first.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Principle scoring without evidence quotes.</description>
        <reason>Models hand back "Principle 4: 4/5" with no quote. Reject any score row missing a quoted source line.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>SAFe-as-framework confusion.</description>
        <reason>Agents pattern-match on "agile + scaling" → SAFe regardless of fit. Add a guard: "if team &lt; 50 people, do not propose SAFe."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>DA lifecycle proliferation.</description>
        <reason>When given 6 lifecycle options the agent picks "all of them apply" — useless. Force a single primary + at most one alternative.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>AAC competency drift.</description>
        <reason>Agents reproduce 2017 competency wording in 2025 contexts. Pin the AAC version in system prompt or grading is dated.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vendor bias.</description>
        <reason>Anthropic-trained models lean toward Atlassian / SAFe content (over-represented online). When asked about DA or IIBA, output is thinner — boost via explicit reference packs.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-edits to constitution.md.</description>
        <reason>Constitution is the single source of truth; agent must propose diffs, never write directly. Always review-then-merge.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Citation of paywalled IIBA / PMI content.</description>
        <reason>Some agents quote BABOK passages verbatim. License risk. Restrict to summary + URL; never inline long quotes.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Confusing Disciplined Agile (PMI) with Disciplined Agile Delivery (Scott Ambler, pre-2019).</description>
        <reason>Different scope, different vocabulary. Pin the post-2019 PMI version unless explicitly using the legacy material.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/framework-fit.md" purpose="Framework comparison matrix and IIBA seven-principles scorecard skeleton."/>
      <template path="templates/sprint-ba-activities.md" purpose="Per-ceremony BA activity checklist for Scrum sprints."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/agile-extension/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/career-resources/a-business-analysis-professionals-foundation-for-success/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/business-analysis-certifications/agile-analysis-certification/"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/disciplined-agile/da-browser"/>
      <link href="https://framework.scaledagile.com"/>
      <link href="https://scrumguides.org/scrum-guide.html"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
