<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="user-story-mapping">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Two-dimensional arrangement of user stories along journey (activities → tasks) and priority (essential → nice-to-have) axes, enabling slice-based release planning and stakeholder alignment.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>user-stories</tag>
      <tag>story-mapping</tag>
      <tag>release-planning</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>babok</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>requirements</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>User Story Mapping</title>

    <summary>A two-dimensional arrangement of user stories along a horizontal user-journey axis (activities → tasks) and a vertical priority axis (essential → nice-to-have), producing a story map that reveals the complete user experience and enables slice-based release planning. The BA owns scope definition: turning the map into formal artifacts (BRD, BPMN, traceability matrix, JIRA epics).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Flat backlogs lose journey context, making release planning a guessing game. Story mapping surfaces the walking skeleton — the thinnest vertical slice that delivers a coherent end-to-end experience — and lets a mixed business/IT audience agree on release scope using a single shared artifact. BABOK v3 §10.46 names it as the canonical technique for linking stories to process steps and traceability.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Sprint-zero or pre-discovery session where the BA must convert a fuzzy idea into a stakeholder-signed release plan.</item>
        <item>Brownfield project with a flat 200+ ticket backlog needing journey context before re-prioritization.</item>
        <item>Compliance/regulated project where each story must trace to a process step, regulation clause, and acceptance criterion.</item>
        <item>Vendor migration: the existing journey is the backbone, gap analysis fills the cells.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder alignment with mixed business + IT audience who need to agree on a release slice.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Maintenance backlog of isolated bug fixes and tech debt — no journey, use WSJF or RICE instead.</item>
        <item>Pure API/platform product with no end-user persona — model with C4 + use cases.</item>
        <item>Team already on a stable release cadence with a healthy backlog and clear roadmap — rebuilding the map is sunk cost.</item>
        <item>One-off internal automation (single user, single happy path) — a 5-step checklist beats a wall map.</item>
        <item>Stakeholders cannot commit 2-4 contiguous hours — a half-attended map produces false consensus.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="framework">
      <p>The backbone is the sequence of user Activities (coarse-grained goals). Under each Activity sit Tasks (specific interactions). Under each Task stack Stories (user story cards) ordered by priority. Horizontal lines drawn across the full map define release boundaries.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Arrange user stories along two axes: horizontal = user journey (activities then tasks), vertical = priority (essential at top, nice-to-have at bottom).</statement>
        <rationale>A flat backlog has no journey context, making release planning impossible. The two-axis structure reveals the walking skeleton — the thinnest complete slice — and lets any stakeholder see what each release delivers end-to-end.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="five-step-procedure">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Complete all five steps in order; skipping Step 4 (vertical priority ordering) before Step 5 (release slicing) produces release lines with no coherent narrative.</statement>
          <rationale>BABOK v3 §10.46 requires the map to represent a complete user experience before slicing; partial maps yield partial release value and false sign-off.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Step 1 — Identify User Activities: map high-level goals in user-journey sequence (e.g., Browse → Select → Purchase → Track → Return).</item>
          <item>Step 2 — Break Down into Tasks: for each Activity, list specific interactions the user performs (e.g., Purchase → Add to cart, Enter shipping, Enter payment, Confirm order).</item>
          <item>Step 3 — Write User Stories: for each Task, write stories using "As a [persona], I want [goal] so that [benefit]" format.</item>
          <item>Step 4 — Arrange Vertically by Priority: top = essential for minimum viable experience; bottom = nice-to-have.</item>
          <item>Step 5 — Slice into Releases: draw horizontal lines to define Release 1 (walking skeleton), Release 2 (enhancements), Release 3 (polish).</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="release-slicing">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Release 1 must deliver a complete user journey (thin vertical slice through all activities), not a complete implementation of one activity.</statement>
          <rationale>A release that completes one activity fully but leaves other activities with no coverage cannot be user-tested end-to-end; the walking-skeleton check fails.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Horizontal slice — cut off entire activities when activities are independent (rarely the right choice for Release 1).</item>
          <item>Vertical slice — thin cut through all activities delivering minimum viability (correct approach for MVP).</item>
          <item>Mixed — combination; most common in practice.</item>
        </list>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Walk the Release-1 line vertically with a real user or surrogate before sign-off: read each cell as a contiguous narrative. If it does not form a coherent story, the slice is wrong.</statement>
          <rationale>Jeff Patton's walking-skeleton check is the concrete test for release-1 coherence; narrative breakdown reveals missing tasks, not missing stories.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="ba-artifact-translation">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Convert each story map cell to formal BA artifacts: BRD section (problem, scope, AC), BPMN participant + task, RTM row (story_id, requirement_id, process_step, test_case_id).</statement>
          <rationale>BABOK treats the map as input to Requirements Analysis and Design Definition (KA 5); without artifact translation the map is a workshop souvenir, not a BA deliverable.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Tag every story cell with persona_id and process_step_id at write time; retrofitting traceability after the workshop is the single biggest time sink in BA delivery.</statement>
          <rationale>Without source tagging, the RTM must be reconstructed from memory — a lossy and slow process that delays sign-off.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Capturing non-functional requirements (performance, security, accessibility, audit) as story map cells.</description>
        <reason>NFRs have no natural cell on the map and are routinely dropped in the vertical-slice mentality. Capture them in a parallel NFR register linked to the map header; review per release slice, not per cell.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating a single-axis prioritized backlog as a story map.</description>
        <reason>A list with no horizontal journey axis loses the context that explains why stories exist; BAs cannot trace them to process steps or write a coherent RTM.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="workshop">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require all five participant roles in the workshop: Product Owner, Business Analyst, Developer, UX Designer, and at least one key stakeholder; refuse to proceed if the decision-maker is absent.</statement>
        <rationale>A half-attended map produces false consensus — absent stakeholders discover the release plan only at review, triggering scope changes that invalidate the map's value.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Duration: 2-4 hours for a complete map; break into two sessions if scope exceeds 5 activities.</item>
        <item>Materials: large wall or whiteboard, sticky notes in 3 colors (activities/tasks/stories), markers.</item>
        <item>Agenda: personas + goals (15 min) → backbone activities (30 min) → tasks (30 min) → stories (60 min) → vertical prioritization (30 min) → release slices (30 min).</item>
      </list>

      <section name="common-mistakes">
        <antipattern>
          <description>Flat backlog — stories written without journey context.</description>
          <reason>No horizontal axis means no way to detect missing tasks or trace requirements to process steps.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Technical stories on the map ("As a system, I want to batch-process orders").</description>
          <reason>INVEST requires user perspective; technical stories belong in a separate architectural backlog, not the story map.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>No release lines defined — map becomes a prioritized list.</description>
          <reason>Without horizontal slice boundaries, the team has no commitment to what ships together and cannot plan iterations.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Capturing exception/unhappy paths only implicitly.</description>
          <reason>Workshops optimize the happy path; add a red-sticky row for exception paths below each task band so they are visible, not forgotten.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>

      <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A BA-led story-mapping engagement maps cleanly to a 4-stage subagent pipeline: (1) elicitation prep — research stakeholders, prior artifacts, regulations; (2) workshop facilitation — structured prompts to extract activities/tasks/stories live, BA validates; (3) artifact translation — convert the map into BRD sections, BPMN, traceability matrix, JIRA epics; (4) validation loop — run an LLM critic over each story for INVEST + AC completeness, then a human BA sign-off.</p>

        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Run story mapping as a four-stage subagent pipeline: elicitation prep → workshop facilitation → artifact translation → validation loop.</statement>
          <rationale>Each stage requires different model capabilities (research, structured elicitation, formatting, critique); a single prompt produces weaker output than staged handoffs.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Do not let the agent decide release boundaries; slicing is a business and risk decision. Lock the agent to "suggest releases" mode, never "commit releases".</statement>
          <rationale>Release boundaries require authority the agent does not have; auto-committed slices bypass stakeholder sign-off and invalidate the validation loop.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>After story generation, run an INVEST critic pass: reject stories that are too large (epic in disguise) or non-independent ("as a system").</statement>
          <rationale>LLMs produce stories that pass a superficial format check but violate INVEST; an explicit critic pass before BA acceptance catches these failures cheaply.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <example type="good" title="Facilitation prompt pattern">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are a BABOK-aligned BA facilitator. Persona pack: {personas}.
Current backbone: {activities}. We are decomposing activity "{a}" into tasks.
Ask 3 elicitation questions targeting the persona's goal, constraints, and
exception path. Output JSON: {questions: [], suggested_tasks: []}.
No prose. No invented tasks not grounded in a question.]]></code>
          <note>Constraints the agent to grounded output only.</note>
        </example>

        <example type="good" title="Translation prompt">
          <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Input: story-map.json (activities, tasks, stories, releases).
For each Release-1 story emit: BRD section (problem, scope, AC), BPMN
participant + task, RTM row (story_id, requirement_id, process_step,
test_case_id). Flag any story missing AC or persona reference.
Output strict JSON matching schema {brd, bpmn, rtm, gaps}.]]></code>
          <note>Enforces full BA artifact output with gap detection.</note>
        </example>

        <section name="agent-gotchas">
          <p>LLMs invent activities to fill obvious-looking gaps in a journey. Constrain the facilitator agent: "only emit activities grounded in a stakeholder quote or prior artifact"; require source citation per node.</p>
          <p>Story generation drifts from INVEST: agents produce stories that are too large (epics in disguise) or technical ("As a system, I want…"). Run an INVEST critic pass with a strict checklist before accepting any agent output.</p>
          <p>Acceptance criteria from LLMs default to happy-path Given/When/Then. Force a structured prompt: "emit ≥1 happy, ≥1 alternate, ≥1 error AC; cite the persona's exception scenario from elicitation".</p>
          <p>Map JSON schemas drift between tools (Miro, Jira, FeatMap). Pin one canonical schema in your repo; convert on the boundary. Otherwise downstream BRD/RTM renderers break silently.</p>
          <p>Persona leakage: agents conflate personas across stories ("As a user…"). Enforce a persona_id enum in the schema and reject stories without it.</p>
          <p>Token blow-up on large maps (200+ stories). Render BRD per activity, not per map; chunk the agent input to one activity at a time and concatenate.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
        <p>The map is a snapshot. Without a discipline of re-mapping every release, it diverges from reality within approximately 6 weeks.</p>
        <p>Vertical "priority" axis collapses MoSCoW + value + risk + sequencing into one column — BAs frequently lose the why behind the order. Keep a separate prioritization matrix.</p>
        <p>LLMs hallucinate plausible-but-fake user activities when the persona is thin. The walking-skeleton check (can a real user complete the flow end-to-end?) breaks if the map was written from imagination.</p>
        <p>Cross-functional (B2B2C, marketplace, multi-actor) journeys do not fit a single backbone. You need swimlane variants per persona, which most tools do not render cleanly.</p>
        <p>Non-functional requirements (performance, security, accessibility, audit) have no natural cell on the map and routinely get dropped — they must be captured in a parallel NFR register.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="human-in-the-loop-checkpoints">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Enforce four mandatory human checkpoints: backbone approval before tasks, Release-1 slice approval before stories, BRD+RTM diff review before publication, NFR register review before sign-off.</statement>
          <rationale>Each checkpoint prevents downstream artifact cascades from building on a flawed foundation; skipping any one checkpoint increases rework cost by at least one stage.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Run a pre-mortem in the first 15 minutes: ask "what would make this map useless in 3 months?". Capture answers as risks; assign owners. Maps die from neglect, not from bad structure.</p>
      <p>Keep two priority axes, not one: vertical = release slice, color/badge = MoSCoW. Single-axis maps lose the regulatory "must" stories under "nice-to-haves" the loudest stakeholder pushed up.</p>
      <p>The BA, not the PO, owns the persona pack going into the workshop. If personas are not validated against real research (≥5 interviews per persona), the map is fiction — flag this in the BRD assumptions section.</p>
      <p>Tag every story cell with persona_id + process_step_id at write time. Retrofitting this for the RTM after the workshop is the single biggest time sink in BA delivery.</p>
      <p>Capture the exception/unhappy paths on a separate row band below the main tasks — same activities, red stickies. Workshops chronically optimize the happy path and ship products that fail under real conditions.</p>
      <p>Walk the Release-1 line vertically with a real user (or surrogate) before sign-off: read each cell aloud as a contiguous narrative. If it does not form a coherent story, the slice is wrong, not the stories.</p>
      <p>Park NFRs (perf, sec, a11y, audit) in a sidebar register linked to the map header; review them per release slice, not per cell.</p>
      <p>Version the map JSON in git alongside the BRD. The diff between v1 and v2 is the change request.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>Tools for rendering and managing story maps include featmap-cli (headless story-map render to SVG/JSON), storiesonboard-api (read/write StoriesOnBoard maps via REST), jira-cli (push map cells as Epics/Stories with parent links), bpmn-js-cli (convert task list to BPMN 2.0 XML headless), python-docx + Jinja2 (BRD/SRS rendering from map JSON), mermaid-cli (render journey diagrams from map backbone), and pandoc (map markdown to DOCX/PDF stakeholder package).</p>
      <p>SaaS and OSS platforms include StoriesOnBoard (purpose-built for story mapping, REST API + webhook, Jira sync), FeatMap (lightweight OSS, JSON export, self-host), Avion (strong UX for live workshops, Jira sync), Miro (most common in workshops, REST API, sticky-note granularity), Mural (better outline to map conversion, REST API + OAuth), Jira + Easy Agile User Story Maps (map lives inside Jira, BA's RTM source of truth), Azure DevOps + Delivery Plans (common in regulated enterprises, REST API), Lucidchart / Lucidspark (useful when map to BPMN conversion is required, REST API), and Confluence (where the BRD + RTM end up, REST API).</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/story-map.md" purpose="Story map document template with backbone, walking skeleton, and per-activity release tables."/>
      <template path="templates/user-story.md" purpose="User story template with Given/When/Then acceptance criteria structure."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.jeffpatton.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/babok/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
