<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-token-structure" title="Design Token Structure and Types">
  <summary>Three-tier token architecture (primitive, semantic, component) with W3C DTCG JSON schema and benefits of single-source-of-truth token management.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Tier Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Organize tokens in exactly three tiers: primitive (raw values) → semantic (purpose-named aliases) → component (component-scoped). Components must reference only semantic tokens, never primitive tokens directly.</statement>
      <rationale>Components that reference primitive tokens (e.g., color.blue.500) make dark-mode and theme swaps impossible without touching every component. Semantic layer is the indirection point that makes theming work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Tier Definitions">
      <p>Primitive: raw values with no semantic meaning. Examples: color.blue.500 = #3B82F6, spacing.4 = 16px. These are the only tier that ever contains actual values.</p>
      <p>Semantic: aliases that give meaning to primitives. Examples: color.text.default references color.gray.900; color.surface.primary references color.white. Names express purpose, not appearance.</p>
      <p>Component: aliases scoped to a specific component. Examples: button.background references color.surface.primary; card.padding references spacing.md. Generate only for components that actually need them.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="W3C DTCG JSON Schema">
      <p>Emit tokens in W3C Design Tokens Community Group format. Each token uses $value (not value) and $type. References use {token.path} syntax.</p>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="json"><![CDATA[{
  "color": {
    "gray": {
      "900": { "$value": "#111827", "$type": "color" }
    },
    "text": {
      "default": { "$value": "{color.gray.900}", "$type": "color", "$description": "Default body text" },
      "muted": { "$value": "{color.gray.600}", "$type": "color" }
    }
  },
  "spacing": {
    "xs": { "$value": "4px", "$type": "dimension" },
    "sm": { "$value": "8px", "$type": "dimension" },
    "md": { "$value": "16px", "$type": "dimension" }
  }
}]]></code>
        <note>Uses $value and $type per current DTCG spec. Semantic tokens reference primitives via {path} syntax.</note>
      </example>
      <reference path="templates/tokens-skeleton.json">Full 3-tier token skeleton</reference>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Benefits">
    <p>Consistency: identical values across web, iOS, Android, visionOS from a single JSON source. Scalability: update once, regenerate all platform outputs via Style Dictionary. Theming: dark/light/high-contrast modes require only semantic-layer overrides, no component changes. Maintenance: single source of truth with a publishable changelog. Collaboration: shared naming vocabulary eliminates designer-developer value drift.</p>
  </section>
</text>
