<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules-and-antipatterns" title="Token Rules, Antipatterns, and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Naming rules, contrast-pairing rule, depth limit, known antipatterns, and agentic workflow guidance for design token systems.</summary>

  <section title="Core Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name semantic tokens by purpose, not appearance. Use color.text.muted, not color.gray.600.</statement>
      <rationale>Appearance-based names make theming impossible — color.gray.600 cannot be a dark-mode override because the name describes the light-mode hue. Purpose-based names survive theme changes because the purpose stays constant.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every semantic foreground token with its background token. Lint every text/background pair for WCAG 2.2 AA contrast (4.5:1 for normal text, 3:1 for large text) in CI.</statement>
      <rationale>Contrast violations are the most common accessibility failure in design systems. Catching them at token-generation time costs seconds; catching them in a11y audit costs sprints.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Limit token nesting depth to four levels maximum (e.g., color.button.primary.hover). Enforce in CI.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs generate tokens with 6–8 nesting levels (color.button.primary.hover.background.disabled). At that depth, naming collapses — no human can find any token in a library of 1,500+ without semantic search.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Treat token rename as a breaking change. Version token packages with SemVer. Ship a migration codemod with every rename.</statement>
      <rationale>Consumers depend on token name stability. A silent rename of color.text.default to color.text.primary breaks every downstream consumer silently — CSS variables go undefined, not errored.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <reference path="templates/token-contrast.mjs">CI script: fail if semantic text/background pair &lt; 4.5:1</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Primitive tokens leaking into component code (e.g., color.blue.500 used in a button component directly).</description>
      <reason>Makes theming and dark mode impossible. Any change to blue.500 breaks every component referencing it unpredictably.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-generated tokens skipping the semantic layer entirely — outputting only primitive and component tiers.</description>
      <reason>Without semantic layer, theming requires editing every component token. Force 3-tier output schema in the prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-deriving dark theme algorithmically from light theme.</description>
      <reason>Algorithmic inversion produces poor contrast and violates accessibility requirements. Dark-mode semantic layer must be hand-tuned and contrast-validated.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Cross-platform output emitting px values for iOS (expects pt) or Android (expects dp/sp).</description>
      <reason>LLMs paste px everywhere without transforms. Style Dictionary must declare unit transforms per platform or assets render at wrong sizes on mobile.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agents can: (a) generate initial 3-tier token JSON from a design brief, (b) lint token files for naming and reference-cycle violations, (c) generate platform outputs (CSS variables, iOS/Android resources, Tailwind config) via Style Dictionary, (d) audit existing CSS for hardcoded values to tokenize. Human review for naming and the semantic layer is mandatory — names outlive the codebase.</p>

    <p>Gotchas: W3C DTCG schema uses $value, not value — agents may emit obsolete shape. Hex/OKLCH conversions produce subtly off colors silently — assert exact round-trip match. Generated dark themes need manual contrast verification — never accept agent-declared "accessible".</p>
  </section>
</text>
