<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="hybrid-delivery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>Combines predictive (stage-gate) and agile methods by risk profile: predictive for contracts/hardware, agile for software. Requires written boundary and translation layer for coherent governance.</summary>
    <category>delivery-model</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>hybrid</tag>
      <tag>delivery-model</tag>
      <tag>waterfall</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
      <tag>enterprise-delivery</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Hybrid Delivery</title>

    <summary>A delivery model that combines predictive (waterfall/stage-gate) and agile methods within a single program, assigning each by component risk profile. The canonical pattern: use predictive for planning, contracting, regulatory submissions, and hardware; use agile for software execution, testing, and iteration. Pure agile and pure waterfall each fail in mixed-reality programs. Hardware/software products need physical milestones alongside iterative firmware; regulated industries need gate evidence alongside fast cycles; enterprise portfolios need quarterly budget cycles alongside two-week sprints. Hybrid is not a compromise — it is an explicit, architected two-cadence model with a defined translation layer between them.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Pure agile and pure waterfall each fail in mixed-reality programs. Hardware/software products need physical milestones alongside iterative firmware; regulated industries need gate evidence alongside fast cycles; enterprise portfolios need quarterly budget cycles alongside two-week sprints. Hybrid is not a compromise — it is an explicit, architected two-cadence model with a defined translation layer between them.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Programs with hardware and software components (medical device, automotive, IoT).</item>
        <item>Regulated software (FDA, FAA, ISO 26262, SOX, GDPR) needing stage gates and V-model evidence.</item>
        <item>Enterprise transformation rollouts: portfolio level uses milestones, delivery teams use Scrum/Kanban.</item>
        <item>Vendor plus internal team mixes where vendor work is fixed-bid (predictive) and internal is iterative.</item>
        <item>Cloud platforms running DevOps + Agile for delivery while ops/finance/security gate quarterly.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure software product team with autonomous backlog and no compliance — full Scrum or Kanban is simpler.</item>
        <item>Startup with fewer than 10 people — ceremony overhead exceeds coordination value.</item>
        <item>Pure fixed-scope construction build where iteration adds risk without value — stay predictive.</item>
        <item>"We do hybrid" with no explicit written boundary — that is incoherence, not a method.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="hybrid-patterns">
      <p>Five named hybrid patterns with their applicability, a decision framework for choosing agile vs. predictive vs. hybrid, and the boundary and translation-layer rules required for coherent reporting.</p>

      <p>Five hybrid patterns:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Water-Scrum-Fall: fixed requirements (predictive) → iterative development (Scrum) → predictive deployment and ops. Use for hardware + software products.</item>
        <item>Agile with Gates: Scrum sprints run inside stage-gate approval checkpoints. Use for regulated industries (FDA, FAA, SOX).</item>
        <item>Phased Agile: large programs where multiple teams iterate within phases governed by predictive milestones. Use for enterprise rollouts.</item>
        <item>Selective Agile: some components use agile (frontend, user research), others stay predictive (backend stable, compliance). Use where components have different risk profiles.</item>
        <item>DevOps + Agile: continuous delivery on the agile arm with quarterly or annual governance checkpoints. The 2026 winning pattern for cloud platforms.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select the delivery approach by component risk profile, not by organizational preference or trend. High uncertainty + frequent change → agile; clear requirements + fixed scope → predictive; mixed characteristics → hybrid; continuous deployment needed → agile + DevOps.</statement>
        <rationale>Method dogma ("we do agile here") applied without fit analysis produces cargo-cult implementations. The framework must reflect actual project characteristics, not team culture preferences.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Draw the boundary in writing inside a program charter or program.yaml: name explicitly which deliverables are predictive (contracts, regulatory submissions, hardware BOMs, charters) and which are agile (software increments, user research, UX iterations).</statement>
        <rationale>Boundary ambiguity is the dominant hybrid failure mode. An undocumented boundary turns into a status theatre where teams argue about which method applies to any given decision.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define exactly one translation table per program: epic ↔ deliverable, story-points ↔ effort, velocity ↔ run rate. Use it for every steering report; never invent new mappings mid-program.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a fixed translation table, steering-committee reporting is inconsistent across presentations. Finance, PMO, and dev teams read the same data with incompatible vocabulary, leading to false alignment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use at most two tools with explicit sync; three or more tools is a smell requiring immediate consolidation.</statement>
        <rationale>Each additional tool adds a sync gap. Agents waste tokens reconciling disagreements between tools; humans lose trust in all data sources when tools disagree.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Match gate frequency to risk profile: monthly for regulated programs, quarterly for steady-state, never weekly (weekly gates are status meetings with a governance label).</statement>
        <rationale>Over-gating the agile arm throttles delivery frequency without commensurate risk reduction. Under-gating the predictive arm creates unbounded risk accumulation. Calibrate gates to actual decision needs.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="failure-modes">
      <p>The six most common hybrid delivery failure modes with concrete descriptions and root-cause explanations.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Boundary ambiguity — hybrid is declared but the line between agile-here and predictive-there is never written down.</description>
        <reason>Every governance decision becomes a negotiation over which method applies. Teams default to the method that benefits them locally, creating incoherence at the program level.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Dual definitions of done — agile arm calls a story "done" when it passes sprint review; predictive arm calls a deliverable "done" when a document is signed. No translation layer exists.</description>
        <reason>Steering-committee status reports are incoherent. A sprint's "80% done" and a milestone's "waiting for signature" cannot be meaningfully combined without a defined mapping.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Tool sprawl — backlog in Jira, Gantt in MS Project, deliverables in SharePoint, risks in Excel. No canonical source of truth.</description>
        <reason>Each tool sync gap creates an opportunity for data to diverge. Agents and PMs spend more time reconciling tool disagreements than managing project risk.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Governance drift — predictive arm enforces a stage gate; agile arm flies through it silently. Or agile gets gated to a quarterly cadence and loses all iteration value.</description>
        <reason>Gate frequency must match actual risk profile. Over-gating agile destroys delivery speed without risk benefit; under-gating predictive work accumulates unbounded risk.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Political compromise disguised as method — hybrid is adopted because PMO wants control and teams want autonomy, not because project characteristics require it.</description>
        <reason>Method choice must follow project fit. When hybrid is a political settlement, neither side commits to the other's discipline, producing incoherent execution with the overhead of both methods.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>EVM applied to the agile arm — SPI and CPI computed from story points multiplied by an hourly rate.</description>
        <reason>Story points are a relative sizing unit, not a labour cost measure. EVM on agile produces SPI/CPI numbers that look precise but measure nothing real. Report agile metrics in agile units; apply EVM only to the predictive arm.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <p>Model the program as a single work-graph (`program.yaml`): milestones (predictive) decompose into epics, epics into team backlogs (agile). A subagent maintains the graph, flags inconsistencies (epic past its milestone date with less than 50% issues done), and drafts gate-review packs from the underlying issue tracker. A "translation layer" agent keeps stage-gate vocabulary (deliverable, baseline, variance) reconciled with agile vocabulary (story, increment, velocity). Never let an agent unilaterally close a stage gate — gate decisions are sponsor calls.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — runs hybrid setup as SDD tasks (program charter, gate definitions, team cadence, translation layer).</item>
        <item>program-graph-curator (sonnet) — maintains `program.yaml`, syncs to Jira/Linear/MS Project, computes milestone-vs-epic alignment.</item>
        <item>gate-review-pack (sonnet) — one week before each gate, assembles deliverables list, evidence links, risk-register slice, EVM snapshot, drafts pack PR.</item>
        <item>cadence-translator (haiku) — converts agile cycle reports into predictive-arm vocabulary for steering-committee.</item>
        <item>dual-rhythm-coach (opus) — activated when team velocity diverges >25% from milestone burn; produces options memo (re-baseline, drop scope, add capacity, change cadence).</item>
        <item>password-scrubber-agent — runs over gate-review packs before distribution; predictive packs frequently leak credentials in screenshots.</item>
      </list>

      <example type="good" title="Program-graph-curator prompt pattern">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are program-graph-curator. Inputs: program.yaml (milestones, epics, team
mappings) and a JQL pull of issues by epic. For each milestone, emit STRICT
JSON: { "milestone_id": "M-NN", "due": "YYYY-MM-DD", "epics": [...],
"issues_total": N, "issues_done": N, "pct_complete": 0.NN,
"burn_status": "ahead|on|behind|at_risk",
"gate_readiness": "ready|gaps|blocked", "gaps": [...], "evidence_links": [...] }
Rules: do not invent issues. burn_status is arithmetic only. Flag any epic
with no team owner or no issues as "ORPHAN".]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Cadence translator prompt pattern">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Convert this cycle report into steering-committee predictive-arm vocabulary.
Map: story → deliverable, increment → milestone progress, velocity →
planned-vs-actual labour. Preserve dates and quantities exactly. No editorial.]]></code>
      </example>

      <p>AI-agent gotchas:</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents over-summarize hybrid programs as "behind" because they conflate vocabulary; force agile metrics in agile units, predictive metrics in predictive units.</description>
        <reason>Conflation of vocabulary leads to false rollup conclusions that miss real risks in one arm while over-focusing on the other.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLMs auto-translate epics into "deliverables" and lose information (acceptance criteria collapse to one line). Keep both views; never destroy detail.</description>
        <reason>Detail loss breaks traceability and makes it impossible to recover original requirements when the inevitably questions arise later.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Date arithmetic is unreliable across calendar conventions (work days vs. calendar days, fiscal vs. ISO weeks). Hard-code the convention in the prompt; have a tool, not the LLM, compute deltas.</description>
        <reason>LLM date math is a known failure mode; systematic errors in burn calculations cascade to wrong gate-readiness assessments.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Stage-gate "go / no-go" must never be auto-emitted — flag readiness only, leave the call to the sponsor.</description>
        <reason>Gate decisions are inherently human / sponsor decisions; auto-emission removes accountability and trains stakeholders to ignore readiness assessments.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>EVM on agile arm is a trap: agents will compute SPI/CPI from story points × hourly rate. Refuse unless the conversion is explicitly accepted by finance.</description>
        <reason>Story points × hourly rate is not earned value; this violates EVM principles and produces misleading financial reports.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-tool sync drift: if Jira and MS Project disagree, pin the system of record per field in `program.yaml`.</description>
        <reason>Without a pinned source-of-truth per field, agents have no deterministic way to decide which value is correct during reconciliation.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vocabulary leakage: predictive uses "milestone, deliverable, baseline"; agile uses "increment, story, velocity". Force terminology per audience.</description>
        <reason>Mixing vocabularies in reports confuses steering-committee members and masks real misalignment between arms.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Bulk gate-pack generation is a leak risk — packs pull from confidential decks/screenshots. Run `password-scrubber-agent` and manual review before sharing.</description>
        <reason>Gate packs aggregate sensitive data; automated generation without scrubbing frequently leaks credentials, financial data, or strategic information.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Long-context drift: program graphs >50 epics blow context. Page by milestone or workstream and operate on slices.</description>
        <reason>Operating on massive program graphs depletes context windows and leads to loss of fidelity in agent analysis.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints are mandatory at: boundary changes, gate decisions, re-baselining, cadence changes, vendor escalations.</statement>
        <rationale>These are structural decisions affecting multiple teams or organizational commitments and must be human-owned.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Best practices for hybrid delivery:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Draw the boundary in writing inside `program.yaml` — name which deliverables are predictive (charter, contracts, regulatory submissions, hardware BOMs) and which are agile (software increments, user research).</item>
        <item>Single backlog of epics, multiple team backlogs of stories — never two competing portfolios. Reconcile in code, not slides.</item>
        <item>Match tool count to boundary count: ideally one tool spans both arms (Azure DevOps, GitLab Ultimate, Jira+Plans). Two max with explicit sync; three+ is a smell.</item>
        <item>Gate cadence proportional to risk — monthly for regulated, quarterly for steady-state, never weekly (that is just a status meeting).</item>
        <item>Define one "translation table" (epic ↔ deliverable, story-points ↔ effort, velocity ↔ run rate) and use it for every steering report.</item>
        <item>Run agile teams on agile rituals, predictive workstreams on stage gates — do not force standups on regulatory submissions or gantt charts on user-research.</item>
        <item>DevOps arm: pair with `cicd-engineer/` and `infrastructure-engineer/` skills; ship on demand, do not let governance throttle deployment frequency.</item>
        <item>Re-baseline predictively only when scope or contract changes; do not re-baseline because velocity slipped.</item>
        <item>Train both PMs and Scrum Masters on the other side; the dominant cultural failure is "agile coach distrusts gantts" or "PM distrusts standups".</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/hybrid-alignment.py" purpose="Script that flags milestone/epic misalignment from a program.yaml file (past due, at risk, orphan epics)."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/agile"/>
      <link href="https://scaledagileframework.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.disciplinedagiledelivery.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/72511.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.amazon.com/Principles-Product-Development-Flow-Second/dp/1935401009"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
