<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo X Analytics Review Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Solo X Analytics Review application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-metrics-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review MUST cover exactly five metrics (impressions, profile visits, net followers, replies-from-strangers, link clicks); follower count alone as headline is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Daniel Vassallo — Small Bets">Impressions and follower count move together for bot-attracting content; replies-from-strangers + link clicks separate audience-growth from engagement theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-20-min-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Total review time MUST be ≤20 minutes per week on a fixed day; overrunning means cutting depth, not extending.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion X-analytics audits 2026">Analytics expand to fill any slot; cap forces signal-over-thorough.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-3x-outlier-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outlier = impressions ≥3x trailing-4-week median; non-outliers MUST NOT be studied as deeply.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion X-analytics audits 2026">Studying every post mistakes randomness for signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-one-experiment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each review MUST produce exactly one named experiment with hypothesis + variable + success metric; zero or multiple experiments are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Justin Welsh — Content OS">Multiple simultaneous variable changes destroy signal; one-at-a-time builds the mental model.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-qualified-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Net followers MUST be tagged % qualified vs unqualified; chasing total-follower numbers without qualified discipline is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Daniel Vassallo — Small Bets">Algorithm-bait attracts unqualified followers at high rates and dilutes pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
