<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelancer Niche Positioning Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1050" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules produce a freelancer one-liner that survives platform search and human skim, with external validation gates before any rollout.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The positioning is exactly one sentence of the form "I do <em>X</em> (concrete service) for <em>Y</em> (named buyer role or industry) so they <em>Z</em> (named outcome)." X is a verb-plus-noun phrase, Y is searchable on the platforms the freelancer uses, Z is an outcome the buyer would say themselves. Multi-sentence positioning is rejected; bullet lists are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-person service business needs a one-line frame that survives Upwork search and LinkedIn skim">A two-sentence positioning forces the buyer to decide whether to read sentence two before committing — they don't. The X/Y/Z one-liner forces every word to earn its place.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The one-liner must satisfy four constraints simultaneously: (a) <em>search-findable</em> — the buyer's likely platform query contains at least one verbatim word from the line; (b) <em>role-specific</em> — Y names a buyer role or industry, never "businesses" or "startups"; (c) <em>outcome-claimed</em> — Z is a measurable or visible result, not an internal activity ("ship features faster" yes, "write clean code" no); (d) <em>defensible in 60 seconds</em> — the operator can give a coherent example for X, Y, and Z without hedging.</statement>
      <rationale source="One-line 'I do X for Y' framing that survives Upwork search and LinkedIn skim">Each constraint kills a specific failure: vague verbs (a) fail to surface in search, vague buyers (b) attract unqualified leads, vague outcomes (c) make the line feel generic, vague defence (d) collapses on the first discovery call.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before public rollout, three external validation gates must pass: (i) <strong>search-find</strong> — at least 3 of 5 representative platform searches the buyer is likely to run surface the new profile in the first two pages; (ii) <strong>peer recall</strong> — 2 of 3 peers, shown the one-liner once for 5 seconds then asked to recall, can name both Y (the buyer) and Z (the outcome); (iii) <strong>buyer paraphrase</strong> — at least 2 prospects in a discovery call paraphrase the line back accurately when asked "what do you think I do?".</statement>
      <rationale source="One-liner must survive search and skim — external validation, not self-judgement">Operators always think their own positioning is clear; external gates are the only way to find out it isn't. Three gates of different shapes (machine search, peer skim, buyer recall) triangulate effectiveness across the surfaces it has to work on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rollout is staged across owned surfaces in a fixed order so failures are detected before they become global: <strong>(1)</strong> site hero copy and one cold-email subject test, <strong>(2)</strong> LinkedIn headline + about-section, <strong>(3)</strong> platform profile (Upwork / Toptal / Contra), <strong>(4)</strong> all secondary surfaces (email signature, business card, conference bio). The operator waits at least 14 days between (2) and (3) to gather signal before changing platform algorithms.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo freelancer rollout discipline — surfaces have different cost-to-revert">Site hero is cheap to revert, platform profiles are not — Upwork's search re-indexes slowly and a wrong one-liner can suppress the profile for weeks. Staging the rollout keeps revertability cheap until the line is proven.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The one-liner has an explicit kill rule: if any of (a) qualified inbound leads from new surface drop &gt; 30% over the first 30 days against the prior baseline, (b) discovery-call buyers consistently ask "so what exactly do you do?" after hearing the line, or (c) the operator cannot defend X, Y, or Z in conversation across three attempts — the line is rolled back to the prior baseline and re-drafted, not patched in place. There is no "let's try a small tweak" middle path.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo freelancer cannot afford slow degradation of pipeline — explicit rollback rule">Without a kill rule the operator sticks with a failing one-liner because each new lead "might be the next one". The 30-day, 3-attempt thresholds are the bright lines that force an honest rewrite instead of slow bleed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical example">
    <example type="good" title="From generalist to validated one-liner">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Before (generalist):
  "Senior full-stack developer with 12+ years of experience in modern web."

Draft:
  "I do Django + Postgres performance work for B2B SaaS CTOs so their
   checkout p99 drops under 300ms before Black Friday."

Constraint check:
  (a) search-findable: "Django performance", "Postgres slow query" → yes
  (b) role-specific: B2B SaaS CTO → yes
  (c) outcome-claimed: p99 under 300ms by named deadline → yes
  (d) defensible: 60s example with k6 + EXPLAIN ANALYZE ready → yes

Validation:
  (i) search-find: 4/5 representative queries surface the profile in page 1-2
  (ii) peer recall: 2/3 peers recall "SaaS CTO" and "p99 / Black Friday"
  (iii) buyer paraphrase: 3 of 4 discovery calls paraphrase accurately

Rollout:
  Day 1: site hero + 1 cold-email subject A/B
  Day 14: LinkedIn headline + about
  Day 28: Upwork profile (delayed deliberately so platform re-index lands
          on the validated line, not a draft)

30-day check:
  Qualified inbound up 22%; rollback rule not triggered; one-liner kept.
]]></code>
      <note>The line shipped only after all three external gates passed; the staged rollout kept the platform profile safe from a half-baked version.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
