<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-gotchas" title="Agent Pitfalls and Best Practices">
  <summary>Common agent-generated mistakes in token pipeline setup and the rules that prevent them.</summary>

  <section title="Agent Pitfalls">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent writes Style Dictionary transforms against the deprecated v3 API.</description>
      <reason>Style Dictionary v4 has a different transform API; v3 transforms silently produce no output or malformed files.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generated SCSS maps use Dart Sass-deprecated syntax (e.g., misplaced !default).</description>
      <reason>Newer Dart Sass deprecations surface only at build time; lint generated SCSS before committing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Color-space metadata (sRGB vs. P3) is dropped during token transform.</description>
      <reason>Transforms silently coerce color spaces; require explicit color-space metadata in the source and validate output format.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent invents Tokens Studio capabilities (e.g., "math expressions") not in current docs.</description>
      <reason>Hallucinated features produce pipeline configs that break at runtime; validate all claimed features against current Tokens Studio documentation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent prunes "unused" tokens automatically using static analysis.</description>
      <reason>Static analysis misses theming, runtime, and per-tenant token references; auto-pruning causes silent regressions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Snapshot-test rendered components after every token change, not just raw value diffs.</statement>
      <rationale>Raw value diffs miss visual regressions caused by aliasing, transforms, or platform-specific rendering differences.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Validate token files against the W3C draft format on every export to keep future tooling compatibility.</statement>
      <rationale>Early validation prevents a forced re-migration when the ecosystem converges on the standard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never auto-apply token PRs that change a primary color without a staged rollout and visual diff review.</statement>
      <rationale>A wrong primary color rebrands the product instantly across all platforms simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
