<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="cross-platform-token-distribution Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for cross-platform-token-distribution as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using rem values in iOS or dp values in CSS output.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Style Dictionary transforms are unit-and-platform-aware but trip on edge cases; always specify the unit transform explicitly per platform.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Relying on Tokens Studio JSON being W3C-compatible without validation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tokens Studio JSON dialect drifts from the W3C draft; round-tripping breaks alias references unless validated on each export.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Semantic token aliasing across platforms expecting one-level resolution.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Android XML resolves only one level deep without custom resolvers; deep alias chains silently produce wrong values.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent writes Style Dictionary transforms against the deprecated v3 API.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Style Dictionary v4 has a different transform API; v3 transforms silently produce no output or malformed files.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Generated SCSS maps use Dart Sass-deprecated syntax (e.g., misplaced !default).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Newer Dart Sass deprecations surface only at build time; lint generated SCSS before committing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Color-space metadata (sRGB vs. P3) is dropped during token transform.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Transforms silently coerce color spaces; require explicit color-space metadata in the source and validate output format.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent invents Tokens Studio capabilities (e.g., "math expressions") not in current docs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hallucinated features produce pipeline configs that break at runtime; validate all claimed features against current Tokens Studio documentation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent prunes "unused" tokens automatically using static analysis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Static analysis misses theming, runtime, and per-tenant token references; auto-pruning causes silent regressions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
