<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Blurred Roles and Team Evolution Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Blurred Roles and Team Evolution plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="venn-overlap-has-single-dri" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Venn-overlap zone (PM∩Design, Design∩Eng, PM∩Eng) MUST have exactly one human DRI; agents may fill the zone but never own the decision.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — agent-team operating notes 2026-Q1">Without a single DRI per zone, parallel role-persona agents produce contradictions and the team ships the loudest recommendation, not the right one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pm-fluency-five-domains" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PMs MUST hold working fluency in design, data, model behavior, distribution, and pricing — not just spec writing and roadmap ownership.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andrew Ng — Sequoia AI Ascent 2024">As AI scales engineering throughput, the bottleneck shifts to discovery, evaluation, and judgment; PMs without adjacent fluency become the constraint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="blur-must-be-symmetric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every 'PM speaks design' expectation MUST be paired with a symmetric expectation on the design side (e.g., designers track metrics); one-sided blurring is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lara Hogan — Resilient Management">Asymmetric blurring is extractive, not collaborative; one side ends up doing two jobs while the other guards specialism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="keep-one-specialist-per-deep-domain" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every deep domain (security, ML eval, accessibility) MUST retain at least one depth specialist; full-blurring in these domains is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — security audit pattern 2026">T-shaped fluency scales; eliminating specialisation creates a team that is mediocre everywhere and expert nowhere.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="quarterly-audit-by-git-shortlog" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Role overlap MUST be re-audited quarterly using commit/PR-author distribution (git shortlog by file area) as the truth signal — not self-reported descriptions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — role-overlap.sh audit findings 2026-Q1">Self-reported role splits are systematically wrong by ~30%; git shortlog surfaces who actually touches which areas.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ratio-is-hypothesis-not-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The 2:1 PM:Engineer ratio (Ng 2024) MUST be treated as a per-team hypothesis to measure, not a universal target to copy.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andrew Ng — Sequoia AI Ascent 2024">The inversion only holds when engineers are heavily AI-augmented; treating it as a target leads to over-hiring PMs and under-building.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
