<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="blurred-roles-team-evolution Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for blurred-roles-team-evolution as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Blurred roles defined in a Notion page but not reflected in actual work assignment or code ownership.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Blurred roles drift back to silos under deadline pressure. The quarterly audit is the forcing function that prevents reversion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Parallel role-persona agents on the same problem produce contradictions; without a human DRI to converge, the team ships the loudest agent's recommendation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always attach a converge step with a named human DRI.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents inherit the prompt's role boundary, so a PM-agent given an engineering codebase will silently write code.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Constrain via tool allow-lists per persona, not via prose instructions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-driven skill assessments (e.g., "rate this PM on data fluency from their PRDs") are noisy and biased toward verbose writers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use as a discussion seed, never as a performance input.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>The "2 PMs : 1 Engineer" inversion only holds when the engineer is heavily AI-augmented; if you measure on baseline engineering throughput, you'll over-hire PMs and under-build.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Track agent-assisted velocity separately.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-role knowledge transfer between agents leaks proprietary context (e.g., the data-agent surfaces customer PII in a design-agent prompt).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run a `password-scrubber-agent` style filter on inter-agent handoffs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
