<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="bash-aliases">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>server-craft</domain>
    <summary>Organized bash alias methodology: simple aliases vs functions, safety flags, modern-tool gating, tab completion, and 60+ categorized shortcuts.</summary>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>bash</tag>
      <tag>alias</tag>
      <tag>shell-productivity</tag>
      <tag>dotfiles</tag>
      <tag>shortcuts</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Bash Aliases for Solo Developer Productivity</title>

    <summary>Organized bash alias and function methodology for solo developer servers: categorized ~/.bash_aliases with sections for system, navigation, git, Docker, systemd, nginx, network, logs, and project-specific shortcuts. Distinguishes simple aliases from function aliases, covers completion-aware wrappers, and provides a complete 60+ alias reference.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>A well-organized alias file reduces repetitive typing by 30+ keystrokes per common operation, prevents mistakes via safety aliases for destructive commands, and documents common operations in a human-readable runbook format. The aliases are the difference between `systemctl --user status nero-core nero-channel-web` and `nero-status`.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Setting up a new server or workstation where productivity shortcuts are missing</item>
        <item>Onboarding to a new project where project-specific aliases speed up repetitive tasks</item>
        <item>Auditing existing .bash_aliases for conflicts, missing completions, or undocumented shortcuts</item>
        <item>Consolidating ad-hoc functions scattered across .bashrc into organized alias files</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Environments where shell config is managed by Ansible/Chef — use those tools instead</item>
        <item>Shared servers with multiple users where one developer's aliases conflict with others</item>
        <item>Scripts and pipelines needing portability across shells (zsh, fish, sh)</item>
        <item>Replacing proper scripts: complex multi-step operations belong in ~/bin/ scripts</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="alias-patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use simple aliases for flag additions and substitutions; use shell functions when you need parameters, conditionals, or multi-step operations.</statement>
        <rationale>Aliases cannot accept positional parameters. Attempting to do so leads to brittle workarounds. Functions handle parameters natively and are easier to debug.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Always add safety confirmation flags to destructive commands: rm -i, mv -i, cp -i.</statement>
        <rationale>A single absent confirmation on rm -rf on a production server has no undo. The interactive flag adds one extra keystroke in exchange for a meaningful safety net.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Gate modern-tool aliases behind command existence checks so the file loads without errors on systems where those tools are not installed.</statement>
        <rationale>The same ~/.bash_aliases is often shared across machines via dotfiles. A missing bat or eza causes a hard error on every new shell if not gated with command -v.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="simple-vs-function">
        <example type="good" title="Simple aliases vs function aliases">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Simple alias: flag additions and substitutions
alias gs="git status -sb"
alias ll="ls -alF --color=auto"
alias grep="grep --color=auto"

# Function alias: needs a parameter
mkcd() { mkdir -p "$1" && cd "$1"; }

# Function alias: multi-step
port() { sudo lsof -i ":${1}" 2>/dev/null || echo "Nothing on port $1"; }

# Function alias: needs conditional logic
extract() {
    [ -f "$1" ] || { echo "'$1' is not a file"; return 1; }
    case "$1" in
        *.tar.gz)  tar xzf "$1" ;;
        *.tar.bz2) tar xjf "$1" ;;
        *.zip)     unzip "$1" ;;
        *.gz)      gunzip "$1" ;;
        *)         echo "Unknown archive format: $1" ;;
    esac
}
]]></code>
        </example>

        <example type="bad" title="Alias anti-patterns">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Wrong: complex logic in alias — use a function instead
alias mything="cmd1; cmd2; if [[ $? -eq 0 ]]; then cmd3; fi"

# Wrong: no existence check, fails on minimal systems
alias cat="bat --paging=never"
alias ls="eza --color=always"
]]></code>
          <note>Aliases are not functions. Any branching, parameters, or multi-step logic belongs in a shell function.</note>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="naming-conventions">
        <list>
          <item>Single-letter abbreviations (g=git, dk=docker) — only for the most frequently used commands</item>
          <item>Prefix+action pattern (dk-ps, sc-restart) — for grouped command families</item>
          <item>Descriptive verb-noun (nero-status, show-ports) — for infrequently used but memorable shortcuts</item>
          <item>Avoid shadowing common system commands unless the alias adds universal improvements (grep, diff)</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="modern-tool-gating">
        <example type="good" title="Gate modern tools with existence checks">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Gate eza aliases behind existence check
if command -v eza &>/dev/null; then
    alias ls="eza --color=always --group-directories-first"
    alias ll="eza -la --color=always --group-directories-first --git"
    alias lt="eza --tree --level=2 --color=always"
else
    alias ll="ls -alF --color=auto"
    alias la="ls -A --color=auto"
fi

# Gate bat alias
if command -v bat &>/dev/null; then
    alias cat="bat --paging=never"
fi
]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section name="completion-wiring">
        <rule>
          <statement>Wire tab completion for short aliases using complete -F so git, docker, and systemctl completions work with single-letter aliases.</statement>
          <rationale>Without completion wiring, tab completion does not complete to git status. Re-wiring completions is a one-time setup that multiplies the value of short aliases.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <example type="good" title="Preserve tab completion for aliases">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Preserve git completion for g alias
alias g="git"
if declare -F __git_complete &>/dev/null; then
    __git_complete g git
fi

# After defining: source ~/.bash_aliases to activate
]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="alias-antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Aliasing a command to itself with different flags, creating an infinite recursion loop.</description>
        <reason>alias rm="rm -rf" calls rm which calls rm again infinitely until the process limit is hit, making rm unusable. Use a different name or a function with \rm to bypass the alias.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Missing quotes around alias values containing spaces or special characters.</description>
        <reason>alias ll=ls -la (unquoted) only aliases ll to ls; the -la is parsed as a separate token and ignored. The alias silently misbehaves rather than throwing an error.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Putting complex logic (if/else, loops, subshells) directly in alias values.</description>
        <reason>Bash aliases do not support compound commands. They appear to work in simple cases but break in subtle ways with quoting, piping, and argument expansion. Use functions for any logic.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Forgetting to source ~/.bash_aliases after making changes and wondering why new aliases do not work.</description>
        <reason>Aliases are loaded at shell startup. Editing the file does not update the running shell. Use `source ~/.bash_aliases` or a reload alias defined early in the file.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding aliases to ~/.bashrc instead of ~/.bash_aliases.</description>
        <reason>Mixing aliases into .bashrc makes the file harder to manage, harder to sync via dotfiles, and prevents isolated reload with a single source command.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <section name="safe-patterns">
        <example type="good" title="Safe alias patterns">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Correct: quoted value, safe shadow of rm
alias rm="rm -i"
# To call original rm without confirmation: \rm file or command rm file

# Correct: reload alias defined early in the file so it is available
alias reload="source ~/.bash_aliases && source ~/.bashrc"
alias ea="vim ~/.bash_aliases && source ~/.bash_aliases"

# Correct: function for any multi-step logic
sysinfo() {
    echo "Uptime: $(uptime -p)"
    echo "Memory: $(free -h | awk '/Mem:/{print $3 "/" $2}')"
    echo "Disk:   $(df -h / | awk 'NR==2{print $3 "/" $2 " (" $5 ")"}')"
}
]]></code>
        </example>

        <example type="bad" title="Unsafe alias patterns">
          <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Wrong: circular alias — infinite recursion
alias rm="rm -rf"

# Wrong: unquoted, the flags are dropped silently
alias ll=ls -la

# Wrong: complex logic in alias, breaks with pipes
alias deploy="cd /srv/app && git pull && make install && systemctl restart app"
# Correct version: define as a function
deploy() { cd /srv/app && git pull && make install && systemctl restart app; }

# Wrong: aliases scattered in .bashrc between unrelated config
export PATH="$HOME/bin:$PATH"
alias gs="git status"    # Don't put this here
export NVM_DIR="$HOME/.nvm"
]]></code>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/bash_aliases" purpose="Complete categorized ~/.bash_aliases with 60+ aliases and functions"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="shell-productivity"/>
      <ref slug="tmux-power-user"/>
      <ref slug="dotfiles-management"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
