<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency-to-SaaS Readiness Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding Agency-to-SaaS Readiness Checklist plus the universal skip/run routing pair (referenced by the decision tree).</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="ip-rights-clear-before-saas" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before the SaaS pivot, the agency MUST hold unambiguous IP rights to all candidate-product code; client-funded codebases without explicit licence-back MUST be excluded.</statement>
      <rationale source="Walker Deibel — Buy Then Build">IP claims surface during diligence and tank valuations; clearing IP before pivot is cheaper than litigating during a deal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="repeatable-asset-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The candidate SaaS MUST come from an asset already used on 3+ paying engagements; one-off code MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brian Casel — Productize">One-off code lacks the production hardening + customer evidence that justifies SaaS pricing; the 3+ rule is the minimum proof of repeatability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="retainer-base-funds-pivot" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The agency retainer base MUST cover 18+ months of SaaS-pivot operating cost; pivots funded by debt or runway-burn MUST be flagged red.</statement>
      <rationale source="Jason Cohen — A Smart Bear blog">SaaS pivots that hit the wall at month 9 force founders back into agency work; the 18-month rule is the realistic floor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="founder-bandwidth-50-percent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The founder MUST commit ≥50% of weekly hours to the SaaS work; &lt;50% commitments MUST be flagged as 'side project' not 'pivot'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Built to Sell — John Warrillow">Sub-50% founder time produces a side-project velocity that loses to even modest competition; the 50% rule separates pivots from hobbies.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="checklist-must-name-owner-per-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every readiness row MUST have a named owner + due date; orphan rows MUST be deleted or assigned.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atul Gawande — The Checklist Manifesto">Orphan readiness rows create false confidence; the named-owner rule is the only structural gate against checklist theatre.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` do not ALL hold OR any disqualifier in `## Skip If` fires, the agent MUST skip this methodology and document the skip reason in the cycle artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">A minimum-form decision tree must route 'preconditions-not-satisfied' to skip; this rule is the canonical target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `## Applies If` ALL hold AND no disqualifier fires, the agent MUST run the methodology end-to-end and produce the artefact specified in 02-output-contract.xml.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Pair to skip-this-methodology; together they form the always-present minimal route.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
