<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency-to-SaaS Readiness Checklist Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five hard rules for the agency-to-SaaS readiness audit.</summary>

  <section title="The five dimensions">
    <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
D1 IP rights to candidate SaaS
   2: Agency-owned IP, no client claims, no contract-bound derivative restrictions
   1: Mixed — some SOWs allow derivative, some don't; manageable carve-out path
   0: Client-owned IP on the candidate work; pivot requires re-build from scratch

D2 Repeatable IP (shipped same shape ≥ 3 times to ≥ 3 clients with similar scope)
   2: Yes, ≥ 3 ships, ≥ 70% scope overlap
   1: 2 ships OR 3+ ships with &lt; 50% overlap (closer to template than product)
   0: 0-1 ships of the candidate shape (no evidence of repeatability)

D3 Codebase ownership
   2: All candidate code lives in agency-owned repos with permissive internal license
   1: Mixed — some in client repos but with extraction rights
   0: Code lives in client repos; extraction requires client signoff or rewrite

D4 Retainer-base stability
   2: ≥ 9 months of runway under retainer-churn scenario (top-1 client leaves)
   1: 6-9 months runway under same scenario
   0: &lt; 6 months runway; pivot threatens agency survival

D5 Founder bandwidth / replacement plan
   2: Designated agency-ops lead in place; founder can spend 30+ h/w on SaaS
   1: Plan exists but lead not yet hired; founder bandwidth limited to ~20 h/w
   0: Founder is sole operator; no realistic replacement plan

Total score → decision
  ≥ 8/10 → READY (proceed to MVP)
  5-7/10 → PRE-WORK NEEDED (close gaps before pivot)
  ≤ 4/10 → NOT VIABLE (revisit after 6+ months)
    ]]></code>
  </section>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-five-dimension-scoring" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every readiness audit scores ALL 5 dimensions on 0/1/2. No "skip" or "later" — undated unknowns score 0. The dimension list is fixed; do not add a 6th to soften a known weak dimension.</statement>
      <rationale source="multi-criteria decision analysis; B2B pivot research (Constantin Bjerke 2023)">Founders systematically over-weight their strongest dimension and under-weight the weakest. The 5-dimension mandatory scoring forces honest assessment of weak areas. Unknown scoring as 0 prevents "we'll figure it out" optimism.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-ip-clause-audit-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dimension D1 (IP rights) requires reading every SOW from the past 24 months for IP / derivative / "work-for-hire" / "all deliverables" language. Score is evidence-backed by a per-SOW table; cannot be assigned on memory.</statement>
      <rationale source="agency-to-product pivots case studies; SoftwareEquity Group 2024 acquirer due-diligence checklist">Agencies routinely sign SOWs with "all deliverables become client property" without realizing it bars productization. Acquirers / investors / customers will ask. Reading the contracts is the only valid evidence. Memory and "I think we own it" are 0 evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-repeatable-evidence-threshold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dimension D2 (repeatable IP) requires ≥ 3 shipped instances to ≥ 3 different clients with ≥ 70% scope overlap to score 2. The "we've kind of done this before" pattern scores 0.</statement>
      <rationale source="lean-startup market validation; Jobs To Be Done switcher data">Agencies often build a custom solution multiple times but with no scope overlap — that's a service, not a product. The 70% overlap threshold is the line between "we have a productizable kernel" and "we have a category of work." Below threshold, the SaaS would be re-inventing from scratch.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-retainer-base-buffer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dimension D4 (retainer stability) requires a 9-month runway under a stress test that assumes top-1 retainer client leaves at month 1. Pivots fail because the agency can't sustain itself through the SaaS build period.</statement>
      <rationale source="startup runway analysis; agency exit case studies">9 months is the minimum SaaS build window for a meaningful MVP + early traction. Anything shorter means panic re-engaging with agency work mid-pivot, which kills both bets. The top-1 churn assumption is realistic — concentration is correlated with pivot announcements (existing client may churn when they sense divided focus).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-founder-replacement-plan" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dimension D5 requires a NAMED operational lead for the agency during the pivot (not "we'll hire one later"). Founder time freed must be ≥ 30 hours/week sustained.</statement>
      <rationale source="founder bandwidth research; "Built to Sell" methodology">Founder time is the silent killer of pivots. Splitting 20 hours between agency + SaaS produces two sub-par outcomes. The replacement lead must be hired BEFORE pivot decision, not as a TBD. Lead in place = realistic 30+ h/w founder time on SaaS.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="A ready agency (score 9/10)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
D1 IP rights:                2  (every SOW signed since 2024 has derivative-rights clause)
D2 Repeatable IP:            2  (shipped CRM-integration tool 7 times, 85% scope overlap)
D3 Codebase ownership:       2  (extracted to agency monorepo; reuse rate 60%)
D4 Retainer base:            2  (15 months runway under top-1-churn scenario)
D5 Founder bandwidth:        1  (ops lead hired Q4'25, ramping; founder at ~25 h/w currently)
Total: 9 — READY (proceed to MVP; address D5 gap with 60-day ramp plan)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates all 5 dimensions scored, evidence-backed.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="A not-ready audit shortcut">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"We've been working in this space for 5 years and the founders are sharp.
We're ready to pivot."

Problem: violates r1 (no dimension scoring), r2 (no SOW audit), r3 (no
repeatable-evidence threshold), r4 (no runway stress test), r5 (no
replacement plan).
Repair: do the actual audit. Most "we're ready" stories score 4-6/10,
which is pre-work, not ready.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Vibes-based readiness is the canonical failure pattern.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
