<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ba-planning Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ba-planning. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce five separate task-scoped artifacts (T1 through T5), not one consolidated BA plan; each artifact has its own approver, cadence, and lifecycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Collapsing five tasks into one document loses the monitoring half (T5) and makes the governance and information management tasks implicitly optional — they are not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Execute KA1 tasks in sequence: T1 approach → T2 stakeholders → T3 governance → T4 information management → T5 performance; dependencies flow forward.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Governance (T3) depends on knowing who the stakeholders are (T2); information management (T4) depends on governance decisions (T3); performance metrics (T5) depend on knowing what artifacts exist (T4). Out-of-order execution produces incoherent plans.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Declare the approach as a combination of plan-driven and change-driven percentages per artifact, not as a binary choice.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Real programs are 70/30 hybrids; pure-binary approach outputs produce artifacts that are either over-planned or under-baselined for their actual volatility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select elicitation techniques by information type and stakeholder count, not by default preference; document the technique-to-session mapping before any session is scheduled.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents default to "interview everything" regardless of context; workshops are more efficient for group consensus, surveys for broad input across large stakeholder populations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign different review cadences per task; do not use a single global review frequency for all five KA1 artifacts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Performance metrics (T5) go stale weekly; stakeholder and governance artifacts drift fortnightly; approach and information management artifacts are stable monthly. A single cadence either over-reviews stable artifacts or under-reviews volatile ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Encode replan triggers as machine-readable YAML in triggers.yml, not prose; prose triggers only fire when a human reads and interprets them.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The monitor agent reads trigger conditions automatically; prose conditions require an LLM to interpret them, introducing interpretation errors and silent misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>List at least three measurable BA performance metrics in T5 on the first cycle with baseline=null and target=null; do not invent baselines before two cycles of data exist.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Invented baselines are post-hoc rationalizations — the first cycle is for measurement establishment, the second for improvement comparison. Skipping T5 entirely means no monitoring loop exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
