<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-ka1-tasks" title="BABOK KA1 Five Tasks">
  <summary>Five BABOK KA1 tasks, ordering constraints, approach selection rules, stakeholder categories, and elicitation technique selection criteria.</summary>

  <section title="Five KA1 Tasks and Ordering">
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce five separate task-scoped artifacts (T1 through T5), not one consolidated BA plan; each artifact has its own approver, cadence, and lifecycle.</statement>
      <rationale>Collapsing five tasks into one document loses the monitoring half (T5) and makes the governance and information management tasks implicitly optional — they are not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Execute KA1 tasks in sequence: T1 approach → T2 stakeholders → T3 governance → T4 information management → T5 performance; dependencies flow forward.</statement>
      <rationale>Governance (T3) depends on knowing who the stakeholders are (T2); information management (T4) depends on governance decisions (T3); performance metrics (T5) depend on knowing what artifacts exist (T4). Out-of-order execution produces incoherent plans.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>T1 — Plan BA Approach: approach selection (plan-driven/change-driven/hybrid), methodology, constraints, rationale. One named approver required.</item>
      <item>T2 — Plan Stakeholder Engagement: stakeholder list, categories, engagement technique per type, availability.</item>
      <item>T3 — Plan BA Governance: decision rights, change control process, approval thresholds, escalation paths, sign-off requirements.</item>
      <item>T4 — Plan BA Information Management: artifact repository path, retention policy, access list, versioning approach.</item>
      <item>T5 — Identify BA Performance Improvements: at least 3 measurable metrics listed on day one even with null baselines and targets.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Approach Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Declare the approach as a combination of plan-driven and change-driven percentages per artifact, not as a binary choice.</statement>
      <rationale>Real programs are 70/30 hybrids; pure-binary approach outputs produce artifacts that are either over-planned or under-baselined for their actual volatility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Plan-Driven indicators: clear scope, stable requirements, high documentation expectation, low change frequency, limited stakeholder availability.</item>
      <item>Change-Driven indicators: uncertain evolving requirements, continuous stakeholder availability, higher risk tolerance, "just enough" documentation norm.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Stakeholder Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Sponsors: executive funding the initiative — decision authority for scope and budget changes.</item>
      <item>Users: people who will use the solution — primary source for functional and usability requirements.</item>
      <item>Implementers: team building the solution — source for feasibility and technical constraints.</item>
      <item>Regulators: compliance bodies — source for mandatory requirements and audit expectations.</item>
      <item>Support: operations and help desk — source for operational and transition requirements.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Listing plausible-sounding stakeholder roles without confirming they exist in the org chart.</description>
      <reason>LLMs invent plausible stakeholders ("Director of UX," "VP of Platform"); gap to reality causes missed sign-offs and broken escalation paths at critical decision points.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Elicitation Technique Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select elicitation techniques by information type and stakeholder count, not by default preference; document the technique-to-session mapping before any session is scheduled.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents default to "interview everything" regardless of context; workshops are more efficient for group consensus, surveys for broad input across large stakeholder populations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Interviews: deep individual understanding, SME knowledge extraction, 1-3 participants.</item>
      <item>Workshops: consensus building, requirements that need group negotiation, 4-15 participants.</item>
      <item>Surveys: broad input, many stakeholders, quantitative preference data, 15+ respondents.</item>
      <item>Observation: process understanding, gap between documented and actual behavior, 1-2 observers.</item>
      <item>Document Analysis: existing-state artifacts, regulatory documents, system specifications.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/ba-approach-document.md">BA approach document covering all six required sections.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/ka1_check.py">Python script validating five KA1 artifacts are present and within review cadence.</reference>
</text>
