<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-monitoring-and-performance" title="BA Planning Monitoring and Performance">
  <summary>Per-task monitoring cadences, replan trigger conditions, performance metric requirements for T5, and common LLM failure modes in KA1 planning.</summary>

  <section title="Monitoring Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign different review cadences per task; do not use a single global review frequency for all five KA1 artifacts.</statement>
      <rationale>Performance metrics (T5) go stale weekly; stakeholder and governance artifacts drift fortnightly; approach and information management artifacts are stable monthly. A single cadence either over-reviews stable artifacts or under-reviews volatile ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>T5 Performance Improvements: weekly cadence — compute BA metrics and emit CR patches if triggers fire.</item>
      <item>T2 Stakeholder Engagement: fortnightly cadence — reconcile stakeholder list against project actuals.</item>
      <item>T1 Approach, T3 Governance, T4 Information Management: monthly cadence.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Replan Triggers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Encode replan triggers as machine-readable YAML in triggers.yml, not prose; prose triggers only fire when a human reads and interprets them.</statement>
      <rationale>The monitor agent reads trigger conditions automatically; prose conditions require an LLM to interpret them, introducing interpretation errors and silent misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Stakeholder added or removed from the project.</item>
      <item>Scope change request merged into the requirements baseline.</item>
      <item>Two or more missed elicitation sessions within one cadence period.</item>
      <item>Performance metric breach (a KPI missing its threshold for two consecutive reviews).</item>
      <item>last_reviewed date older than the task's cadence threshold.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="T5 Performance Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>List at least three measurable BA performance metrics in T5 on the first cycle with baseline=null and target=null; do not invent baselines before two cycles of data exist.</statement>
      <rationale>Invented baselines are post-hoc rationalizations — the first cycle is for measurement establishment, the second for improvement comparison. Skipping T5 entirely means no monitoring loop exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>T5 first-cycle metrics: (1) requirement defect density = defects found in validation / total requirements; baseline: null; target: null. (2) elicitation throughput = requirements documented per session; baseline: null. (3) rework rate = requirements changed after baseline / total baselined; baseline: null.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Omitting T5 on the first cycle because "we don't have baselines yet."</description>
      <reason>Without T5, there is no instrumentation; the second cycle cannot improve because it has nothing to improve from. Baselines are collected during the first cycle, not before it.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM merges the five BABOK KA1 tasks into a single "BA Plan" document and silently drops T4 and T5.</description>
      <reason>Information management and performance improvement are the least visible KA1 tasks; LLMs drop them because they appear in fewer training examples. Validate output against the five-task schema; reject if any task is missing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM produces vague governance approvers ("leadership," "the product team") in T3.</description>
      <reason>Vague approvers cannot sign off on anything; escalation paths point to a role, not a person. Require an email or @-handle; reject role-only outputs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM rewrites full artifact content during monitoring instead of emitting CR patches.</description>
      <reason>Full-doc overwrites destroy the approver's ability to review changes incrementally; CR patches force explicit diff review. Cap monitor agent at 5 changes per artifact per run.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
