<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ba-planning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ba-planning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Listing plausible-sounding stakeholder roles without confirming they exist in the org chart.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs invent plausible stakeholders ("Director of UX," "VP of Platform"); gap to reality causes missed sign-offs and broken escalation paths at critical decision points.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Omitting T5 on the first cycle because "we don't have baselines yet."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without T5, there is no instrumentation; the second cycle cannot improve because it has nothing to improve from. Baselines are collected during the first cycle, not before it.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM merges the five BABOK KA1 tasks into a single "BA Plan" document and silently drops T4 and T5.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Information management and performance improvement are the least visible KA1 tasks; LLMs drop them because they appear in fewer training examples. Validate output against the five-task schema; reject if any task is missing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM produces vague governance approvers ("leadership," "the product team") in T3.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vague approvers cannot sign off on anything; escalation paths point to a role, not a person. Require an email or @-handle; reject role-only outputs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM rewrites full artifact content during monitoring instead of emitting CR patches.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Full-doc overwrites destroy the approver's ability to review changes incrementally; CR patches force explicit diff review. Cap monitor agent at 5 changes per artifact per run.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
