<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-discovery-process" title="Pain Point Discovery Framework">
  <summary>Five-step process: define scope, mine four source tiers, categorize, score with Pain Intensity Matrix, extract root causes.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Research Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before mining, define audience, context, domain, and a numeric goal (e.g., 20 pain points in 4 hours) so scope is bounded and progress is measurable.</statement>
      <rationale>Unbounded research produces unfocused lists; a numeric goal forces prioritization of sources and stops the researcher from mining indefinitely without output.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Mine Four Source Tiers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Mine at least 3 source types across all four tiers: Tier 1 (direct complaints: Reddit, Twitter, G2, App Store), Tier 2 (questions: Quora, Stack Overflow, Google PAA), Tier 3 (forums: Slack, Discord, Facebook, Indie Hackers), Tier 4 (job boards: Upwork, Fiverr, LinkedIn Jobs).</statement>
      <rationale>Single-source mining misses the pain landscape; job board queries ("looking for someone to...") reveal pain points users are willing to pay to outsource — the strongest signal outside of direct payment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Categorize Pain Points">
    <p>Eight categories: Time Waste (takes too long), Money Loss (costs more than it should), Complexity (too hard to understand), Integration (tools don't work together), Reliability (doesn't work consistently), Support (can't get help), Process (workflow is broken), Learning (hard to get started). Categorize before scoring to reveal systemic patterns invisible in individual items.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Score with Pain Intensity Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each pain point using: Score = (Frequency x 0.3) + (Severity x 0.25) + (Reach x 0.2) + (Spend x 0.15) + (Alternatives x 0.1). Scale each 1-5. Priority: &gt;4 critical, 3-4 significant, 2-3 moderate, &lt;2 deprioritize.</statement>
      <rationale>Unweighted pain lists give equal priority to frequent-minor and rare-critical pains; the weighted formula reflects that frequency and severity matter more than willingness to pay in early discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Extract Root Causes via 5 Whys">
    <rule>
      <statement>For top-scored pains, run 5 Whys to find the root cause before designing any solution; also use the JTBD format: "When [situation], I want to [action], so I can [outcome]."</statement>
      <rationale>Surface pain often has a different root cause than it appears; solving the symptom leaves the root intact and the user's job undone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Pain: "I spend 3 hours/week on expense reports." Why 1: Reports are manual. Why 2: No auto-import. Why 3: No OCR integration. Why 4: IT won't approve new tools. Why 5: Process takes 6 months. Root: Organizational friction in tool adoption — not a product problem.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pain-log.md">Structured pain log with scoring fields</reference>
  <reference path="templates/reddit-collector.py">PRAW script to collect pain signals from a subreddit</reference>
</text>
