<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-and-antipatterns" title="Pain Point Research Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete research output examples for two audiences and six common mistakes with fixes.</summary>

  <section title="Example: Email Marketers">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Scope: solo marketers managing newsletters. Top pains by score: Deliverability issues (r/emailmarketing, Reliability, 4.5); Pricing spikes with growth (Reddit, Money, 4.0); Segmentation complexity (G2 reviews, Complexity, 4.2); Confusing analytics (Twitter rants, Complexity, 3.8); Clunky template editing (App reviews, Process, 3.5). Root cause: tools built for big teams, not solopreneurs. Opportunity: simple email tool optimized for under 10K subscribers.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Online Course Creators">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Scope: first-time course creators. Top pains: Video editing takes forever (Indie Hackers, Time Waste, 4.6); Students don't complete (Twitter, Process, 4.1); Platform fees too high (Reddit, Money, 4.3); Marketing is overwhelming (Facebook groups, Complexity, 4.0); Don't know what to teach (Quora, Learning, 3.9). Root cause: creators are content experts, not tech or marketing experts. Opportunity: done-for-you course launch service.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Surface-level research: reading only post titles, not comments.</description>
      <reason>Titles are clickbait; the pain signal is in the comments where users explain their situation with specificity.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Only one source type.</description>
      <reason>Single-source research is blind to the pain landscape; each tier reveals a different aspect of the problem space.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Not quantifying frequency or severity — treating all pains as equally important.</description>
      <reason>Without scoring, the loudest pain (most vocal users) wins over the most frequent pain (most users affected).</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring who is complaining; noting only what they complain about.</description>
      <reason>Segment matters: a pain that is severe for freelancers may be irrelevant for enterprise users even if the surface complaint is identical.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Confirmation bias: only documenting expected pain points.</description>
      <reason>Unexpected pains are often the most actionable; filtering them out produces a research report that confirms assumptions rather than challenges them.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Limitations">
    <rule testable="false">
      <statement>Every quote extracted by an LLM must be verified against the actual source URL before use in any decision; do not trust scores generated without explicit dimension inputs.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs hallucinate forum posts and review quotes; pain scoring is subjective and agent scores should be treated as a starting hypothesis requiring human sanity-check.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/prompt-collect.txt">LLM prompt to collect and tabulate pain signals</reference>
  <reference path="templates/prompt-score.txt">LLM prompt to apply Pain Intensity Matrix scoring</reference>
</text>
