<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="pain-point-research Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for pain-point-research as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Surface-level research: reading only post titles, not comments.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Titles are clickbait; the pain signal is in the comments where users explain their situation with specificity.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Only one source type.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Single-source research is blind to the pain landscape; each tier reveals a different aspect of the problem space.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Not quantifying frequency or severity — treating all pains as equally important.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without scoring, the loudest pain (most vocal users) wins over the most frequent pain (most users affected).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring who is complaining; noting only what they complain about.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Segment matters: a pain that is severe for freelancers may be irrelevant for enterprise users even if the surface complaint is identical.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Confirmation bias: only documenting expected pain points.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Unexpected pains are often the most actionable; filtering them out produces a research report that confirms assumptions rather than challenges them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
