<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="market-research-tam-sam-som Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for market-research-tam-sam-som. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For B2B markets, use government establishment data (US Census BDS, Eurostat) as the top-down customer count anchor — it is free and primary.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LinkedIn Sales Navigator counts are inaccessible for pipelines; Statista customer counts are paywalled. Government data is free, primary, and reliable for establishment counts by NAICS/NACE code.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run all three methods independently before triangulation. Never run bottom-up after reviewing top-down results — anchoring bias inflates the bottom-up estimate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">If the agent sees a $10B top-down TAM before computing the bottom-up, it will unconsciously reverse-engineer to produce a consistent number. Independence requires sequential blind computation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If methods diverge by more than 2x, do NOT average — report the range and flag the divergence. Investigate the outlier method before reconciling.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Averaging incompatible methods produces false precision. A 2x spread signals that one method's assumptions are wrong; averaging hides the problem and misleads investors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the ICP definition in one sentence and wait for explicit confirmation before fetching any number. "All SMBs" is not an ICP.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents computing TAM/SAM/SOM without a locked ICP will scope to different customer segments across the three methods, making triangulation impossible and producing numbers that cannot be compared.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
