<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="market-research-tam-sam-som Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for market-research-tam-sam-som as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LinkedIn employee count × $200K rule used for companies under 20 people or for services businesses.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The rule undercounts services and overcounts seed-stage SaaS. It is only valid for growth-stage B2B SaaS companies where sales-to-headcount ratios are established.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs hallucinate market-size numbers fluently; they require a URL for every figure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reject any line without a source URL. LLMs generate plausible-sounding numbers (e.g. "$4.2B by 2027") that have no factual basis. The URL is the only enforcement mechanism.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Confirmation bias: if the user hints at a target market size, the agent will reverse-engineer to that number.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-commit the methodology and share the ICP definition before revealing the hypothesis. The agent must compute the number before seeing the founder's expectation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Currency drift: agents mix USD, EUR, GBP within one report.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Normalize to USD with a dated FX rate in the report preamble. Require the agent to convert all figures before synthesizing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Confusing GMV with revenue: marketplaces report GMV; SaaS reports ARR. Adding them is invalid.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The agent must identify the revenue metric type for each competitor before including it in the competitor-based sizing. Mixed metrics produce incorrect TAM estimates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale training data: the model "knows" 2023 market sizes and uses them unless forced to fetch.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a fresh web fetch for any post-2024 market number. Add an explicit instruction: "Do not use training data for market size figures; always fetch from a cited source."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Multiplication of fractions: 0.6 × 0.5 × 0.5 × 0.01 generates false precision.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Round each multiplier to one significant figure before multiplying.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring growth: a static $5B TAM today may be $9B at a 12% CAGR in 5 years.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SOM horizon must match TAM horizon. If sizing for 3-year SOM, use 3-year-forward TAM figures.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>"LinkedIn employee count × $200K" rule undercounts services and overcounts seed-stage SaaS.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Disable for any company under 20 people. Use this heuristic only for growth-stage B2B SaaS companies with established sales-to-headcount ratios.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
