<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="AWS Lambda Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules every application of `AWS Lambda` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="memory-cpu-tuned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each function&apos;s memory MUST be tuned via AWS Lambda Power Tuning state machine; the chosen memory must be justified in the function&apos;s README.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda Power Tuning project">Default 128MB memory is rarely optimal; Power Tuning typically halves cost or latency.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="snapstart-or-provisioned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Latency-sensitive Lambdas (p99 &lt; 500ms required) MUST use SnapStart (Java, .NET, Python, Ruby) OR Provisioned Concurrency. On-demand cold starts are forbidden for that tier.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda SnapStart docs; cold-start postmortems">Cold starts for latency-sensitive endpoints break SLOs; SnapStart / PC closes that gap.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="idempotency-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lambdas triggered by SQS / Kinesis / DynamoDB Streams / EventBridge MUST be idempotent (use Powertools Idempotency or equivalent).</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda Powertools docs; event-driven postmortems">Event sources retry on failure; non-idempotent handlers double-charge / double-write / corrupt state.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="structured-logs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lambda logs MUST be JSON-structured with correlation_id, request_id, and Lambda Powertools Logger or equivalent; print() / unstructured logs are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda Powertools docs">Unstructured logs break CloudWatch Logs Insights queries + lineage; JSON logs are searchable + parseable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="xray-tracing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production Lambdas MUST have AWS X-Ray active tracing on; trace headers propagated to downstream services (HTTP / SDK calls).</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS X-Ray docs">Without tracing, debugging cross-service latency is guesswork; X-Ray surfaces the actual hop costs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="dlq-and-retry" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Async event sources MUST have a DLQ + retry policy bounded (max retries ≤ 3 for SQS, retention 14d on DLQ). Sync Lambdas MUST return structured errors.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda event sources docs">Without DLQ, failed async invocations vanish; bounded retries prevent infinite loops.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="least-privilege-execution-role" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Execution roles MUST be per-function (or per-tightly-coupled group), with IAM Access Analyzer policy generation + manual review. Wildcard `*` resources forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS IAM Best Practices; IAM Access Analyzer">Shared / wildcard execution roles leak across functions; per-function roles bound blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="layers-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lambda layers MUST be pinned by ARN + version (no `$LATEST`); shared layers MUST be cross-account-shared with read-only resource policy.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Lambda Layers docs">`$LATEST` layer pins drift silently and break running functions during AWS infra events; ARN+version is the only reproducible pin.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>