<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-audit-types" title="Content Audit Types and When to Run Them">
  <summary>Defines four audit types, the decision matrix for choosing them, and recommended audit frequency by content type.</summary>

  <section title="Audit Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose audit type based on the decision being made: quantitative (inventory — what exists) when scope is unknown; qualitative (quality evaluation) when decisions require quality scoring; comparative (consistency check) when merging or migrating; ROI-focused (analytics-driven) when prioritizing update investment.</statement>
      <rationale>Using a qualitative audit when an inventory suffices wastes effort. Using an inventory-only audit when quality decisions are needed leaves the hardest question unanswered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Quantitative: count and categorize. Qualitative: assess against rubric criteria (accuracy, relevance, quality). Comparative: check consistency across content. ROI-focused: analytics-driven — traffic, engagement, conversions per URL.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="When to Run Each Type">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a full audit (quantitative + qualitative) before any website redesign, content strategy development, or site consolidation. Run rolling quantitative audits for SEO governance. Skip audit entirely for greenfield (no content yet) and for sites under ~50 pages.</statement>
      <rationale>Sites under 50 pages are faster to review manually than to set up crawl tooling. Greenfield needs content modeling, not auditing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Audit Frequency">
    <list>
      <item>Core pages: quarterly</item>
      <item>Blog/news: bi-annually</item>
      <item>Help/support: quarterly</item>
      <item>Product pages: after major releases</item>
      <item>Legal/policy: annually</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat content governance as ongoing, not a one-time event. Establish quality standards, review processes, update schedules, ownership, and archival policies after the first audit.</statement>
      <rationale>One-time audits decay immediately without governance. Content reverts to its pre-audit state within 6-12 months without structured ownership and review triggers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
