<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-scoring-rubric" title="Content Scoring Rubric and Agentic Pipeline">
  <summary>Accuracy/relevance/quality rubric, action decision matrix, and agentic pipeline architecture for LLM-assisted scoring.</summary>

  <section title="Scoring Dimensions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score every URL on three dimensions: accuracy (1-5: is the content correct?), relevance (1-5: do users need this?), and quality (1-5: is the writing clear and complete?). Average the three scores to produce an overall score driving the action column.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-dimension scoring (quality only, or traffic only) misses critical cases: high-traffic but inaccurate content causes brand damage; accurate but unreachable content is wasted investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Action matrix: 4.0+ → keep as is; 3.0-3.9 → update/improve; 2.0-2.9 → rewrite or consolidate; below 2.0 → remove or archive.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat "consolidate" as a distinct action from "remove." Do not collapse low-traffic pages directly to remove when a canonical merge is the better play.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM scoring agents over-classify low-traffic pages as remove. Canonical merging preserves link equity and consolidates thin content without losing it entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Rubric Locking">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the rubric prompt as a versioned YAML file in the repo. Fix temperature=0 and pin the model version for every scoring run. Do not mix scores from different rubric versions or model versions.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM quality scores drift across runs at non-zero temperature. Same page can score 3 vs 4 without a locked rubric. Cross-cycle comparisons require identical scoring conditions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sample 5-10% of LLM scores for human review on every run. Track inter-rater agreement (Cohen's kappa target &gt;0.6) before trusting at scale.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs score coherently but not necessarily correctly for brand voice or strategic relevance. Human spot-checks provide the calibration signal needed to trust the automated column.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pipeline Architecture">
    <rule>
      <statement>Join three data sources before scoring: crawl (existence and structure), GSC (search demand), and GA4 (in-product behavior). Auditing crawl-only produces SEO blind spots.</statement>
      <rationale>Crawl-only audits miss search demand. A low-traffic page with high GSC impressions is under-optimized, not low-value. GA4 shows in-product use that GSC cannot capture.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-extract main content (Trafilatura or Readability) and cap input at ~6k characters per URL before LLM scoring. Do not feed raw HTML.</statement>
      <rationale>Full HTML blows context window and introduces navigation, boilerplate, and script noise. Pre-extraction improves scoring accuracy and reduces token cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rubric.yaml">Version-controlled scoring rubric for LLM prompt injection</reference>
    <reference path="templates/audit-pipeline.py">Async Python pipeline: crawl → extract → score → write scored.jsonl</reference>
  </section>
</text>
