<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="content-audit-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for content-audit-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Incomplete inventory from sitemap-only crawl missing orphan pages, JS-rendered SPAs, PDFs behind auth, and gated content.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Sitemap-only crawls miss 15-30% of URLs depending on site quality. Combine sitemap with log-file or GSC impressions inventory to capture orphans. Exclude gated content before LLM ingestion.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Inventory keyed by URL string rather than URL hash, producing double-counting from redirects and trailing-slash variants.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Redirects and trailing slashes silently duplicate rows. Hash the canonical URL after redirect resolution and use the hash as the join key.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Pages scored by LLM whose value is primarily visual (galleries, infographics, video) receive falsely low quality scores.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs cannot see images. Flag image-heavy pages with a content-type classifier before scoring and route them to human review instead of automated scoring.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Content less than 90 days old scored as low-traffic and flagged for removal.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>GA4 data lags new content by weeks to months. Apply a recency guard: exclude any URL with a publish date less than 90 days before the audit date from traffic-based scoring.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Gated or PII-containing pages sent to a cloud LLM scoring agent without exclusion.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gated content may contain PII. Add a robots-style allowlist check upstream of the scoring agent. Never ingest content the user has not consented to share with an external model.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Running Opus-tier scoring on all URLs in a large site without tiering.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>50k URLs at Opus pricing is non-trivial cost. Use Haiku for first-pass triage, escalate only borderline URLs (score 2-4) to a higher-tier model for re-scoring.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
