<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-audit-and-prioritize" title="Automation Audit and Prioritization">
  <summary>Time audit process, task categorization, ROI formula, and prioritization matrix for selecting automation targets.</summary>

  <section title="Time Audit Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track all activities for one week before selecting automation targets. Do not automate based on memory — track actual time spent.</statement>
      <rationale>Perceived time cost is unreliable. People underestimate daily tasks (done automatically) and overestimate rare tasks (memorable but infrequent). One week of tracking reveals the actual cost distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Repetitive: same email, same data entry, same lookup — automate</item>
      <item>Sequential: multi-step processes triggered by an event — automate</item>
      <item>Scheduled: daily or weekly recurring tasks — automate</item>
      <item>Decision-heavy: strategy, creative judgment — do not automate</item>
      <item>Relationship: sales calls, personal support — partially automate (prep, follow-up)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Automation ROI Formula">
    <rule>
      <statement>Only build automations with a projected ROI greater than 5x in the first year. Below this threshold, maintenance overhead typically exceeds the time saved.</statement>
      <rationale>Automations require ongoing maintenance (tool updates, API changes, logic fixes). Low-ROI automations become net-negative over a 12-month period when maintenance is factored in.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>ROI = (time saved per occurrence x occurrences per month) / (build time + monthly maintenance time). Target: &gt;5x annual return.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Prioritization Matrix">
    <list>
      <item>High priority: daily task, 30+ minutes → automate first</item>
      <item>High priority: error-prone process with costly mistakes (payment, data sync)</item>
      <item>Medium priority: weekly task, 1+ hour → automate second</item>
      <item>Medium priority: impacts customer experience directly</item>
      <item>Low priority: rare task (less than monthly)</item>
      <item>Skip: nice-to-have convenience with minimal time cost</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/automation-audit.md">Weekly time audit template with task categories</reference>
</text>
