<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-robustness-and-tools" title="Automation Robustness and Tool Selection">
  <summary>Error handling requirements, monitoring patterns, tool comparison, and antipatterns for workflow design.</summary>

  <section title="Robustness Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every automation must have: error notification, logging, and a manual fallback path. Silent failures are more damaging than no automation.</statement>
      <rationale>An automation that fails silently (no notification, no log) produces incorrect business state without any signal. A failed lead capture automation means lost leads with no visibility. The manual fallback ensures the process continues even when the automation breaks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Error notification: Slack or email alert when automation fails</item>
      <item>Logging: record each execution with timestamp and status</item>
      <item>Manual fallback: documented steps to run the process without the automation</item>
      <item>Testing: run with sample data before going live</item>
      <item>Staging period: run automation in parallel with manual process for 1 week</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Tool Selection">
    <list>
      <item>Zapier: best for general integrations, no-code, wide app coverage, $Free-599/mo</item>
      <item>Make (formerly Integromat): complex multi-step workflows, visual builder, $Free-299/mo</item>
      <item>n8n: self-hosted, developer-friendly, full control, $Free-50/mo</item>
      <item>IFTTT: simple single-trigger automations, $Free-5/mo</item>
      <item>Pipedream: developer-friendly, serverless, JavaScript/Python, $Free-199/mo</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>For self-hosted environments or complex pipelines requiring custom code, use n8n over Zapier. For quick no-code integrations between popular SaaS tools, use Zapier.</statement>
      <rationale>n8n provides full code execution (Python, JavaScript) and self-hosting, eliminating per-task pricing and data privacy concerns. Zapier provides faster setup with a larger pre-built connector library.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Automating a process before running it manually at least twice and documenting the exact steps.</description>
      <reason>An undefined process cannot be correctly automated. Automating ambiguity at machine speed produces large-scale incorrect outcomes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Building complex branching logic into a single automation workflow.</description>
      <reason>Complex automations are fragile and hard to debug. Split complex logic into simpler, chained automations. Each automation should do one thing clearly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting up an automation and not reviewing it for 3+ months.</description>
      <reason>APIs change, SaaS tools update, data formats shift. An unreviewed automation silently breaks months after deployment. Review all active automations monthly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/automation-inventory.md">Registry of active automations with status tracking</reference>
</text>
