<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-comp-universe" title="Comparable Company Universe Construction">
  <summary>Rules for building a valid comp set with survivorship-bias mitigation and archetype classification.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Build the comp universe before classifying the founder's idea. Anchoring on the founder's preferred archetype biases the universe selection and produces a confirmation table, not a benchmark.</statement>
    <rationale>If you know the founder wants "subscription" before pulling comps, you unconsciously include more subscription companies. The benchmark must be built blind to the preferred conclusion.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Always include at least 2 dead or acquihired comparables in the comp set. Without them, medians overstate viability by 20-40%.</statement>
    <rationale>Survivorship bias: the public-listed and well-documented companies are the ones that succeeded. The failures and acquihires that define the real distribution are invisible unless explicitly sought.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Comp Set Requirements">
    <list>
      <item>Minimum 8 comparables; downgrade from "benchmark" to "case studies" if fewer than 8 are available</item>
      <item>Mix required: public (S-1/10-K), late-stage private (Crunchbase), acquired (M&amp;A press), dead (Crunchbase "Closed")</item>
      <item>At least 20% private and at least 10% dead or acquihired</item>
      <item>Cap any single comp's weight at 1/N — one dominant peer in a 5-comp set is no longer a benchmark</item>
      <item>Cohort by stage (seed/Series-B/listed) AND geography (US/EU/RoW) before computing medians</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Archetype Classification">
    <list>
      <item>subscription: more than 60% of revenue from recurring payments</item>
      <item>one-time: more than 60% from non-recurring purchases</item>
      <item>transaction: more than 60% from per-transaction fees (including marketplace commission)</item>
      <item>advertising: more than 60% from ad inventory or sponsorships</item>
      <item>marketplace: commission + payments + seller subscriptions + ad fees combined (all-in take rate)</item>
      <item>hybrid: no single stream above 60%; tag with the two dominant streams and their split</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never collapse a hybrid model into a single archetype. Shopify is not "subscription" — it is subscription + payments + advertising. Tag hybrid + split, or the archetype table lies.</statement>
      <rationale>Collapsing hybrid revenue models produces incorrect ARPU and gross margin medians. A "subscription" comp that is actually 40% subscription + 40% payments will distort the subscription archetype's metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Definition Glossary (required at top of every report)">
    <list>
      <item>ARR: annualized recurring revenue from subscription contracts only</item>
      <item>ARPU: ARR divided by total active paying accounts</item>
      <item>ACV: annual contract value for a single customer (can differ from ARPU if multi-year discounts apply)</item>
      <item>Gross margin: (revenue - COGS) / revenue; excludes operating expenses</item>
      <item>Gross logo retention: percentage of customer accounts retained year-over-year regardless of expansion or contraction</item>
      <item>NDR (Net Dollar Retention): revenue retained + expansion - contraction - churn from the prior-year cohort</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always pair NDR with gross logo retention. NDR above 110% can coexist with gross logo churn above 25% in a land-and-expand model. Reporting NDR alone hides the real churn problem.</statement>
      <rationale>NDR is a vanity metric when reported in isolation. A small base of large expanding accounts drives NDR up while the majority of smaller accounts churn — the pattern that precedes a retention crisis.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
