<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-metric-harvest" title="Metric Extraction and Normalization">
  <summary>Rules for extracting financial metrics from filings and pricing pages and normalizing across currencies, periods, and line-item definitions.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Tag every metric with source_url and filing_period (YYYY-Qn). Benchmarks without provenance cannot be reviewed, challenged, or refreshed.</statement>
    <rationale>Metrics cited without filing dates become unverifiable over time. Partners and product managers need to know whether a comp's metrics are from last quarter or three years ago.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Primary Sources (ranked by reliability)">
    <list>
      <item>S-1 and 10-K filings: gold standard for ARR, gross margin, gross logo retention, NDR, CAC payback — use SEC EDGAR full-text search</item>
      <item>Wayback Machine pricing snapshots at filing date: list price verified at the moment the metrics were reported</item>
      <item>G2 reviewer-disclosed spend: effective pricing from actual buyers, with contract renewal context</item>
      <item>Crunchbase + press: funding stage, headcount, and M&amp;A status for private comps</item>
      <item>ChartMogul, Baremetrics, ProfitWell public benchmark datasets: pre-computed medians by ARPU band</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Normalization Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Convert all non-USD currency at the filing-period FX rate, not today's rate. Record the FX rate used in the comps CSV.</statement>
      <rationale>Currency moves of 10-20% per year between major pairs (EUR/USD, GBP/USD) distort historical comparisons if today's rate is applied retroactively to prior-period filings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Strip one-time line items (professional services, implementation fees, hardware) from ARR. Include them in a separate "services revenue" column if material (above 10% of total revenue).</statement>
      <rationale>One-time revenue mixed into ARR overstates recurring revenue by 10-25% for companies with implementation-heavy sales motions, making their subscription margins appear higher than reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Annualize monthly numbers. Never compare a monthly ARPU from one comp against an annual ACV from another without explicit normalization.</statement>
      <rationale>Period mismatch is the most common metric error in comp tables. $100/month ARPU is $1,200 ACV, not $100 — a 12x difference that distorts tier-mix and LTV/CAC comparisons.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pricing Page Normalization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Wayback Machine to pin pricing pages to the filing date for each comp. A pricing page scrape newer than the filing period quotes a different price than what the comp's financials reflect.</statement>
      <rationale>SaaS pricing changes frequently (often annually). Using today's pricing against last year's metrics produces false unit-economics comparisons because the price that generated those metrics was different.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
