<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-distribution-and-overlay" title="Distribution Build and Founder-Plan Overlay">
  <summary>How to produce P25/P50/P75 distributions per archetype and overlay the founder's plan with a green/yellow/red flag system.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Quote distribution (P25/P50/P75), never a single median. Single medians create false precision and hide the strategic range the founder needs to understand.</statement>
    <rationale>The spread between P25 and P75 is the actionable signal. A P25-P75 ARPU spread of $15-$80 in a category tells the founder the model has not standardized. A $40-$50 spread tells them it has.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <section title="Distribution Build">
    <list>
      <item>Compute P25/P50/P75 per archetype AND per stage (seed/Series-B/listed)</item>
      <item>Flag comps more than 2 standard deviations from the median with a footnote explaining the cause (e.g., compute COGS, hardware revenue, geographic discount)</item>
      <item>Annotate trends: last 4-8 quarters delta per metric (e.g., usage-based share moved from 20% to 38% of new ARR in dev-tools cohort 2022-2025)</item>
      <item>Flag any P50 metric that shifts more than 10% quarter-over-quarter as a "regime change" warrant for the trend-analysis methodology</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/bm-distribution.sh">Script emitting P25/P50/P75 per archetype from comps.csv</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Founder-Plan Overlay">
    <list>
      <item>Green: founder's planned metric within P25-P75 for their archetype and stage</item>
      <item>Yellow: founder's metric within P10-P25 or P75-P90 — flagged as ambitious or conservative</item>
      <item>Red: founder's metric outside P10-P90 — requires explicit justification or model revision</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not rewrite the founder's plan. Emit a delta only — which cells are out-of-band and what is the most likely source of the discrepancy (model choice, stage mismatch, geography, or pricing page vs. realized ACV).</statement>
      <rationale>Rewriting the plan conflates the market-researcher deliverable (distributions) with the product-manager deliverable (decisions). The researcher surfaces the gap; the founder owns the response.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Re-Run Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-run the benchmark every 2 quarters. Flag any P50 metric that shifts more than 10% as a "regime change" and open an SDD task for the product-manager to revise the roadmap ARR targets.</statement>
      <rationale>SaaS economics shift materially over 6-month periods in fast-moving categories. A benchmark that is 12 months old guides product and pricing decisions toward the wrong target distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
