<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="04-antipatterns" title="Business Model Benchmarking Antipatterns">
  <summary>Common structural failures and AI-agent gotchas in competitor benchmarking and business model classification.</summary>

  <section title="Structural Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Building a comp set with only public-listed companies</description>
      <reason>Survivorship bias: public companies run higher gross margin (78-82%) than venture-stage privates (60-70%) because of scale. Transplanting the median onto a $2M ARR target produces unachievable targets.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Freemium conversion cited as "20%" without denominator disclosure</description>
      <reason>Companies cite conversion against activated or "qualified" users; system-wide conversion from signups is 1-4%. Always normalize to signups or the comparison is meaningless.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>NDR reported without gross logo retention</description>
      <reason>NDR above 110% coexists with gross logo churn above 25% in land-and-expand; the combination indicates an expansion-dependent model at high risk if new logo growth slows.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Averaging cross-stage comps (seed + listed) without cohort annotation</description>
      <reason>A seed-stage Crunchbase pricing page averaged with a listed 10-K produces metrics that apply to neither stage. Cohort by stage before computing any statistic.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent reads "annualized recurring revenue" and treats it as ARPU</description>
      <reason>ARR / ARPU / ACV are three different denominators. Require a glossary block in the output before any metric. Conflating them produces LTV calculations that are 10-500x off.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent forces Shopify into "subscription" archetype</description>
      <reason>Shopify revenue is approximately 40% subscription, 40% payments (Merchant Solutions), and 20% other. Collapsing it to subscription distorts the subscription archetype's gross margin median by 5+ points.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent reports marketplace headline commission (e.g., Etsy 6.5%) as the take rate</description>
      <reason>All-in take rate including seller subscriptions, payment fees, and ad revenue is 13-18% — 2x or more the headline commission. Headline commission misleads strategic pricing decisions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent uses today's pricing page against last year's filing metrics</description>
      <reason>SaaS pricing changes frequently; Wayback Machine snapshots at filing date are required to compare pricing to the financial metrics reported in the same period.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent ships a verdict ("this model is viable") instead of a distribution</description>
      <reason>The market-researcher deliverable is distributions (P25/P50/P75). The verdict belongs to the researcher sibling and the product manager. Inverting this boundary mixes two distinct roles.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/bm-distribution.sh">Script emitting P25/P50/P75 per archetype from comps.csv with N-per-archetype warning</reference>
</text>
