<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-trends" title="2026 Product Development Trend Axes">
  <summary>Four primary trend axes for 2026 product development practice, each with impact and evidence requirements.</summary>

  <section title="Trend Axes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor every trend claim to one URL with a 2025-or-later published date. Reject any claim without a primary source.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM training data is structurally behind real markets. Without a recency gate, agents assert 2023-era practices as 2026 trends.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>AI-augmented ideation — AI scans market trends, identifies gaps, surfaces weak signals from user research; humans decide which signals matter. Impact: pattern recognition at scale.</item>
      <item>Continuous customer feedback — real-time product iteration loops replacing quarterly user research cycles. Impact: shorter hypothesis-to-evidence cycle.</item>
      <item>Rapid pivots — quarterly adjustment cadence replacing annual planning. Impact: lower cost of being wrong, faster signal response.</item>
      <item>Cross-functional teams — PM + Design + Engineering co-owning discovery and delivery. Impact: reduced handoff latency, shared accountability.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Human Ideation Flow">
    <p>AI-augmented ideation is a collaboration pattern, not a replacement. The correct sequence: AI scans market data and surfaces weak signals → AI clusters patterns from user research → Human evaluates which signals are actionable for this product context → Together the pair generates data-grounded feature or product ideas.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Log the human override rate for AI-surfaced ideas. If humans accept more than 90%, the LLM is rubber-stamping, not ideating. If fewer than 10%, the prompt is broken.</statement>
      <rationale>Override rate is the only objective signal that the AI-human collaboration is calibrated. Without it, "AI-augmented ideation" is a label on whatever the team was already doing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Speed Requirements">
    <p>2025+ expectation: insights must be actionable while still relevant. Days, not weeks for turnaround on concept validation. Ability to pivot campaigns and refine prototypes in real-time rather than on fixed sprint cadences.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate process trends (how teams work) from consumer trends (what users want) in every trend brief. Do not mix them in one bullet list.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed trend lists hide which items are actionable for engineering vs marketing. Process trends drive team-shape decisions; consumer trends drive feature and positioning decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Research Outputs">
    <list>
      <item>Market Analysis Reports — size, trends, competitive landscape</item>
      <item>User Need Assessments — pain points, unmet needs with source citations</item>
      <item>Concept Validation Studies — test ideas before building, minimum 10 data points</item>
      <item>Feature Priority Reports — what to build first, ranked by evidence strength</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Consumer Trends (2025-2026)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Consumer trend bullets require URL-grounded citations. Do not accept "sustainability" or "AI-first" as a finding without a primary source published in 2025 or later.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs recycle consumer trend language from training data. "Brands that do good" has appeared in trend lists since 2018; it is only meaningful if current primary data shows it driving purchase decisions in your specific market.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Increasing demand for brands demonstrating measurable social impact</item>
      <item>Sustainable and eco-friendly product attributes as decision factors</item>
      <item>Blending quantitative and qualitative data in a single research platform</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-methodology.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-gotchas.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/collect-trends.py"/>
    <link path="templates/score-signals.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
