<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-methodology" title="Trend Research Pipeline">
  <summary>Two-pass pipeline for trend research: broad signal collection, then scored triage using recency, evidence, and applicability dimensions.</summary>

  <section title="Two-Pass Pipeline">
    <p>Pass 1 (Opus-led): strategic scan ingests the four trend axes, emits a structured JSON spec per signal with fields: trend, signal, source_url, confidence (0-1), impact (H/M/L). Pass 2 (Sonnet-led, parallel): one subagent per trend axis fetches WebSearch + WebFetch evidence and writes one section. Final reviewer subagent merges sections, deduplicates, and flags unsourced claims.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Human must approve the Pass 1 JSON spec (the 4-6 trend axes and their framing) before Pass 2 sweeps begin.</statement>
      <rationale>Pass 2 costs significant WebSearch quota. If the axes are wrong, all that work is wasted. The checkpoint is cheap; the correction is not.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Signal Scoring">
    <p>Score each signal on three dimensions, max 9 points total. Drop any signal scoring below 5.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Recency: 3 if published within 30 days, 2 if 31-90 days, 1 if 91-180 days, 0 if older than 180 days</item>
      <item>Evidence: 3 if primary source (vendor changelog, primary research), 2 if 3+ independent citations, 1 if secondary aggregator</item>
      <item>Applicability: 0-3 assigned by the human reviewer based on fit to this specific product context</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/score-signals.py">Python script implementing recency/evidence scoring and threshold filtering</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Output Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Date-stamp every claim at the bullet level, not just the document. Future agents diff bullet-dates to detect staleness.</statement>
      <rationale>Document-level dates hide which specific claims aged out. Bullet-level dates let the next quarterly run surgically replace stale items rather than regenerating the entire brief.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Include a "kill list" section: for every trend you adopt, name one current practice you stop.</statement>
      <rationale>Trend reports without subtractions are theatre. A kill list forces the team to make a real trade-off and signals which prior commitments are being abandoned.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Persist the raw signals as .aidocs/research/raw/signals.jsonl. The diff between this quarter and the previous file is more useful than the polished narrative.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Recommended Subagents">
    <list>
      <item>faion-research-agent (mode: market or ideas) — orchestrator for trend signal collection</item>
      <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — converts accepted trend implications into backlog/ features with acceptance criteria</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Route any feature spawned by trend research through faion-sdd-executor-agent with explicit acceptance criteria. "Act on trend X" is not a feature.</statement>
      <rationale>Trend-to-feature translation without acceptance criteria produces vague tickets that no one can implement or verify.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
