<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-gotchas" title="Trend Research Gotchas">
  <summary>Critical failure modes in trend research: training-cutoff bias, hallucinated cross-functional claims, SEO-ranked results, vendor copy, human-in-the-loop gates.</summary>

  <section title="Training Cutoff Bias">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting trend assertions without a 2025+ URL, resulting in 2023-era practices presented as 2026 trends.</description>
      <reason>LLM training data is structurally behind real markets. "OKRs revival" and "design sprints" were popular in 2023 and will confidently appear as 2026 trends unless a hard recency gate is enforced.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Over-indexing on US and San Francisco Bay Area sources without requiring EU or APAC primary sources.</description>
      <reason>Most LLM training data and most tech media is US-centric. A trend that is maturing in SF may be early or absent in EU/APAC markets. Require at least one EU and one APAC source per trend axis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Hallucinated Claims">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting "cross-functional teams" or "rapid pivots, quarterly cycles" as findings without a concrete artifact (org chart, job posting, public retro, case study).</description>
      <reason>These are popular LLM completions that recombine from training data regardless of evidence. Require a named team or published case study; reject cadence claims without a specific organisation and source.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Letting three citations to the same secondary article inflate confidence for a claim.</description>
      <reason>HBR, McKinsey blog, and Forbes often cite each other. Three links to the same underlying source count as one evidence point, not three.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Search Quality">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using raw WebSearch results ranked by SEO rather than by publication date.</description>
      <reason>SEO-optimised blog spam ranks above primary research. Sort by published date in the scraper and down-rank domains on a vendor-blog denylist before summarising.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer primary sources (Linear's public changelog, PostHog's product blog, Dovetail's annual research reports) over secondary aggregators for trend evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Primary sources reflect real practice at named organisations; secondary aggregators amplify whatever is fashionable regardless of whether it ships outcomes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scope Creep">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Conflating product-development-trends-2026 with product-development-trends (the non-year-pinned sibling methodology).</description>
      <reason>Two subagents running simultaneously on overlapping prompts produce two reports that a merge agent will silently resolve by choosing one, discarding the other.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap the token cost of the synthesis stage by pre-filtering signals with the scoring script before invoking Opus-class synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale>Synthesis on 50+ unfiltered signals on Opus can exceed 100k tokens. The scoring script reduces the input to the 8-12 strongest signals, keeping synthesis cost proportionate to the value delivered.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Human-in-the-Loop Checkpoints">
    <list>
      <item>After Pass 1 JSON spec: human confirms the 4-6 trend axes are the right ones for this product context before Pass 2 sweeps begin.</item>
      <item>Before writing into .aidocs/product_docs/: human accepts the final scored signal table. Hallucinated tool or vendor names must not land in deliverables.</item>
      <item>Before merging trend report into roadmap: human signs off on framing. This document shapes roadmap conversations.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
