<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-panel-types" title="Spatial UI Panel Types, Ergonomics, and Window Management">
  <summary>Four spatial panel types with their behaviors, use cases, and ergonomic constraints; window management conventions; and concrete DO/DON'T rules for spatial UI placement.</summary>

  <section title="Panel Type Taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to world-locked panels for reference content and body-locked panels for primary UI; reserve hand-attached panels for ephemeral quick-access tools only.</statement>
      <rationale>World-locked panels are stable and restful for sustained reading. Body-locked panels follow position but not head rotation, keeping primary UI reachable without arm fatigue. Hand-attached panels are convenient but fatiguing if used for sustained interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use head-locked panels in visionOS (Apple HIG forbids it) and avoid them in Quest unless the use case is specifically HUD telemetry with explicit user consent.</statement>
      <rationale>Head-locked UI prevents the user from looking away from content without moving the UI, creating a coercive visual experience and causing discomfort. Current platform HIGs converge on this prohibition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>World-locked: fixed in world space; use for reference content, anchored documents, spatial annotations</item>
      <item>Head-locked: follows gaze direction; restricted to HUD overlays only, never for primary UI</item>
      <item>Body-locked: follows user position but not rotation; use for menus, tool palettes, primary app windows</item>
      <item>Hand-attached: positioned on wrist or hand; use for quick-access controls, contextual micro-menus</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Ergonomic Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Place primary panels at a minimum 1 m distance from the user's head; content closer than 0.5 m causes vergence-accommodation conflict and eye strain.</statement>
      <rationale>The human visual system has difficulty resolving vergence (where eyes point) and accommodation (where eyes focus) at close distances in optical HMDs. 1 m is the established safe minimum for sustained content.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap panel angular size at 40° of field of view; larger panels force head movement to read content, creating fatigue.</statement>
      <rationale>40° of FoV allows comfortable reading without head movement. Panels that fill 80° or more require constant scanning, mimicking the fatigue of an oversized monitor at close range.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set interactive target minimum at 60x60 pt at 1 m apparent distance in visionOS, or approximately 3 cm physical size for direct-touch interactions.</statement>
      <rationale>Smaller targets cause selection errors with gaze-and-pinch at the tracking latency typical of current HMDs. Platform guidelines (Apple HIG) formalize these minima.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Reference document: world-locked at 1.5 m, 35° wide. Tool palette: body-locked, right-side, 0.8 m, 20° wide. Quick bookmark: hand-attached left wrist. All targets 70x70 pt.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Navigation menu: head-locked, 0.3 m away, 60° wide. Causes eye strain, constant vergence conflict, and blocks 60% of FoV, occluding world content.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Window Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Persist panel positions across sessions where the platform supports it (ARWorldMap, OpenXR persistent anchors); rebuild gracefully when persistence fails.</statement>
      <rationale>Spatial memory — the ability to return objects to where the user left them — is a key usability advantage of spatial computing. Losing panel positions on each launch removes this advantage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide redundant input modalities for all spatial interactions: gaze-and-pinch, controller trigger, and voice at minimum; never assume hand tracking is reliable.</statement>
      <rationale>Hand tracking fails under gloves, low lighting, fast motion, and non-standard hand morphology. Controller fallback must be designed in, not added after.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/SpatialApp.swift">Minimal visionOS scene scaffold with WindowGroup, Volume, and ImmersiveSpace</reference>
  </section>
</text>
