<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SLO Design From User Journeys Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn SLO design from a metric-picking exercise into a journey-grounded contract before the first production deploy.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-journey-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every SLI MUST be expressed as a ratio of "good events / valid events" tied to a named user journey; raw single-metric SLIs (CPU%, p95 latency alone) are forbidden as service-level indicators.</statement>
      <rationale>SRE practice (Google SRE book, ch. 4) is unambiguous that journey-grounded ratios are the only SLI form that aligns with user-perceived reliability. Raw infra metrics are decoration; the dashboards become noise on-call learns to ignore.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Journey: "User completes checkout"
SLI = count(checkout_requests_total{result="success",
            duration_le="2s"})
    / count(checkout_requests_total{valid="true"})
SLO target: 99.5% over 30 days]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-three-slos-max" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A service MUST define no more than 3 SLOs at first launch; pick the journeys that produce revenue, retention, or trust — not every endpoint.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams that ship 20 SLOs on day one cannot keep them honest, alerts get muted, and the entire SLO discipline loses credibility. Limiting to 3 forces a journey-ranking conversation with product/business — exactly the alignment SLO design is meant to produce.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-baseline-anchored-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The initial SLO target MUST be set within ±1 percentage point of the 30-day historical SLI performance; aspirational "we'll do 99.99%" targets without baseline measurement are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Without it the dashboards are decoration — and so are aspirational SLOs. Targets disconnected from current performance either trip immediately (alert fatigue) or never trip (zero signal). Anchoring on measured baseline keeps the SLO meaningful from day one.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-business-sign-off" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every SLO MUST be reviewed and signed off by a business stakeholder (product manager, founder, or customer-success lead) who confirms that the target reflects acceptable customer impact.</statement>
      <rationale>SLOs without business sign-off mean engineering picks numbers in a vacuum and product is surprised when capacity / cost / freeze decisions cite the SLO. The sign-off converts the SLO into a shared contract.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every SLO MUST name a single accountable owner (handle) who is responsible for the SLI implementation, the dashboard, and the periodic review; team-only ownership is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale>Like every operational artefact, SLOs decay without a named caretaker. The owner is who triages "is this SLI broken or is the service actually broken" at 02:00, and who drives the quarterly review.</rationale>
      <example type="bad">
        <description>"Owner: SRE team"</description>
        <reason>When the SLI breaks at 02:00, the team channel goes unread until the morning standup and the SLO loses credibility.</reason>
      </example>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
