<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-interaction-patterns">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Input modalities for spatial computing: hand tracking, controllers, gaze, voice, gesture. Choose primary per task with fallback modality for accessibility.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-interaction</tag>
      <tag>input-modalities</tag>
      <tag>xr-design</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>gesture-design</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>spatial</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-24</created>
    <updated>2026-04-25</updated>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Spatial Interaction Patterns</title>
    <summary>Input modalities and interaction patterns for spatial (AR/VR/MR) computing: hand tracking, controllers, gaze, voice, and gesture. Design interaction state machines for direct manipulation, ray-cast selection, or gaze+dwell with primary + fallback modalities.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Spatial interaction has fundamentally different constraints than touch or mouse. Each input modality (hands, controllers, gaze, voice) has different precision, latency, fatigue, and accessibility tradeoffs. Fixed pattern catalog without platform context hides hardware-specific constraints: Vision Pro is gaze-pinch first; Quest 3 emphasizes controllers; HoloLens leans hand-tracking + air-tap. Choosing the wrong modality causes fatigue (gorilla-arm, dwell fatigue), accessibility failures, and poor discoverability.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Choosing input modality (hands / controllers / gaze / voice / gesture) per task in an XR app.</item>
        <item>Designing interaction state machines for direct manipulation, ray-cast selection, or gaze+dwell.</item>
        <item>Drafting accessibility-friendly multi-modal alternatives (voice or gaze fallback for fine motor).</item>
        <item>Specifying gesture vocabulary and conflict resolution in mixed-input apps.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>2D mobile/desktop interactions — wrong vocabulary entirely.</item>
        <item>Pure 360° lean-back content where the user does not interact.</item>
        <item>Pre-strategy phases — pair with spatial-ux-fundamentals first to set field/scale before pattern choice.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Input Modalities">
      <p>Five primary input channels for spatial interaction:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Hand tracking — Direct manipulation, natural interactions, high comfort at close range.</item>
        <item>Controllers — Precise input, gaming, creative work, reliable in all lighting.</item>
        <item>Gaze — Selection, navigation, accessibility, passive input, avoids arm fatigue.</item>
        <item>Voice — Commands, input, hands-free, text entry, works across modalities.</item>
        <item>Gesture — Shortcuts, commands, quick actions, discoverable only with onboarding.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Interaction Patterns">
      <section name="Direct Manipulation">
        <p>User grabs objects in 3D space with their hands:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Grab and move objects — primary pattern for direct spatial interaction.</item>
          <item>Pinch to resize — fine motor control, high precision.</item>
          <item>Two-hand rotation — symmetric, spatial manipulation.</item>
          <item>Physics-based throwing — satisfying but discoverable only with onboarding.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Ray-Casting">
        <p>User points at distant objects via controller or hand:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Point at distant objects — ray from hand or controller through 3D space.</item>
          <item>Selection confirmation (click/pinch) — commit action at target.</item>
          <item>Laser pointer metaphor — visual feedback, familiar from VR gaming.</item>
          <item>Good for menus, far content — complements direct manipulation.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Gaze + Dwell">
        <p>User looks at target; dwell time confirms:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Look at target — gaze vector as primary input.</item>
          <item>Dwell time confirms selection — timing window (600-1200 ms) before action fires.</item>
          <item>Good for accessibility — avoids arm fatigue, works with limited motor.</item>
          <item>Avoids arm fatigue — pure eye-based, no arm raise required.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Integration — When to use">
      <list>
        <item>Choosing input modality (hands / controllers / gaze / voice / gesture) per task in an XR app.</item>
        <item>Designing interaction state machines for direct manipulation, ray-cast selection, or gaze+dwell.</item>
        <item>Drafting accessibility-friendly multi-modal alternatives (voice or gaze fallback for fine motor).</item>
        <item>Specifying gesture vocabulary and conflict resolution in mixed-input apps.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Where it fails / limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Fixed pattern catalog hides hardware-specific constraints: Vision Pro is gaze-pinch first; Quest 3 emphasizes controllers; HoloLens leans hand-tracking + air-tap.</item>
        <item>Doesn't address fatigue economics (gorilla-arm, dwell fatigue, controller wrist load) — needs supplementary ergonomic data.</item>
        <item>Multi-input conflict (voice + hand + gaze in same moment) is a known failure mode the table glosses over.</item>
        <item>Performance: heavy hand-tracking + ray-cast at 90 Hz causes thermal throttling on standalone HMDs.</item>
        <item>Accessibility: gaze+dwell users with nystagmus or limited gaze control have no fallback in many engines.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic workflow">
      <p>Drive Claude to produce a per-task input matrix (task × modality) with a recommended primary + fallback, then expand each into a state machine (idle → hover → engaged → committed → released) with timing thresholds. A second agent runs heuristic checks: conflict between modalities, missing accessibility fallback, fatigue red flags. Engine code (Unity XR / RealityKit / WebXR) is generated only after human review of the state machine.</p>
      <section name="Recommended subagents">
        <list>
          <item>faion-ux-researcher-agent — usability-test plan for each pattern with HMD users.</item>
          <item>faion-usability-agent — heuristic eval for fatigue, conflict, and accessibility.</item>
          <item>A custom xr-input-state-linter — given a state-machine spec, flag missing transitions or overlapping triggers.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Prompt pattern">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[For task <T> on <device>, produce:
- Primary input modality + rationale (precision, fatigue, social context).
- Fallback modality (accessibility / when primary unavailable).
- State machine: idle, hover, engaged, committed, released. Trigger + timing per transition.
- Conflict rules vs. concurrent modalities.]]></code>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI tools">
      <list>
        <item>Unity xr-interaction-toolkit — Standard XR input abstraction (docs.unity3d.com/Packages/com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit)</item>
        <item>OpenXR khronos-tools — Cross-vendor input layer (khronos.org/openxr)</item>
        <item>Apple visionOS Simulator (xcrun simctl) — Drive gaze-pinch in CI (developer.apple.com/visionos)</item>
        <item>meta-quest-developer-hub — Sideload + capture input traces (developer.oculus.com/downloads)</item>
        <item>Three.js + WebXR Input Profiles — Web-based gesture testing (github.com/immersive-web/webxr-input-profiles)</item>
        <item>MediaPipe Hands — Hand-tracking outside HMD for prototyping (google.github.io/mediapipe)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Services &amp; apps">
      <p>XR platforms and input frameworks:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Unity 6 + XRI (Commercial) — Yes (CLI build). De facto standard XR input library.</item>
        <item>Unreal + OpenXR (Commercial) — Partial. More codegen friction.</item>
        <item>Apple RealityKit / Reality Composer Pro (Free, Apple) — Limited. Vision Pro native; gaze+pinch idioms baked in.</item>
        <item>Bezi / ShapesXR (SaaS) — Partial. Spatial wireframing with input intent.</item>
        <item>Microsoft MRTK3 (Mixed Reality Toolkit) (OSS) — Yes. Hand + voice + eye for HoloLens/Quest.</item>
        <item>Tobii / Pupil Labs (SaaS + SDK) — Yes. Standalone eye-tracking SDKs for fallback design.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="State Machine Linter">
      <p>Inline state-machine validation in Python:</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[import json, sys
REQUIRED = {"idle", "hover", "engaged", "committed", "released"}
def lint(spec):
    issues = []
    for ix, ix_spec in spec["interactions"].items():
        states = {s["name"] for s in ix_spec["states"]}
        missing = REQUIRED - states
        if missing: issues.append(f"{ix}: missing states {missing}")
        triggers = {}
        for s in ix_spec["states"]:
            for t in s.get("transitions", []):
                key = (s["name"], t["trigger"])
                if key in triggers:
                    issues.append(f"{ix}: duplicate trigger {t['trigger']} from {s['name']}")
                triggers[key] = t["to"]
        if not ix_spec.get("fallback_modality"):
            issues.append(f"{ix}: missing fallback modality")
        if ix_spec.get("primary_modality") == "gaze_dwell" and \
           ix_spec.get("dwell_ms", 0) < 600:
            issues.append(f"{ix}: dwell <600ms causes mis-fire")
    return issues
if __name__ == "__main__":
    for i in lint(json.load(open(sys.argv[1]))): print(i)]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="Best practices">
      <list>
        <item>Default to the platform's idiomatic primary (gaze-pinch on Vision Pro, controllers on Quest, air-tap on HoloLens) and only override with strong reason.</item>
        <item>Always pair direct manipulation with a ray-cast fallback for distant or large objects — reach is not infinite.</item>
        <item>Throw + physics is satisfying but discoverable only with onboarding; don't make it a primary action.</item>
        <item>Provide haptic + audio + visual confirmation on commit; spatial input is noisier than touch.</item>
        <item>Use 600-1200 ms dwell defaults for gaze-confirm; below 600 ms causes mis-fires, above 1200 ms feels broken.</item>
        <item>Budget for "fatigue scenes" — design 5-min sit breaks into long workflows.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-agent gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs invent gestures that the platform doesn't recognize (custom finger snaps, etc.); constrain to OpenXR / platform gesture sets only.</item>
        <item>Generated state machines often skip the released state, leaking event handlers in engine code.</item>
        <item>Auto-generated Unity / RealityKit code drifts behind SDK versions; pin versions in the prompt.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoint: any new gesture or pattern must be validated in HMD by a designer; agents cannot judge fatigue, comfort, or social-acceptability ("clap in public" passes lint but fails reality).</item>
        <item>For accessibility: the agent must explicitly justify fallback modality choice; do not accept "user can also use controller" without a switch/voice path.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/inputs">Apple Human Interface Guidelines — visionOS Inputs</link>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/resources">Meta Quest VR Interaction Patterns</link>
      <link href="https://learn.microsoft.com/windows/mixed-reality/mrtk-unity">Microsoft MRTK3 docs</link>
      <link href="https://khronos.org/openxr">OpenXR Specification</link>
      <link href="https://github.com/immersive-web/webxr-input-profiles">W3C WebXR Input Profiles</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
