<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Demo Recap Email Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules with rationale + source for demo-recap-email-template. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="six-block-shape" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every recap email MUST carry six blocks in this order: header (sprint + date + attendees), demoed features (linked to tickets), decisions made (with named decider), scope deltas (added / removed / parked), open items (with named owner + due date), next demo date + scope.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMBOK 7 stakeholder communications">PMBOK 7 stakeholder communications — applies to Demo Recap Email Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-decider" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every decision MUST name the human who made it; ambiguous attribution ('the team agreed') is forbidden — use HiPPO-override discipline from facilitation-anti-patterns.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 stakeholder analysis">BABOK v3 stakeholder analysis — applies to Demo Recap Email Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="delta-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each scope delta MUST cite the ticket id (or new ticket created) where the change is captured; prose-only scope deltas are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Change control discipline (PMBOK)">Change control discipline (PMBOK) — applies to Demo Recap Email Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="owner-and-date" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each open item MUST have a single named owner and an ISO date; a bare to-be-decided placeholder is rejected — escalate to sponsor instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-owner accountability principle">Single-owner accountability principle — applies to Demo Recap Email Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="send-within-24h" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Recap email MUST be sent within 24 hours of demo end; later than that the client memory drift dominates and the email loses authority.</statement>
      <rationale source="Communication-recency research">Communication-recency research — applies to Demo Recap Email Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ack-or-objection-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Email asks client for ack or objection within 48 hours of send; silence beyond that window is recorded as 'tacit acceptance' in the engagement log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Outsource governance practice">Outsource governance practice — applies to Demo Recap Email Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the engagement has no recurring demo cadence or the client refuses written records, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Demo Recap Email Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
