<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for interview-recording-redaction-pipeline. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="consent-record-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every recording MUST have a consent record (signed or recorded verbal) linked to the file; consent missing → auto-delete after grace period.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Article 7 + HIPAA">GDPR Article 7 + HIPAA — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="transcript-generated-locally" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Transcript MUST be generated by a tool the BA controls (local Whisper, on-prem ASR); external SaaS transcript without BAA / DPA is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Data-processor discipline">Data-processor discipline — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="auto-redact-pii-categories" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pipeline MUST auto-redact at least 8 PII categories: names, emails, phone numbers, addresses, SSN/NIE/IPN, credit-card numbers, IP addresses, medical IDs. Output flags un-redactable spans for human review.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Article 4 + HIPAA Safe Harbor">GDPR Article 4 + HIPAA Safe Harbor — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="human-review-checkpoint" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto-redacted transcript MUST pass a named human reviewer before sharing; the review event is logged with reviewer id + timestamp.</statement>
      <rationale source="Two-person rule for sensitive data">Two-person rule for sensitive data — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="retention-tiered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Retention tiered: raw recording 30 days, redacted transcript 12 months, derived analysis 5 years; each tier auto-deletes after its window.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR storage-limitation principle">GDPR storage-limitation principle — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="access-log-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every access to raw recording or unredacted transcript MUST be logged (who, when, why); access without logging is treated as a breach.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-trail discipline">Audit-trail discipline — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="breach-process-defined" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If a recording leaks (storage breach, access without log, redaction failure), engage breach process: notify within 24h, isolate, root-cause within 7 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Article 33">GDPR Article 33 — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If no recordings exist or BA has no custody of recordings, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Interview Recording Redaction Pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
