<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Trunk-Based Challenges &amp; Diagnostics Failure Modes" version="2.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="blame-tbd" severity="high">
      <symptom>Postmortem after the third trunk break of the week concludes 'trunk-based development is wrong for us; let's go back to GitFlow'.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="field experience">Team treats trunk-based development as the cause; ignores missing gate (CI speed, branch protection, flags).</root-cause>
      <fix>Run the ordered checklist. Fix the first failing gate. Re-evaluate after 2 weeks before any structural change to branching.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="kitchen-sink-recommendation" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Report lists 17 actions; team prioritises by gut; nothing improves in 6 weeks.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="field experience">Failed to apply ordered checklist; treated all symptoms equally.</root-cause>
      <fix>Identify ONE first failing check. Ship its fix. Re-measure. Only then move to the next.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="single-reviewer-bottleneck" severity="medium">
      <symptom>All PRs touching domain X queue behind Alice; PRs age 2 days waiting.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="field experience">Single-reviewer policy by accident, not design.</root-cause>
      <fix>Train a second reviewer; rotate primary-reviewer monthly; add CODEOWNERS with at least 2 entries per path.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="long-branch-with-feature-too-big" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Developer opens a 9-day branch claiming 'feature is too big to chunk'.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="field experience">Task decomposition not applied; BbA available but not used.</root-cause>
      <fix>Apply trunk-based-branch-by-abstraction; split the work into trunk-merged increments behind a flag.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="untracked-flags" severity="high">
      <symptom>Audit finds 47 active flags; no one knows what 12 of them gate; old flags still being evaluated at runtime.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="field experience">No flag inventory; cleanup tickets never filed.</root-cause>
      <fix>Build .aidocs/feature-flags.md as the canonical inventory; require task-id + cleanup-ticket per flag; review weekly until backlog &lt; 10 stale flags.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
