<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="STAR Interview Method Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the STAR Interview Method methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale. Hard rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For every story the candidate tells, probe Situation/Task/Action/Result completeness explicitly; reject pronoun ambiguity ('we did X' → 'what did YOU do?').</statement>
      <rationale source="Behavioral interviewing literature (Janz et al.)">STAR's diagnostic power depends on completeness; partial stories (S + R only) leave action invisible and surface team narratives instead of individual evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Notes are evidence-anchored: each scorecard line cites a specific quote, action, or number from the story — not the interviewer's interpretation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — calibration retro Q4 2025">Anchored notes make debrief defensible; interpretive notes ('seemed driven') collapse on push-back.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Submit the scorecard within 24h of the round; later submission contaminates with other candidates and post-hoc rationalization.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — interview QA Q2 2026">Memory decay is fastest in the first 24h; latency in submission has measurable effect on inter-rater disagreement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each behavioral round covers ≥2 competencies in 45-60 minutes; one-competency rounds waste candidate and interviewer time and force per-round overhead.</statement>
      <rationale source="Structured Hiring practice handbook">Cost-per-signal is what the interview process optimizes; coverage breadth per round dominates other tactical choices.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hire/no-hire recommendation MUST be present on the scorecard with at least two cited pieces of evidence; 'lean hire' without evidence is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — calibration retro Q4 2025">Recommendations without evidence push the debrief into 'whose gut do we trust' territory; cited evidence forces calibration.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
