<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Growth Affiliate Marketing Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Growth Affiliate Marketing` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="commission-ltv-capped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Total commission per acquired customer MUST be &lt;= 25% of LTV in the first 12 months. Recurring tiers allowed but capped at 30% lifetime.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tapfiliate / Impact partner-economics analyses">Commissions above the cap turn affiliate channel into a worse-than-paid-ads channel — high CAC + share of LTV. Cap forces deliberate tradeoff vs. paid.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="cookie-duration-30-90-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cookie attribution window MUST be 30-90 days. Shorter under-rewards consideration cycles; longer creates over-attribution + revenue dispute.</statement>
      <rationale source="affiliate-platform default settings; partner agreement reviews">30 days catches direct-response sales; 60-90 catches B2B consideration cycles. Outside this range, attribution becomes noise or theft.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ftc-disclosure-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every affiliate MUST agree to FTC disclosure rules in writing (US partners) + ASA/EU equivalents where applicable. Audit &gt;= 10% of placements quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale source="FTC 16 CFR Part 255; ASA guidance UK 2024">Undisclosed affiliate content is a regulatory liability AND a trust hit. FTC fines + platform deplatforming risk. Disclosure is the contract; quarterly audit is the proof.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="recruit-by-audience-match-not-size" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Affiliate recruitment MUST prioritize audience-match over follower count. 10k-engaged &gt; 100k-broadcast for conversion.</statement>
      <rationale source="PartnerStack benchmarks 2024; Pat Flynn affiliate playbook">Big-list affiliates send tire-kickers; small-list niche affiliates send buyers. Recruitment criteria: audience overlap + content alignment + engagement rate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="fraud-detection-active" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Active fraud detection MUST run (cookie stuffing, self-referrals, brand-keyword bidding). Quarterly affiliate audit + click-pattern monitor.</statement>
      <rationale source="Impact / Refersion fraud-detection docs">Affiliate fraud (cookie stuffing, brand-name bidding, fake conversions) silently leaks 10-25% of program budget. Active detection + auditable cancellation policy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
