<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-program-design" title="Affiliate Program Design">
  <summary>Commission models, payout terms, cookie duration, fraud prevention rules, and program structure decisions.</summary>

  <section title="Commission Models">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap total commission at less than 30% of 12-month LTV; anything above makes the program net-loss when factoring in platform and admin costs.</statement>
      <rationale>Commission must be sustainable at scale. A 40% payout on a $99 LTV product produces a slow bleed as the affiliate roster grows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <section title="Model Types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Choose the commission model based on product type: percentage-of-sale for digital subscriptions, flat fee for high-ticket services, recurring (lifetime) for SaaS with high LTV, tiered for motivating top performers.</statement>
        <rationale>Recurring commissions on SaaS align affiliate incentives with retention; flat fees suit high-ticket or services where LTV is predictable but average order value is high.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Program Terms">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set cookie duration to 30-90 days; use last-touch attribution by default and document it explicitly in affiliate terms.</statement>
      <rationale>Cookie duration below 30 days loses affiliates who produce delayed conversions from content like blog posts. Attribution model must be declared up front to avoid disputes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Delay payouts 30-60 days after the sale to cover the refund window; pay outstanding commissions on program termination.</statement>
      <rationale>Paying out before the refund window closes loses money on cancellations. Reliable on-schedule payment is the top factor affiliates use to rate a program.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Set a minimum payout threshold ($50-100) and pay monthly on a fixed schedule.</statement>
      <rationale>Small payouts create processing overhead. A predictable schedule builds trust; erratic payments cause affiliate churn.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Fraud Prevention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Explicitly prohibit brand-keyword PPC bidding, coupon-site listing, spam/unsolicited email, and incentivized traffic in program terms; monitor for violations and enforce termination.</statement>
      <rationale>Coupon-site and brand-keyword affiliates cannibalize cheap organic conversions. Spam traffic violates FTC endorsement rules and can produce chargebacks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag transactions where the same IP records more than 3 sales in 1 hour, click-to-conversion time is under 30 seconds, or referrer is a known coupon domain.</statement>
      <rationale>These patterns indicate click stuffing or transaction injection. Automated fraud sweeps before payout approval prevent irreversible losses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Two-tier (MLM-style) commission structures where affiliates earn on recruits' sales.</description>
      <reason>Attracts low-quality recruiters; creates FTC compliance risk and tax-form complexity with no proportional lift in quality referrals.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Backstop cookie-only attribution with promo codes and logged-in-user attribution to recover the 20-40% of conversions lost to iOS 14.5, ITP, and ad-blockers.</statement>
      <rationale>Cookie-only tracking understates affiliate contribution and underpays honest affiliates while overpaying last-click coupon sites that inject themselves after attribution is broken.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/payout-calc.py">Monthly payout calculation with 30-day refund holdback</reference>
</text>
