<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-recruitment-and-enablement" title="Affiliate Recruitment and Enablement">
  <summary>Affiliate type selection, outreach approach, asset library requirements, and onboarding sequence design.</summary>

  <section title="Affiliate Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize niche newsletter writers as first-recruit targets; they typically offer the highest CPM-equivalent ROI versus broad bloggers because their audience trust is higher and topic alignment is tighter.</statement>
      <rationale>Newsletter writers have direct inbox access to a pre-qualified audience. Open rates above 25% with prior sponsored content signal monetization willingness and audience trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <section title="Type Reference">
      <p>High-value types in order of typical effort-to-revenue: newsletter writers (low effort, targeted), course creators (low effort, curriculum integration), power users/existing customers (low effort, authentic voice), comparison sites (medium effort, high intent traffic), content bloggers (medium effort, SEO value), agencies recommending to clients (medium effort, B2B).</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Outreach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Personalize outreach with a specific reference to the affiliate's recent content before mentioning the program; generic "partnership opportunity" emails get ignored.</statement>
      <rationale>Affiliates receive mass outreach constantly. A specific reference proves you are a real reader and increases reply rate significantly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>State the commission structure and average monthly earnings range in the first outreach message; affiliates will not reply to vague "great opportunity" messages.</statement>
      <rationale>Time is the affiliate's constraint. Concrete numbers allow instant triage. "Our top affiliates earn $X/month" backed by real distribution data also sets honest expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/affiliate-welcome-email.md">Welcome email with link, dashboard access, quick-start steps</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Asset Library">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide at minimum: unique tracking links, banner ads (multiple sizes), email swipe copy, social post copy, demo video, and case studies before recruiting affiliates.</statement>
      <rationale>Affiliates promote what is easy to use. Without assets, even motivated affiliates stall. The asset library quality is the single biggest predictor of activation rate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Launching the program without an asset library and expecting affiliates to create their own promotional materials.</description>
      <reason>Affiliates abandon programs that require significant creative work; they move to programs that make promotion frictionless.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Onboarding Sequence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a structured onboarding sequence: Day 0 welcome + credentials, Day 1 dashboard tutorial, Day 3 best-performing strategies, Day 7 check-in, Day 14 first-sale tips, Day 30 recap.</statement>
      <rationale>80% of affiliates who don't produce a sale in the first 30 days never will. A structured onboarding shortens time-to-first-sale and increases the activation rate above 30%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a "top 10 starter playbook" covering the highest-converting tactics from existing affiliates so new partners can copy proven approaches immediately.</statement>
      <rationale>New affiliates lack context on what messaging and channels work. Sharing winning tactics reduces experimentation time and aligns affiliate copy with brand standards.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Ongoing Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Recompute LTV quarterly and adjust commission tiers accordingly; never let affiliates discover a commission cut mid-campaign.</statement>
      <rationale>Affiliates plan promotional calendars around commission rates. Surprise cuts destroy trust and trigger public complaints in affiliate communities.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
