<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-affiliate-marketing Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-affiliate-marketing as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Two-tier (MLM-style) commission structures where affiliates earn on recruits' sales.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Attracts low-quality recruiters; creates FTC compliance risk and tax-form complexity with no proportional lift in quality referrals.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Launching the program without an asset library and expecting affiliates to create their own promotional materials.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Affiliates abandon programs that require significant creative work; they move to programs that make promotion frictionless.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Inactive affiliate tail: signing up many affiliates without a pruning process.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>80% of affiliates produce zero sales. An unpruned roster inflates support overhead and dilutes program resources. Healthy programs continually recruit quality partners and prune inactive ones quarterly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Paying commissions before the refund window closes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cancellations and chargebacks that arrive after payout are unrecoverable losses. The 30-day holdback is non-negotiable arithmetic, not a courtesy.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
