<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tracking-and-examples" title="Affiliate Tracking Metrics and Real Examples">
  <summary>Key program metrics with formulas and benchmarks, plus SaaS and course affiliate program case studies.</summary>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track five program-level metrics weekly: affiliate activation rate (target above 30%), conversion rate (target above 2%), revenue per active affiliate, CAC via affiliates (must stay below 30% of LTV), and fraud rate (target below 1%).</statement>
      <rationale>These five metrics together diagnose whether the program is healthy. Low activation rate means recruitment or onboarding failure; high CAC means commission is too high or traffic quality is low.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <section title="Formulas">
      <p>Affiliate activation rate = affiliates with 1+ referral / total affiliates. Conversion rate = sales / clicks. CAC via affiliates = total commissions paid / customers acquired. Fraud rate = flagged transactions / total transactions.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS affiliate program: project management tool. Structure: 30% recurring commission, 60-day cookie, monthly payouts at $50 minimum. Recruited 50 productivity bloggers, 15 joined, 5 became active promoters. Results over 12 months: 200 customers, $60K ARR attributed, $18K commissions paid. Effective affiliate CAC: $90 vs $150 via paid ads — 40% more efficient.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Course affiliate program: $500 online course. Structure: 40% per sale ($200 flat), 30-day cookie. Targeted newsletter writers in niche, created co-branded landing pages, provided exclusive bonuses. Results: 50 affiliates, 300 sales ($150K revenue), $60K commissions paid — 10x ROI on program management cost.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Inactive affiliate tail: signing up many affiliates without a pruning process.</description>
      <reason>80% of affiliates produce zero sales. An unpruned roster inflates support overhead and dilutes program resources. Healthy programs continually recruit quality partners and prune inactive ones quarterly.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Paying commissions before the refund window closes.</description>
      <reason>Cancellations and chargebacks that arrive after payout are unrecoverable losses. The 30-day holdback is non-negotiable arithmetic, not a courtesy.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Tools Reference">
    <p>Platform options: Rewardful (Stripe-native SaaS), FirstPromoter (SaaS-focused), PartnerStack (B2B deeper PRM), Lemon Squeezy and Paddle (built-in affiliate for digital products). Fraud detection: pandas for transaction pattern analysis, playwright for brand-keyword PPC monitoring. Payouts: Wise or PayPal Mass-Pay for cross-border.</p>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/payout-calc.py">Monthly payout calculation with refund holdback</reference>
  <reference path="templates/affiliate-agreement.md">Affiliate agreement key points</reference>
</text>
