<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="LinkedIn Founder Post Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of LinkedIn Founder Post Template MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="one-hook-type" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each post MUST use exactly one of seven hook types: contrarian, postmortem, customer-quote, day-in-life, mistake, mini-framework, prediction. Multi-hook posts are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Justin Welsh, LinkedIn Operating System (2024)">Single-hook posts are 3x more readable; multi-hook posts read as listicles and lose the founder voice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="word-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post body MUST be 180-220 words. Below 180 reads as tweet, above 220 reads as article.</statement>
      <rationale source="LinkedIn dwell-time benchmarks Q4 2025">LinkedIn algorithm rewards dwell-time in this range; outside it dwell-time collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-link-in-body" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>No URL in the post body. CTA URL lives in first comment only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Algorithm reverse-engineering reports 2025">LinkedIn algorithm down-ranks posts with body links by 30-50%; comment placement preserves reach.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="single-cta" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post MUST have exactly one CTA (book / subscribe / DM / comment-keyword). Multi-CTA posts dilute action.</statement>
      <rationale source="LinkedIn cohort data 2025">Multi-CTA posts halve click-through; conversion analytics confirm single-CTA wins.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lived-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Post body MUST cite &gt;=1 piece of lived evidence (specific number, named customer, dated event). Generic prose is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Founder-voice content audit 2025">Specifics distinguish founder voice from AI-generated content; readers tune out generic prose within 8 seconds.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
