<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="LB Layer Selection Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for L4 vs L7 selection. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="l4-only-uniform-tcp-udp" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose L4 ONLY when traffic is pure TCP / UDP without content-routing needs (gaming, streaming, database proxies, raw Redis). L4 must NOT be selected for HTTP workloads that need URL/path routing.</statement>
      <rationale source="HAProxy + A10 L4-vs-L7 reference">L4 has near-zero per-packet inspection cost but cannot read HTTP. Forcing L4 onto HTTP workloads with content routing requires hacks (separate ports per path) that break basic L7 features.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="l7-required-for-content-routing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick L7 when ANY of: content-based routing (path, header, host, cookie); SSL termination at the LB; HTTP header manipulation; WAF integration; API-gateway features.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cloudflare LB learning hub + Mozilla guidelines">These features all require parsing HTTP — only L7 can express them. Workarounds at L4 (DNS sharding, port-per-path) collapse into operational debt.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ssl-terminates-at-l7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If TLS termination at the LB is required, the LB MUST operate at L7. L4 pass-through ends TLS at the backend; L4 termination is only possible with a private-key on the L4 box (rare, increases blast radius).</statement>
      <rationale source="Mozilla TLS guidelines + cloud LB references">Mixing "L4" with "terminate TLS here" usually means the agent really wants L7 — confront the inconsistency rather than build something exotic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="hybrid-l4-front-of-l7-for-anycast" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For anycast or cross-zone IP-level distribution, layer an L4 LB (AWS NLB, GCP Network LB, HAProxy TCP mode) IN FRONT of an L7 LB (ALB, Ingress-Nginx, Envoy). Treat them as two distinct tiers, not a single binary choice.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Global Accelerator + GCP LB references">L4 owns anycast + connection multiplexing; L7 owns content routing. Collapsing both responsibilities into one product is rarely optimal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-l4-with-l7-features" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject any architecture proposal that names "L4" but lists L7 features (URL routing, header rewrite, WAF, cookie persistence). Either upgrade the choice to L7 or split into hybrid L4-front-of-L7.</statement>
      <rationale source="A10 L4-vs-L7 reference">This contradiction is the single most common LLM failure on LB design. Catching it at review time avoids 6-month rebuilds.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
