<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule testable="true">Every hook bank row has exactly 6 fields: hook_text, pattern (one of: contrarian / before-after / number-callout / question / list-promise / story-tease / mistake-confession / data-drop), platform, post_url, impressions_24h, qualified_replies; rows missing any field are excluded from the working bank.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Tag each row with a "result" bucket using fixed thresholds against the author's rolling-90-day median: FLOPPED ≤0.5×, AVERAGE 0.5-2×, SPIKED ≥2×; never tag by gut feel, always relative to your own baseline.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Maintain the bank in a single file (csv, sheet, or markdown table) committed weekly; if the bank is not in version control, it decays — out-of-sight banks are abandoned within 6 weeks per observation.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Before writing any new post, re-read the top-10 SPIKED rows for the target platform and pick one pattern to remix; writing from a blank page is the bank's failure mode.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Retire patterns that flop ≥3 times in a row on the same platform; record the retirement reason; do not over-rotate, but stale patterns are noise and lower the bank's average signal.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Add NEW patterns only when you observe a SPIKED post that does not fit any existing pattern; the bank stays small (≤15 patterns) — too many patterns is indistinguishable from no patterns.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Monthly review: compute median impressions per pattern × platform; promote one rising pattern to the top of the bank, demote one falling; share the review summary in the build log to compound learning publicly.</rule>
  <example>Indie hacker hook bank (X column), top 3 SPIKED rows: (1) "before-after" — "Yesterday: 4 hours debugging in Rails console. Today: one CLI command." → 8.2k imp / 14 replies / 2× median. (2) "mistake-confession" — "Shipped a $0 invoice to 312 customers last night. Here's the postmortem." → 11.4k / 38 / 2.8×. (3) "data-drop" — "47% of my churn happens in the first 48 hours. Here's what I changed:" → 6.1k / 9 / 1.6×. Tuesday's draft starts by remixing #2 with a new mistake.</example>
</text>
