<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Hook Bank Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules every hook-bank application must enforce. Hard rules; designed to prevent gut-feel bucketing, pattern explosion, and dead banks.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-six-field-schema" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every bank row carries exactly 6 fields: hook_text, pattern, platform, post_url, impressions_24h, qualified_replies. Rows missing any field are excluded from the working bank.</statement>
      <rationale source="Form-discipline research (Cooper, About Face, 2014)">Silently-empty fields collapse into "we forgot" and the bank loses audit value. A fixed 6-field schema makes filtering and aggregation deterministic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-bucket-against-rolling-median" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tag each row with a bucket using fixed thresholds against the author's rolling-90-day median impressions on that platform: FLOPPED ≤0.5×, AVERAGE 0.5-2×, SPIKED ≥2×. Never tag by gut feel.</statement>
      <rationale source="Build-in-public practitioner data on hook performance">Author-relative baselines beat industry benchmarks; an account at 500 impressions and an account at 50000 impressions cannot share thresholds. Fixed math removes the recency-bias trap of "this one felt good".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-version-controlled-storage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The bank lives in a single file (CSV, sheet, or markdown table) committed to version control and reviewed weekly. Banks not in version control are abandoned within 6 weeks per observation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene research; Patio11 swipe-file longevity essays">Out-of-sight artefacts decay; git makes the bank a first-class teammate with diff history.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-remix-before-blank-page" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before writing any new post, re-read the top-10 SPIKED rows for the target platform and pick one pattern to remix. Writing from a blank page is the bank's failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cognitive-load research; copywriting practitioner experience">The blank-page tax is the actual bottleneck; remix-from-proven reduces draft time from 20 minutes to 3 minutes empirically.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-retire-after-three-flops" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Retire patterns that FLOP ≥3 times in a row on the same platform. Record the retirement reason. Do not over-rotate, but stale patterns are noise and lower the bank's average signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="A/B-test discipline literature on dropout">Three-strike rules balance false-negatives against keeping dead weight; documenting retirement preserves institutional memory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-cap-patterns-at-fifteen" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The active pattern allowlist is capped at ≤15 entries. Add a new pattern only when an unclassified SPIKED post is observed. Beyond 15, classification becomes indistinguishable from no patterns.</statement>
      <rationale source="Categorisation cognitive limits (Miller's 7±2 + Cowan's working-memory bounds)">More than ~15 categories overload the writer; the bank loses its remix-fast property.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-monthly-review-with-promotion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monthly review: compute median impressions per pattern × platform. Promote one rising pattern to the top of the bank, demote one falling. Share the review summary in the build log to compound learning publicly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Build-in-public flywheel research; spaced-repetition theory">Periodic promotion/demotion forces decision points; public sharing converts learning into distribution.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the 6-step procedure end-to-end and run the validator before declaring the bank ready.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree leaves must reference a rule id. The run leaf maps "preconditions met" to the canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">The skip leaf needs a real rule id so non-applicable inputs route cleanly out instead of producing false-positive verdicts.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
