<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Hook Bank Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed when running a hook bank. Each pairs symptom + root cause + fix keyed to the methodology rules.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="fm-gut-feel-bucketing" severity="high">
      <symptom>Bank rows tagged SPIKED or FLOPPED without the impression ratio matching the threshold; weekly review shows recency-biased classifications.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Cognitive-bias research on availability heuristic">Author overweights the most recent post or the one with social proof; ignores the 90-day median.</root-cause>
      <fix>Move bucket assignment into the validator script: bucket derived from impressions_24h / platform_medians[platform]. Reject manual overrides. Rule r2.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-pattern-explosion" severity="high">
      <symptom>patterns_active grows to 25+ entries; classification becomes meaningless; remix-step takes longer than blank-page writing did.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Categorisation cognitive limits">Every SPIKED post triggers a new pattern; no pruning discipline.</root-cause>
      <fix>Cap at 15 (r6). Monthly review must demote one when promoting a new one. Validator rejects bank files with patterns_active.length &gt; 15.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-dead-bank" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Bank file last committed 8 weeks ago; new posts written from scratch despite the bank's existence.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Operational-hygiene literature on out-of-sight artefacts">No weekly cadence; reviewed_at field absent or stale.</root-cause>
      <fix>Calendar weekly review (15 min). Pre-commit hook fails if reviewed_at &gt; 14 days old when bank file changes. Surface staleness in the build-update post.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="fm-blank-page-restart" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Author opens the post editor without re-reading the SPIKED top-10; draft time creeps back to 20 minutes.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Habit-formation research">No trigger linking "open editor" to "read SPIKED top-10".</root-cause>
      <fix>Stash the SPIKED top-10 view as the editor's starting screen (browser bookmark, terminal alias, sheet pinned tab). Rule r4 becomes a workflow not a wish.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
