<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="brainstorming-techniques">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>communicator</domain>
    <summary>Four structured group ideation techniques (Classic, Brainwriting 6-3-5, Round Robin, Reverse) following Osborn's 4 rules; separate diverge and converge phases.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>brainstorming</tag>
      <tag>facilitation</tag>
      <tag>ideation</tag>
      <tag>group-dynamics</tag>
      <tag>convergence</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="brainstorming-ideation"/>
      <ref slug="ideation-methods"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Brainstorming Techniques</title>

    <summary>Brainstorming techniques structure group ideation to maximize quantity and diversity of ideas while preventing dominant voices and premature evaluation. Four core techniques: Classic Brainstorming (open verbal, 4-8 people), Brainwriting 6-3-5 (written rotation, 6 people, 108 ideas in 30 min), Round Robin (enforced equal turns, 4-10 people), and Reverse Brainstorming (invert the problem to surface risks and unobvious solutions). All four follow Osborn's 4 rules: defer judgment, go for quantity, encourage wild ideas, build on others' ideas.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Unstructured "just share ideas" sessions produce fewer ideas than structured techniques because dominant voices suppress quieter contributors, premature criticism kills half-formed ideas before they develop, and "we've always done it this way" thinking blocks divergent exploration. Separate diverge (generate, no evaluation) and converge (cluster, vote, score) phases are the most important structural rule.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating a large idea set for a well-defined problem (product name, feature list, risk audit)</item>
        <item>Running async remote ideation where participants write before discussing (Brainwriting works in shared docs)</item>
        <item>Breaking a creative block with structured diverge → converge cycles</item>
        <item>Exploring risks via Reverse Brainstorming when stakeholders are too polite to surface problems directly</item>
        <item>Ensuring equal participation from introverts and senior-junior mixed groups</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Convergence and decision-making — brainstorming is divergent only; run a separate evaluation step after</item>
        <item>Solo ideation with a single narrow constraint; SCAMPER or direct prompting works better</item>
        <item>When the "problem" is actually a predefined requirement masquerading as an open question</item>
        <item>Time-critical triage where idea quantity is irrelevant</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="core-rules">
      <p>Four structured techniques for generating ideas in groups; technique selection depends on group size, introvert ratio, available time, and whether the goal is to surface risks or generate solutions.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Enforce Osborn's 4 rules during the diverge phase: defer judgment, go for quantity, encourage wild ideas, build on others' ideas with "Yes, and..." instead of "No, but...".</statement>
        <rationale>Criticism during idea generation reduces output quantity by 28-40% (Osborn, 1953). The evaluation phase is separate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never mix generation and evaluation in the same pass. Two distinct phases — diverge then converge — produce better idea sets than one combined pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Premature convergence causes anchoring bias: the group stops generating after finding the first good idea instead of exploring the full space.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="classic-brainstorming">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run in five steps: Define problem (5 min) → Warm-up exercise (5 min) → Generate ideas (15-20 min) → Cluster similar ideas (10 min) → Vote/prioritize (10 min). For 4-8 people, 45-60 min.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping the warm-up exercise reduces idea quantity. A 5-minute creative exercise (unrelated word associations, visual prompts) primes divergent thinking.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="brainwriting-6-3-5">
      <rule>
        <statement>Each of 6 people writes 3 ideas in 5 minutes, then passes their paper clockwise. Each subsequent round reads prior ideas and adds 3 more. After 6 rounds: 108 ideas from 6 people. Works in shared docs for remote teams. Exactly 6 people, 30 min.</statement>
        <rationale>Written format eliminates speaking order bias and interruption. Introverts and junior team members contribute at equal rate to senior or extroverted colleagues.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="round-robin">
      <rule>
        <statement>Go around the group; each person shares exactly one idea per turn. "Pass" is permitted but the person must contribute on the next round. No commenting or interruption until the full round is complete. 4-10 people.</statement>
        <rationale>Sequential turns prevent dominant voices from filling all available air time. The no-comment rule lets each idea stand on its own before group response.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="reverse-brainstorming">
      <rule>
        <statement>Invert the problem: instead of "How do we improve X?", ask "How could we make X as bad as possible?". Brainstorm negative answers, then reverse each negative into a positive solution. 4-8 people.</statement>
        <rationale>Groups are more willing to criticize than prescribe. Reverse framing accesses honest risk knowledge that polite groups suppress in forward brainstorming.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Problem: "How do we increase customer satisfaction?"
Reversed: "How do we make customers hate us?"

Negative ideas → Reversed solutions:
- Long hold times → Callback system
- Rude staff → Empathy training program
- Hidden fees → Transparent pricing page
- Complicated returns → One-click return form
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="before-session">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define a specific, single-question objective before the session. "Discuss the product" is not an objective. "Generate 20+ ideas for reducing onboarding churn from 40% to below 25%" is.</statement>
        <rationale>A vague objective produces vague output. A specific question with a quantity target gives the group a clear success criterion.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Invite 4-8 people with diverse backgrounds and roles. More than 10 makes facilitation unmanageable. Fewer than 4 lacks the cross-pollination that produces non-obvious ideas.</statement>
        <rationale>Diversity of perspective is the primary predictor of idea novelty in brainstorming research.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="during-session-problems-and-fixes">
      <list>
        <item>Dominant talker: switch to Brainwriting or Round Robin to enforce structured turns</item>
        <item>Criticism creeping in: "Hold that thought for the evaluation phase"</item>
        <item>Running out of ideas: apply a constraint ("what if budget were 10x?"), change perspective ("what would a user say?"), use SCAMPER</item>
        <item>Off-topic drift: "Parking lot" — capture the idea on a separate board for later</item>
        <item>Group too quiet: individual silent writing for 2 min before sharing</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="convergence-dot-voting">
      <rule>
        <statement>Give each participant 3-5 dots. Participants vote on their favorite ideas from the clustered list. Top-voted ideas move forward for evaluation. No discussion during voting.</statement>
        <rationale>Dot voting externalizes preferences simultaneously, preventing the anchoring effect of verbal polling where the first opinion heard shapes all subsequent votes.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="convergence-impact-effort-scoring">
      <rule>
        <statement>Score each idea on Impact (weight 3x) and Feasibility (weight 2x). Avoid over-weighting cost and time (1x each) — cheap but low-impact ideas should not win over expensive but transformative ones.</statement>
        <rationale>Default human judgment over-weights effort and under-weights impact. Explicit weighting corrects this bias.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Quick Wins: high impact, low effort — implement first</item>
        <item>Major Projects: high impact, high effort — schedule and resource</item>
        <item>Fill-ins: low impact, low effort — optional backlog</item>
        <item>Time Sinks: low impact, high effort — reject</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping the convergence step after ideation — leaving participants with a list but no prioritization or owner assignments.</description>
      <reason>Ideas without owners and priorities evaporate. The session feels productive but produces no action, which destroys trust in future brainstorming sessions.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A subagent receives a problem statement and a technique selector (classic / brainwriting / round-robin / reverse). It generates ideas in a structured bulk pass, then clusters via semantic grouping in a second pass. A third pass scores clusters against an impact/effort rubric and returns a shortlist. The facilitator-script logic (Osborn's 4 rules, silence cues) is embedded in the system prompt, not in conversation turns.</p>

      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-brainstorm — structured diverge/converge cycles; use for multi-round ideation with review gate. General Claude Opus call — for generating wild-idea batches where novelty matters more than structure.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <prompt purpose="bulk-generate"><![CDATA[
Generate exactly 30 ideas for: <PROBLEM>.
Rules: no criticism, quantity over quality, wild ideas encouraged.
Format: numbered list only. No explanations.
      ]]></prompt>
      <prompt purpose="second-pass-clustering"><![CDATA[
Cluster these 30 ideas into 5-7 themes.
For each theme: name, 3-5 member ideas, one-line rationale.
      ]]></prompt>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <list>
        <item>miro-cli (unofficial) — Programmatic Miro board creation for remote brainstorm boards. npm: miro-api SDK</item>
        <item>obsidian-mcp — Write clustered ideas as notes with backlinks. MCP server for Obsidian</item>
        <item>Miro (SaaS, partial REST API for boards/cards) — Agent can create sticky notes, but real-time cursor presence is human-only</item>
        <item>MURAL (SaaS, partial REST API) — Similar to Miro; session management limited</item>
        <item>Stormboard (SaaS, no API) — Human-only</item>
        <item>Excalidraw (OSS, JSON import) — Agent can generate JSON scene files; no live session support</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="dedup-utility">
      <p>Inline utility — bulk idea deduplication:</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
# Remove near-duplicate ideas from a brainstorm list (simple Jaccard)
def dedup_ideas(ideas: list[str], threshold: float = 0.5) -> list[str]:
    from itertools import combinations
    def jaccard(a: str, b: str) -> float:
        sa, sb = set(a.lower().split()), set(b.lower().split())
        return len(sa & sb) / len(sa | sb) if sa | sb else 0.0
    keep = list(ideas)
    to_remove = set()
    for i, j in combinations(range(len(keep)), 2):
        if i not in to_remove and jaccard(keep[i], keep[j]) >= threshold:
            to_remove.add(j)
    return [idea for idx, idea in enumerate(keep) if idx not in to_remove]
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Split the prompt into two calls: pure generation (no evaluation language), then pure clustering. Mixing them causes premature convergence.</item>
        <item>Use Reverse Brainstorming first when stakeholders resist criticism — "How would we destroy this product?" gets honest answers.</item>
        <item>For impact/effort scoring: weight impact 3x, feasibility 2x; keep cost/time at 1x to avoid over-optimizing for cheapness.</item>
        <item>Seed the brainwriting pass with one "wild" idea per round to prevent the LLM settling on safe output.</item>
        <item>When simulating multiple personas in Round Robin, assign specific roles (skeptic, optimist, user, engineer) rather than anonymous "person N".</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs default to evaluation language ("this is a good idea because...") even when prompted not to — enforce format strictly (numbered list, no justification).</item>
        <item>The "108 ideas from 6-3-5" calculation is theoretical; agent-generated ideas plateau in novelty around 30-40 without persona switching or domain constraint injection.</item>
        <item>Dot voting in an automated context requires a separate agent or human in the loop — never let the generating agent also vote, as it will favor its own first-pass ideas.</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint required before moving from cluster to scoring: the agent's semantic clustering can merge genuinely distinct ideas with similar wording.</item>
        <item>Large idea lists (100+) hit context limits during the scoring pass; chunk into 25-idea batches with accumulated scoring state.</item>
        <item>AI-generated idea lists tend to cluster around obvious solutions; second-pass prompting is required to force weird/wild ideas.</item>
        <item>Deferred judgment principle breaks down when the LLM ranks or filters in the same pass that generates.</item>
        <item>Classic Brainstorming (6-3-5) assumes a fixed group; agent must simulate multiple personas, which can produce homogeneous output.</item>
        <item>No real group dynamics: the "energy dip" recovery techniques (change method, take break) don't apply to single-agent runs.</item>
        <item>Quantity ≠ quality; agent can hit 108 ideas in seconds, but clustering and scoring become the bottleneck.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/session-plan.md" purpose="Brainstorm session plan with objective, technique, agenda, results capture"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-generate.txt" purpose="Prompt for bulk idea generation (diverge pass only, no evaluation)"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-cluster.txt" purpose="Prompt for clustering a generated idea list into themes"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://dschool.stanford.edu/resources/brainstorm-rules"/>
      <link href="https://www.ideou.com/blogs/inspiration/how-to-brainstorm"/>
      <link href="https://developers.miro.com/reference/api-reference"/>
      <ref slug="brainstorming-ideation"/>
      <ref slug="ideation-methods"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
