<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="azure-nat-gateway Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for azure-nat-gateway. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Size NAT Gateway public IP count based on expected peak outbound concurrent connections: each public IP provides ~64,000 SNAT ports. Add one additional public IP per 50,000 expected concurrent outbound connections. For web scrapers, batch HTTP, or connection-heavy workloads exceeding 50,000 concurrent connections, use multiple public IPs (max 16 per NAT Gateway) or a public IP prefix.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">SNAT port exhaustion silently drops connections — the application sees random timeouts with no Azure error. The default single-IP configuration is sufficient for typical workloads (&lt;10,000 concurrent outbound) but fails for high-fanout patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Standard SKU public IP with zone-redundant allocation (zones: ["1", "2", "3"]) for production NAT Gateways. Basic SKU public IPs are not supported with NAT Gateway.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Zone-redundant IP ensures NAT Gateway survives an AZ failure. Basic SKU IPs are incompatible with NAT Gateway and cause a deploy-time error that is confusing to diagnose.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set `idle_timeout_in_minutes` based on application connection patterns. Default is 4 minutes; increase to 10-15 minutes for applications that keep long-lived TCP connections idle (database connection pools, websockets, gRPC streams). Do NOT set it to 120 minutes (maximum) by default — connections remain in the SNAT table longer, consuming ports.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">SNAT port exhaustion is exacerbated by long idle timeouts. Each idle connection holds a SNAT port for the duration of the timeout. Connection pools that recycle connections frequently benefit from shorter timeouts (4-10 min); only set higher for genuinely long-lived streams.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure metric alerts for `SNATConnectionCount` dropping below expected thresholds and for SNAT port utilization approaching 80% of capacity. Enable diagnostic logs on the NAT Gateway to a Log Analytics workspace. Alert on connection drops (`DroppedPackets` metric) as an early warning of SNAT exhaustion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">SNAT exhaustion manifests as silent connection drops — no Azure error, no application error code, just timeouts. Without proactive monitoring, high-fanout workloads fail intermittently in production before the issue is identified.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
