<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Lead Qualification Rubric Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Solo Lead Qualification Rubric application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-axes-fixed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score MUST evaluate exactly 4 axes: budget clarity, decision authority on call, sane timeline, no scarring contractor history. Adding axes is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Solo BANT-equivalents drift to 10+ axes and become unusable; 4 axes preserve speed and discrimination.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-numeric-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each axis MUST produce an integer 0-3 score; the rubric returns the sum and a verdict (qualify / triage / decline).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Numeric outputs let routing automation act on the score; free-text disqualifies automation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-no-budget-then-decline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Leads without budget clarity (score 0 on budget axis) MUST be auto-declined regardless of other axes.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Solo operators cannot afford long-tail discovery on no-budget leads; the lower bound is decisive.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-authority-on-call" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision authority MUST be confirmed on the discovery call, not assumed from title. Title-only assumptions are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Title rarely maps to authority in small companies; the call is the only reliable signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-scar-flag" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>History axis MUST flag prior bad-contractor experiences (3+ contractors in 12 months OR named billing disputes). Flagged leads route to triage, not auto-qualify.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Scarred leads consume disproportionate operator energy; the flag prevents misallocation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
