<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Lead Qualification — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that govern the four-dimensional ICE-style score (1-5 each, max 20) and the pass / soft-pass / decline thresholds.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-four-dimensions" testable="true">
      <statement>Always score four dimensions: Budget-clarity, Decision-on-call, Timeline-realism, Contractor-trauma-history. Each on a 1-5 integer scale. Never score on fewer than four; never collapse to a single number without the per-dimension table.</statement>
      <rationale source="Christensen JTBD / Sean Ellis ICE / HubSpot BANT retirement">BANT collapsed four concerns into a binary qualify/disqualify, which forces an LLM to over-weight the loudest signal in the thread. Per-dimension scoring forces evidence per axis and exposes the trade-off (e.g. clear budget but unclear authority).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-evidence-per-score" testable="true">
      <statement>Every dimension score must cite at least one verbatim quote from the DM/email thread. A score without a citation is invalid and must be coerced to NULL.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-hallucination practice">LLMs given a transcript will confabulate budgets, role titles, and timelines that were never stated. Verbatim grounding is the only reliable falsifier.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-thresholds" testable="true">
      <statement>Total ≥ 14 → BOOK discovery call. Total ∈ [10,13] → SOFT-PASS, send a single calibration question first. Total &lt; 10 → POLITE-DECLINE with templated reply. Never proceed to paid discovery / proposal work below 14.</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical — Brennan Dunn (Double Your Freelancing) close-rate cohort">In freelancer cohorts tracking discovery-to-paid conversion, leads scoring &lt; 14 on equivalent multi-axis rubrics close at &lt; 8%, but consume 2.4× the proposal time of qualified leads. The threshold is a margin-defense rule, not a snobbery rule.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-rate-floor-coupling" testable="true">
      <statement>If the prospect's quoted or implied budget is below the operator's rate-floor (loaded from `solo-rate-floor-calculator`), then Budget-clarity is automatically forced to 1, regardless of how unambiguous the budget statement is. A clearly-stated bad budget is still a bad budget.</statement>
      <rationale source="kalzumeus.com rate-floor argument">The most common LLM scoring mistake is rewarding "they were upfront about $2k" with a 5 on Budget-clarity. Upfront and unaffordable is still unaffordable. Coupling to the operator's floor turns clarity into qualified-clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-trauma-history-asymmetric" testable="true">
      <statement>Contractor-trauma-history is scored asymmetrically: a clean history scores 5, one bad prior engagement scores 3, two or more bad priors score 1. Score CANNOT exceed 3 if the thread contains any of the marker phrases: "last developer disappeared", "previous freelancer", "burned by", "another agency", "rescue", "salvage". A 1 here vetoes the total — push to POLITE-DECLINE regardless of other dimensions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Patrick McKenzie / Jonathan Stark consulting bibliography">Scarred prospects re-enact the trauma. They under-pay, micro-manage, and dispute scope. The asymmetric veto exists because the other three dimensions cannot compensate: a 5-5-5-1 lead is statistically worse than a 3-3-3-3 lead.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Score anchors per dimension">

    <example type="good" title="Budget-clarity anchors">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
5 — exact number stated AND ≥ rate-floor: "Budget is $8k for the build."
4 — range stated AND midpoint ≥ floor:    "Somewhere between $5k and $10k."
3 — unit stated, total unclear:           "$80/hr is what we paid last guy."
2 — vague but positive:                   "We have budget approved."
1 — silent OR explicitly below floor:     "What's the cheapest you'd go?"
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1+r4: clarity AND ≥ floor required for 4-5. Below-floor caps at 1.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Decision-on-call anchors">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
5 — prospect is founder/owner, will be on call alone.
4 — decision-maker + one technical contributor.
3 — middle manager who reports decision; cycle 1-2 weeks.
2 — committee implied: "I'll loop in my partner / CTO / wife."
1 — gatekeeper: "I'm researching for my boss / client."
      ]]></code>
      <note>r2: must cite the quote that triggered the score.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Timeline-realism anchors">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
5 — start in 2-6 weeks, duration matches scope reality.
4 — start in 6-12 weeks, duration reasonable.
3 — "no rush, when you can".  (Soft signal — risk of indefinite drift.)
2 — "we're flexible" with no anchor date.
1 — "by Friday" / "we needed this last month" / "yesterday".
      ]]></code>
      <note>Counter-intuitive: BOTH "yesterday" AND "no rush" score badly. The first scopes scope-creep; the second never closes.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Single-signal scoring (r1 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Lead said "budget is $20k". Scored 5/20 → BOOK.

Wrong: r1 demands 4 dimensions. Authority, timeline, trauma all
unscored. Score is invalid; output must be rejected.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1 violation — the most common LLM shortcut.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
