<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Competitor Tracker — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that keep a solo competitor tracker producing signal instead of devolving into doom-scrolling competitor blogs.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-to-seven-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The matrix MUST track 5-7 competitors. Fewer than 5 misses near competitors; more than 7 is too many for solo to keep current. New entrants are added only by retiring an existing entry (with rationale).</statement>
      <rationale source="Crayon CI benchmarks, solo-founder time-budget research">Empirically, solo founders who track &gt; 8 competitors stop maintaining the matrix within 3 months. The 5-7 range produces sustainable maintenance with adequate coverage. The retire-to-add constraint forces deliberate prioritization.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-stable-schema" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Matrix columns (attributes) are defined ONCE and held stable across weeks. Forbidden: adding new attributes mid-scan to investigate a single move (creates partially-filled columns and matrix decay). New attribute additions happen only at the monthly refresh.</statement>
      <rationale source="Time-series data hygiene, dashboard-design literature">Schema-drift kills longitudinal value. The whole point of the matrix is to see CHANGE over time per attribute. Mid-month schema changes destroy that.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-45-min-time-box" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Weekly scan MUST complete in 45 minutes wall-clock. The block is a hard timer. If 45 min runs out: stop, log "scan incomplete" with which channels weren't checked, schedule a follow-up of max 15 min if a delta needs action. The time-box is the budget; protect it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cal Newport deep-work / time-box research, solo-founder ops literature">Without a time-box, competitor research expands to fill available time (Parkinson's law) and crowds out higher-leverage product / sales work. The 45-min cap forces the scan to be efficient and focused.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-delta-action-or-noop" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every delta logged MUST have either (a) a queued action with date OR (b) an explicit no-op note with reason ("interesting but doesn't affect our roadmap because X"). Forbidden: deltas logged with neither — that creates a "watch list" of nothing.</statement>
      <rationale source="GTD / OKR action discipline, post-research action-rate studies">Delta-without-decision is noise that masquerades as signal. Forcing action-or-explicit-no-op makes the tracker either drive decisions or visibly stop being worth maintaining.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-monthly-prune" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Once a month, prune the matrix: remove competitors whose moves haven't influenced any decision in 90 days (with reason), add at most one new competitor IF a strong candidate has emerged, review schema attributes for relevance (drop attributes that have shown no variance across competitors AND time).</statement>
      <rationale source="Sunset-by-default information hygiene, attention-management literature">Without pruning, matrices accumulate stale competitors and dead attributes. Monthly prune keeps the matrix lean and the scan time fitting in 45 min.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical example">

    <example type="good" title="Weekly delta journal entry with action queued">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Week of 2026-05-19
Channels scanned: changelog (5/5), pricing (5/5), blog (4/5 — missed
  Competitor C, queued for follow-up), social (skipped — low signal),
  hiring (3/5)
Time: 42 min

Deltas:
  Competitor A: shipped "AI write-assist" feature in beta (changelog
    2026-05-17).
    Action queued: review feature against our roadmap, decide if it
    changes our Q3 messaging. Owner: me. Date: 2026-05-23.

  Competitor B: dropped Starter tier from $19 to $9.
    Action queued: re-check our pricing positioning thread; if
    still differentiated on Y, no change needed.
    Owner: me. Date: 2026-05-22.

  Competitor C: blog channel not scanned this week.
    Action queued: 10-min catch-up scan Wednesday.

  Competitor D: hiring "Founding GTM Lead".
    No-op with reason: hiring signal doesn't change our weekly
    decisions; revisit next month if pattern continues.

  Competitor E: no detected change.

Matrix update: A's feature change updated in column "last-shipped".
  No schema changes this week.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2, r3, r4: stable schema, time-box respected, every delta has action OR explicit no-op.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Doom-scroll without action">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Week of 2026-05-19
Time: 2h 15min (no time-box enforced)

Notes: "Competitor A added AI thing. Competitor B did a pricing
test. Competitor C wrote an article about onboarding. Competitor
F (new!) launched a Product Hunt campaign. Competitor G is doing
interesting things on Twitter. We should keep an eye on all of
them. Maybe revisit later."

Actions queued: 0
Decisions made: 0
Time cost: 2h 15min
Roadmap impact: zero
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r3, r4 violations — time bleed without decision output.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
