<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="key-trends-summary">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd</domain>
    <summary>Six major shifts relevant to SDD practitioners in 2025: SDD paradigm, docs-as-code, ADRs, LLM-first workflows, platform engineering, OpenTelemetry. Load before architectural planning sessions.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
      <tag>trends</tag>
      <tag>architecture</tag>
      <tag>platform-engineering</tag>
      <tag>observability</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Key Trends Summary 2025-2026</title>
    <summary>Orientation reference covering six major shifts relevant to SDD practitioners: SDD becoming the dominant paradigm for AI-assisted development (intent → spec → plan → execute → review); docs-as-code and LLM-optimized documentation; ADRs as standard practice at AWS, Google Cloud, and Microsoft Azure; LLM-first workflows (context packing, spec-first, agentic MCP); platform engineering growth (45% → 80% of large orgs by 2026); OpenTelemetry as the #2 CNCF project for observability. Load at the start of architectural planning sessions, not per-task.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>The bottleneck has shifted from implementation to specification — LLMs generate code at scale, but quality specifications remain a human-centric skill. Adoption metrics: 65% of developers use AI tools weekly, 25% of YC W25 codebases are 95%+ AI-generated, MCP has become the standard protocol for agent-tool interaction. Teams that treat specs as programming interfaces for AI agents ship faster with lower defect rates than teams that rely on narrative requirements.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When an agent needs to orient itself on current SDD, observability, and platform tooling before advising on architecture</item>
        <item>When a human asks what tools to use for SDD/documentation in 2025-2026</item>
        <item>As a context document before quarterly roadmap sessions</item>
        <item>When evaluating whether to adopt a new tool (Kiro, Tessl, MCP, etc.)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>As a replacement for methodology-specific docs — use dedicated methodology folders for actionable guidance</item>
        <item>For time-sensitive tool decisions — this is a snapshot; verify market share data currency before committing</item>
        <item>For domains not covered here (the doc covers SDD, ADRs, living docs, platform engineering, observability)</item>
        <item>When the agent already has current context from a more specific source</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Specification-Driven Development">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat the specification as the source of truth; code is its output, not the input to understanding.</statement>
        <rationale>SDD emerged as the dominant paradigm for AI-assisted development in 2025. The core principle — intent is the source of truth — reverses the traditional relationship where code is read to understand intent.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Core workflow: Intent (human) → Spec (human + LLM draft) → Plan (LLM + human review) → Execute (LLM) → Review (human).</p>
      <p>SDD effectiveness by scenario:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Feature work in existing systems (N to N+1): highest effectiveness</item>
        <item>Greenfield with clear requirements: high</item>
        <item>Legacy modernization: medium-high</item>
        <item>Exploratory/R&amp;D work: medium</item>
        <item>Vibe coding / rapid prototypes: low (use different approach)</item>
      </list>
      <p>Key SDD tools as of 2025: Amazon Kiro (full SDD workflow with hooks), Spec Kit (GitHub/Microsoft open-source), Tessl (framework and registry), Claude Code (native SDD support).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Living Documentation">
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat documentation as first-class code: version-controlled, CI/CD pipelines, automated testing.</statement>
        <rationale>Documentation that is not in version control becomes stale immediately. Docs-as-code enables the same quality gates applied to code to be applied to documentation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Docs-as-code core stack: Markdown/MDX format, Git storage, static site generators (Docusaurus, MkDocs, Mintlify), automated linting and link checking in CI/CD.</p>
      <p>LLM-optimized documentation patterns:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Clear heading hierarchy: better LLM parsing</item>
        <item>Explicit context sections: reduced hallucination</item>
        <item>Code blocks with language tags: accurate code generation</item>
        <item>API contracts in specs: type-safe integration</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Developer Portal Landscape">
      <p>Developer portals are UI; platforms are the backend. The portal is not the platform.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Backstage (89% market share): large orgs, extensibility, TechDocs integration</item>
        <item>Port (rising): service catalogs, workflows, REST API for agent registration</item>
        <item>Cortex (growing): service ownership, scorecards</item>
        <item>Roadie (SaaS leader): Backstage without ops overhead</item>
        <item>Mintlify: llms.txt standard; Anthropic uses for Claude docs</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Load this trends document at the start of quarterly roadmap sessions; do not load it per-task.</statement>
        <rationale>Trend documents are orientation resources, not per-task guides. Loading per-task wastes context tokens and produces over-confident recommendations based on trend data that should be treated as directional.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Architecture Decision Records">
      <rule>
        <statement>ADRs are append-only: never edit an accepted ADR; create a new one that supersedes the old decision.</statement>
        <rationale>ADRs are the decision history. Editing them erases the reasoning trail future engineers use to understand why the system is the way it is. Agents asked to "clean up" docs may delete ADRs — explicitly prohibit deletion in executor prompts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>ADR lifecycle: Draft → Review → Accepted → [Superseded | Deprecated]. Storage pattern: docs/adr/0001-use-postgresql.md.</p>
      <p>ADR standard practice at: AWS, Google Cloud, Microsoft Azure, UK Government.</p>
      <p>AWS best practices (200+ ADRs experience):</p>
      <list>
        <item>Keep review meetings 30-45 minutes (focused)</item>
        <item>One decision per ADR (simpler review)</item>
        <item>Separate design doc from ADR (reference, not embed)</item>
        <item>Push for timely decisions (most are two-way doors)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag any roadmap decision citing this trends document as "trend-based assumption" since market share statistics (Backstage 89%, adoption rates) become stale within 6-12 months.</statement>
        <rationale>Trend data has implied precision it does not have. ADRs citing trend data without source dates and caveats mislead future engineers who encounter the record without temporal context.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="LLM-First Workflow Adoption">
      <p>Adoption metrics as of 2025 (directional, verify currency):</p>
      <list>
        <item>65% of developers use AI coding tools weekly (Stack Overflow)</item>
        <item>25% of Y Combinator W25 codebases are 95%+ AI-generated</item>
        <item>~25% of Microsoft and Google code is AI-generated</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not treat "90% of Claude Code's code is written by Claude Code itself" as a quality target; it is a marketing claim, not a benchmark.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents citing adoption statistics as quality targets produce overconfident recommendations. The metric measures output volume, not quality or correctness.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Effective LLM Workflow Patterns">
      <list>
        <item>Context packing: brain-dump everything the model should know; include high-level goals, invariants, examples of good solutions, approaches to avoid</item>
        <item>Spec-first workflow: write detailed spec before any code; break work into small testable chunks; provide extensive codebase context; review everything generated</item>
        <item>Incremental generation: generate small, testable chunks rather than entire features at once</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use MCP (Model Context Protocol) for agent-tool integration — it has become the standard protocol for agent interactions as of 2025.</statement>
        <rationale>MCP components: Servers (tool providers), Clients (AI agents), Resources (context data), Tools (callable functions). Using MCP-compatible tools ensures agents work with a standard interface rather than custom integrations per tool.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="LLM-First Challenges">
      <list>
        <item>Context window limits: mitigate with chunking, RAG, better prompts</item>
        <item>Hallucination: mitigate with human review gates, testing</item>
        <item>Spec drift: mitigate with continuous validation against spec.md</item>
        <item>Non-determinism: mitigate with CI/CD quality gates</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Platform Engineering">
      <p>Platform team adoption: 45% of large orgs in 2022 → 80% projected by 2026 (Gartner). The driver is developer experience — platform teams reduce cognitive load by providing "golden paths" that make the right thing easy.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Distinguish platform (backend system) from portal (frontend UI); investing in portal without platform produces expensive dashboards with no underlying capability.</statement>
        <rationale>A common mistake: teams build Backstage (portal) without the underlying platform (Kubernetes, Terraform, CI/CD pipelines). The portal can only surface what the platform provides.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Platform: Kubernetes, Terraform — provisions, deploys, orchestrates</item>
        <item>Portal: Backstage, Port — discovers, accesses, visualizes</item>
      </list>
      <p>Golden paths map directly to SDD constitution.md: define the paved road once, enforce it in quality gates. Metrics that matter: time to first commit, deployment frequency, lead time for changes, mean time to recovery.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="OpenTelemetry and Observability">
      <rule>
        <statement>Start with OTel traces on agent task boundaries (start/end/error) before adding metrics and logs — traces provide the most value for debugging agent failures.</statement>
        <rationale>Traces show the execution path through a system; for debugging agent failures, seeing which steps ran, in what order, and where they failed is more valuable than aggregate metrics or unstructured log lines.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>OpenTelemetry is the #2 CNCF project (after Kubernetes) and the de-facto standard for vendor-neutral telemetry as of 2025.</p>
      <p>OpenTelemetry core pillars:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Logs: event records</item>
        <item>Metrics: measurements over time</item>
        <item>Traces: request flow across services</item>
        <item>Profiles: resource consumption (added 2025)</item>
      </list>
      <p>OTel collector patterns:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Agent: per-instance, low latency</item>
        <item>Gateway: centralized, easier ops</item>
        <item>Hierarchical: agent + gateway combined (recommended for agent pipelines)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply shift-left observability: instrument at every stage (dev → test → stage → prod), not only in production.</statement>
        <rationale>Observability gaps in dev and test environments mean failures are first detected in production. Shift-left observability catches performance regressions and error patterns in earlier, cheaper-to-fix stages.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </content>
</methodology>
