<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Procurement Process: Make-or-Buy, SOW, Contract Types">
  <summary>Core procurement workflow: decide make vs buy, define scope via SOW, choose contract type, source vendors, and manage ongoing performance.</summary>

  <section title="Make-or-Buy Decision">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decide make-vs-buy before writing any SOW. Evaluate cost, control, speed, expertise, and risk transfer explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping this step leads to outsourcing work that should be internal (losing IP) or building internally when a vendor is cheaper and faster.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Key factors: fixed vs variable cost, control level, access to specialist expertise, risk ownership, and long-term switching cost. Switching cost is routinely underestimated — factor in knowledge transfer, vendor lock-in, and transition time.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Statement of Work">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every external engagement requires a SOW with: scope (in and out), numbered deliverables, acceptance criteria per deliverable, milestone dates, and payment tied to acceptance not activity.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague SOWs are the top cause of scope disputes. Acceptance-linked payment aligns vendor incentives with buyer outcomes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/sow.md">SOW skeleton with all required sections</reference>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>SOW says "develop the mobile app to a high standard" — no deliverables listed, no acceptance criteria, payment on delivery date.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>SOW lists D1 (design mockups, accepted when stakeholder sign-off), D2 (working app, accepted when App Store approval + 95% crash-free rate), payment 25% / 50% / 25% at milestone acceptance.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Contract Type Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose FFP when scope is at least 80% defined; T&amp;M with a NOT-TO-EXCEED cap when scope is evolving; CPFF only for research with inherently unknowable cost.</statement>
      <rationale>FFP without defined scope incentivises vendors to minimise effort. Uncapped T&amp;M transfers all cost risk to the buyer. CPFF for routine work is fiscally irresponsible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Any T&amp;M contract must include a weekly burn report and a hard cap. Uncapped T&amp;M is open-ended risk.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a cap, T&amp;M scope creep is invisible until the invoice arrives.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Vendor Sourcing">
    <p>Use the right sourcing instrument: RFI to gather market info, RFP for formal solution proposals, RFQ for price quotes on defined work, sole-source only when justified with documented rationale.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require references AND a structured reference-call rubric. References without a rubric are positive-bias noise.</statement>
      <rationale>Vendors select their best references; a structured interview reveals actual weaknesses.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Vendor Management">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track deliverables against SOW, reconcile invoices against milestones, and maintain a quarterly vendor scorecard (on-time %, defect rate, escalation count). Renew or churn based on data.</statement>
      <rationale>Set-and-forget vendor management is the second most common procurement failure mode after vague SOWs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Negotiate exit terms before signing: notice period, data handback, transition assistance, IP transfer. Trapped-buyer is the most common contract failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Renegotiating exit terms after the relationship sours produces the worst outcomes for both parties.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
