<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="procurement-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for procurement-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Lowest-price wins: selecting the cheapest vendor without weighting quality, experience, and risk.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Price is the most legible criterion but the weakest predictor of delivery success. Low-price vendors frequently compensate by minimising scope or requesting change orders.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Acceptance criteria written as subjective goals ("high quality code", "good performance").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Subjective criteria cannot be evaluated at acceptance time, creating disputes. Require testable thresholds: defect density, response time, test coverage percentage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Evaluation matrix weighted at 5–10% for references, then not interviewing references in a structured way.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>References are positive-bias by selection; without a rubric the criterion adds no information and can be gamed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Multi-supplier / prime + sub arrangements treated as a single-vendor procurement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Partner ecosystems require separate SOWs, liability chains, and IP ownership clauses per party. Combining them obscures accountability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Legal clauses are jurisdiction-specific; LLMs default to US-style clauses and miss EU GDPR processor terms, UK MAC clauses, German UWG provisions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always require legal review for cross-border SOWs; do not rely on agent-drafted clauses.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Indemnification caps drift: agents draft "uncapped" indemnification by default — require explicit cap (often 1x or 2x annual fees).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Review every generated contract clause for liability caps before sharing with vendors.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Data residency / sub-processor language is missing from generic LLM SOW templates; mandatory for GDPR, HIPAA, SOC 2 buyers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If compliance is required, specify it in the agent prompt explicitly.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Currency drift in multi-region SOWs: agents put a USD figure in a EU SOW without an exchange clause; demand price-adjustment language.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lock exchange rates or add an explicit price-adjustment clause for multi-currency SOWs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Make-vs-buy bias: agents tend to recommend "buy" for software (training data favours SaaS marketing); explicitly weight switching cost and IP ownership.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Provide explicit guidance on make-vs-buy weighting before agent analysis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Vendor-name hallucination is common in shortlist drafting; always require a user-supplied vendor list, never let the agent invent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Supply a curated vendor list as agent input; never let it generate candidate names.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Evaluation matrix can be reverse-engineered: if you tell an LLM the answer, it will weight the criteria to justify it. Lock weights before scoring.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Define and commit to evaluation weights before receiving proposals.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Acceptance criteria written by agents are often subjective ("high quality"); demand testable criteria (% test coverage, defect density, response time).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Review every acceptance criterion for objectivity and testability before signing SOW.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
