<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Buyer-Interview-for-Freelancers Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules specific to interviewing buyers of a freelance service. They extend the Mom Test floor with service-buyer mechanics.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-past-behavior-bias" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every primary question MUST elicit specific past behavior, not anticipated future intent. "When was the last time you hired a [role]?" is acceptable. "Would you hire someone like me?" is forbidden. Hypothetical-buy questions produce polite false-positives that destroy freelance pipelines.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fitzpatrick, The Mom Test (2014)">Service buyers are even more likely to say polite-yes than product users, because they don't want to discourage a freelancer they like. Past-behavior questions surface friction the buyer actually paid to solve.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-budget-authority" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every interview MUST surface: who controls the budget for this category of work, what the typical line-item size is, and whether the interviewee can sign or only recommend. A buyer who cannot sign is a champion, not a buyer — treat the conversation as champion-mapping and follow up with the actual signer.</statement>
      <rationale source="Service-business sales research (Sandler, Challenger Sale)">Freelancers consistently lose deals after months of interviews because they were talking to influencers, not signers. Asking the budget question early is uncomfortable; not asking it is more expensive.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-switching-pain" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the buyer is currently working with another vendor (in-house, agency, another freelancer), the interview MUST capture the switching pain: what would make them stop? What did the last vendor do that they wish they had not? What did they wish that vendor had done? Vague answers ("we'd be open to alternatives") are not switching pain — they are politeness.</statement>
      <rationale source="JTBD Forces of Progress (Moesta) applied to service buyers">Habit + Fear keep buyers with incumbents long past dissatisfaction. Without naming the specific switching trigger, the freelancer pitches into an inertia wall.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-vendor-wishlist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every interview ends with: "What do you wish a vendor like me had asked you?" The answer is gold — it surfaces the question the buyer cannot directly request but wants asked. These answers feed the next interview iteration AND the service one-pager rewrite.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field practice from freelancer-buyer interview studies (Pat Flynn, Brennan Dunn case studies)">Buyers are far better at evaluating questions than answering them. This single closing question consistently produces the highest-leverage data of the interview.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-disqualifiers" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Disqualifiers MUST be defined before interviews start: (a) cannot identify a real past project in this category, (b) budget is &lt; 30% of freelancer's target rate, (c) decision timeline &gt; 12 months out. Hitting any disqualifier ends the interview politely after 15 minutes. The freelancer's time is the scarce resource.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sales operations research on call qualification (BANT, MEDDIC)">Without disqualifiers, freelance research becomes free consulting. The interviewee gets value; the freelancer gets fatigue. Pre-committed disqualifiers protect the research pipeline.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Past-behavior question that obeys r1">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Walk me through the last time you brought in outside help for [category].
- Who initiated it?
- What was the trigger event that week?
- How did you pick the vendor — what did you compare?"
      ]]></code>
      <note>Past tense, specific, asks about decision process, not preference.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Hypothetical question that violates r1">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"If you were hiring someone like me, what would you be looking for?"
      ]]></code>
      <note>Polite-yes generator. Buyer answers with virtues, not requirements. Throws away the interview slot.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
