<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="solution-assessment">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>A structured evaluation of a solution's ability to meet the business need and deliver expected value. Covers four assessment types, compares actuals against requirements and success metrics, identifies limitations, and produces a recommendation. Run at 30/60/90 days post-deployment, not as a one-shot event.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>solution-evaluation</tag>
      <tag>business-value</tag>
      <tag>post-implementation</tag>
      <tag>assessment</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Solution Assessment</title>

    <summary>A structured evaluation of a solution's ability to meet business need and deliver expected value, covering four assessment types and producing a recommendation at 30/60/90 days post-deployment.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Solutions are built but value is never measured; user complaints are unstructured; the gap between promised and delivered remains invisible; lessons are not captured. Structured assessment forces a pre-agreed success baseline, makes variance visible, distinguishes "not met" from "deprecated requirement", and closes the delivery loop by feeding a remediation backlog.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>30/60/90-day post-launch checkpoints when the business case promised quantified outcomes</item>
        <item>Pre-go-live deployment readiness gate: aggregate QA, ops, support, training, and security signals into a single accept/reject</item>
        <item>Phase-gate reviews on long programs (CRM, ERP, billing migrations) before funding the next phase</item>
        <item>Vendor/SaaS contract renewal — assess deployed solution against original requirements and SLA</item>
        <item>Compliance/audit cycles (SOX, ISO, HIPAA) requiring documented evaluation that requirements were met</item>
        <item>Post-incident assessment: was the failure a missed requirement, implementation gap, or unmeasured non-functional?</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Throwaway prototypes or internal tools with 5 or fewer users — run a 15-minute retrospective instead</item>
        <item>Pre-PMF early-stage startups where requirements change every sprint — use continuous discovery</item>
        <item>When there is no baseline: without a measured "before", variance cannot be computed and the report is meaningless</item>
        <item>As a substitute for ongoing monitoring — a one-shot report that sits until the next audit is the canonical anti-pattern</item>
        <item>When the assessor reports to the project sponsor whose bonus depends on the result — independence is required</item>
        <item>Pure technical performance tuning (latency, throughput) — use SRE/SLO frameworks instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="assessment-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run four assessment types at distinct points: Design Assessment (during design — validate proposed solution meets requirements before build), Implementation Assessment (during build — verify correct implementation against spec), Deployment Assessment (at go-live — confirm readiness: QA, ops, support, training, security), Post-Implementation Assessment (after deployment at 30/60/90 days — measure actual delivered value).</statement>
        <rationale>A single end-of-project assessment misses implementation errors that could be fixed cheaply during build and cannot baseline-compare value because no pre-launch measurement was taken.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="success-criteria">
      <p>Five Success Criteria Categories:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Business Value: ROI achieved, revenue increased, cost reduced — measured against original business case projections</item>
        <item>Functional: features work as specified in requirements — measured against requirements compliance table</item>
        <item>Performance: speed, reliability, scalability — measured against NFR thresholds defined in requirements</item>
        <item>Usability: user satisfaction score, adoption rate — measured via survey and analytics</item>
        <item>Compliance: regulatory requirements met — measured via audit findings and control effectiveness</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="assessment-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1 — define assessment criteria and lock metric definitions with baseline queries. Step 2 — assess against requirements (compare actual to expected per requirement). Step 3 — evaluate business value (measure actuals against targets). Step 4 — identify limitations (document gaps and their business impact). Step 5 — recommend: accept, accept with remediation plan, require additional changes, or reject.</statement>
        <rationale>Steps without a defined order produce incomplete assessments; skipping step 1 (locking baselines) invalidates step 3 (value measurement).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="timing-triggers">
      <p>Assessment timing triggers by phase:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Design complete → Design review assessment</item>
        <item>Sprint complete → Implementation check (sample requirements verified)</item>
        <item>Before go-live → Deployment readiness assessment</item>
        <item>30 days post go-live → Initial post-implementation assessment</item>
        <item>90 days post go-live → Full post-implementation assessment</item>
        <item>Annually → Ongoing value assessment (contract renewal, phase-gate)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="quality-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every metric verdict must cite at least one evidence URL with a retrieved_at timestamp. Never declare a metric "Met" based on memory, dashboard screenshots, or verbal reports — require a queryable primary source (analytics export, finance export, ticketing export).</statement>
        <rationale>Agents hallucinate KPI values when data connectors are missing; humans misremember or report the number that supports the conclusion they want. Primary source citation is the only defense.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every metric row must include sample size. A metric hit on n=12 is not a hit — it is statistically inconclusive. Require the original power calculation's minimum sample size before calling any metric "Met".</statement>
        <rationale>Small samples produce variance that cannot be distinguished from noise; declaring success on underpowered data leads to wasted follow-on investment and erodes trust in future assessments.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Triangulate every business-value metric with at least two independent sources (e.g., analytics + finance, or analytics + survey). Single-source verdicts are fragile and gameable.</statement>
        <rationale>A single metric source can be manipulated by changing how the query is run; two independent sources must agree before a verdict is reliable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use numeric variance bands for met/partial/not-met verdicts: variance ≥ 0% = Met; -15% to 0% = Partially Met; less than -15% = Not Met. Never use qualitative verdicts — "seems on track" is not a verdict.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs and humans both cluster verdicts in "partially met" when thresholds are not defined; numeric bands force a deterministic decision.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Mark requirements as "Deprecated" (not "Not Met") when the underlying business need has changed since the requirement was written. A binary Met/Not Met verdict on a stale requirement incorrectly penalizes the delivery team.</statement>
        <rationale>Requirements written 9 months before delivery may reflect a different business context; forcing a Met/Not Met verdict on stale requirements produces misleading assessment reports.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>No baseline — cannot measure improvement. "Revenue went up after deployment" without a baseline is not a business value assessment.</description>
        <reason>Lock baselines before development starts using the same query and data source that will be used at assessment time.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Survey-only assessment under-samples churners — surveys reach users who still use the solution; the ones who churned never answer.</description>
        <reason>Reconcile survey n with active user count; flag if response rate is below 30% or if churned users are absent from the panel.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>One-shot assessment — a single 30-day report misses the honeymoon effect; real friction shows at 90+ days.</description>
        <reason>Run assessments at 30, 60, and 90 days; compare the three reports. A metric that was on-track at 30 and at-risk at 60 is the real story.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Assessor reports to the project sponsor whose bonus depends on the result — independence is compromised.</description>
        <reason>Route assessment through a different reporting chain or external reviewer. Independence is what gives the report weight at the steering committee.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="examples">
      <example type="good" title="CRM Implementation Assessment">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Solution: CRM Phase 1
Assessment Type: Post-Implementation (90 days)
Assessor: Independent BA (not on delivery team)

Requirements Compliance:
- 85% requirements fully met (17/20)
- 10% partially met (2/20) — mobile sync and bulk export features
- 5% not met (1/20) — deferred to Phase 2 (stakeholder-approved)

Business Value:
| Metric          | Baseline | Target | Actual | Variance | Status    |
|-----------------|----------|--------|--------|----------|-----------|
| Lead conversion | 12%      | +20% → 14.4% | 14.2% | -1.4%  | On Track  |
| Sales cycle     | 28 days  | -15% → 23.8d | 24.7d | -3.8%  | On Track  |
| Data accuracy   | 78%      | 95%    | 97%    | +2%      | Exceeded  |

Recommendation: Accept with remediation plan.
  - Mobile sync (partial): add to Phase 2 backlog within 30 days.
  - Sales cycle target: within -15% threshold; monitor at 120-day check.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="User Feedback Interpretation">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Survey Results (n=50, active user base=210, response rate=24%):

| Question                    | Score (1-5) |
|-----------------------------|-------------|
| Easy to learn               | 4.2         |
| Meets my work needs         | 3.8         |
| Performance acceptable      | 3.5         |
| Would recommend to colleague| 3.9         |

Caution: response rate 24% (<30% threshold) — churned users not represented.
Action: pull support ticket volume for non-respondents; reconcile before
  declaring satisfaction scores valid.

Key themes from free-text (n=50 responses):
- Performance needs improvement: mentioned 15 times → Critical issue
- Missing data export to Excel: mentioned 8 times → High priority backlog
- Training materials helpful: mentioned 12 times → Retain in onboarding
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-workflow">
      <p>Drive Solution Assessment as a four-pass evidence pipeline that mirrors the four assessment types. (1) **Frame pass** — a sonnet agent ingests the original spec, business case, and requirements register and emits structured `{requirements[], success_metrics[], baseline_values[], assessment_scope}`. No verdicts yet. (2) **Evidence-gathering pass** — parallel agents pull from product analytics (Mixpanel/PostHog/GA4), the ticketing system (Jira/Linear/GitHub), the support tool (Zendesk/Intercom), and survey results, emitting `{requirement_id, source, raw_metric, retrieved_at, sample_size}`. (3) **Verdict pass** — an opus agent compares actuals against targets per requirement and per metric, emitting `{requirement_id, status: met|partial|not_met|deprecated, variance_pct, evidence_urls[], confidence}` plus an issues register synthesized from support tickets clustered by topic. (4) **Recommendation pass** — an opus agent fuses (3) into Immediate / Short-term / Long-term action lists with owners and a final accept/conditional/reject verdict; only this pass produces prose. The decision (sign or rework) stays human; agents produce the table, the human signs the cover memo.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Known failure modes and mitigation:</p>
      <list>
        <item>**Survivorship bias in user feedback**: surveys reach the users who still use the solution. The ones who churned never answer. n=50 with a 4.2 satisfaction can mask 200 silent leavers; always reconcile survey n with active-user count.</item>
        <item>**Goodhart on KPIs**: once the team knows "lead conversion +20%" is the success metric, lead-quality definitions drift to make the number land. Lock metric definitions in the original business case and re-verify them at assessment time.</item>
        <item>**Variance ≠ causation**: revenue went up 18% post-deployment may be the solution, market tailwind, a competitor's outage, or the new comp plan. Without a control group / pre-post diff-in-diff the variance column is correlational at best.</item>
        <item>**Requirement drift**: REQ-014 was written 9 months before deployment. If the underlying business changed, "Met" or "Not Met" is the wrong question; the requirement is stale. Mark these explicitly as "deprecated" instead of forcing a binary verdict.</item>
        <item>**Recency bias on issues**: the issues list inflates whatever broke last week and forgets the silent successes from month one. Pull issues from the ticketing system over the full review period, not from team memory.</item>
        <item>**Adoption ≠ value**: 95% adoption looks great, but if the workflow it replaced was 90% efficient and the new one is 70% efficient, mandatory adoption *destroyed* value. Always cross-check adoption with productivity / cycle-time metrics.</item>
        <item>**Single-snapshot assessments**: 30 days post-launch most users are still in honeymoon mode; 12 months in, novelty fades and real friction shows. One-shot reports overstate success.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Lock metric definitions and baselines in the original business case; re-verify them at assessment time using the same query/source. Drift here invalidates the whole report.</item>
        <item>Always include sample size on every metric row; a target hit on n=12 is not a hit, and reviewers must see this.</item>
        <item>Triangulate every business-value metric with a second source (analytics + finance, or analytics + survey). Single-source verdicts are fragile.</item>
        <item>Time-box the review window explicitly (e.g. "30 days starting 2026-03-15") and stamp `retrieved_at` on every fact. Without windows, "actual" silently mixes pre- and post-launch traffic.</item>
        <item>Cluster support tickets by topic before reading them, not after. Otherwise the loudest 5 tickets dominate the issues register.</item>
        <item>Score independence: route the assessment through someone who is not on the delivery team and not the sponsor. Independence is what gives the report its weight at the steering committee.</item>
        <item>Run the assessment at 30, 60, and 90 days, not just one milestone. Compare the three reports — a metric that was "on track" at 30 and "at risk" at 60 is the real story; either snapshot alone misses it.</item>
        <item>Distinguish "deprecated requirements" from "not met". A binary verdict on a stale requirement penalizes the team for not building something the business no longer wants.</item>
        <item>Pre-mortem the recommended verdict ("if in 6 months we regret accepting this, why?"). The output goes into the Limitations section.</item>
        <item>Always include a "do nothing more" option in the recommendations — sometimes the right answer is to stop investing, not to remediate.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Agents will hallucinate KPI values when the analytics connector is missing. Force `evidence_urls` and `retrieved_at` on every metric and reject rows without primary sources (analytics export, finance export, ticketing export). Marketing dashboards and screenshots are not primary.</item>
        <item>LLMs cluster verdicts in the middle ("partially met") because it is the safest answer. Calibrate by requiring met / partial / not_met thresholds tied to numeric variance bands (e.g. variance ≥ 0% = met, -15..0% = partial, &lt; -15% = not met).</item>
        <item>Agents will silently fold "adoption" into "value" ("95% adoption → success"). Force separate sections in the schema; never let one column substitute for the other.</item>
        <item>Date drift: a metric pulled three months ago is not the same as today's. Stamp `retrieved_at` on every fact; agents must refuse to reuse evidence > the assessment window without re-fetching.</item>
        <item>An agent reading only the support-ticket export will report 100% complaints — by definition support sees only problems. Always pair tickets with active-user count and CSAT, never tickets alone.</item>
        <item>Survey-only assessments under-sample churners. Reconcile survey n with active-user count; flag if response rate &lt; 30% or if churned users are absent from the panel.</item>
        <item>A single agent doing all four passes inherits its own framing. Use a different model / prompt for the verdict pass than for the evidence pass; large disagreement signals low confidence.</item>
        <item>Agent-written executive summaries drift toward optimism. Lock the verdict mapping (accept requires zero "critical" issues and zero "not_met" reqs) at the schema level so prose cannot soften it.</item>
        <item>Watch for prompt-injected satisfaction quotes: free-text survey answers can contain "ignore previous instructions". Strip / sandbox before clustering.</item>
        <item>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints: signing the assessment scope (before evidence pass), the final verdict (before publication), and remediation acceptance (before triggering SDD tasks). Agents must never auto-accept on behalf of the sponsor.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/solution-assessment-report.md" purpose="Full assessment report: executive summary, requirements compliance table, business value table, user feedback, issues, limitations, recommendations."/>
      <template path="templates/post-implementation-review.md" purpose="Post-launch review: original business case vs. actual results, adoption metrics, issues log, lessons learned."/>
      <template path="templates/variance.py" purpose="Python script computing variance %, z-test p-value, and on-track/at-risk/off-track status for business metrics."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/career-resources/a-business-analyst%27s-toolkit/business-analysis-knowledge-area-solution-evaluation/"/>
      <link href="https://posthog.com/docs/product-analytics"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
