<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-four-pillars" title="Four Pillars of Design System Success">
  <summary>Clear ownership, usable components, strong documentation, and real adoption — four testable pillars that predict long-term design system survival.</summary>

  <section title="Pillar 1: Clear Ownership">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign a single DRI (Directly Responsible Individual) per pillar — not a committee. Committees produce zero accountability.</statement>
      <rationale>Brad Frost and NNG adoption research both show that ownership gaps are the primary cause of design system abandonment; a committee diffuses responsibility until nobody acts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate governance (who decides what enters the system) from maintenance (who fixes bugs); these are distinct accountabilities.</statement>
      <rationale>Conflating governance and maintenance creates decision bottlenecks during incidents and diffuse responsibility during roadmap planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pillar 2: Usable Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ship v0 with core components only (button, input, select, card, modal, typography, color tokens); do not wait for full coverage.</statement>
      <rationale>Waiting for completeness delays adoption; teams re-create components in the gap, creating the parallel system the design system was meant to replace.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Write a deprecation policy before v0 ships, not after the first regret; set the expectation that components can leave the system.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a deprecation policy, every component is implicitly permanent; the system accumulates debt that blocks refactoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pillar 3: Strong Documentation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every component must have at least one "do" and one "don't" example; generic copy does not count.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-generated and template-driven documentation tends toward generic copy; concrete examples are the only form that transfers correct usage to new contributors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Embed Figma library version and code package version in the docs site so designers and developers can see drift at a glance.</statement>
      <rationale>Version drift between design and code is invisible without explicit version display; version mismatch is a leading cause of spec-vs-implementation divergence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pillar 4: Real Adoption">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure adoption by splitting greenfield vs. legacy code; reporting aggregate coverage overstates progress.</statement>
      <rationale>A 60% aggregate coverage can mean 100% new code + 0% legacy; the legacy gap is where the most user-facing inconsistencies live.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie adoption metrics to a perf/a11y baseline so 100% component coverage cannot hide quality regressions.</statement>
      <rationale>A system component that passes usage tracking but ships with a11y violations or render-blocking CSS is worse than a raw HTML element with neither problem.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Adoption metric split: greenfield vs. legacy</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Greenfield (new code): 94% design-system components
Legacy (pre-DS code):  31% design-system components
Overall:               61% (misleading without the split)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
