<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="wireguard-vpn">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>server-craft</domain>
    <summary>Configure WireGuard VPN server with split-tunnel dev machine, full-tunnel mobile, and site-to-site home gateway. Cryptokey routing for access control.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>wireguard</tag>
      <tag>vpn</tag>
      <tag>networking</tag>
      <tag>security</tag>
      <tag>linux</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>WireGuard VPN</title>

    <summary>Configure WireGuard as a VPN server on a Linux VPS with multiple peer types: split-tunnel dev machine (VPN subnet only), full-tunnel mobile (all traffic), and site-to-site gateway (VPS to home LAN). Uses cryptokey routing — each peer's AllowedIPs list determines which packets are routed to it.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>WireGuard is ~4,000 lines vs OpenVPN's 100,000+, runs as a kernel module (built-in since Linux 5.6), and achieves near-wire speed. For solo developers it eliminates exposing database ports publicly — services bind to 127.0.0.1 on the VPS and are accessible only through the VPN tunnel.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Accessing internal VPS services (PostgreSQL, Redis, RabbitMQ) securely without exposing ports to the internet</item>
        <item>Creating a site-to-site tunnel between a VPS and home network/Raspberry Pi</item>
        <item>Routing all mobile traffic through the VPS for privacy on public Wi-Fi</item>
        <item>Restricting SSH access to VPN subnet only (after VPN is confirmed working)</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When you only need SSH access — an SSH tunnel (`ssh -L`) is simpler and requires no server-side setup</item>
        <item>When your provider already offers a managed VPN or private networking between servers — use that instead</item>
        <item>As a replacement for UFW — WireGuard controls which hosts can connect; UFW controls which ports are exposed. Both are needed</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="cryptokey-routing">
      <p>When a packet arrives on a WireGuard interface, the source IP is checked against every peer's AllowedIPs. If it matches, the packet is accepted and decrypted with that peer's key. If it does not match any peer's AllowedIPs, the packet is silently dropped.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>AllowedIPs serves two purposes: ingress filter (which source IPs to accept) and egress routing table (which destination IPs to send to this peer).</statement>
        <rationale>This dual role is the core of WireGuard's simplicity — no separate routing table entries needed, no certificate authority, just keys and IP ranges.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
# Server sees packets from 10.0.0.2 → trusts them if signed by laptop's key
# Server sees packets for 10.0.0.2 → encrypts and sends to laptop

Peer (laptop): AllowedIPs = 10.0.0.2/32
Peer (RPi + LAN): AllowedIPs = 10.0.0.3/32, 192.168.1.0/24
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="key-types">
      <p>Three types of keys: private key (generated with `wg genkey`, never leave device, chmod 600), public key (derived from private with `wg pubkey`, share with peers), preshared key (optional symmetric key for post-quantum resistance, generated with `wg genpsk`).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Private key — generated with `wg genkey`. Never leave the device. chmod 600.</statement>
        <rationale>Private keys must be protected from unauthorized access. chmod 600 ensures only the owner can read.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Public key — derived from private key with `wg pubkey`. Share with all peers who need to connect to you.</statement>
        <rationale>Public keys are safe to share publicly; they are cryptographically derived from the private key.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Preshared key — optional symmetric key shared between two specific peers. Adds a post-quantum resistance layer. Generated with `wg genpsk`.</statement>
        <rationale>Preshared keys provide defense-in-depth against potential future quantum computers that might break ECDH.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="network-architecture">
      <p>VPS acts as the hub. All peers connect to it. Peer-to-peer traffic routes through the VPS unless direct routing is configured.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
VPS wg0: 10.0.0.1/24  (hub)
  Peer: dev laptop  10.0.0.2/32  (split tunnel)
  Peer: home RPi    10.0.0.3/32 + 192.168.1.0/24  (site-to-site)
  Peer: phone       10.0.0.4/32  (full tunnel)
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="full-tunnel-vs-split-tunnel">
      <p>The only difference is AllowedIPs on the client config. Full tunnel: `AllowedIPs = 0.0.0.0/0, ::/0` — all traffic routes through VPN. Split tunnel: `AllowedIPs = 10.0.0.0/24` — only VPN subnet uses tunnel, internet goes direct.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="server-interface-section">
      <p>Server Interface section specifies PrivateKey, Address /24, ListenPort, and PostUp NAT rules. IP forwarding required on server.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
[Interface]
PrivateKey  = <server-private-key>
Address     = 10.0.0.1/24
ListenPort  = 51820
SaveConfig  = false

# NAT — replace eth0 with actual interface (ip route | grep default)
PostUp   = iptables -A FORWARD -i wg0 -j ACCEPT; iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
PostDown = iptables -D FORWARD -i wg0 -j ACCEPT; iptables -t nat -D POSTROUTING -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use Address = x.x.x.1/24 on the server (not /32) so the wg0 interface owns the entire /24 subnet.</statement>
        <rationale>A /32 on the server means the server only has its own IP. With /24, the kernel knows all 10.0.0.x addresses are reachable via wg0 and routes them correctly.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="peer-section">
      <p>Each peer gets a Peer section with PublicKey, PresharedKey, AllowedIPs, and PersistentKeepalive for NAT traversal.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
# Laptop — split tunnel
[Peer]
PublicKey          = <laptop-pubkey>
PresharedKey       = <laptop-preshared-key>
AllowedIPs         = 10.0.0.2/32

# Home RPi — site-to-site with LAN access
[Peer]
PublicKey          = <rpi-pubkey>
PresharedKey       = <rpi-preshared-key>
AllowedIPs         = 10.0.0.3/32, 192.168.1.0/24
PersistentKeepalive = 25

# Phone — full tunnel
[Peer]
PublicKey          = <phone-pubkey>
PresharedKey       = <phone-preshared-key>
AllowedIPs         = 10.0.0.4/32
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Set PersistentKeepalive = 25 for peers behind NAT (home RPi, mobile).</statement>
        <rationale>NAT tables expire idle UDP sessions. Without keepalive, a peer behind NAT will lose its ability to receive packets after ~30 seconds of silence.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ip-forwarding">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# /etc/sysctl.d/99-wireguard.conf
net.ipv4.ip_forward = 1
net.ipv6.conf.all.forwarding = 1

# Apply immediately
sudo sysctl -p /etc/sysctl.d/99-wireguard.conf
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="site-to-site-routing">
      <p>To reach the home LAN (192.168.1.0/24) from any VPN peer: add the LAN subnet to the RPi peer's AllowedIPs on the server, and enable forwarding + NAT on the RPi.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
# Server: RPi peer entry
[Peer]
PublicKey  = <rpi-pubkey>
AllowedIPs = 10.0.0.3/32, 192.168.1.0/24

# RPi wg0.conf: forward traffic to/from home LAN
[Interface]
PostUp   = iptables -A FORWARD -i wg0 -o eth0 -j ACCEPT; iptables -A FORWARD -i eth0 -o wg0 -j ACCEPT; iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
PostDown = iptables -D FORWARD -i wg0 -o eth0 -j ACCEPT; iptables -D FORWARD -i eth0 -o wg0 -j ACCEPT; iptables -t nat -D POSTROUTING -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="dev-machine-split-tunnel">
      <p>Goal: reach VPS internal services (PostgreSQL, Redis) without routing internet traffic through VPN. AllowedIPs includes only VPN subnet.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
# /etc/wireguard/wg0.conf on dev machine
[Interface]
PrivateKey = <dev-private-key>
Address    = 10.0.0.2/32

[Peer]
PublicKey          = <server-pubkey>
PresharedKey       = <preshared-key>
Endpoint           = SERVER_PUBLIC_IP:51820
AllowedIPs         = 10.0.0.0/24
PersistentKeepalive = 25
        ]]></code>
        <note>Internet traffic continues via normal gateway. Only 10.0.0.x traffic uses VPN.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="mobile-full-tunnel">
      <p>Route all mobile traffic through VPS for privacy on public Wi-Fi.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="ini"><![CDATA[
[Interface]
PrivateKey = <phone-private-key>
Address    = 10.0.0.4/32
DNS        = 1.1.1.1

[Peer]
PublicKey          = <server-pubkey>
PresharedKey       = <preshared-key>
Endpoint           = SERVER_PUBLIC_IP:51820
AllowedIPs         = 0.0.0.0/0, ::/0
PersistentKeepalive = 25
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Generate mobile config, then create QR code for import
sudo cat /etc/wireguard/clients/phone.conf | qrencode -t ansiutf8
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="restrict-ssh-to-vpn-subnet">
      <p>After confirming VPN works, restrict SSH access to VPN IPs. This eliminates the SSH attack surface for external scanners.</p>

      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# /etc/ssh/sshd_config
AllowUsers nero@10.0.0.0/24

# Or UFW rule (after removing the 0.0.0.0 SSH rule)
sudo ufw delete allow 22022/tcp
sudo ufw allow from 10.0.0.0/24 to any port 22022 proto tcp comment 'SSH via VPN'
sudo ufw reload
        ]]></code>
        <note>Test VPN SSH works before applying. Keep a rescue console session open.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="vpn-status-check">
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Show all peers and last handshake time
sudo wg show

# Check handshake age (stale = no handshake in 3+ min)
sudo wg show wg0 latest-handshakes

# Data transferred per peer
sudo wg show wg0 transfer

# Verify IP forwarding
cat /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward  # should be 1
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/wg0-server.conf" purpose="Server config with multiple peer types (laptop, RPi+LAN, phone)"/>
      <template path="templates/wg0-client-full.conf" purpose="Linux/macOS full-tunnel client (0.0.0.0/0)"/>
      <template path="templates/wg0-client-split.conf" purpose="Split-tunnel client (VPN subnet only)"/>
      <template path="templates/wg0-client-mobile.conf" purpose="Mobile client config (scan as QR code)"/>
      <template path="templates/wg0-home-gateway.conf" purpose="Home RPi/gateway site-to-site config"/>
      <template path="templates/sysctl-wireguard.conf" purpose="IP forwarding settings for WireGuard server"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/generate-wg-keys.sh" purpose="Generate private, public, preshared keys for a new peer"/>
      <script path="scripts/add-wg-peer.sh" purpose="Add peer to running interface, generate client config and QR code"/>
      <script path="scripts/wg-status.sh" purpose="Show peer handshake age, data transfer, active/stale status"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.wireguard.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.wireguard.com/quickstart/"/>
      <link href="https://www.wireguard.com/netlink/"/>
      <link href="https://ubuntu.com/server/docs/vpn-wireguard"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
