<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Ops Metrics Basics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Ops Metrics Basics` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="5-10-not-50" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set MUST contain 5-10 metrics. Fewer leaves blind spots; more dilutes ownership. Reject configs with &gt; 10 board / weekly metrics.</statement>
      <rationale source="Andy Grove HBR Output Management; OpenView 2023 SaaS benchmarks">Cognitive limit on metric reasoning — beyond 10 metrics nobody can hold the system in their head, ownership decays, alerts get ignored.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="locked-formula-per-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each metric MUST have one canonical SQL / formula stored alongside the config. Recomputations across tools forbidden — single source of truth.</statement>
      <rationale source="Looker / Mode metrics-store best-practice">Same name + different formula across reports produces uncomparable numbers + heated meetings. Locked formula prevents drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="target-and-alert-per-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each metric MUST carry an explicit target value AND an alert threshold. Metrics without targets are observation, not management.</statement>
      <rationale source="OKR / SaaS planning corpus">Without target the metric is a thermometer not a thermostat. Alert threshold makes the metric actionable — change behaviour, not just report.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="cadence-tiered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cadence MUST be tiered: daily pulse (&lt;= 3 metrics, automated), weekly review (5-10 metrics, owner-led), monthly deep-dive (segments, cohorts). Single weekly-only cadence is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tomasz Tunguz weekly business review; ProfitWell ops cadences">Tiered cadence matches metric latency. Daily catches fires; weekly catches trends; monthly catches structural shifts. Single cadence misses two of three.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="named-metric-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each metric MUST name a single human owner. Group owners (&apos;marketing&apos;, &apos;#growth&apos;) are rejected — accountability decays without a name.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal RACI for metrics">Group-owned metrics rot. Named owner has lever to drive the metric + answer for misses at the review.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
