<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tracking-and-review" title="Tracking Stack, Targets, Alerts, and Review Cadence">
  <summary>Data sources, lean tracking stack options, target-setting approach, alert thresholds, and review cadence for operators.</summary>

  <section title="Lean Tracking Stack">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the simplest stack that answers your questions: Stripe → Google Sheets → Looker Studio covers 80% of solopreneur needs before a data warehouse is justified.</statement>
      <rationale>Complex analytics stacks require maintenance overhead that consumes time that could be spent on the business. Looker Studio's Stripe connector provides MRR, churn, and cohort data without custom SQL.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Stack options by scale: smallest — Stripe + Google Sheets + Looker Studio; mid — Stripe + PostHog free tier + Looker Studio; largest pre-warehouse — Stripe + Mixpanel/Amplitude + Metabase.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Target Setting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set targets with three-level status thresholds: green (within 10% of target), yellow (10-20% below target), red (more than 20% below target); review red metrics in the next daily check-in.</statement>
      <rationale>Binary pass/fail targets produce false urgency and panic. Three-level thresholds match response effort to deviation severity and prevent over-reaction to normal variance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Alert Triggers">
    <p>Configure alerts for four conditions: revenue drop greater than 20% week-over-week (investigate immediately), churn rate above threshold (review immediately), zero sales for 24+ hours (check payment system health), CAC above target (review ad spend).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Review Cadence">
    <p>Four frequencies: Daily pulse check (2 minutes — revenue and zero-sales alert); weekly performance review (30 minutes — full metrics table, went-well, needs-attention, next-week actions); monthly deep analysis (2 hours — cohort trends, CAC/LTV reconciliation, churn diagnosis); quarterly strategy review (half day — target reset, OKR alignment).</p>
    <reference path="templates/weekly-review.md">Weekly review template with metrics table and action items</reference>
  </section>
</text>
