<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Thematic Analysis Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Thematic Analysis application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-two-pass-coding" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Coding MUST proceed in two passes: open coding (per-line tags, no scheme) -&gt; axial coding (collapse into themes). Single-pass coding is rejected because it bakes in interpretation before the data has spoken.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Two-pass coding is the established qualitative standard (Braun &amp; Clarke); skipping the open pass causes researchers to map data to their hypothesis rather than the other way round.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-dual-coder-kappa" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Two independent coders MUST tag &gt;=20% of the corpus separately; Cohen's kappa across their codes MUST be &gt;= 0.6. Below 0.6 = reconcile codebook and re-code before continuing.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Single-coder qualitative work is indistinguishable from confirmation bias; the kappa gate forces disagreement to surface and be resolved.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-saturation-check" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Coding stops only after 3 consecutive new transcripts produce zero new themes (saturation). Stopping at a fixed N without saturation evidence is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Fixed-N stopping rules under-sample rare themes and over-sample common ones; saturation is the empirically-defended rule from grounded-theory practice.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-quote-anchored-themes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every theme in the final report MUST be anchored to &gt;=2 direct verbatim quotes with transcript-id + timestamp/line-number. Themes without anchors are stripped.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Un-anchored themes drift into the analyst's prior beliefs; quote anchoring makes the report falsifiable by the reader.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-backlog-handover" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The report MUST emit a per-theme backlog row: theme_id, severity (low/med/high), proposed action, evidence count, owner. Reports without a backlog hand-off are rejected as documentation rather than insight.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Insight is action that did not happen yet; the backlog row turns the theme into a unit of work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
