<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Messaging House Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every messaging house must enforce. These prevent the most common failure: per-channel divergence where the buyer hears different value props in different places.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-one-root-value-statement" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exactly ONE root value statement at the top. One sentence, max 18 words, includes who-it's-for + what-it-does + outcome. Reject houses with 2+ root statements OR statements exceeding 18 words.</statement>
      <rationale source="positioning craft (April Dunford)">Multiple root statements confuse buyers; long statements lose the spine. 18 words forces clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-exactly-three-pillars" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exactly THREE pillars supporting the root. Not 2 (too thin), not 4+ (loses focus). Each pillar names a discrete area of value. Reject houses with pillar count != 3.</statement>
      <rationale source="memorability research">Buyers retain three; four becomes "a list." Three is the canonical positioning pillar count for a reason.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-min-two-proof-points-per-pillar" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each pillar carries 2-4 proof points. Each proof point is one of: data (with source), customer quote (with named attribution), demo asset (with link). Reject pillars with &lt; 2 proof points OR proof points without evidence type.</statement>
      <rationale source="evidence-based marketing">Pillars without proof are claims; claims without evidence don't convert. Each pillar needs at least two evidence types so a buyer with one objection still finds another to lean on.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-channel-variant-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each pillar produces per-channel variants for ≥ 3 channels (X, LinkedIn, email, ads, landing). Variants must preserve the pillar's core idea AND respect the channel's character limits + voice. Reject variants that drift to a different pillar.</statement>
      <rationale source="channel-consistency studies">Buyers exposed to consistent messaging across 3+ channels convert 2-3× higher. Variants that drift fragment the buyer's mental model.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-content-lead-ownership" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The house has a named owner (content lead) who approves all per-channel variants before publish. Reject houses without a single named owner OR houses where individual channel writers commit variants directly.</statement>
      <rationale source="brand consistency literature">Distributed ownership leads to local optimization (each writer optimizes their channel; collective consistency suffers). One owner enforces consistency at the gate.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Filled messaging house">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Root value:
  "Faion gives solo developers shipped product in weeks, not months,
   by combining a Claude Code add-on with 1300+ methodologies."

Pillars:
  P1: 10× output. Same budget.
     Proof: customer quote (alex@indie), data: 3 launches in 90 days
  P2: One person, full SDD lifecycle.
     Proof: demo: 7-min spec → ship video,  customer quote (jess@solo)
  P3: Methodology depth, not just templates.
     Proof: data: 52 skills × 1300 methodologies, customer quote (sam@dev)

Per-channel variants:
  X (P1):       "Solo dev. 3 launches in 90 days. With Faion."
  LinkedIn (P1): [200 chars expanded with quote + outcome]
  Email subj (P2): "Spec → ship in one afternoon"
  Landing hero (root): the root statement, full sentence
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r2, r3, r4 in a complete house.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Pillar inflation, weak proof points">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Root: "We help businesses transform with cutting-edge AI solutions."  (24 words, vague)

Pillars: P1 Innovation, P2 Quality, P3 Speed, P4 Cost-effective, P5 Reliable, P6 Scalable
Proof: each pillar has 1 generic claim, no evidence.

Per-channel: all variants say "transform with AI" — no pillar
differentiation. Buyer hears the same vague thing in 5 places.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r2, r3, r4 simultaneous violations.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
