<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="immersive-design-principles">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Design balanced immersive experiences for AR/VR/MR by calibrating immersion levels, preventing motion sickness, and ensuring comfort across device platforms.</summary>
    <category>spatial</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>immersive-design</tag>
      <tag>vr</tag>
      <tag>ar</tag>
      <tag>mr</tag>
      <tag>xr</tag>
      <tag>comfort</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
    <related>
      <ref slug="spatial-accessibility"/>
      <ref slug="hmd-design-patterns"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Immersive Design Principles</title>

    <summary>Immersive experiences (AR/VR/MR/XR) balance presence with comfort. Four immersion levels exist: passthrough (real + overlays), blended (mixed real/virtual), immersive (full virtual), and portal (windows into virtual). Design with depth, realistic motion physics, environmental awareness, and smooth transitions. Address motion sickness, disorientation, eye strain, and arm fatigue via fixed reference points, grounding, proper depth of field, and rest positions. Test with real headsets and diverse user populations (glasses-wearers, 50+, first-time HMD users) because team tolerance is unrepresentative.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Immersion can overwhelm or disorient users. Uncontrolled immersion erodes presence and causes motion sickness, disorientation, eye strain, and arm fatigue. Without deliberate immersion-level design, experiences that feel comfortable in 5-minute demos fail in 20-minute sessions.</p>
      <p>Vision Pro, Quest 3, Pico 4, and HoloLens 2 each track differently; principles tuned for one platform fail on another. Hardware drift (eye-tracking, EyeSight, hand-tracking latency) moves the comfort baseline. Static documentation cannot capture motion-physics nuance; you need in-headset playtests, not figmas.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing for AR/VR/MR headsets (Vision Pro, Quest 3, Pico 4, HoloLens 2) where immersion level must be deliberate.</item>
        <item>Mixed-reality enterprise tools (training, remote assistance, surgery planning) where over-immersion is a safety risk.</item>
        <item>Spatial gaming and entertainment where immersion-comfort tradeoff drives session length.</item>
        <item>Designing transitions between passthrough and fully-immersive states (the moment most discomfort happens).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>2D mobile / web flows without spatial component.</item>
        <item>Simple AR effects (face filters, product try-on snippets) — overkill for one-shot interactions.</item>
        <item>Marketing-only "VR demo" projects with no real user-research budget; principles are wasted without testing.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="immersion-levels">
      <p>Each immersion level trades presence against cognitive load and motion risk. Select one per scene and transition deliberately.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pick one immersion level per scene, transition deliberately. Mixed signals (head-locked + world-locked together) cause disorientation.</statement>
        <rationale>Conflicting reference frames break spatial orientation. Clarity on whether UI is fixed to head or world prevents mode confusion and motion sickness.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Passthrough-first for productivity apps">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Passthrough (AR navigation)
├─ Real world: GPS map, street view overlaid on camera feed
├─ Reference: fixed earth/GPS frame
└─ Comfort: naturalistic; zero vection risk
        ]]></code>
        <note>Opt into full immersion only when the task demands it.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Blended for remote work">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Blended (MR workspace)
├─ Real: desk, hands
├─ Virtual: floating windows, collaboration avatars
├─ Reference: room-scale with seated anchor
└─ Comfort: high session tolerance (30+ min)
        ]]></code>
        <note>Hybrid mode suits knowledge work without full immersion burden.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Sudden immersion toggle without fade">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Click button → instant black fill → full virtual environment
│
└─ Disorientation, nausea on fast headset, vestibular overload
        ]]></code>
        <note>Missing transition fade lets vection spike. Transition fade ≥0.2s is non-negotiable below 90 Hz.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Mixing head-locked UI (crosshairs, fixed menus) with world-locked objects (moving enemies, environmental geometry) in the same viewport.</description>
        <reason>Conflicts in reference frame (head vs. world) create vestibular conflict. Users experience disorientation and motion sickness.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="motion-and-comfort">
      <p>Motion sickness, disorientation, eye strain, and arm fatigue are the four pillars of immersive-design comfort. Address each via distinct design moves.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Comfort vignette during locomotion (snap turn or smooth) is non-negotiable below 90 Hz. Arm-rest poses are required for sessions > 10 min. Fixed reference points prevent motion sickness; clear grounding with stable horizon prevents disorientation.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 90 Hz, visual latency causes vection (perceived self-motion). Vignette (darkening peripheral vision) reduces nausea-inducing optical flow. Arm support and seated-mode reduce fatigue-driven dropout. Horizon stability anchors spatial perception.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Seated-mode with arm rest">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Session > 5 min → provide seated-mode
├─ Head center at ~1.5 m eye height (not floor)
├─ Hand poses: arms supported by armrests
├─ Interaction: finger/wrist only; no reaching
└─ Fatigue: zero arm fatigue in 30+ min sessions
        ]]></code>
        <note>Arm fatigue is the silent churn killer. Seated-mode is non-negotiable for productivity and gaming.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Vignette on snap turns below 90 Hz">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Snap turn (instantaneous 45° yaw)
├─ At t=0: fade to black (0.1s ramp)
├─ At t=0.1–0.15s: rotate viewpoint
├─ At t=0.2s+: fade back to scene
└─ Comfort: reduces post-rotational nausea by 80%+
        ]]></code>
        <note>Vignette masks accelerated optical flow perception. 0.2s fade is minimum; 0.4s is safer for sensitive users.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="No comfort vignette on locomotion">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Smooth turn or snap at 60 Hz, no vignette
│
└─ Peripheral optical flow → vection → nausea in 30–120 sec
        ]]></code>
        <note>Unmasked motion-to-photon latency spike causes simulator sickness (SSQ positive after 2–5 min).</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Comfort guidelines are population averages; ~10% of users get sick regardless of "best practice" defaults.</description>
        <reason>Vestibular sensitivity varies 5–10x across population. Genetic factors, prior motion-sickness history, and medication all shift the comfort baseline. No single design works for all.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hardware drift: principles tuned for Quest 2 fail on Vision Pro (eye-tracking, EyeSight) and vice versa.</description>
        <reason>Each platform has different latency, refresh rate, field of view, and hand-tracking fidelity. Retest on every platform target.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use agents to draft immersion-level decisions, comfort checklists, and transition state-machines, but verify every motion/locomotion decision in a real headset with at least 3 testers across 30+ minutes. LLMs do not feel motion sickness; they will confidently approve a vection pattern that ships nausea.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Agents may draft immersion-level decisions and comfort checklists. Every motion/locomotion decision MUST be verified in-headset with ≥3 testers for ≥30 minutes before shipping.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs can plausibly argue for any motion pattern. Vestibular response cannot be predicted from text; only embodied testing reveals nausea-inducing patterns.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <note>Recommended subagents: `faion-ux-researcher-agent` (generates spatial usability test scripts, comfort-rating questionnaires like SSQ and VRSQ), `faion-usability-agent` (heuristic walkthrough against Oculus / Apple HIG checklists).</note>

      <example type="good" title="Comfort review checklist generator">
        <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
#!/usr/bin/env bash
# gen-comfort-checklist.sh — emit per-scene comfort review file
SCENE="${1:?scene name}"
mkdir -p "review/$SCENE"
cat > "review/$SCENE/comfort.md" <<MD
# $SCENE — Comfort Review
- [ ] Ground plane present and stable
- [ ] Horizon line within 5° of expected
- [ ] No head-locked UI elements
- [ ] Locomotion method declared: ____
- [ ] Vection events <3s, with comfort vignette
- [ ] Frame rate ≥72 Hz (Quest), ≥90 Hz (Vision Pro)
- [ ] Transition fade ≥0.2s on immersion changes
- [ ] Arm-rest poses for sessions >10 min
- [ ] Subtitle/voice option present
- [ ] SSQ pre/post measurement plan
MD
        ]]></code>
        <note>Inline bash generator for per-scene comfort review. Run after each layout change.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>These practices are learned from failures in production VR/AR/MR deployments.</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Default to passthrough-first for productivity apps; opt into full immersion only when the task demands it. Provide seated-mode for any experience > 5 min. Test with people who wear glasses, are over 50, and have never used an HMD — your team's tolerance is unrepresentative.</statement>
        <rationale>Passthrough reduces cognitive load and allows quick context-switching. Seated-mode eliminates arm fatigue (the silent churn killer). Diverse testers catch population-specific comfort failures that homogeneous teams miss.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLMs have systematic biases when evaluating immersive experiences. Pin these explicitly in prompts:</p>

      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Force agents to justify immersion-level tradeoffs. Motion physics descriptions sound plausible in text and feel terrible in headset — never ship without playtest. Never accept agent claims like "this should run at 90 Hz" without on-device profiling. Vendor HIGs (Apple visionOS vs. Meta vs. Pico) contradict each other; pick one platform per prompt and explicitly exclude cross-vendor averaging.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to "more immersive = better" framing. Text-plausible motion patterns cause vestibular overload in-headset. Latency budgets (motion-to-photon) cannot be verified by LLM; they need on-device profiling. Vendor platforms differ so much that cross-platform synthesis produces nonsense.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <p>Example prompt for agent-assisted immersion-level review:</p>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are reviewing an XR scene description for immersion-comfort balance.
Inputs: {scene_summary, locomotion_method, session_length_min, target_device}.
Output JSON: {
  immersion_level: passthrough|blended|immersive|portal,
  comfort_risks: [{risk, severity, mitigation}],
  transition_smoothness: 0-5,
  ssq_red_flags: [...]
}
Cite the Oculus VRC or Apple visionOS HIG section per finding. No invented citations.
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <rule testable="false">
        <statement>Use platform-specific profiling tools to validate latency, frame rate, and hand-tracking jitter. No agent can verify these.</statement>
        <rationale>Motion-to-photon latency is platform-specific. Agents cannot measure real-time performance.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
oculus-cli (ovrplatformutil)
  – Build/upload Quest builds, fetch perf metrics
  – https://developer.oculus.com/downloads/package/oculus-platform-utility/

xrgears / OpenXR validation layers
  – Runtime conformance checks
  – https://github.com/KhronosGroup/OpenXR-SDK

realitytool (Xcode)
  – Validate visionOS scene assets, USDZ packaging
  – Xcode 15+

adb logcat -s VrApi,XrApi
  – Pull comfort-related runtime warnings on Quest
  – Android SDK
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Meta Horizon OS dashboard (SaaS, Limited)
  – Comfort/perf dashboards behind auth; manual export.

Apple App Store Connect (SaaS, Limited)
  – visionOS analytics; no public agent API.

Unity Cloud Build (SaaS, Yes)
  – CLI + REST; automate immersion-test build pipelines.

Unreal Horde (OSS, Yes)
  – Self-host CI/CD for high-fidelity XR.

ShapesXR (SaaS, Partial)
  – Collaborative spatial review; export to Unity.

Reality Composer Pro (macOS app, No)
  – Manual workflow for visionOS USDZ scenes.
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/spatial-layout"/>
      <link href="https://developer.oculus.com/resources/bp-vrc-quest/"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/OpenXR-SDK"/>
      <ref slug="spatial-accessibility"/>
      <ref slug="hmd-design-patterns"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
