<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="User Control and Freedom Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every user-control-freedom application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-undo-over-confirm" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For reversible actions, prefer undo (toast + 5-10s window) over confirmation dialogs. Confirmation is reserved for irreversible, high-stakes operations.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — undo vs confirmation research">Confirmation overuse causes dialog fatigue; users dismiss without reading, defeating the safety purpose.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-soft-delete-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Content deletion defaults to soft delete (trash / archive). Permanent delete requires an explicit secondary confirmation.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — destructive-action research">Soft delete preserves recovery while clearly differentiating routine from final deletion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-modal-three-exits" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every modal MUST have THREE exit paths: X button, Escape key, click-outside-modal. Missing any one is a violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG 2.2 + NNG modal research">Different users reach for different exits; missing any path creates a trap for that population.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-wizard-back" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-step wizards MUST show step count and provide Back navigation on every step except the first; a persistent Exit option MUST be available throughout.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — wizard pattern research">Trapped-in-wizard is one of the highest-friction patterns; visible escape is the fix.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-fatigue-dialogs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>"Are you sure?" confirmations are FORBIDDEN for non-destructive or routine actions.</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — confirmation fatigue research">Routine confirmations train users to dismiss; the dialog stops working when it matters.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-focus-trap-tested" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Focus traps MUST be verified with axe-core / pa11y / Playwright. Agent audit identifies structural absence; live verification is required for sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG 2.2 — Focus Order; F-066 wave grounding">Static review cannot detect runtime focus traps; tooling is mandatory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-irreversible-severity1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An irreversible action with NO confirmation AND NO undo is severity 1 (blocker).</statement>
      <rationale source="NNG — error recovery research">No recovery path is the highest-cost UX defect; it blocks user trust.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
