<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-patterns" title="User Control Implementation Patterns">
  <summary>Control mechanisms (undo, cancel, exit, reset), undo vs. confirmation decision rule, and implementation patterns for modals, forms, and multi-step flows.</summary>

  <section title="Control Mechanisms">
    <p>
      Undo — reverse the last action; prefer this over confirmation for reversible operations.
      Redo — restore an undone action.
      Cancel — discard current changes and return to previous state.
      Back — return to previous screen in a flow.
      Close — exit current context (modal, panel, overlay).
      Reset — restore default settings.
    </p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer undo over confirmation dialogs for reversible actions.</statement>
      <rationale>Undo feels less disruptive, reduces friction for expert users, and does not interrupt the action flow; confirmation dialogs should be reserved for irreversible, high-stakes operations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Undo vs. Confirmation Decision Rule">
    <p>Use undo when: action is frequent, recovery is technically possible, impact is moderate (e.g., deleting a list item).</p>
    <p>Use confirmation when: action is irreversible, impact is severe, action is rare (e.g., permanently deleting an account, canceling a subscription).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use soft delete (move to trash/archive) by default for any content deletion; permanent delete requires explicit secondary confirmation.</statement>
      <rationale>Soft delete gives users a recovery window and eliminates accidental permanent data loss without requiring a confirmation dialog on every deletion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Modal Exit Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every modal must have at least three exit paths: X button, Escape key, and clicking outside the modal.</statement>
      <rationale>Users expect all three; implementing only one or two creates trapped-user scenarios for keyboard and mouse users respectively.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Gmail "Undo send" — action completes immediately, then a dismissible toast offers 5-30 second undo window. Removes the need for a "Are you sure?" dialog before sending.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Newsletter popup with no X button and no close option — user must subscribe or refresh page. Forced modal with no exit is a trapped-user antipattern.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Multi-Step Flow Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show step count and provide Back navigation on every step of a multi-step wizard except the first; provide a persistent Exit option throughout.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who cannot see progress or navigate backward feel trapped and abandon; visible progress and exits reduce abandonment in long flows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not use "Are you sure?" confirmations for non-destructive or routine actions.</statement>
      <rationale>Confirmation fatigue causes users to click through without reading; reserve confirmations for genuinely destructive operations only.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/control-audit.md">User Control Audit table template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/verify-escape-exits.spec.js">Playwright test for modal Escape key behavior</reference>
</text>
