<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="User Control Rules, Accessibility, and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Concrete audit rules, accessibility requirements for control mechanisms, common mistakes, and agent limitations.</summary>

  <section title="Audit Checklist Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every user-facing action must be assessed for: undo availability, cancel availability, exit mechanism, and recovery method.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing any one of these for a high-impact action is a usability defect; systematic audit prevents gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag high-severity gaps as: irreversible action with no confirmation AND no undo.</statement>
      <rationale>The combination of irreversibility and lack of both undo and confirmation is the highest-risk pattern; it must be addressed before shipping.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Requirements">
    <p>
      Keyboard shortcuts for undo (Ctrl+Z) and redo (Ctrl+Y/Shift+Z) must be implemented.
      Escape key must always close modals and dismiss overlays.
      Focus must return to the triggering element when a modal closes.
      Undo actions must be announced to screen readers.
      Cancel and close buttons must have text labels, not icon-only affordances.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No undo for frequently performed actions.</description>
      <reason>Users who make frequent mistakes in high-volume workflows lose trust quickly when recovery requires more effort than the original action.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hidden or hard-to-find Cancel buttons in forms and dialogs.</description>
      <reason>Users who cannot find the exit feel trapped; Cancel must be visually prominent and near the primary action button.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Confirmation dialog overuse — "Are you sure?" on every action including non-destructive ones.</description>
      <reason>Confirmation fatigue causes users to dismiss dialogs without reading, defeating their purpose for high-stakes actions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Usage Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair agent audit with axe-core or pa11y run; agent cannot detect focus traps in rendered interfaces.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent identifies structural absence of controls from descriptions; actual keyboard navigation testing requires browser tooling.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Undo and cancel implementation decisions require engineering sign-off; agent audit identifies the need, not the technical approach.</statement>
      <rationale>Undo architecture depends on backend event sourcing, transaction logs, or soft-delete patterns that require engineering judgment on consistency and rollback scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/verify-escape-exits.spec.js">Playwright test to verify Escape key closes modals</reference>
</text>
