<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="user-control-freedom Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for user-control-freedom as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>No undo for frequently performed actions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users who make frequent mistakes in high-volume workflows lose trust quickly when recovery requires more effort than the original action.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Hidden or hard-to-find Cancel buttons in forms and dialogs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users who cannot find the exit feel trapped; Cancel must be visually prominent and near the primary action button.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Confirmation dialog overuse — "Are you sure?" on every action including non-destructive ones.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confirmation fatigue causes users to dismiss dialogs without reading, defeating their purpose for high-stakes actions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent audit based on action names alone may miss context-dependent severity.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Delete" in a shopping cart (trivially reversible) is different from "delete account" (high stakes). Always provide action context.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent cannot detect focus traps in rendered interfaces without accessibility tooling.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always pair agent audit with axe-core or pa11y run. Agent identifies structural absence of controls from descriptions; actual keyboard navigation testing requires browser tooling.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Assuming undo/cancel implementation decisions are within agent scope.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Undo/cancel implementation decisions require engineering sign-off; agent audit identifies the need, not the implementation approach. Undo architecture depends on backend patterns that require engineering judgment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting agent recommendation of confirmation dialogs without review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent may recommend confirmation dialogs for actions where the better solution is undo (more modern, less disruptive); review recommendations against the undo-vs-confirmation heuristic.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Trusting agent verification of keyboard shortcuts without browser testing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Keyboard shortcut verification (Escape, Ctrl+Z) requires live browser testing; agent cannot substitute for Playwright or manual keyboard navigation checks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
