<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-cadence" title="Continuous Discovery Cadence: Three Loops and Capacity Rules">
  <summary>Three operating loops (daily, weekly, sprint) for integrating discovery into normal delivery rhythm, with capacity rules and leakage detection.</summary>

  <section title="Three Discovery Loops">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run three loops in parallel: daily behaviour-watcher (analytics diffs, anomaly digests), weekly interview cycle with repository tagging, sprint-cadence opportunity-mapper updating the opportunity-solution tree.</statement>
      <rationale>Each loop captures a different signal type at the right frequency. Collapsing all three into one weekly meeting misses fast behavioural signals and buries slow qualitative ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Daily loop output: route digests to humans only on threshold breaches, not on every metric movement. Continuous monitoring produces alert fatigue without threshold gates.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents running 24/7 without threshold gates flood teams with noise, causing discovery fatigue that mirrors the problem it was meant to solve.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Capacity Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Allocate 15-20% of team capacity to discovery every sprint. Ship at least one experiment per sprint, even small ones. Cadence beats perfection.</statement>
      <rationale>Discovery allocated to "leftover time" is the first thing cut when delivery pressure rises. Hard capacity allocation makes it visible in sprint planning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Research Repository">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every interview snippet to an opportunity in a single repository. Without tagging, continuous discovery is continuous chatter. Maintain a rolling participant panel of 30-50 users with rotation to prevent sample bias.</statement>
      <rationale>The same lesson "rediscovered" quarterly is a sign of a discovery practice with no memory. A tagged repository converts recurring insight cost into a one-time investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Combine at least two signal types per discovery theme: interview data alone, behavioural data alone, or support tickets alone are insufficient triangulation.</statement>
      <rationale>Users say one thing and do another. Single-source discovery over-indexes on expressed rather than revealed preference.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Leakage Check">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every shipped feature must be traceable to a tagged opportunity in the research repository. Leakage (shipped features with no linked opportunity) above 30% signals delivery has decoupled from discovery.</statement>
      <rationale>High leakage means the team is building based on internal opinion rather than discovered user need, negating the investment in continuous discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/check-leakage.py">Python script that computes leakage ratio and exits non-zero above 30%.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Triangulation Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Hold a monthly "what changed in user behaviour" review using analytics diffs, not anecdotes. Compare against trailing 4 weeks, not last 7 days, to filter seasonality.</statement>
      <rationale>7-day comparisons trigger false anomalies on weekends and holidays. Trailing 4-week baseline absorbs normal weekly patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-antipatterns.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
