<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="continuous-discovery Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for continuous-discovery as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery theatre: weekly interviews held but never tied back to decisions. The cadence tracks attendance, not impact.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Discovery that generates insights nobody acts on wastes researcher time and erodes team confidence in the practice. Require each interview cycle to produce at least one tagged opportunity or a documented null result.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Same 5 power users interviewed every week, producing a confirmation chamber.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Power users are not representative users. Their advanced usage patterns actively mislead feature prioritization. Rotate the participant panel on a fixed schedule.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Discovery and delivery teams operating as separate units: discovery becomes a wishlist generator nobody implements.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Discovery findings must map directly to the team that makes build decisions. Separate org structures create a handoff gap where insights are filtered by priority politics.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Synthesis agent over-summarises: many distinct interview quotes collapse into 2-3 generic themes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generic themes lose actionable signal. Set a minimum number of distinct themes and require evidence count per theme before accepting synthesis output.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Sentiment classifier reports high confidence on small samples (n less than 15).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Statistical significance requires sufficient sample size. Refuse confidence above 0.8 below n=15 and flag sample size in all synthesis output.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents recommend "schedule more interviews" as the remedy for any gap in understanding.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Interviews are expensive. Behavioural data and support ticket analysis should be the first resort; interviews are the escalation path when data is ambiguous.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent pushes interview transcripts with interviewee names to shared repositories without redaction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>PII leakage via research tools is a trust and legal risk. Add a scrubber step before any transcript touches an external repo.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
