<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Fixed-Price Three-Point Estimation Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules turn the generic PERT formula into a defensible outsource fixed-price bid. Every number is anchored, every assumption is recorded, every risk reserve is disclosed.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every WBS leaf carries three estimates in senior-developer hours: O (optimistic, "best case, no surprises"), M (most likely, "what we'd actually expect"), P (pessimistic, "everything that can go wrong, did"). Each leaf has a one-line anchor citing the comparable past task or evidence basis; leaves without an anchor are rejected as fabricated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Three-point recipe tuned to outsource vendor economics">Estimates without a comparable past task are wishful thinking. Anchoring to senior-dev historical actuals is the only way the buyer's procurement team can probe the number and find it defensible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An AI-agent productivity factor is applied at the WBS-leaf level, not at the project total. Tasks that are AI-amplifiable (boilerplate, codegen, test-scaffolding) get factor 0.4-0.7 on M; tasks that are AI-resistant (novel architecture, regulated integrations, debugging production incidents) get factor 1.0. The factor for each leaf is recorded with a one-line justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="AI-agent productivity factor in vendor bids">A single project-level "20% AI discount" hides the truth: AI accelerates some categories of work dramatically and others not at all. Leaf-level factoring lets the bid honestly reflect mixed scope and survives the buyer asking "where did the AI savings come from?".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Risk reserves are calculated separately from O/M/P, not blended into P. Each leaf is tagged with categorical risk loadings: integration_unknown (5-15%), regulatory_scope_change (10-25%), third-party_dependency_lag (5-10%), client_decision_latency (5-20%). The reserve is summed and presented as a single line item alongside the bid, never hidden inside leaf estimates.</statement>
      <rationale source="Vendor risk reserves must be auditable, not buried">When risk loading is folded into P, the buyer can't separate "the work is genuinely uncertain" from "the vendor is padding". Disclosing the reserve line wins trust and creates room for negotiated descope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Monte Carlo simulation runs at least 10,000 iterations with a triangular or PERT-beta distribution per leaf, recording the project-cost CDF. The bid is set at the P85 of the simulation, not the sum of M or the sum of P. The histogram and CDF are stored with the bid and shown to the internal approver before submission.</statement>
      <rationale source="Three-point + Monte Carlo recipe">P85 is the empirically defensible point: roughly 1-in-6 odds of overrun, which matches a healthy vendor risk appetite. Summing M underbids consistently; summing P overbids and loses every competitive deal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The bid converts senior-dev hours to price using a loaded hourly rate that explicitly separates: direct cost (senior-dev loaded), overhead multiplier, target margin, and risk reserve. The four components are visible to the internal approver and to the negotiation team. The customer-facing price collapses them, but the internal record keeps them disjoint for post-mortem analysis after delivery.</statement>
      <rationale source="Senior dev hourly economics in fixed-price bids">When the four price components are blended into one number, no one can learn from the bid post-mortem: was margin eroded, was overhead under-counted, did the reserve absorb a real risk, or did scope grow? Keeping them disjoint is the only way to improve the next bid.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical example">
    <example type="good" title="Bid sheet for a 14-week outsource integration project">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
WBS leaf "OAuth migration to client SSO":
  O = 24h  M = 56h  P = 120h
  anchor: "comparable to Project Q3-2025 OAuth-to-Azure-AD migration (62h actual)"
  AI factor: 0.7 (codegen for token handlers AI-amplifiable; SSO config not)
  Risk loadings: integration_unknown 10%, client_decision_latency 15%

WBS leaf "PCI-DSS scope review":
  O = 16h  M = 32h  P = 80h
  anchor: "AcmeCo 2024 scope review took 36h with similar card surface"
  AI factor: 1.0 (regulated, not amplifiable)
  Risk loadings: regulatory_scope_change 20%

Simulation (10k iters, PERT-beta):
  Project cost p50 = €68k
  Project cost p85 = €92k   ← bid set here
  Project cost p99 = €124k

Internal pricing breakdown:
  Direct (senior-dev loaded €110/h × hours)     €58k
  Overhead multiplier (1.35)                    €20k
  Target margin (15% on direct+overhead)        €12k
  Disclosed risk reserve                         €8k
  ────────────────────────────────────────────
  Customer-facing bid                           €98k

Submitted document shows:
  "Bid €98,000 fixed, including €8,000 disclosed risk reserve.
   Reserve unspent at handover is credited back as 50/50 split per MSA §7."
]]></code>
      <note>The buyer sees a single price; procurement gets the reserve disclosure; the vendor's internal team keeps the four components disjoint for post-delivery learning.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
