<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="pricing-research">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Determine optimal pricing by anchoring on value delivered, analyzing competitors, and using Van Westendorp method with N≥30 customer research to design 3-tier structures.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>pricing</tag>
      <tag>pricing-strategy</tag>
      <tag>value-based-pricing</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>customer-research</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Pricing Research</title>

    <summary>A methodology for determining optimal pricing by combining value-capture math, competitor analysis, Van Westendorp willingness-to-pay research, and tier design. The rule: anchor on value delivered first (target 10-20% capture rate), map the competitive field, validate with customer research (N≥30 for statistical significance), then design 2-3 tiers with a clear anchor, main revenue tier, and entry option.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Pricing set by gut feel or competitor copying leads to chronic underpricing (leaving revenue on the table) or overpricing (losing customers). Value-based anchoring prevents the commodity race-to-the-bottom. The Van Westendorp method produces an empirically grounded acceptable price range rather than a single guess. Three tiers with a 2-3x jump between them exploit anchoring psychology to direct most customers to the mid-tier.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch: setting initial price for a SaaS, course, template pack, or service.</item>
        <item>Re-pricing: revenue-per-customer is below 10% of value delivered.</item>
        <item>Designing a new tier (Pro / Enterprise) on top of an existing plan.</item>
        <item>Choosing between subscription, usage-based, one-time, or hybrid models.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Fewer than 10 paying customers — insufficient signal; use competitor anchor + intuition and iterate.</item>
        <item>Highly bespoke enterprise sales where price is negotiated per deal.</item>
        <item>Marketplace or two-sided platforms where take-rate dynamics dominate.</item>
        <item>Regulated pricing (healthcare, energy, telecom) where compliance frameworks apply instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="value-and-models">
      <p>How to quantify value delivered, apply the value-capture formula, select the right pricing model, and benchmark against competitors.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Quantify value delivered before looking at competitor prices; anchor on value to prevent pricing in a race to the bottom.</statement>
        <rationale>Competitor-anchored pricing is a commodity strategy. Value-based anchoring reveals how much more or less than the market your product justifies.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the value-capture formula: Max Price = (Value Delivered x Capture Rate) - Switching Cost. Typical capture rate: 10-20% for enabling tools, 30-50% for revenue-generating tools.</statement>
        <rationale>The 10-20% rule is folklore — not a calibrated number. High-leverage revenue-generating tools capture much more. Use the formula as a floor, not a ceiling.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Value quantification example">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Tool saves 5 hours/week
User time value: $50/hour
Monthly value: 5 x $50 x 4 = $1,000/month
Capture 10%: $100/month max price
Capture 20%: $200/month max price]]></code>
      </example>

      <p>Value types to quantify:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Time saved — hours per week x hourly rate x 4 weeks.</item>
        <item>Money saved — direct cost reduction per month.</item>
        <item>Money earned — new revenue enabled per month.</item>
        <item>Risk reduced — estimated cost of prevented problems.</item>
        <item>Quality improved — cost of doing this worse without the tool.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Choose the pricing model that scales with the customer's value consumption; subscription for ongoing use, usage-based for variable consumption, one-time for discrete deliverables.</statement>
        <rationale>Misaligned pricing models create friction at renewal. Customers who use a subscription product only once per quarter will churn; usage-based retains them.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Pricing model options:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Subscription — best for sticky ongoing-value tools (most SaaS).</item>
        <item>One-time — best for discrete deliverables: courses, templates, guides.</item>
        <item>Usage-based — best for variable consumption: API calls, storage, seats added.</item>
        <item>Freemium — best for PLG products where network effects or viral spread matters.</item>
        <item>Tiered — best when customer segments have clearly different needs and budgets.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Build a pricing matrix for at least 5 competitors with entry, mid, and pro tier prices and feature gating before finalizing your own structure.</statement>
        <rationale>The competitive context sets customer expectations and defines what "normal" looks like in the market. Pricing outside the range requires explicit positioning justification.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Passing a single scraped pricing page snapshot to an analyzer agent and treating it as current.</description>
        <reason>Competitor pricing is A/B tested per visitor and changes frequently. Always pass freshly-scraped HTML; stale data misprices the product.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="tiers-and-validation">
      <p>Rules for designing pricing tiers, the Van Westendorp willingness-to-pay method, validation approaches, and antipatterns in tier construction.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Design 3 tiers: entry (low-friction acquisition), pro (main revenue target), enterprise (anchor at top). The middle tier should be where you want most customers.</statement>
        <rationale>Three options exploit anchoring psychology. The top tier makes the mid-tier look reasonable; the bottom tier captures price-sensitive leads who upgrade over time.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Price jumps between tiers should be 2-3x; each tier needs one compelling "must-have" feature unavailable in the tier below.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a clear differentiator, customers stay on the lowest tier. The 2-3x jump is a rough guideline — test your specific market. For solopreneur SaaS, $9/$19/$39 often outperforms $9/$27/$81.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Always offer annual pricing at 16-20% discount; never omit annual for products targeting retention over acquisition.</statement>
        <rationale>Annual plans halve churn and improve cash flow. Customers who pay annually are more invested and use the product more.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding a "Custom / Enterprise" tier to the public pricing page without any enterprise customers.</description>
        <reason>It signals unachieved scale. Enterprise prospects see it and call; you have no process for them. Add this tier when you have actual enterprise sales motion.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule>
        <statement>Ask the 4 Van Westendorp questions with at least 30 same-segment respondents before quoting an "optimal price".</statement>
        <rationale>Below N=30, the intersection point is noise. Agents compute 4-decimal-place "optimal prices" from N=5 interviews — reject these results explicitly.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>The 4 Van Westendorp questions:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Q1: "At what price would this be too expensive to consider?" (Too Expensive)</item>
        <item>Q2: "At what price would this be expensive but worth considering?" (Expensive)</item>
        <item>Q3: "At what price would this be a good deal?" (Cheap)</item>
        <item>Q4: "At what price would this be too cheap to trust?" (Too Cheap)</item>
      </list>

      <p>Optimal price = intersection of "Too Cheap" and "Too Expensive" curves. Acceptable range = between "Cheap" and "Expensive".</p>

      <p>Validation methods:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch pricing page — measure clicks and signups by tier before building.</item>
        <item>A/B test prices — different cohorts; measure conversion; require statistical significance before concluding.</item>
        <item>Launch at higher price — easier to discount than to raise prices later.</item>
        <item>Grandfather pricing — keep early adopters at original price when raising; goodwill outweighs marginal revenue from churn.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Any price change greater than 15% requires human review before publishing; automated repricing can cause customer-trust damage that surveys won't predict.</statement>
        <rationale>Price anchoring is a psychological contract. Breaking it without communication generates churn and negative word-of-mouth that outweighs revenue gain.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-workflow-and-gotchas">
      <p>Run as a 4-stage pipeline. Stage 1 (haiku): scrape the pricing matrix for ≥5 competitors (entry/mid/pro) plus their feature gating. Stage 2 (sonnet): compute value-capture math from the founder's value claims; flag if capture &gt; 25% (probably overpriced) or &lt; 5% (underpriced). Stage 3 (sonnet): design 3 candidate tier structures and label psychology (anchor, decoy, growth-path). Stage 4 (opus): write a Pricing Research Report with confidence level + a validation plan (A/B test, pricing-page intent, customer-development calls). Founder picks the launch price.</p>

      <p>Failure modes and gotchas:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Van Westendorp requires N ≥ 30 same-segment respondents to be statistically meaningful. Agents quote "Optimal price = $X" from N=5 interviews — that's noise, not signal.</item>
        <item>"10-20% of value delivered" capture rate is industry-folklore, not a calibrated number. Anchoring there can leave 50%+ on the table for high-leverage tools.</item>
        <item>Competitor pricing pages are increasingly opaque ("Contact us") or A/B tested per visitor. Agents that scrape once get a stale snapshot.</item>
        <item>The "2-3x price jump between tiers" rule fails for low-priced solopreneur SaaS (e.g., $9 → $19 → $39 outperforms $9 → $27 → $81).</item>
        <item>Annual discount math (~17% for "2 months free") cannibalizes monthly cohort if billing is not gated behind a clear upgrade event.</item>
        <item>Pricing-page A/B tests have huge variance; agents conclude "price X wins" from non-significant lifts.</item>
        <item>LLMs trained on 2022 data quote stale competitor prices. Always pass freshly-scraped HTML into the analyzer agent.</item>
        <item>Agents will happily compute Van Westendorp on N=4 responses and quote a 4-decimal-place "optimal price". Reject results below N=30 with explicit error.</item>
        <item>Capture-rate of "10-20%" is repeated as if it's a law. It's not — high-leverage tools (revenue-generators) capture 30-50%+ in practice.</item>
        <item>LLM-generated tier features tend to be vague ("priority support", "advanced analytics"). Force a specific feature list with measurable units.</item>
        <item>"Decoy" tiers should be designed deliberately, not as an afterthought. Agents pad the top tier with random features; require explicit rationale.</item>
        <item>Annual-discount math: agents say "12 months for the price of 10 = 17% off" but charge 16.7% — bias toward the cleaner 20%.</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint: any price change > 15% should be reviewed before publishing — automated reprice can cause customer-trust damage that survey data won't predict.</item>
        <item>Currency / locale: agents default to USD. International pricing requires PPP adjustment and local-tax handling (VAT, GST) — flag explicitly.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Best practices:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Anchor on value before competitors. Competitor-anchored pricing is a race to the bottom in commodity categories.</item>
        <item>Charge in the currency / units that scale with the customer's value (per-seat for collaboration, per-event for analytics, per-GB for storage).</item>
        <item>Always offer annual at ~16-20% discount — it improves cash flow and halves churn on average.</item>
        <item>Three tiers is the sweet spot: anchor (decoy at top), main (where you want most customers), entry (low-friction acquisition).</item>
        <item>Don't include the 4th "Custom" tier on the public page if you have no enterprise customers yet — it signals scale you don't have.</item>
        <item>Re-validate every 6 months. Markets shift; AI-augmented competitors compress prices fast.</item>
        <item>Grandfather existing customers when raising prices. Public goodwill > marginal revenue from churn.</item>
        <item>Test pricing-page copy more than the price itself — value framing typically moves conversion more than the dollar number within ±20%.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pricing-research-report.md" purpose="Full report template: value analysis, competitor matrix, customer research, recommended structure, validation plan."/>
      <template path="templates/quick-pricing-check.md" purpose="Lightweight 1-page pricing check: competitor benchmark, value estimate, customer feedback, recommendation."/>
      <template path="templates/van-westendorp.py" purpose="Python script: reads CSV of 4-question survey responses, outputs optimal price point and indifference price."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.priceintelligently.com/blog"/>
      <link href="https://www.profitwell.com/recur/all/pricing-strategy"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Westendorp%27s_Price_Sensitivity_Meter"/>
      <link href="https://hbr.org/2018/06/a-quick-guide-to-value-based-pricing"/>
      <link href="https://stripe.com/guides/atlas/pricing"/>
      <link href="https://docs.posthog.com/experiments/manual"/>
      <link href="https://www.openviewpartners.com/expansion-saas-benchmarks/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
