<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Topical Authority Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Topical Authority application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-pillar-and-clusters" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Structure content as topic clusters: one pillar page (broad overview of the topic) supported by 8-30 cluster articles (specific subtopics). The pillar MUST link to every cluster; every cluster MUST link back to the pillar. Missing bidirectional wiring is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">Google's helpful-content and semantic-relevance systems assess topical coverage; a cluster of 10-30 interlinking articles signals deeper expertise than one highly-optimised page. AI Overviews preferentially cite recognised topical authorities.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-comprehensive-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each cluster article MUST answer all PAA questions for its subtopic, cover ≥1 edge case competitors miss, and be refreshed every ≤6 months. Articles that repeat what the pillar already covers without adding depth are rejected as cluster-dilution.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">Google's helpful-content evaluation rewards content that fully satisfies user intent; thin clusters dilute rather than amplify authority.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-anchor-text-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Link from each cluster article back to the pillar AND to 2-4 related clusters using keyword-rich, descriptive anchor text. Bare "click here" / "this article" anchors are rejected; over-optimised exact-match anchors on external links are also rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">Anchor text reinforces keyword relevance internally without the manipulation risk that triggers external-link penalties; lazy anchors waste a free signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-entity-coverage-matrix" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The topic-map MUST list the entities (people, products, concepts, places) extracted from the top-10 SERP titles + H2s for the head term, tagged with `mention_count`. Cluster articles collectively MUST cover every entity with `mention_count ≥ 4`. Entity gaps are tracked as a deliberate backlog, not silently skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">Entity coverage is the strongest correlate of topical relevance scoring; missing high-frequency entities is the single biggest reason a cluster ranks below the top-10.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-named-cadence-and-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The topic-map artefact MUST name a single owner who publishes on a stated cadence (e.g. 2 articles / week for 12 weeks). Cadence + owner are part of the artefact; "we'll see how it goes" cadences are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source 2026-05-20">Topical authority compounds slowly; without a committed cadence the cluster ships incomplete and the authority signal never accumulates.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
