<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Partner Swap Deal Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Partner Swap Deal Template MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="adjacent-not-competing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Swap partners MUST be in adjacent (not competing) specialties. Same-specialty swaps are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Freelancer swap-deal audit 2025">Same-specialty swaps collapse on every overlap; trust erodes; deals break in 6 months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="fee-split-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST name fee-split policy (referral fee X%, finders fee flat $, or none — symbolic only). Implicit splits cause disputes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal swap-deal debrief data">Implicit fee handling generates 60% of swap-deal disputes; explicit terms avoid it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="conflict-of-interest-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST define what happens when both partners want the same client (first-touch wins, joint pitch, decline). Un-defined conflicts kill deals.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene — partnership deals">Conflict-of-interest moments determine whether the deal survives or breaks; defined rules survive them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="scope-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST name in-scope referral types (vertical, stack, budget band). Out-of-scope swaps create noise and reciprocity guilt.</statement>
      <rationale source="Swap-deal audit 2025">Generic 'send anyone' swaps generate misfit referrals; named scope filters at the source.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="annual-audit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deal MUST be audited annually (swap count, win-rate, fee-split balance). Indefinite deals without audit lose trust quietly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational hygiene — partnership deals">Audits surface drift early; renegotiations are easier than breakups.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
