<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-brand-audit" title="Employer Brand Audit Framework">
  <summary>Perception-vs-reality audit process using Glassdoor, LinkedIn, candidate surveys, and exit interviews.</summary>

  <section title="Audit inputs">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run brand audits annually at minimum. A gap greater than 1.0 on a 5-point scale between internal perception (employee surveys) and external perception (Glassdoor/Comparably) signals repositioning is needed.</statement>
      <rationale>A large perception gap means either the EVP over-promises (candidates arrive disappointed) or the brand under-communicates genuine strengths (missed talent).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Glassdoor: overall rating, review themes (pros/cons frequency), response rate trend.</item>
      <item>LinkedIn: follower growth rate, organic post engagement, career page conversion rate.</item>
      <item>Candidate surveys: post-interview NPS, "why declined" categories, source attribution.</item>
      <item>Employee surveys: eNPS, top-ranked EVP pillars vs. bottom-ranked, open-text themes.</item>
      <item>Exit interviews: top 3 stated reasons for leaving, manager-specific patterns.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Competitor benchmarking">
    <rule>
      <statement>Compare each EVP pillar against 3-5 direct talent competitors. Identify where you lead, where you are table-stakes, and where you trail — and never claim leadership where you trail.</statement>
      <rationale>Candidates research employers on Glassdoor and LinkedIn before applying. Positioning claims that contradict visible competitor data undermine recruiter credibility in screening calls.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Glassdoor response protocol">
    <rule>
      <statement>Respond to every Glassdoor review within 48 hours, including positive ones. Cap responses at 80 words. Never use "We are committed to..." Never dispute employee experience; only describe actions taken or planned.</statement>
      <rationale>Over-defensive responses go viral and amplify negative reviews. Responses that dispute employee perception demonstrate the exact culture problems reviewers described.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-publishing Glassdoor responses without human approval.</description>
      <reason>Agent-generated responses that contradict employee experience or sound legalistic create PR incidents that are harder to recover from than the original review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/glassdoor-response.txt">Response structure for Glassdoor reviews: acknowledge, describe action, 80-word cap.</reference>
</text>
