<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Employer Branding Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every employer-branding artefact (audit, content calendar, testimonial, review response) must satisfy before external publication.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-trace-to-evp-pillar" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every external-facing brand asset (LinkedIn post, careers page block, testimonial, ad) MUST name exactly one EVP pillar (Compensation, Benefits, Career, Work Environment, or Culture/Purpose) and link to the proof points behind it. Assets that do not name a pillar are rejected at review.</statement>
      <rationale source="EVP-anchored brand discipline">Untraced assets become "vibe" copy that contradicts hiring conversations and offer letters; pillar-anchoring forces consistency between brand and EVP and gives recruiters a citation when candidates question a claim.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-named-quote-attribution" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Employee testimonials MUST be attributed to a named human (first name + role + tenure band) and carry a written consent record. Anonymous or fabricated quotes are rejected; "an engineer said …" without a record is treated as fabrication.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brand-integrity / employment law">Anonymous testimonials are presumed manufactured by readers and frequently violate consent policies; named attribution is both the integrity check and the legal record.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-unverified-placeholder-for-dei" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Diversity, compensation-band, and retention statistics MUST be supplied by HRIS-sourced data; if unavailable at draft time, insert the literal token "UNVERIFIED" so a human fills it from HRIS before publication. Agents must NEVER synthesize these numbers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reputation + legal risk control">Synthesized DEI / pay numbers create reputation incidents the moment an employee contradicts them; the UNVERIFIED placeholder is fail-loud and forces the human checkpoint.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-48h-review-response-sla" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Glassdoor, Indeed, and Comparably reviews MUST receive a drafted response within 48 hours of posting. The draft is reviewed by the named brand owner before posting; responses that breach the SLA are flagged in the weekly brand metrics report.</statement>
      <rationale source="Crisis-prevention practice">Unanswered reviews compound; a brand that responds within 48h is read as engaged regardless of star rating, while silence is read as confirmation. Tracking the SLA in metrics keeps drift visible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-cliche-strip-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A post-pass MUST strip generic clichés ("innovative", "passionate", "fast-paced", "world-class", "rockstar", "ninja") from every draft asset. Assets shipping with banned tokens are returned for rewrite.</statement>
      <rationale source="Editorial signal-density">LLM-default phrases add word count without signal and are the most common reason candidates label brand copy "corporate speak"; the strip-pass is mechanical and removes the lowest-quality copy without human time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies-If preconditions fail OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or to no methodology at all).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application of a methodology produces worse artefacts than no methodology at all because downstream consumers trust the schema and act on bad data. The skip-record makes the non-application traceable so future audits can detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
