<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-content-strategy" title="Employer Brand Content Strategy">
  <summary>Content calendar structure, channel-specific voice rules, and employee testimonial intake pipeline.</summary>

  <section title="Content calendar structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Rotate four content types in a 4-week repeating cycle: employee spotlight, behind-the-scenes, culture moment, job opening promo. Every slot must trace back to a named EVP pillar.</statement>
      <rationale>Mechanical calendars without novelty injection decay after 4-6 weeks of engagement. The 4-type rotation balances brand-building with hiring intent and gives the algorithm enough variety to avoid suppression.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Week 1: Employee spotlight (LinkedIn) — personal story tied to Growth or Purpose pillar.</item>
      <item>Week 2: Behind-the-scenes (Instagram/video) — ≤90s, culture moment in action.</item>
      <item>Week 3: Culture moment (LinkedIn long-form) — ≤300 words, specific event or milestone.</item>
      <item>Week 4: Open role promo (LinkedIn + Indeed) — paired with "what we're building" context post.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Channel-specific voice rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use the same post copy across channels. LinkedIn requires professional framing; Instagram requires visual-first brevity; careers blog allows long-form authenticity.</statement>
      <rationale>Channel voice mismatch produces flat copy that is suppressed by algorithms and dismissed by audiences. The same text on LinkedIn and TikTok will underperform on both.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap LinkedIn hashtags at 3-5 per post. Never stuff more than 5.</statement>
      <rationale>LinkedIn best practice is 3-5 hashtags; more signals low-quality content and suppresses organic reach.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Testimonial intake pipeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every employee testimonial must have a signed consent form and image release before publication. Use DRAFT-only status with [NAME] [TITLE] tokens until consent is captured and confirmed.</statement>
      <rationale>Publishing testimonials without consent exposes employees and the company to legal liability. Agents must never auto-publish; always require explicit human confirmation that consent is on file.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require employee-supplied raw quotes before drafting testimonials. Never synthesize quotes from job-offer letters, LinkedIn profiles, or performance reviews.</statement>
      <rationale>AI-generated testimonials that were not said by real employees are ethically indefensible and legally risky if used in candidate-facing materials.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Repurposing one testimonial format across all channels without adaptation.</description>
      <reason>A 300-word LinkedIn testimonial becomes unreadable on Instagram; a 30-second video quote loses context in a blog post. Repurpose with channel-specific editing, not copy-paste.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/content-calendar.md">4-week brand content plan with per-slot hook, body, CTA, asset brief.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/testimonial-brief.md">Employee testimonial intake: raw quote fields, consent checklist, approval flow.</reference>
</text>
