<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules-and-gotchas" title="Employer Branding Agent Rules">
  <summary>Human-approval gates, ToS constraints, and antipatterns for employer branding agent workflows.</summary>

  <section title="Human-approval gates">
    <rule>
      <statement>Any external publication — LinkedIn post, Glassdoor response, Instagram content, blog post — requires human approval before publish. Agents draft; humans approve and post.</statement>
      <rationale>Brand voice drift, DEI misrepresentation, and legally risky compensation claims are impossible to fully prevent at generation time. The approval gate is the only reliable safeguard.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>DEI claims (diversity percentages, ERG names, inclusion programs) must be sourced from HRIS data, not synthesized. Every DEI claim in a draft must have a data citation or be marked UNVERIFIED.</statement>
      <rationale>Invented diversity statistics are a serious legal and reputational risk. Candidates and journalists verify claims; inaccurate statistics cause brand damage that exceeds the original benefit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="ToS and legal constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not scrape Glassdoor or Indeed without their official API (Glassdoor for Employers tier). Automated scraping without API access violates ToS and can result in employer account suspension.</statement>
      <rationale>A suspended employer account on Glassdoor removes all company review responses and brand profile, causing permanent brand damage that exceeds the value of scraped data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Cliché injection in every brand draft: "passionate team," "world-class culture," "amazing people."</description>
      <reason>These phrases appear on 90%+ of employer brand pages and provide zero differentiation. They train candidates to ignore the content.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generating fake employee names or composite quotes when raw material is missing.</description>
      <reason>Fabricated employee voices are unethical and constitute false advertising in candidate-facing materials. Always require real employee input before drafting.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Brand voice drift across 50+ content generations without re-anchoring.</description>
      <reason>Agents drift from the established voice even when the brand guide is in context. Include 3 approved sample posts in every content generation prompt to re-anchor tone.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
