<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="change-control">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Formal process evaluating proposed changes to scope, schedule, cost, or quality. Requires written CR with impact analysis, tiered authority matrix, and register tracking all requests.</summary>
    <category>change</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>change-control</tag>
      <tag>scope</tag>
      <tag>ccb</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
    </tags>
    <related>
      <ref slug="earned-value-management"/>
      <ref slug="scope-management"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Change Control</title>

    <summary>Change control is the formal process that evaluates every proposed change to scope, schedule, cost, or quality against the approved baseline before any work begins. It requires a written change request with impact analysis, a tiered decision-authority matrix, and a register that tracks both approved and rejected requests — because rejected requests that resurface three times are real requirements signals.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Uncontrolled changes are the mechanism by which scope creep destroys budgets. "Small" changes bypass analysis and accumulate silently. A formal process makes every change visible, analyzes its cost before commitment, and creates an audit trail. Bundling minor changes weekly prevents bureaucratic overhead while maintaining control.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Fixed-bid or fixed-scope contracts where every change has billing implications.</item>
        <item>Multi-stakeholder programs with a Change Control Board (CCB) and tiered authority.</item>
        <item>Regulated work (medical, finance, government) where audit trail of approved changes is mandatory.</item>
        <item>Any project where scope creep cost more than 15% of original budget on prior runs.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure agile sprints with an empowered Product Owner — backlog reordering replaces CR ceremony.</item>
        <item>Internal tools or R&amp;D where changes are the work.</item>
        <item>Solo projects — apply a lightweight CHANGES.md instead.</item>
        <item>Phases before the scope baseline is signed off — there is nothing to "change" yet.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="step1-receive-and-log">
      <rule>
        <statement>Capture every change request in writing with a unique ID before any analysis or work begins; verbal requests are not change requests.</statement>
        <rationale>Undocumented changes become disputed scope — the requester remembers agreement, the team remembers refusal, and neither has evidence. A CR ID creates a paper trail from the moment of request.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Required fields at receipt: requester name and role, date submitted, plain-language description of the change, business justification, and urgency.</p>
      <p>CR status lifecycle: Submitted → Under Review → Approved / Rejected / Deferred → Implemented (if approved) → Closed.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step2-impact-analysis">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every impact analysis must include a "do nothing" option; omitting it prevents the explicit cost-of-inaction reasoning that justifies or rejects the change.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a baseline option, decision makers compare change variants against each other rather than against the status quo, which inflates the perceived value of every change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Impact areas to assess for every CR:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Scope — which features or WBS elements are affected.</item>
        <item>Schedule — additional days; which milestones move.</item>
        <item>Cost — additional budget; which line items are affected.</item>
        <item>Quality — impact on standards, testing, technical debt.</item>
        <item>Risk — new risks introduced; existing risks affected.</item>
        <item>Resources — who must work on it; opportunity cost to other work.</item>
        <item>Test impact — regression and integration testing required (explicitly, not bundled into "Quality").</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="step3-decision-with-tiered-authority">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define decision-authority thresholds in writing at kickoff, post them publicly, and do not revise them without sponsor agreement; thresholds that drift upward make every change a "minor" change.</statement>
        <rationale>Without written thresholds, PMs informally expand their own authority over time ("it's only 2 days, I'll approve it myself"), which bypasses the sponsor and sponsor approval stops being meaningful.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Minor (e.g., less than 1 day, less than $500) — PM approves.</item>
        <item>Medium (e.g., 1-5 days, $500-$5,000) — Sponsor approves.</item>
        <item>Major (e.g., more than 5 days, more than $5,000) — CCB approves.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Bundle minor CRs into a weekly "minor changes" approval batch to maintain cadence without per-request ceremony; present the aggregate schedule and cost impact, not individual items.</statement>
        <rationale>Per-item approval for minor changes produces either rubber-stamping (no real bar) or approval fatigue; aggregate presentation makes the cumulative cost visible and triggers escalation when it crosses a threshold.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step4-implement-and-close">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tie every approved CR to a baseline-update commit (WBS, schedule, budget) in the same PR; scope changes without corresponding document updates create drift between the plan and the baseline.</statement>
        <rationale>A CR logged as "approved" but not reflected in the scope baseline and schedule produces a team working to the new scope while reporting against the old baseline — a measurement error masquerading as performance.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="rejected-cr-intelligence">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track rejected CRs with reason codes; the same request appearing three or more times is a real requirements signal that the scope statement missed something important.</statement>
        <rationale>Repeated rejections signal a stakeholder need that the current baseline does not address; ignoring the pattern leads to workarounds, shadow implementations, or post-launch demands that cost more than addressing the need would have.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="hidden-change-detection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Review merged PRs weekly against the current scope baseline to detect developer-driven scope additions that bypassed the CR process.</statement>
        <rationale>Gold plating and feature additions that appear in code but not in any CR are invisible to the change register; they consume budget, add untested scope, and may fail acceptance.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating developer-initiated refactors that change observable behavior as out-of-scope for change control.</description>
        <reason>Behavioral changes affect the scope baseline regardless of their technical framing; refactors that add, remove, or alter features must follow the CR process even if the developer considers them "internal" changes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-cr-workflow">
      <rule>
        <statement>The CR-drafting agent ingest free-form change requests (Slack, email, meeting notes) and normalizes them into typed CR records with WBS IDs touched and needs_clarification[] fields; humans retain decision authority and the budget veto.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent normalization removes the bottleneck of PM transcription while preserving human judgment on approval; the agent surfaces incomplete information explicitly rather than letting it hide in narrative.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>The CR agent must never transition a CR to "Approved" status; only named authority holders approve — the agent drafts, logs, and flags, never decides.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated approval removes human accountability; a CR approved by a bot has no accountable decision-maker and cannot be used as evidence in contract disputes or audits.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM-generated impact analyses that underestimate testing and regression effort by treating "test impact" as a sub-item of "quality" rather than a separate line item.</description>
        <reason>Testing effort for scope changes is typically 30-50% of implementation effort; bundling it into "quality" makes it invisible and leads to systematically undercosted CRs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="emergency-changes">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define an emergency-CR fast lane for incident-triggered changes: abbreviated impact analysis (30-minute time-box), single-approver authority, and mandatory retroactive full documentation within 24 hours.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a fast lane, teams bypass change control entirely during incidents to meet response SLAs; the fast lane maintains the audit trail while respecting the urgency.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/change-request-form.md" purpose="Structured CR form with impact analysis and options table"/>
      <template path="templates/change-register.md" purpose="Register table template with status tracking"/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/cr_drift.sh" purpose="Sums schedule/cost impact of approved CRs in a Markdown register"/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="earned-value-management"/>
      <ref slug="scope-management"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-and-standards/foundational-standards/pmbok-guide-7th-edition">PMI, PMBOK Guide 7th ed., Delivery Performance Domain — Change Management</link>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/80644.html">ISO/IEC 20000-1:2018 — Change Management process</link>
      <link href="https://www.axelos.com/certifications/itil-certifications">ITIL 4 — Change Enablement practice</link>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
