<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Risk Register Framework">
  <summary>Six-step cycle for identifying, scoring, responding to, and monitoring project risks and opportunities.</summary>

  <section title="Identification">
    <p>Brainstorm threats and opportunities across four categories: Technical (technology failures, complexity), External (vendor delays, regulation), Organizational (resource loss, priority shifts), Project Management (poor estimates, scope creep). Techniques: team brainstorming, expert interviews, checklist review, historical project analysis.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Probability Scale">
    <list>
      <item>Very Low — rare, &lt;10%</item>
      <item>Low — unlikely, 10-30%</item>
      <item>Medium — possible, 30-50%</item>
      <item>High — likely, 50-70%</item>
      <item>Very High — almost certain, &gt;70%</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Impact Scale">
    <list>
      <item>Very Low — &lt;5% budget or schedule effect</item>
      <item>Low — 5-10% effect</item>
      <item>Medium — 10-20% effect</item>
      <item>High — 20-40% effect</item>
      <item>Very High — &gt;40% or project failure</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring">
    <p>Risk Score = Probability level (1-5) x Impact level (1-5). Priority: 15-25 = High (immediate action); 8-14 = Medium (monitor closely); 1-7 = Low (periodic review).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Threat Response Strategies">
    <list>
      <item>Avoid — eliminate the threat by changing approach or removing the risky element</item>
      <item>Transfer — shift to a third party via insurance, outsourcing, or contractual clauses</item>
      <item>Mitigate — reduce probability or impact (prototype first, add testing, cross-train)</item>
      <item>Accept — acknowledge and plan contingency; requires contingency_amount or contingency_plan</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Opportunity Response Strategies">
    <list>
      <item>Exploit — ensure the opportunity occurs (assign best resources, accelerate)</item>
      <item>Share — partner with another party to capture the benefit</item>
      <item>Enhance — increase probability or impact (more marketing, better timing)</item>
      <item>Accept — take the benefit if it occurs; no special action required</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Ownership and Monitoring">
    <p>Every risk has exactly one named owner responsible for: monitoring triggers, executing the response if the trigger fires, and updating status. Review weekly: add new risks, update P/I as situation changes, close resolved risks, track response effectiveness. Top-5 risks appear at every steering committee.</p>
  </section>
</text>
