<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Risk Register Rules">
  <summary>Concrete, testable rules for producing and maintaining a valid risk register.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Every risk must have exactly one named individual as owner; "the team" is not valid.</statement>
    <rationale>Risks without a single owner are observed, not managed. Accountability requires a name.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Every trigger must be an observable signal — a metric, log event, or date — not a subjective phrase like "if it gets bad".</statement>
    <rationale>Unobservable triggers cannot be monitored; risks activate without warning.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Every Accept strategy entry must include a contingency_amount or contingency_plan field; Accept without contingency is invalid.</statement>
    <rationale>Accept without a contingency is denial dressed as a strategy. When the risk materialises there is no prepared response.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Risk score must equal probability_level x impact_level; stored score must match computed value or the register is invalid.</statement>
    <rationale>Score integrity is required for heatmap accuracy and prioritisation correctness.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Include at least one opportunity (positive risk) for every ten threats; reject registers that contain only threats.</statement>
    <rationale>Sponsor approval rates rise when upside is made visible. LLMs drop opportunities by default.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Calibrate the impact scale with a project-specific reference point (e.g. "High impact = &gt;$50k or &gt;1 month delay") before scoring.</statement>
    <rationale>Uncalibrated scales produce inconsistent scores across assessors and over time.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Risk-driven contingency (sum of probability x cost_impact per open risk) must replace flat-percentage reserves for any project with an active risk register.</statement>
    <rationale>Flat reserves systematically over- or under-fund based on risk profile; risk-driven calculation calibrates to actual exposure.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Identifying risks once at kickoff and never updating the register.</description>
    <reason>Static registers go stale within weeks; new risks appear continuously and scored risks change as context evolves.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Using "Communication breakdown" as a risk in every register.</description>
    <reason>Generic risks from LLM defaults are not project-specific; they add noise and dilute the register's signal.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Scoring more than 70% of risks as Medium/Medium (3/3).</description>
    <reason>Uniform scores indicate anchoring bias; force a roughly normal distribution across the 5x5 matrix.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
