<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-referral-programs Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-referral-programs. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default to double-sided rewards (both referrer and referee benefit); single-sided programs feel exploitative and convert 20-30% worse on the invitee side.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The invitee receiving a reward removes the psychological burden of accepting a favor and signals the program is legitimate, not just a multi-level scheme.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Size the reward at 20-50% of CAC; recompute as CAC drifts rather than fixing a round-number amount permanently.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A reward below 20% of CAC is often not motivating. Above 50%, the economics deteriorate relative to paid channels. LTV must exceed 3x CAC for a double-sided program to be sustainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ask for referrals at win moments: post-purchase, after a positive review, after a support win, at feature milestones, at subscription renewal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Satisfaction is at its peak at win moments. Users are primed to share when they have just experienced value — not on first visit, not during checkout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Provide a one-click copy link as the primary sharing mechanism; add email, social, and in-app invite as secondary options. Long referral links must be shortened.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Every extra click in the sharing flow reduces i by 10-20%. Copy-link is the highest-participation channel because it requires no authentication or form.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use deterministic fraud rules (IP overlap, payment-method match, signup velocity) rather than LLM judgment; flag candidates for human review rather than auto-banning.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs are not reliable fraud adjudicators. Deterministic feature computation is auditable and consistent; final ban decisions require a human-in-loop to avoid legal exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
