<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-design" title="Referral Program Design: Rewards, Triggers, Friction">
  <summary>How to design the reward structure, choose trigger points, and minimize sharing friction in a referral program.</summary>

  <section title="Reward Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Default to double-sided rewards (both referrer and referee benefit); single-sided programs feel exploitative and convert 20-30% worse on the invitee side.</statement>
      <rationale>The invitee receiving a reward removes the psychological burden of accepting a favor and signals the program is legitimate, not just a multi-level scheme.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Double-sided cash/credit: best for SaaS and e-commerce with high LTV</item>
      <item>Referrer-only: acceptable for very low-margin products</item>
      <item>Tiered: more referrals unlock larger rewards — drives power-user participation</item>
      <item>Product-based: free storage, free month — retains cost within product margin</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Size the reward at 20-50% of CAC; recompute as CAC drifts rather than fixing a round-number amount permanently.</statement>
      <rationale>A reward below 20% of CAC is often not motivating. Above 50%, the economics deteriorate relative to paid channels. LTV must exceed 3x CAC for a double-sided program to be sustainable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trigger Points">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ask for referrals at win moments: post-purchase, after a positive review, after a support win, at feature milestones, at subscription renewal.</statement>
      <rationale>Satisfaction is at its peak at win moments. Users are primed to share when they have just experienced value — not on first visit, not during checkout.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Do NOT ask: first visit (no relationship established)</item>
      <item>Do NOT ask: after a complaint or support escalation</item>
      <item>Do NOT ask: during the checkout flow (distracts from conversion)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Reducing Sharing Friction">
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a one-click copy link as the primary sharing mechanism; add email, social, and in-app invite as secondary options. Long referral links must be shortened.</statement>
      <rationale>Every extra click in the sharing flow reduces i by 10-20%. Copy-link is the highest-participation channel because it requires no authentication or form.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Unique link: one click to copy, short URL</item>
      <item>Email invite: pre-written message, recipient can be pasted</item>
      <item>Social share: Twitter, LinkedIn, WhatsApp buttons</item>
      <item>QR code: for physical/in-person contexts</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
