<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-referral-programs Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-referral-programs as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Fraud explosion: self-referrals, referral farms, multi-account abuse without deterministic detection rules.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents detect patterns but final ban decisions need human-in-loop. Deterministic feature computation (IP overlap, payment-method overlap, signup velocity) paired with rules-engine flags allows human review without LLM hallucination.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Mis-attribution when users clear cookies, switch devices, or use ad blockers — first-touch vs last-touch logic not explicit.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Attribution ambiguity must be resolved in writing before launch. Default to last-touch for simplicity unless you have cross-device tracking infrastructure; document the choice in every dashboard.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Reward fulfillment lag (manual credit approval) breaks the trust loop.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Requires idempotent automation. Use a unique (referrer_id, referee_id, event) key to make credit operations idempotent and reduce manual review to fraud exceptions only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Viral coefficient (K) plateaus quickly; agents over-optimizing reward size erode margin without meaningful K lift.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>K improves with friction reduction (invites/user = i) and conversion rate (c). Reward size affects only motivation; above-optimal rewards are pure expense. Focus agent optimization on cycle-time reduction and friction cuts first.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
