<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-landing-page-design">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>conversion-optimizer</domain>
    <summary>AIDA-structured landing page copy: Attention, Interest, Desire, Action. Headline: [Outcome]+[Timeframe]+[Without Pain]. Single CTA per section. Social proof below CTA increases CVR 10-15%.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>landing-pages</tag>
      <tag>copywriting</tag>
      <tag>conversion-rate</tag>
      <tag>aida</tag>
      <tag>cta-optimization</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Landing Page Design</title>

    <summary>AIDA-structured landing page copy methodology: Attention (hero captures interest in 5 seconds), Interest (benefits not features), Desire (social proof), Action (single CTA per section). Headline formula: [Outcome] + [Timeframe] + [Without Pain Point]. One primary CTA per page. Social proof placed directly below the hero CTA increases CVR by 10-15%.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Most landing pages fail by trying to do too much — multiple CTAs confuse visitors, feature focus loses customers who care about outcomes, and slow load times (over 3 seconds) cause abandonment before the page renders. The "So what?" test converts features to benefits: "AI-powered" becomes "Get answers in seconds, not hours." FAQ sections should address conversion objections ("Can I cancel anytime?"), not product questions. Numbers outperform vague claims everywhere: "40% improvement" beats "significant improvement" for click-through.</p>
      <p>The landing page is the final conversion funnel stage where messaging must be laser-focused. Each page section should have a single, clear objective: the hero has one job (grab attention and state value), the benefits section has one job (explain why the product matters), the CTA section has one job (drive action). Visitors expect to answer three core questions in the first 10 seconds: What is this? Why should I care? What do I do next? If any answer is unclear or missing, they abandon the page.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Writing multiple headline variations for A/B testing (5-10 per session).</item>
        <item>Drafting full landing page copy: hero, problem agitation, benefits, how-it-works, FAQ, final CTA.</item>
        <item>Auditing existing copy against the conversion checklist (above-fold, copy, trust, technical).</item>
        <item>Generating testimonial rewrites: transforming generic quotes into specific-result format.</item>
        <item>Applying the "So what?" test to a feature list to produce benefit copy.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Visual design and layout decisions — agent produces copy; Figma/Webflow work is separate.</item>
        <item>A/B test execution — agent writes variants but cannot run tests (use Optimizely or VWO).</item>
        <item>Page speed optimization — a technical task outside copy scope; run Lighthouse separately.</item>
        <item>Generating fake testimonials — fabricated quotes are FTC violations.</item>
        <item>Final CVR prediction — agent-estimated ranges are benchmarks, not guarantees.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="aida-structure">
      <p>Rules for each AIDA section: hero, problem agitation, solution/benefits, how-it-works, social proof, FAQ, and final CTA. The AIDA framework (Attention, Interest, Desire, Action) maps to the visitor's decision journey. Each section must smoothly transition from the previous one, building urgency and lowering friction toward the final conversion.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Hero must include: headline (6-12 words, benefit not feature), subheadline (expands with specificity), product visual, one CTA button, and a social proof line ("Trusted by X users").</statement>
        <rationale>Visitors decide in 5 seconds whether to scroll. Every missing element reduces the probability they continue. The social proof line directly below the CTA button increases CVR by 10-15%.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Headline formula: [Outcome] + [Timeframe] + [Without Pain Point]. Write 10 variations before selecting the final one.</statement>
        <rationale>The first headline written is rarely the best. Forcing 10 variations surfaces options that use more specific language and stronger benefit framing.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Headline with outcome, timeframe, and pain point removed">
        <note>Headline: "Build your SaaS in 2 weeks without writing backend code" — outcome (build SaaS), timeframe (2 weeks), without pain (no backend code).</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Generic feature-focused headline">
        <note>Headline: "The AI-Powered Platform for Modern Developers" — no outcome, no timeframe, no pain addressed. This describes what the product is, not what it does for the user.</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Testimonial formula: "[Specific result achieved] in [timeframe]. Before [product], I struggled with [problem]. Now [positive outcome]." — [Name], [Title] at [Company].</statement>
        <rationale>Generic testimonials ("Great product!") add no conversion value. Specific results with numbers and named individuals are credible and benchmarkable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Social proof effectiveness order: customer logos (B2B) > testimonials with photos > case studies > numbers ("50K users") > press mentions > ratings.</statement>
        <rationale>Logos borrow institutional credibility. Named testimonials borrow personal credibility. Anonymous numbers are least credible because they cannot be verified.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent-polished testimonials with fabricated specifics (company names, exact numbers not from the original quote).</description>
        <reason>Fabricated testimonials are FTC violations and destroy trust when discovered. Agent should format and polish real quotes, never invent specifics.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule>
        <statement>FAQ must address conversion objections, not product questions. "Can I cancel anytime?" and "Is my data secure?" convert better than "How do I import my data?"</statement>
        <rationale>At the FAQ stage, visitors are close to converting but have unresolved concerns. Answering usage questions serves existing users; answering objections serves prospects.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Repeat the main CTA with: benefit reminder, risk reversal (30-day money-back, no credit card, free trial), and urgency if appropriate.</statement>
        <rationale>Visitors who scroll to the bottom are high-intent but may have lingering hesitation. Risk reversal removes the last friction at the decision moment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/saas-page-structure.md">Full SaaS landing page section order with placeholder content for all AIDA elements</reference>
      <reference path="templates/audit-checklist.md">Conversion checklist to score above-fold, copy, trust, and technical elements</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="copy-rules">
      <p>Headline formula application, feature-to-benefit conversion test, copy quality rules, and failure modes to avoid.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the "So what?" test to every feature statement. Ask "So what?" until the answer describes a user outcome, then use that as the copy.</statement>
        <rationale>Features describe what the product does. Benefits describe what the user gets. Customers buy outcomes, not capabilities. The "So what?" chain forces outcome-focused language.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Feature-to-benefit conversion">
        <note>Feature: "AI-powered" → "So what?" → "Get answers in seconds, not hours." Feature: "99.9% uptime" → "So what?" → "Never lose a sale to downtime."</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agent must be constrained to 3 most differentiating benefits, ignoring the rest. Without this constraint, agents list all features and dilute the message.</statement>
        <rationale>A page that tries to communicate 10 benefits communicates zero. Constraint forces prioritization of the benefits that match the ICP's most urgent pain.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use numbers everywhere: "40% improvement" beats "significant improvement". "Trusted by 5,000 users" beats "trusted by thousands". Specificity is credibility.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague claims are unverifiable and dismissed by skeptical visitors. Specific numbers signal that the claim is based on measurement, not marketing.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>FAQ generation without a real list of customer objections produces questions the target audience does not actually ask. Source FAQ from support tickets and sales calls.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents will generate plausible-sounding FAQs that do not match actual conversion blockers. Real objections come from real conversations, not from inference.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Multiple CTAs on the same page section.</description>
        <reason>Multiple CTAs create decision paralysis and split attention. Each section must have one primary action. Secondary CTAs belong in the footer or nav only.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Generic hero headline that could apply to any product in the category.</description>
        <reason>Generic headlines do not differentiate the product from competitors. Specificity in the ICP pain and the outcome is required to stop the scroll.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No mobile preview before launch.</description>
        <reason>Over 50% of landing page traffic is mobile. Above-the-fold elements on mobile differ significantly from desktop. Agent audits do not catch visual layout issues on small screens.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Page load over 3 seconds.</description>
        <reason>Each second of load time past 2 seconds reduces conversion rate by approximately 4.4%. This is a technical issue (images, CDN, JS bloat), not a copy issue — run Lighthouse to identify slow resources and optimize before final page launch.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agent must receive: product name, one-sentence description, ICP definition, top 3 pain points, key benefits (not features), real social proof, and CTA goal before generating copy.</statement>
        <rationale>Without specific ICP pain language, agent copy sounds like every other SaaS landing page. The quality of the brief determines the quality of the output.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Copy quality depends entirely on input quality. A vague brief ("write a landing page for an AI tool") produces vague output. A specific brief ("We serve indie developers who build AI agents. Their pain: spending 3 weeks on prompt engineering that becomes technical debt. Our benefit: templates that keep prompts maintainable. Social proof: used by 500+ developers at Y Combinator companies. CTA: start free trial") produces a landing page that converts because every sentence addresses a specific audience pain in their language.</p>

      <p>The testimonial section deserves particular attention because it bridges between product features and user outcomes. A generic testimonial ("Great product!") is a red flag that signals the real customer feedback did not exist or was too weak to use. Instead, require testimonials that follow the formula: specific result + timeframe + problem context + current state + proof point (ideally a number). Example: "Cut our API development time by 60% — spent 6 weeks on integrations before, now 2 weeks thanks to auto-generation. Already used for 12 production APIs." This works because a reader can see themselves in the same situation and predict similar results.</p>

      <reference path="templates/prompt-full-copy.txt">Agent prompt for complete AIDA landing page copy from ICP brief</reference>
      <reference path="templates/audit-score.py">Score landing page sections against conversion checklist criteria</reference>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/saas-page-structure.md" purpose="Full SaaS landing page section order with placeholder content."/>
      <template path="templates/audit-checklist.md" purpose="Above-fold, copy, trust, technical conversion checklist."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-full-copy.txt" purpose="Agent prompt: complete AIDA landing page copy from ICP brief."/>
      <template path="templates/audit-score.py" purpose="Score landing page sections against conversion checklist criteria."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.unbounce.com/landing-pages/"/>
      <link href="https://www.optimizely.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.convert.com/"/>
      <link href="https://www.vwo.com/ab-testing/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
