<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="knowledge-areas-overview">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>BABOK organizes BA into six knowledge areas. Routing index for selecting applicable areas and sub-methodologies.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>knowledge-areas</tag>
      <tag>routing</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>framework</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>BA Knowledge Areas Overview</title>

    <summary>BABOK organizes BA work into six knowledge areas. This routing index answers which apply and directs to sub-methodologies.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without a framework map, BA activities appear as a random collection of tasks. Teams skip critical areas, produce inconsistent deliverables, and cannot explain which activities are appropriate for their project type. The BABOK knowledge area model provides a coherent structure that applies across waterfall, agile, and hybrid delivery contexts, while the five perspectives (Agile, BI, IT, Business Architecture, BPM) adapt it to specific domains.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project kickoff where the BA has no plan and needs to select which knowledge areas apply.</item>
        <item>Scoping a BA effort for a new feature or epic.</item>
        <item>Auditing an in-flight project for BA knowledge area coverage gaps.</item>
        <item>Onboarding a new BA or AI agent to a domain — load this first to get the routing map.</item>
        <item>Routing inside a multi-agent BA pipeline to decide which sub-agent runs next.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>You already know the specific technique needed — load the target methodology directly, skip the overview.</item>
        <item>Small single-feature task with one stakeholder and known scope — overhead exceeds value.</item>
        <item>Pure software design with no business requirements — use software-architect skills instead.</item>
        <item>Agile teams with a working backlog and clear DoR/DoD — BABOK formalism adds friction.</item>
        <item>Certification study — this file is operational context, not exam preparation.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="knowledge-areas">
      <p>All six knowledge areas: purpose, key tasks, outputs, and linked methodologies.</p>

      <section name="ka-1-planning-and-monitoring">
        <p>KA-1: Business Analysis Planning and Monitoring</p>
        <p>Purpose: plan how BA work will be done and track performance.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Plan BA Approach — define how BA will be performed; output: BA approach document.</item>
          <item>Plan Stakeholder Engagement — identify and plan work with stakeholders; output: stakeholder engagement approach.</item>
          <item>Plan Governance — define decision-making for requirements; output: governance approach.</item>
          <item>Plan Information Management — define how BA info is stored and accessed; output: information management approach.</item>
          <item>Identify Improvements — assess BA performance, recommend improvements.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Linked methodologies: ba-planning, stakeholder-analysis.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="ka-2-elicitation-and-collaboration">
        <p>KA-2: Elicitation and Collaboration</p>
        <p>Purpose: draw out information from stakeholders and confirm results.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Prepare for Elicitation — understand scope, select techniques; output: elicitation activity plan.</item>
          <item>Conduct Elicitation — draw out relevant information; output: elicitation results (unconfirmed).</item>
          <item>Confirm Results — verify understanding with stakeholders; output: elicitation results (confirmed).</item>
          <item>Communicate BA Information — ensure shared understanding.</item>
          <item>Manage Collaboration — encourage stakeholders to work together.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Linked methodologies: elicitation-techniques. Techniques: interviews, workshops, observation, surveys, document analysis, prototyping, brainstorming, focus groups.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="ka-3-requirements-lifecycle-management">
        <p>KA-3: Requirements Lifecycle Management</p>
        <p>Purpose: manage requirements through their full lifecycle.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Trace Requirements — ensure alignment at different levels; output: requirements (traced).</item>
          <item>Maintain Requirements — keep accurate and consistent; output: requirements (maintained).</item>
          <item>Prioritize Requirements — rank by importance; output: requirements (prioritized).</item>
          <item>Assess Changes — evaluate proposed changes; output: change assessment.</item>
          <item>Approve Requirements — obtain agreement; output: requirements (approved).</item>
        </list>
        <p>Linked methodologies: requirements-traceability, requirements-lifecycle, requirements-prioritization. Outputs: traceability matrix, requirements baseline, change impact analysis.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="ka-4-strategy-analysis">
        <p>KA-4: Strategy Analysis</p>
        <p>Purpose: understand the current state and define the change strategy to achieve the future state.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Analyze Current State — understand existing environment; output: current state description.</item>
          <item>Define Future State — define goals and objectives; output: future state description.</item>
          <item>Assess Risks — identify uncertainties; output: risk assessment results.</item>
          <item>Define Change Strategy — develop approach to achieve future state; output: change strategy.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Linked methodologies: strategy-analysis. Techniques: gap analysis, SWOT, business model canvas, capability assessment, risk analysis.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="ka-5-requirements-analysis-and-design-definition">
        <p>KA-5: Requirements Analysis and Design Definition</p>
        <p>Purpose: structure, specify, model, verify, and validate requirements; define design options.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Specify and Model Requirements — output: requirements (specified/modeled).</item>
          <item>Verify Requirements — ensure quality standards met; output: requirements (verified).</item>
          <item>Validate Requirements — ensure alignment with business goals; output: requirements (validated).</item>
          <item>Define Requirements Architecture — ensure requirements support each other.</item>
          <item>Define Design Options — define solution approaches.</item>
          <item>Analyze Value and Recommend — assess options, recommend solution.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Linked methodologies: use-case-modeling, user-story-mapping, data-analysis, business-process-analysis, decision-analysis, interface-analysis, requirements-validation, acceptance-criteria, requirements-documentation.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="ka-6-solution-evaluation">
        <p>KA-6: Solution Evaluation</p>
        <p>Purpose: assess solution performance and the value it delivers.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Measure Solution Performance — define how performance is measured; output: performance measures.</item>
          <item>Analyze Performance Measures — examine data against expected value; output: performance analysis.</item>
          <item>Assess Solution Limitations — investigate problems and causes; output: solution limitations.</item>
          <item>Assess Enterprise Limitations — investigate enterprise factor impacts.</item>
          <item>Recommend Actions — identify actions to increase value; output: value improvement recommendations.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Linked methodologies: solution-assessment. Outputs: performance metrics, value realization report, improvement recommendations, lessons learned.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="classification-and-perspectives">
      <p>Requirements Classification, Perspectives, and Usage by Phase</p>

      <section name="requirements-classification">
        <p>Requirements Classification</p>
        <p>BABOK classifies requirements into four types based on their role in the change initiative:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Business requirements — WHY the change is needed. Example: increase market share by 10%.</item>
          <item>Stakeholder requirements — WHAT users and stakeholders need. Example: faster order processing.</item>
          <item>Solution requirements — WHAT the system does (functional and non-functional). Example: calculate shipping cost in under 2 seconds.</item>
          <item>Transition requirements — HOW to get from current to future state. Example: migrate 3 years of order history.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="babok-perspectives">
        <p>BABOK Perspectives</p>
        <p>Five perspectives adapt the six knowledge areas to specific delivery contexts. Declare one perspective explicitly at project start — leaving it implicit produces inconsistent output across agents.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Agile — iterative, collaborative; extends to scaled frameworks (SAFe, LeSS) and DevOps.</item>
          <item>Business Intelligence — data analysis and reporting; expanded to AI/ML and advanced analytics.</item>
          <item>Information Technology — systems and technology; cloud-native, microservices, API-first.</item>
          <item>Business Architecture — enterprise-level design; digital transformation and platform thinking.</item>
          <item>Business Process Management — process optimization; intelligent automation and process mining.</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>Pair the overview with one declared perspective before any agent generates BA deliverables.</statement>
          <rationale>Without explicit perspective, models default to IT-perspective regardless of actual need; a BPM initiative gets system requirements when the user wanted process improvements.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="underlying-competencies">
        <p>Underlying Competencies</p>
        <p>Skills required for effective BA work across all knowledge areas:</p>
        <list>
          <item>Analytical — creative thinking, decision making, systems thinking, problem solving.</item>
          <item>Behavioral — ethics, accountability, trustworthiness, adaptability.</item>
          <item>Business — business acumen, industry knowledge, organization knowledge.</item>
          <item>Communication — verbal, written, listening, non-verbal.</item>
          <item>Interaction — facilitation, leadership, teamwork, negotiation.</item>
          <item>Tools and Technology — modeling tools, documentation platforms, automation tools.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="knowledge-area-usage-by-project-phase">
        <p>Knowledge Area Usage by Project Phase</p>
        <p>Match situation to primary knowledge area focus:</p>
        <list>
          <item>New project starting → Planning, Strategy Analysis.</item>
          <item>Gathering requirements → Elicitation, Requirements Analysis.</item>
          <item>Managing changes → Lifecycle Management.</item>
          <item>System implementation → Analysis, Solution Evaluation.</item>
          <item>Post go-live → Solution Evaluation.</item>
          <item>Process improvement → Strategy Analysis, Requirements Analysis.</item>
        </list>
        <rule>
          <statement>For agile projects, collapse Planning and Strategy into a single Sprint 0 deliverable. The BABOK linear flow is wrong for iterative teams.</statement>
          <rationale>Treating BABOK as a rigid sequential process on agile projects produces waterfall artifacts with sprint-shaped naming; compress and adapt.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Skipping knowledge areas because "this is a small project".</description>
          <reason>Small projects skip Planning (no stakeholder map) and Evaluation (no feedback loop); both failures produce avoidable rework in subsequent iterations.</reason>
        </antipattern>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Using BABOK as a rigid process instead of a competency and knowledge framework.</description>
          <reason>BABOK is descriptive, not prescriptive. Applying it linearly on agile projects produces waterfall artifacts even when the team is running sprints.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ba-coverage-checklist.md" purpose="Per-project checklist tracking applicable KAs, deliverable status, and location."/>
      <template path="templates/ba-plan.md" purpose="Business Analysis Plan template covering scope, KA approach, and resources."/>
    </templates>

    <section name="agentic-workflow-and-integration">
      <p>Treat the 6 KAs as a routing tree, not a sequential pipeline. A planner agent classifies the inbound request into one or more KAs, then dispatches per-KA subagents in parallel where dependencies allow. Always commit the KA classification to a memory file before dispatch — downstream agents read it instead of re-classifying. End every run with a KA-3 trace pass so artifacts stay linked.</p>
      <p>This overview is an index-level integration guide. It does not duplicate per-methodology agent files (those live next to each named methodology under business-analyst/, ba-core/, ba-modeling/). Use it to pick which KA — and which downstream methodology — an agent should run.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Classify every BA request into one or more KAs before generating any deliverable. Use the KA classification result as shared state that all downstream agents read — never re-classify per task.</statement>
        <rationale>Skipping the classification step causes agents to draft KA-5 specs when the actual gap is KA-1 stakeholder mapping; re-classifying per task produces inconsistent results across the pipeline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="implementation-considerations">
      <p>BABOK is artifact-heavy. LLMs over-produce structure (10-page docs for a 3-feature MVP). Force scope before generation.</p>
      <p>KA-3 (Lifecycle) requires a system of record (Jira/Linear/ADO). An agent without write access can only emit drafts; traceability matrices stay stale unless wired to the issue tracker.</p>
      <p>KA-4 (Strategy) needs ground truth about current state (org chart, KPIs, capability map). LLMs hallucinate plausible-but-wrong baselines without a document source.</p>
      <p>KA-6 (Solution Evaluation) needs telemetry. No metrics → agent invents metrics. Block this branch unless an analytics datasource is attached.</p>
      <p>The 6-KA framing is BABOK v3 (waterfall-leaning). For pure agile/discovery, prefer pm-agile/ and product-manager/ skills instead.</p>
      <p>LLMs default to KA-5 (modelling) on any input. Fight this — most real failures are KA-1 (no stakeholder map) or KA-3 (no traceability). Make the planner explicitly score all 6 KAs before dispatch.</p>
      <p>Agents will fabricate "industry standard" KPIs in KA-6. Require a citation or a datasource path for every metric; reject otherwise.</p>
      <p>BABOK terminology collides with agile terminology (e.g. "requirement" vs "story", "stakeholder" vs "persona"). Pin a glossary in the agent's system prompt — drift causes traceability errors when artifacts cross teams.</p>
      <p>Verification (KA-5) is distinct from Validation (KA-5). Two separate tasks. Do not let one prompt produce both — they require different mental modes (quality vs business fit) and a single pass usually does neither well.</p>
      <p>Multi-agent runs across KAs duplicate stakeholder lists. Centralise stakeholder register in one file referenced by all KA agents — never let each agent maintain its own copy.</p>
      <p>KA-3 traceability matrices require stable IDs. If your agent assigns IDs at generation time, they renumber on every run. Use content-hash IDs or pull IDs from the issue tracker before drafting.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices-for-implementation">
      <p>Classify before generating. Skipping the KA-routing step makes agents draft KA-5 specs when the actual gap is KA-1 stakeholder mapping. This is the single most common failure mode in BA automation.</p>
      <p>Persist the classification (e.g. in .aidocs/ba-routing.json) so re-runs converge instead of reclassifying and producing inconsistent guidance.</p>
      <p>For KA-3, never let an agent both author and approve a requirement in the same run — split into author and reviewer agents with different prompts to maintain separation of concerns.</p>
      <p>KA-2 and KA-5 should always emit machine-readable artifacts (JSON requirement objects, BPMN XML, Gherkin) alongside the human prose. Prose-only output breaks downstream traceability.</p>
      <p>Use the BABOK competency table (analytical/behavioural/business/communication/interaction) as a tag set for prompt routing — e.g. tasks tagged interaction:facilitation go to the faion-brainstorm skill rather than a solo agent.</p>
      <p>Cap each KA artifact to a hard line budget (KA-1 plan ≤ 200 lines, KA-4 strategy ≤ 300, KA-5 spec ≤ 500 per epic). Without caps LLMs balloon docs into unusable proportions.</p>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="knowledge-areas-detail"/>
      <ref slug="methodologies-detail"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
