<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="retention-compliance">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Paired framework for employee retention (stay interviews, exit analysis, 9-box reviews) and hiring compliance (legal requirements, DEI practices, audits).</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>retention</tag>
      <tag>compliance</tag>
      <tag>hiring</tag>
      <tag>dei</tag>
      <tag>hr</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Retention and Hiring Compliance</title>

    <summary>A paired framework covering two related HR domains: employee retention (stay interviews, exit analysis, 9-box talent reviews, internal mobility) and hiring compliance (legal requirements per funnel stage, DEI practices, process audits). Retention is cheapest before people quit; compliance failures are discovered during audits or litigation.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Exit interviews tell you why people left after the cost is sunk. Stay interviews with high performers surface flight risk early when action is still possible. On the compliance side, a single non-compliant question in an interview can trigger EEOC scrutiny; mapping legal requirements to each funnel stage turns compliance from a post-hoc audit into an in-process gate.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Quarterly stay-interview cycle for high-performer retention.</item>
        <item>Annual or post-attrition talent review using the 9-box grid.</item>
        <item>Auditing a hiring process for legal compliance (protected-class question exposure, FCRA, pay equity).</item>
        <item>DEI initiative requiring structured sourcing, blind review, and diverse panels.</item>
        <item>Post-mortem after a compliance incident or exit pattern analysis.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Individual performance management — that belongs in the manager's 1:1 cadence, not a retention framework.</item>
        <item>Executive compensation strategy — requires specialized total-rewards expertise.</item>
        <item>Jurisdictions with highly specific labor law (medical, aviation, finance) — consult legal counsel first; this framework is not legal advice.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="retention-strategies">
      <p>Stay interview framework, exit interview analysis process, talent review using the 9-box grid, and the five primary retention levers.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Address retention levers in this priority order: manager relationship, growth opportunity, recognition, compensation, flexibility. Fixing compensation first when manager issues exist wastes budget.</statement>
        <rationale>Gallup's State of the American Workplace consistently identifies the manager relationship as the primary driver of voluntary turnover, above compensation. Compensation interventions have a 3-6 month effect before the underlying issue resurfaces.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="lever-definitions">
        <p>Manager relationship: psychological safety, feedback quality, career investment, fairness. Growth: visible career paths, L&amp;D budget, stretch assignments, promotion criteria. Recognition: regular appreciation (specific, timely), bonuses tied to outcomes, peer recognition. Compensation: market-rate base pay with regular benchmarking; pay equity across demographics. Flexibility: remote or hybrid options, schedule flexibility, time-off policies.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="stay-interviews">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Conduct stay interviews with high performers quarterly; never substitute exit interviews for stay interviews — exit interviews surface the reason after the cost is sunk.</statement>
          <rationale>By the time a high performer has accepted a competing offer, the retention cost has already been paid. Stay interviews identify flight risk 3-6 months earlier, when low-cost interventions are still available.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <section name="stay-interview-questions">
          <p>"What do you look forward to at work each day?" — surfaces engagement drivers to protect.</p>
          <p>"What would make you consider leaving?" — surfaces risk factors before they become decisions.</p>
          <p>"What would you change about your role or the team?" — surfaces friction points.</p>
          <p>"Do you feel recognized for your contributions?" — surfaces recognition gaps.</p>
          <p>"What can I do to better support you?" — surfaces manager action items.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section name="exit-interviews">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Aggregate exit interview themes quarterly; a single exit reason is anecdote, a pattern across 5+ exits is a systemic issue requiring action.</statement>
          <rationale>Exit interview data is only actionable when analyzed as a trend. Individual exit reasons are often rationalized post-decision; patterns reveal the underlying organizational driver.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <list>
          <item>Conduct exit interviews with a neutral HR person, not the direct manager.</item>
          <item>Use standardized questions: why leaving, what could have retained you, would you recommend us?</item>
          <item>Code free-text responses into 5-8 categories quarterly.</item>
          <item>Report themes with volume and trend to leadership.</item>
          <item>Track whether recommended actions from prior quarters were implemented.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="nine-box">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Run a 9-box talent review annually for all employees; classify by current performance and assessed potential; identify flight risk separately from performance.</statement>
          <rationale>The 9-box surfaces succession gaps (no one in the "high performance, high potential" quadrant for a critical role) and retention priorities (Stars with high flight risk need immediate stay interviews).</rationale>
        </rule>

        <section name="nine-box-grid">
          <p>Stars (high performance, high potential): highest retention priority; development-investment candidates; flight risk if unchallenged. Rising stars (medium performance, high potential): need stretch assignments to develop. Experts (high performance, low potential): stable, high-value; do not over-promote. Risk (low performance, high potential): unclear situation; reassign or investigate engagement. Stable (medium performance, medium potential): core workforce; maintain with standard development. Exit candidates (low performance, low potential): performance management, not retention investment.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="compliance">
      <p>Legal compliance requirements at each hiring funnel stage, DEI practices per stage, and process audit framework for identifying legal and equity risk.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Audit every interview question against the protected-class list before using it in a live interview; a single non-compliant question in a recorded or documented interview creates EEOC exposure.</statement>
        <rationale>In the US, protected classes under Title VII, ADEA, ADA, and equivalent state laws include race, color, religion, sex, national origin, age (40+), and disability. Questions that reasonably imply any of these — even indirectly (e.g., "When did you graduate?") — are non-compliant regardless of intent.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <section name="compliance-per-stage">
        <p>Job posting: no discriminatory language (age, gender, race markers); include EEO statement; publish salary range where required by law (California, Colorado, NYC, others).</p>
        <p>Application: only job-relevant questions; no questions about prior salary history (illegal in many US jurisdictions); no protected-class questions.</p>
        <p>Screening: screen on job-related criteria only; document screening criteria before reviewing candidates; apply criteria consistently to all applicants.</p>
        <p>Interviews: no questions about age, religion, national origin, marital status, disability, pregnancy, arrest record (vs. conviction in many states), or union membership. All questions must be job-related.</p>
        <p>Assessments: use only validated, job-related assessments; document validity evidence; ensure accessibility for candidates with disabilities (ADA).</p>
        <p>Background checks: obtain written consent per FCRA (US); do not use arrest records without individualized assessment; follow "ban the box" laws in applicable jurisdictions.</p>
        <p>Offers: apply consistent compensation criteria; conduct pay equity analysis before extending offers; document offer rationale.</p>
        <p>Records: retain applications, interview notes, and scorecards per EEOC guidelines (1 year for most records; 2 years for federal contractors).</p>
      </section>

      <section name="dei-practices">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Require a diverse candidate slate of at least two underrepresented candidates in every final interview round before extending an offer.</statement>
          <rationale>LinkedIn and McKinsey data consistently show that when only one underrepresented candidate reaches the final round, statistical chance of hire approaches zero. The diverse slate requirement creates the conditions where merit-based selection is possible.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <section name="dei-per-stage">
          <p>Sourcing: proactively source from HBCUs, women's colleges, coding bootcamps, and community organizations; employee referral programs without diversity goals amplify existing demographic homogeneity.</p>
          <p>Job postings: use inclusive language tools (Textio, Gender Decoder); remove gendered language and unnecessary requirements; add explicit statement of flexible work options.</p>
          <p>Screening: run blind resume review (remove name, graduation year, school) for first pass; use standardized criteria applied consistently.</p>
          <p>Interviews: require diverse interview panels; brief all panelists on the scoring rubric and behavioral anchors before the loop begins; debrief includes explicit anti-bias check ("Are any concerns about the candidate actually about a non-job-related characteristic?").</p>
          <p>Offers: run pay equity analysis comparing the offer to current employees in the same role/level/geography before extending; close unexplained gaps before the offer is made.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section name="process-audit">
        <rule testable="true">
          <statement>Audit the full recruiting process annually against six dimensions: time-to-fill delays, candidate drop-off patterns, hire quality, candidate experience, compliance, and cost; act on at least one finding per audit.</statement>
          <rationale>Process audits without required action items become reporting exercises. Assigning each finding an owner and a follow-up date converts audit outputs into improvements.</rationale>
        </rule>

        <section name="audit-dimensions">
          <p>Time-to-fill: where are the delays? Which roles/levels/departments consistently exceed the benchmark?</p>
          <p>Drop-off: at which stage do candidates exit? Is drop-off equal across demographic groups or concentrated?</p>
          <p>Quality: are hires meeting expectations at 90 days and 1 year? Are any sources or channels producing systematically lower quality?</p>
          <p>Candidate experience: what do post-process surveys show? What are the common friction points?</p>
          <p>Compliance: are all interview questions documented and compliant? Are records retained correctly? Are assessments validated?</p>
          <p>Cost: where is cost-per-hire above target? Can any stage be optimized without quality trade-off?</p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-workflow">
      <p>Drive retention + compliance as a five-track program owned by `faion-recruiter-agent` plus `faion-people-analytics-agent` (specialization). Track A — stay interviews: opus designs the question set + frequency per segment; humans run the conversations; sonnet codes themes from notes. Track B — exit analysis: sonnet codes exit interviews into a controlled vocabulary; opus does quarterly trend synthesis with statistical thresholds. Track C — talent review: sonnet drafts 9-box pre-reads from performance + manager input; opus produces succession-gap analysis; the rating itself is human, calibrated in a session. Track D — compliance audit: sonnet checklists against jurisdictional rules (with explicit jurisdiction parameter); opus interprets findings; legal sign-off mandatory before any action. Track E — DEI hiring audit: sonnet computes disparate-impact ratios on legitimately-collected demographic data; opus produces intervention designs; bias review by `general-purpose` reviewer with fresh context.</p>

      <section name="recommended-subagents-retention">
        <list>
          <item>`faion-recruiter-agent` — primary; owns retention + compliance + audit work.</item>
          <item>`faion-research-agent (mode: market)` — comp-benchmarking when retention data points to comp.</item>
          <item>`general-purpose` reviewer (sonnet, fresh context) — adversarial pass on DEI language, compliance interpretations, exit-interview theme coding.</item>
          <item>`faion-employer-brand-agent` — drafts retention-program comms.</item>
          <item>Legal counsel (human) — non-optional reviewer for any compliance or DEI intervention.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="prompt-patterns-retention">
        <p>Stay-interview design (segment-aware): Design a stay-interview question set per skills/faion/knowledge/pro/comms/hr-recruiter/retention-compliance/README.md. Segment: senior engineers, tenure 18-36 months, post comp-cycle. Known concerns from last pulse: [pasted]. Cadence: quarterly. Output 8-10 questions max, mixing: engagement drivers, risk factors, growth, recognition, manager support. Each question must elicit a behavior or fact, not an opinion. Forbidden: "Are you happy?", "How is everything?". Provide a follow-up probe per question.</p>

        <p>Exit-interview thematic coding: Given N exit-interview transcripts (attached) and the controlled vocabulary (attached), code each transcript with: primary reason, secondary reason(s), departure pattern (push / pull / personal), retention-recoverable (Y/N with evidence), key quote (verbatim, single sentence). Do not invent codes; use only the supplied vocabulary. If a transcript does not fit, mark "uncoded" with explanation. No aggregate statistics yet.</p>

        <p>Disparate-impact computation: Inputs: stage-by-stage candidate data with demographic flags collected per jurisdiction rules (attached). Compute four-fifths-rule pass ratios per protected class per stage. Flag stages where any class is below 80% of the highest-class rate. Output: pass-rate table + flagged stages + minimum sample size needed for significance. Do not interpret; do not recommend; do not infer demographics from names.</p>
      </section>

      <section name="cli-tools-retention">
        <list>
          <item>`pandas` + `scipy.stats` — Disparate-impact, four-fifths rule, kappa for rater agreement</item>
          <item>BambooHR / Rippling / HiBob / Workday API — HRIS pulls for tenure, comp, manager chain</item>
          <item>Lattice / 15Five / Culture Amp API — Engagement / pulse / stay-interview data</item>
          <item>Greenhouse / Lever / Ashby API — Hiring funnel demographics for DEI audits</item>
          <item>`dbt` + `duckdb` — Cohort retention warehousing</item>
          <item>`pyreadstat` — Survey data import (SPSS/Stata/SAS) for legacy datasets</item>
          <item>`gh` + GitHub Pages — Audit report version control</item>
          <item>`op` (1Password CLI) — Pull HRIS API tokens without committing secrets</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="services-hris">
        <p>BambooHR / Rippling / HiBob (SaaS HRIS, agent-friendly REST): Tenure, comp, manager hierarchy. Workday / SAP SuccessFactors (SaaS HRIS enterprise, partial agent-friendly): Heavy auth + audit logging. Lattice / 15Five / Culture Amp / Peakon (SaaS engagement, agent-friendly REST): Engagement + stay-interview workflows. Glint (LinkedIn) (SaaS engagement, limited agent-friendly): Strong analytics, weak API. Visier / One Model (SaaS people analytics, agent-friendly REST): Cohort retention, predictive turnover. ChartHop / Pave (SaaS comp + people, agent-friendly REST): Comp equity audits, banding. Pyn (SaaS lifecycle nudges, agent-friendly REST): Manager-as-coach automation. Workhuman / Bonusly (SaaS recognition, agent-friendly REST): Recognition data feeds retention models. Eightfold / Findem / SeekOut (SaaS sourcing AI, partial agent-friendly): Bias audits required (disparate impact). HireRight / Checkr (SaaS background, agent-friendly REST): Compliance-heavy; consent flow stays human. OneTrust / TrustArc (SaaS privacy/GDPR, agent-friendly REST): Data inventory + DSAR automation. Holistic AI / Arthur / Fiddler (SaaS AI audits, agent-friendly REST): Algorithmic bias monitoring (NYC AEDT, EU AI Act).</p>
      </section>

      <section name="best-practices-retention">
        <list>
          <item>Stay interviews are about action, not measurement. If you have no intent or budget to act on findings, do not run them.</item>
          <item>Run exit interviews via a neutral party (HR Ops, not the manager). Departing employees mute candor with their direct chain.</item>
          <item>Code exit data with a tight controlled vocabulary (15-25 codes max). Free-text aggregation is unreliable, even with LLMs.</item>
          <item>9-box ratings calibrate in a live cross-functional session; pre-reads are pre-reads, not the rating.</item>
          <item>Compliance: maintain a jurisdictional matrix (US-state, EU-country, UK, Canada-province) covering: protected classes, retention periods, consent for screening, AEDT/AI-Act requirements. Refresh annually with counsel.</item>
          <item>DEI: focus on systemic interventions (slate diversity, structured interviews, blind resume review, comp equity audits) not individual decisions.</item>
          <item>Run a disparate-impact audit on every new screening tool *before* turning it on, then quarterly.</item>
          <item>Always preserve the demographic data and the model decision together for audit; AEDT requires bias-audit publication for many tools.</item>
          <item>Track retention by cohort (start year + role family) not company-wide; mask hides everything.</item>
          <item>Avoid "engagement" vanity metrics divorced from action; pulse fatigue is real and reduces signal.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="agent-gotchas-retention">
        <list>
          <item>Demographic inference from names / emails / photos is illegal in many jurisdictions and unreliable everywhere. Never let an agent infer; only operate on legitimately-collected, consented data.</item>
          <item>LLMs over-summarize exit-interview free text; high-impact unique reasons get smoothed into popular themes. Force "show every quote that appears only once" alongside themes.</item>
          <item>"Compliance advice" from an LLM is not legal advice; agents must always defer to counsel and cite jurisdiction explicitly.</item>
          <item>DEI language drift: agents reach for buzzwords ("diverse perspectives", "lived experience") that vary in reception. Adversarial review with a fresh-context reviewer is mandatory.</item>
          <item>Disparate-impact ratios computed on n &lt; 30 per group are meaningless; agents will report them anyway. Add a sample-size gate.</item>
          <item>Stay-interview questions auto-generated by an agent gravitate toward "engagement" theatre; force behavior + fact-eliciting questions.</item>
          <item>9-box "potential" ratings encoded by an agent inherit historical bias; never let an agent pre-fill potential. Performance, yes; potential, never.</item>
          <item>Auto-emailed retention surveys / stay-interview invites violate CASL / CAN-SPAM / GDPR if there's no internal-comms-consent basis; route through internal newsletters infrastructure, not transactional email.</item>
          <item>Mandatory human-in-loop: (1) every compliance interpretation (counsel), (2) every DEI intervention (DEI lead), (3) every 9-box rating (manager + HRBP), (4) any disparate-impact-flagged stage (counsel + DEI), (5) any retention action affecting comp / role / manager assignment.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="recruitment-funnel-optimization"/>
      <ref slug="recruiting-process"/>
      <ref slug="structured-interview-design"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
