<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="spec-requirements Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for spec-requirements. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every FR must satisfy all five SMART criteria: Specific (one interpretation only), Measurable (testable pass/fail), Achievable (technically feasible), Relevant (traces to a user story), Time-bound (MoSCoW priority assigned).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Ambiguous requirements are the largest source of rework. SMART forces precision at authoring time, not during implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use "System SHALL" imperative voice for every FR. Never use "should", "can", "may", or "will".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">"SHALL" is unambiguous in requirements engineering and signals a testable mandatory constraint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ban ambiguous words: "fast", "good", "easy", "support", "handle". Replace with quantified targets.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These words cannot be tested — they produce requirements that pass review but fail verification.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign each FR exactly one MoSCoW priority: Must (cannot launch without), Should (important but not critical), Could (nice to have), Won't (explicitly excluded from this release).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without explicit prioritization, every requirement defaults to Must and MVP scope explodes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Must requirements must not exceed 60% of total FR count. If they do, re-classify or split the feature.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Enforcing this ratio preserves the MVP concept and prevents scope creep disguised as priority.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every FR must reference at least one user story (US-X). Every Must FR must reference at least one acceptance criterion (AC-X).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Traceability ensures every implemented requirement has a business reason and a verification condition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use sequential identifiers: FR-001, FR-002; US-001; AC-001. Never use section headings as identifiers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">IDs are stable references across spec, design, and implementation documents. Headings change; IDs should not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write every AC in Given-When-Then format with specific values, not generic placeholders. "Given user is on registration page" is acceptable; "Given user enters valid data" is not.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Specific values make ACs directly executable as BDD tests without interpretation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cover at minimum: happy path, error handling (validation failure), boundary condition, security scenario (unauthorized access or injection). Performance scenario required for any Must NFR.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents and reviewers systematically skip boundary and security scenarios unless coverage is explicitly mandated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every NFR must specify a measurement method, not just a target. "Response time SHALL be &lt; 500ms p95, measured server-side under 1000 concurrent users" is complete; "&lt; 500ms" alone is not.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A target without a measurement method is unverifiable — performance tests cannot be designed without knowing the conditions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before writing any requirement, create a Business Value Statement: [WHO] currently cannot [WHAT] because [WHY]. This results in [IMPACT]. By implementing [SOLUTION], we will [BENEFIT].</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents and reviewers need the "why" anchor before requirements; without it, Achievable and Relevant criteria cannot be validated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write use cases only for multi-step workflows with multiple actors or complex branching. Single-actor, linear flows do not need a use case — a user story with AC is sufficient.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Use case overhead on simple features adds documentation burden without improving clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
