<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Remote Workshop Toolkit — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every remote / hybrid BA workshop must obey. These are the rules that compensate for the lack of a shared physical room — skipping any of them collapses the workshop into a meeting.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-pre-read-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A workshop runs only after a 1-2 page pre-read has been circulated ≥48h before the live session AND ≥70% of attendees have acknowledged reading it (reaction, comment, or written pulse).</statement>
      <rationale source="Amazon 6-pager practice; Lencioni — Death by Meeting">In-person workshops absorb context cost in the room; remote workshops collapse if even 30% of attendees arrive unread. The pre-read shifts context to async, freeing live time for synthesis. The 70% acknowledgement floor is the early-warning that the workshop is mis-scheduled.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-breakout-protocol" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every breakout MUST have: (a) named facilitator, (b) named timekeeper, (c) named scribe with explicit canvas frame, (d) a one-paragraph deliverable definition, (e) a read-out template the breakout completes before returning. No "go discuss" without the four roles.</statement>
      <rationale source="Liberating Structures (1-2-4-All); Atlassian Team Playbook">Unmoderated breakouts in remote workshops produce silence, off-topic chat, or domination by one voice. The four-role contract forces structure and the read-out template forces synthesis. Returning breakouts MUST present, not narrate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-camera-and-mic-policy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Camera policy is stated in writing and acknowledged on the calendar invite. Default: cameras on for plenary, optional in breakouts. Mics on by default in breakouts of ≤6 people. "Mic muted, camera off, listening" is not a participation mode.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stanford research on Zoom fatigue (Bailenson 2021); Microsoft hybrid-work studies">The lurker is the default failure mode in remote workshops. A clear policy named in advance prevents the awkward live confrontation. Hybrid workshops require the in-room participants to use individual laptops to avoid the room-vs-remote asymmetry.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-time-zone-splitting" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the stakeholder cohort spans ≥3 time zones with no overlap window where ≥80% of attendees are in working hours, the workshop MUST be split into two sessions OR run with an explicit async-relay protocol (one session, the other gets recording + canvas to extend).</statement>
      <rationale source="GitLab All-Remote Playbook; Doist async-first guidance">A 6am or 11pm slot for any participant produces second-class participation. The 80% working-hours floor is the gate; splitting is cheaper than the silent quality loss.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-async-pulse-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For multi-session workshops, an async pulse (3-5 questions, ≤5 min completion) runs between sessions. ≥80% response rate is the threshold to proceed to the next live session; below that, schedule a follow-up rather than push forward.</statement>
      <rationale source="Liberating Structures — TRIZ pattern; Atlassian Health Monitor">Without pulses, multi-session workshops decay between sessions: people forget, decisions drift, blockers pile up. The pulse re-anchors and surfaces blockers before the next session has to deal with them live.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Hybrid kickoff workshop run-book excerpt">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Pre-read sent: T-72h. Acknowledgement at T-24h: 9/12 (75%) — passes floor.
Live session 1 (90 min, all in working hours by time-zone split rule):
  00-10  Plenary, ground rules visible on canvas
  10-30  Breakout A (4 people, eu-stakeholders) — process map as-is
         facilitator: Anna; timekeeper: Roman; scribe: Olha;
         canvas-frame: miro/process-map/as-is/eu;
         deliverable: 8-12 step process with hand-off owners
  10-30  Breakout B (4 people, us-stakeholders) — same canvas, us scope
  30-45  Read-out: each breakout presents using the template
  45-75  Plenary synthesis (merge canvases)
  75-90  Decisions list + parking lot + async-pulse plan
Async pulse: T+24h, 4 questions, 11/12 responses (92%).
Session 2: T+5d. Pre-read updated. Same protocol.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1-r5 in a single run.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="The classic 90-minute meeting pretending to be a workshop">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"All-day workshop, 9am-5pm Eastern, no pre-read, breakouts at lunch
if there's time, cameras optional, recording will be shared."
9am EU: that's 3pm — fine for some, exhausted for others;
breakouts skipped because the day fell behind;
3 people lurked the whole day, no decisions captured.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1, r2, r3, r4 all violated. The workshop produced a recording, not a decision.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
