<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Persona Building Process and Data Requirements">
  <summary>Five-step evidence-anchored persona building process: data gathering, pattern clustering, segment definition, persona construction, and validation with a falsification clause.</summary>

  <section title="Data requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run at least 10 customer interviews before creating any persona; fewer interviews produce stereotypes, not archetypes.</statement>
      <rationale>Below 10 interviews, pattern confidence is too low to distinguish signal from individual variation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply a no-demographics-first rule: write goals and frustrations before any demographic detail.</statement>
      <rationale>Demographics trigger stereotype completion in both humans and LLMs; goals and frustrations derived first stay grounded in interview evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every bullet in every persona must cite the supporting interview IDs. Never invent demographic detail not present in the transcripts.</statement>
      <rationale>Hallucinated quotes and invented demographics are the most damaging failure mode — they justify wrong decisions with false specificity.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Clustering dimensions">
    <p>Cluster utterances across four dimensions: Goals (what they want to achieve), Frustrations (what blocks them), Behaviours (how they work and buy), Information Sources (where they learn and get influenced). Each cluster needs a one-sentence pattern, supporting interview IDs, and three verbatim quotes.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Propose at most one primary persona and one negative persona (who NOT to target) per research round without explicit approval to add more.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple personas at pre-traction stage dilute focus; negative personas are consistently skipped and are as valuable as positive ones for positioning.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation and refresh">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair the persona doc with one paragraph titled "How we would notice this persona is wrong" — a falsification clause.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a falsification clause, personas accumulate institutional momentum and survive past their useful life.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Refresh cycle: minor update quarterly (interview signals, support ticket categories); major rebuild on pivots or new markets.</statement>
      <rationale>Personas frozen at year-one data keep echoing in year-three decisions against a different reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Show the draft persona to actual customers and ask if they recognize themselves; measure recognition rate before using for decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Recognition testing is the fastest validation that the archetype maps to reality rather than to the research team's assumptions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Distribution">
    <rule>
      <statement>Distribute the persona where decisions are made: PM Notion, marketing brief template, sales playbook. A persona-only document gathers dust.</statement>
      <rationale>Personas only change behaviour when they are embedded in the artifacts people already use for decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
