<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Persona Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Two worked persona examples with evidence-anchored structure, and antipatterns that produce fictional or useless personas.</summary>

  <section title="Worked examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Persona: Newsletter Nate (SaaS for freelance writers). Based on 14 interviews.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Newsletter Nate

**Who:** 34-year-old freelance writer running a paid newsletter with 2,000 subscribers ($4K/month from writing).

**Goals:** Grow subscriber base to 10,000; reduce time on operations; launch a course.

**Frustrations:** Email platform is expensive at scale (INT-003, INT-007, INT-011);
no easy way to sell digital products (INT-002, INT-009); analytics are confusing (INT-005).

**Quote (INT-007):** "I'm a writer, not a tech person. I just want it to work."

**Buying trigger:** Switches when current tool fails or pricing surprise hits at a growth milestone.

**Falsification:** If >30% of new signups are NOT running a paid newsletter, this persona is wrong.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Persona: Agency Amy (project management for agencies). Based on 11 interviews.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Agency Amy

**Who:** 38-year-old agency owner, 5-person design agency, $500K annual revenue.

**Goals:** Stop projects going over budget (INT-001, INT-006); improve client communication (INT-004);
scale without adding overhead (INT-008, INT-010).

**Frustrations:** Team uses 6 different tools (INT-001, INT-003, INT-008);
clients don't understand project status (INT-004, INT-006).

**Quote (INT-003):** "I need my team aligned without micromanaging."

**Buying trigger:** Current tool failure causes a client escalation or budget overrun.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Persona with stock photo, alliterative name, and invented demographics not drawn from interviews.</description>
      <reason>Polished presentation signals quality but predicts nothing; invented detail justifies wrong decisions with false confidence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating 5 or more personas before reaching $10K MRR or equivalent traction.</description>
      <reason>Multiple personas at pre-traction stage fragment focus; start with one primary and expand only after traction confirms segment boundaries.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Persona updated annually or never.</description>
      <reason>Personas frozen at founding data echo year-one assumptions in year-three decisions; require quarterly minor refresh and post-pivot major rebuild.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No negative persona defined.</description>
      <reason>Without defining who not to target, teams waste acquisition budget on high-churn, high-support-cost, price-sensitive users that fit no sustainable segment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/persona-full.md">Full persona template</link>
    <link path="templates/persona-lean.md">Lean persona for rapid iteration</link>
    <link path="templates/persona-negative.md">Negative persona template</link>
    <link path="templates/build-persona.py">Anthropic SDK script for transcript clustering</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
