<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-authentication" title="Google Ads API Authentication">
  <summary>OAuth 2.0 + developer token authentication model, credential components, token access levels, and security rules.</summary>

  <section title="Required Credentials">
    <list>
      <item>Developer Token: API access identifier from ads.google.com</item>
      <item>OAuth 2.0 Client ID: application identifier from Google Cloud Console</item>
      <item>OAuth 2.0 Client Secret: application secret from Google Cloud Console</item>
      <item>Refresh Token: long-lived token for generating access tokens</item>
      <item>Login Customer ID: Manager Account (MCC) ID — required only for MCC access</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Developer Token Levels">
    <list>
      <item>Test Account: unlimited requests against test data — apply in Google Ads UI</item>
      <item>Basic Access: 15,000 daily requests — requires approved application</item>
      <item>Standard Access: 10,000 requests per customer — requires company verification</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a Test Account developer token during development. Promote to Basic or Standard Access only when moving to production with real customer accounts.</statement>
      <rationale>Test Account tokens are approved instantly; Basic and Standard Access require review and verification that blocks development if not planned ahead.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Authentication Flow">
    <list>
      <item>1. Create Google Cloud Project</item>
      <item>2. Enable Google Ads API in the project</item>
      <item>3. Create OAuth 2.0 credentials (web or desktop app)</item>
      <item>4. Get Developer Token from ads.google.com account settings</item>
      <item>5. Generate Refresh Token via OAuth flow</item>
      <item>6. Configure client library with google-ads.yaml or dict</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/google-ads.yaml">google-ads.yaml template with all required credential fields</reference>
    <reference path="templates/client-setup.py">Python client initialization patterns using YAML and dict</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store all credentials in environment variables or a secrets manager. Never commit credentials to version control.</statement>
      <rationale>Leaked credentials grant full API access to all linked ad accounts, enabling unauthorized spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Use separate credentials for test and production environments</item>
      <item>Rotate refresh tokens periodically (at least annually)</item>
      <item>Apply least-privilege access — only request scopes needed</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
