<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-account-structure" title="Google Ads Account Hierarchy and Campaign Management">
  <summary>Resource hierarchy from MCC to keyword, GAQL query patterns for listing customers and campaigns with metrics, and campaign status update pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Resource Hierarchy">
    <list>
      <item>Manager Account (MCC) — top level, optional</item>
      <item>Customer Account — ad account; parent of all campaigns</item>
      <item>Campaign — budget and targeting settings</item>
      <item>Ad Group — container for ads and keywords</item>
      <item>Ad — creative content</item>
      <item>Keyword — search targeting</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>When querying or mutating resources, always provide the correct customer_id at the level of the resource being accessed, not the MCC ID.</statement>
      <rationale>Using the MCC ID for customer-level operations causes authorization errors. The login_customer_id configures MCC context; customer_id targets the specific account.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="GAQL Query Pattern">
    <p>Google Ads uses GAQL (Google Ads Query Language) — a SQL-like query syntax for all report and list operations via GoogleAdsService.search().</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>List campaigns with metrics: SELECT campaign.id, campaign.name, campaign.status, metrics.impressions, metrics.clicks, metrics.cost_micros FROM campaign WHERE campaign.status != 'REMOVED' ORDER BY campaign.name. Divide cost_micros by 1,000,000 to get currency value.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the REST API directly instead of the Python client library for complex operations.</description>
      <reason>The client library handles proto-plus marshaling, retry logic, and error code mapping automatically. Raw REST requires manual handling of all edge cases.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Campaign Status Update">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use CampaignOperation with an update_mask to modify only specified fields. Never send a full campaign object for updates.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an update_mask, the API resets all unspecified fields to defaults, corrupting campaign settings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Valid status values: ENABLED, PAUSED, REMOVED</item>
      <item>REMOVED is permanent for campaigns — use PAUSED to stop delivery temporarily</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
