<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-phases-and-aha" title="Aha Moment Discovery, TTV Optimization, and 5-Phase Checklist">
  <summary>How to find the Aha moment from cohort data, reduce TTV to under 5 minutes, and the 5-phase sequential implementation checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Aha Moment Discovery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Find the Aha moment using two methods: (1) behavioral correlation — find the action most correlated with Day-30 retention in converted vs churned cohorts, minimum 200 converted users; (2) qualitative validation — interview 5+ converted customers asking "when did you decide to pay?". Both must agree before treating the Aha event as validated.</statement>
      <rationale>Behavioral correlation alone overfits to noisy events. Qualitative interviews confirm causality vs coincidence. Requiring both methods reduces false Aha moment choices by ~60% vs cohort-only approaches.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Slack Aha: first message sent in a channel with teammates.</item>
      <item>Dropbox Aha: first file synced across two devices.</item>
      <item>Zoom Aha: first successful video call completed.</item>
      <item>Notion Aha: first page created and shared with a collaborator.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="TTV Reduction Tactics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Target TTV (time from signup to Aha moment) under 5 minutes. This requires: pre-configured demo state or sample data, social login option, skip option for all non-critical steps, and a single guided path to the core action.</statement>
      <rationale>TTV under 5 minutes is achievable only with templates or pre-seeded data — an empty product with a setup wizard is rarely under 15 minutes. Pre-seeding is an engineering requirement, not a UX recommendation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Progressive onboarding (learn while doing): high impact.</item>
      <item>Pre-configured templates and example data: high impact.</item>
      <item>Interactive tutorial with guided first action: high impact.</item>
      <item>Social login (Google, GitHub): medium impact, removes password friction.</item>
      <item>Single-player mode (defer team features until solo value proven): medium impact.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="5-Phase Implementation Checklist">
    <p>Phase 1 — Foundation: define Aha moment, measure current TTV, map user journey to value, identify conversion triggers, set up product analytics.</p>
    <p>Phase 2 — Free Tier Design: choose PLG model, define free tier limits, create upgrade triggers, design self-serve checkout, build pricing page.</p>
    <p>Phase 3 — Activation Optimization: simplify signup to under 3 fields, create onboarding flow, add templates/examples, build interactive tutorial, reduce TTV to under 5 minutes.</p>
    <p>Phase 4 — Monetization: define PQL criteria, build PQL scoring (see plg-metrics), create upgrade prompts, set up automated email playbooks, add sales-assist for ACV above $1K/month.</p>
    <p>Phase 5 — Expansion: identify expansion triggers (seat growth, usage growth), build seat/usage upgrade flows, create upsell playbooks, track expansion revenue and net revenue retention.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="In-Product Upgrade Trigger Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show upgrade triggers contextually at the moment of need: at 80% of limit consumption, when user attempts a gated feature, when team collaboration signal fires. Never show during first session, during a critical workflow, or more than once per session.</statement>
      <rationale>Contextual triggers convert at 3-5x time-based pop-ups. First-session prompts break trust before value is demonstrated.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>All upgrade trigger copy must reference the user's actual behavior ("You've created 4 of 5 projects") not generic upsell language ("Get more features").</statement>
      <rationale>Behavior-personalized copy converts at 2-3x generic copy in PLG upgrade prompt tests.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
