<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-playbooks" title="Freemium-to-Paid, Trial-to-Paid, and Expansion Playbooks">
  <summary>Three Day-N state-machine playbooks with human approval gates and implementation rules for PLG conversion sequences.</summary>

  <section title="Playbook 1: Freemium-to-Paid">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger the freemium-to-paid playbook at 80% of limit consumption (not 100%). All messages must queue with approved=False and require human review before send.</statement>
      <rationale>Triggering at 100% means the user has already hit a wall; at 80% the message feels helpful rather than punitive. Auto-sending campaigns without human review risks mis-sent mass communications.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Day 0: in-app limit notification — "You have 1 project remaining. Pro plan unlocks unlimited."</item>
      <item>Day 2: email if no action — value of upgrading + social proof from a similar company.</item>
      <item>Day 5: in-app reminder — remaining capacity with specific upgrade benefit.</item>
      <item>Day 7: email — time-limited discount offer (20% off first 3 months).</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/day-n-playbook.py">Python scheduler generating the freemium-to-paid Day-N queue</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Playbook 2: Trial-to-Paid">
    <list>
      <item>Trial Days 1-3 (Activation focus): welcome email with quickstart, in-app checklist toward Aha moment, chat widget for questions.</item>
      <item>Trial Days 4-7 (Value demonstration): usage-report email citing what the user accomplished, feature discovery prompts, social proof from similar companies.</item>
      <item>Trial Days 8-11 (Conversion intent): PQL scoring check; high PQL score triggers sales outreach; low PQL stays in automated nurture.</item>
      <item>Trial Days 12-14 (Urgency): countdown in product UI, final email with actual usage stats injected ("You've created X projects"), clear upgrade CTA.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Playbook 3: Expansion (Seat Growth)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger expansion playbook from leading signals — 3+ active users from same org, @mentions in comments, external sharing — not from admin seat count alone. Route high-PQL accounts above ACV $1K/month to sales SDR; below that, automation closes the loop.</statement>
      <rationale>Leading behavioral signals predict expansion intent days before seat limits are reached. Waiting for the seat limit to fire gives competitors time to make the case for a switch at renewal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>In-product message to any user: "Your team is growing — add more members on Team plan."</item>
      <item>Email to admin: team activity report showing collaboration value, Team plan benefits.</item>
      <item>High PQL score: sales call offer for Team or Enterprise tier.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Playbook Implementation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Ship Phase 1 (Foundation) end-to-end before starting Phase 2. The checklist order is sequential because each phase depends on prior instrumentation.</statement>
      <rationale>Building upgrade triggers (Phase 2) before measuring TTV (Phase 1) optimizes a funnel with no baseline; lift cannot be measured without before/after instrumentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Self-serve checkout instrumentation must include payment-failure events. Tracking only successful upgrades misses the largest BoF leak in most PLG products.</statement>
      <rationale>Payment failures are the most common bottom-of-funnel drop-off and are often 2-3x more frequent than successful upgrades. Invisible failures prevent any checkout optimization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
