<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Prototype Process and Fidelity">
  <summary>Five-step prototyping process with fidelity decision matrix and handoff artifact checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Fidelity Decision Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose fidelity based on what you need to learn, not on how much time you have.</statement>
      <rationale>Fidelity that exceeds learning needs wastes design time and creates false attachment to visuals before validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>
      Low fidelity (paper, basic wireframes) → concept testing, hours to create.
      Medium fidelity (clickable screens, key interactions) → flow testing, days to create.
      High fidelity (near-final, animated) → experience testing, weeks to create.
      Code prototype (HTML/CSS/React) → technical feasibility, engineering time.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-Step Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write learning objectives before selecting tools or fidelity level.</statement>
      <rationale>Objectives determine scope; scope determines fidelity; fidelity determines tool. Reversing this order produces over-built prototypes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Step 1: Define objectives — state each as a testable question (e.g., "Can users complete checkout without help?").</p>
    <p>Step 2: Determine fidelity — use the matrix above. When in doubt, start lower.</p>
    <p>Step 3: Create prototype — include key screens, critical interactions, realistic content, and a clear user path. Prototype the riskiest assumption first.</p>
    <p>Step 4: Test with users — define 3-5 tasks, observe without intervening, note failures and confusion.</p>
    <p>Step 5: Iterate — fix major issues, re-test if critical flows changed, document decisions, hand off.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit moderated test tasks to 3-5 per session.</statement>
      <rationale>More tasks produce fatigue and diluted observations, not more insight.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Prototype Types">
    <p>
      Paper — sketches and paper screens; fast, cheap, anyone can facilitate.
      Clickable (Figma hotspots) — linked screens; quick to build, shareable, testable.
      Interactive (Figma/Framer/ProtoPie) — animations and transitions; realistic but time-intensive.
      Code (React/HTML) — technical validation; highest fidelity, real implementation constraints.
    </p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Clickable Figma prototype for checkout flow validation: create screen designs, add hotspots, link screens, define transitions. Tests flow comprehension without investing in animations.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Building a ProtoPie interactive prototype with full animations before any user has seen the basic flow. Wastes days on polish that testing may invalidate entirely.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Handoff Artifacts">
    <p>When handing off to development, include: prototype link (interactive reference), screen specs (measurements), interaction specs (behavior definitions), assets (icons/images), component library reference, and documented edge cases (error states, empty states).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document what was NOT prototyped and why.</statement>
      <rationale>Prevents stakeholder scope creep during handoff; sets correct expectations for what remains unvalidated.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/prototype-plan.md"/>
    <link path="templates/testing-notes.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
