<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Consistency and Standards Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Consistency and Standards application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-five-layers-covered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The audit MUST cover all five layers: internal, external, visual, functional, verbal. Partial-layer audits are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Single-layer audits miss the orthogonal failure modes; visual-only audits ignore terminology drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-variation-counted" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every audited element MUST carry a numeric variation count. "Many" / "lots" is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Numeric counts make the gap measurable and the consolidation outcome verifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-impact-prioritised" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consolidation recommendations MUST be ranked by user impact (frequency × visibility × confusion risk). Unranked lists are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Unranked lists devolve to "low-hanging fruit first" and miss the high-impact buried-but-rare cases.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-industry-conventions-checked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>External-layer findings MUST cite the platform convention (iOS HIG section, Material spec, WCAG criterion) the product violates.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Citing the convention makes the recommendation reviewable; uncited claims become opinion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-design-system-codified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every Must-fix finding MUST be paired with a design-system entry (token, component, or pattern). Findings without codification are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Without codification the same drift recurs next quarter; the system entry is the durable fix.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-31 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
