<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Consistency and Standards — Framework and Implementation">
  <summary>Five consistency types, the prioritization hierarchy, and concrete implementation patterns for visual, functional, and verbal layers.</summary>

  <section title="Consistency Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply consistency across all five layers: internal (within product), external (with platform/industry), visual (appearance), functional (behavior), and verbal (language).</statement>
      <rationale>Addressing only visual consistency while ignoring verbal consistency still forces users to relearn terminology between sections — each layer independently increases cognitive load when violated.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Consistency Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>When internal and external conventions conflict, always defer to industry conventions first, then platform conventions, then product family conventions.</statement>
      <rationale>Users bring expectations from the wider ecosystem. Violating well-established industry patterns to enforce internal uniqueness always costs more in user confusion than it gains in brand distinctiveness.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1. Industry conventions (highest priority)</item>
      <item>2. Platform conventions (iOS HIG, Material Design)</item>
      <item>3. Product family conventions (sibling products)</item>
      <item>4. Internal application conventions</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Visual Consistency Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a single canonical color, size, and spacing value for each semantic role and apply it without exception.</statement>
      <rationale>Even one exception trains designers to treat the system as optional, accelerating drift. The value of a token system is in its 100% adoption.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Primary action: always #0066CC. Destructive action: always #CC0000. Success: always #00CC66. Warning: always #FFCC00. Spacing base unit: 8px; all margins are multiples (8, 16, 24, 32).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Functional Consistency Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>The same gesture or interaction must produce the same result everywhere in the product without exception.</statement>
      <rationale>If swipe-left deletes in one list but navigates in another, users cannot build a reliable mental model and will trigger unintended actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Logo click always goes to home. Back button always goes to previous page. Search always in top area. Single click selects; double click opens/edits.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Verbal Consistency Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose one term per concept and enforce it across all UI text, documentation, and support content — no synonyms in the same product.</statement>
      <rationale>Using "Create" on one screen and "Add" on another makes users wonder if they are different operations. One term per concept eliminates that doubt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Create (not Add/New/Insert). Delete (not Remove/Trash/Erase). Edit (not Modify/Change/Update). Save (not Store/Apply/Confirm). Success (not Done/Complete/OK). Error (not Failed/Problem/Issue).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Measuring Consistency">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure consistency by counting distinct style variants for each UI element, not by subjective assessment of whether things "look consistent".</statement>
      <rationale>Subjective assessment is not repeatable and cannot track improvement over time. Counting variants (3 button styles found, target 1) produces a trackable metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
