<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Feedback Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Pipeline turning scattered inbound feedback (support, NPS, app-store, sales, social) into ranked product themes via fixed taxonomy, segment-weighted scoring, and close-loop tracking.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="single-canonical-store" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All feedback channels (support, NPS, app-store, sales, social, in-app widget) MUST normalize into one canonical store with {source, date, user_id, segment, plan_tier, verbatim, classification} per item.</statement>
      <rationale source="Productboard / Canny implementation patterns">Multi-store feedback gets re-summarized by each consumer; canonical store enables segment-weighted ranking and de-dup.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="fixed-taxonomy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Classification MUST use a fixed published taxonomy (&lt;=30 leaves, &lt;=3 levels). New categories require a quarterly taxonomy-review and migration of past items.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — feedback-classification audits">Drift in taxonomy breaks trend lines and makes recurring themes look like new ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="segment-weighted-ranking" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Theme priority MUST factor segment_ARR × retention_risk × frequency. Raw vote counts alone are forbidden — they over-weight enterprise-customer power users.</statement>
      <rationale source="B2B SaaS prioritization literature">Raw counts privilege the loudest segment; ARR × retention reflects business impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="close-loop-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Items flagged 'will-do' or 'under-consideration' MUST trigger a close-loop email to the requester within 14 days. Items flagged 'won't-do' MUST log a rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer feedback research — close-loop impact">Without close-loop, requesters disengage and the feedback channel decays.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-theme-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Once per month the PM MUST review the top 10 themes (segment-weighted) and link each to a backlog item, kill decision, or explicit deferral with rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Productboard / Canny operational patterns">Themes without monthly disposition pile up; the channel becomes a complaint mailbox, not a decision input.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — pre-PMF with &lt;5 items/week; compliance-bound feedback awaiting DPA review; sentiment-only loop without commitment to act; single-channel vendor-AI product), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
