<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pipeline" title="Feedback Management Pipeline">
  <summary>Defines the six-stage feedback pipeline (Collect → Categorize → Analyze → Prioritize → Act → Close Loop), feedback source quality matrix, and fixed taxonomy rules.</summary>

  <section title="Feedback Sources">
    <list>
      <item>Support tickets: high volume, high quality (real blocking issues).</item>
      <item>In-app feedback: medium volume, medium quality (prompted, context-rich).</item>
      <item>App store reviews: medium volume, mixed quality (public, visible to prospects).</item>
      <item>Social media: variable volume, variable quality (unsolicited, context-poor).</item>
      <item>Sales calls: low volume, high quality (prospect-level, high intent).</item>
      <item>NPS surveys: medium volume, medium quality (prompted, structured).</item>
      <item>User interviews: low volume, very high quality (solicited, in-depth).</item>
      <item>Analytics: high volume, high quality for behavioral patterns.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Fixed Taxonomy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin the taxonomy in every triage prompt as a closed enum and validate all agent output against it. Never allow the agent to invent new tags.</statement>
      <rationale>Taxonomy drift makes aggregation impossible; "billing" on Monday becomes "pricing" on Friday, destroying trend analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Type: bug | request | enhancement | confusion | praise | complaint.</item>
      <item>Topic: onboarding | core-A | core-B | billing | integrations | performance | other.</item>
      <item>Segment: free | solo | pro | geek | unknown.</item>
      <item>Sentiment: positive | neutral | negative.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always store the original verbatim alongside tags. Never let the agent paraphrase the user's words — re-tagging later is impossible without the source string.</statement>
      <rationale>Close-loop emails that paraphrase the user's original complaint sound robotic and erode trust; the exact quote is irreplaceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Six-Stage Pipeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 1 — Centralize: maintain one canonical feedback store (Productboard, Canny, Linear, or Notion). Auto-import from all active sources; no channel-exclusive silos.</statement>
      <rationale>Feedback scattered across channels prevents pattern detection and creates unequal attention between loud (social) and quiet (support ticket) channels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 2 — Triage: categorize each item individually, not in batch. Require a confidence field; route items below 0.7 confidence to a human queue.</statement>
      <rationale>Batch triage hides per-item confidence and causes the model to over-cluster; individual processing surfaces edge cases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 3 — Aggregate: weight aggregations by ARR / retention risk / segment, not raw mention count. A silent enterprise account outweighs 10 vocal free-tier users.</statement>
      <rationale>Mention-count aggregation reproduces the squeaky-wheel bias; segment weighting aligns feedback priority with business impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 4 — Prioritize: link feedback themes to backlog items using RICE or equivalent; record "build / won't do / need more info / already planned" decision for every significant theme.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a link between feedback and backlog, themes are acknowledged but never acted on; the explicit four-option decision forces a documented choice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 5 — Act: when a decision is made, assign an owner and a target sprint or explicit deferral date. Themes without owners are never shipped.</statement>
      <rationale>Ownership without a deadline produces indefinite deferral; the sprint assignment is the commitment mechanism.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stage 6 — Close Loop: notify requesters when their feedback ships, is declined (with honest reason), or needs more information. Keep close-loop emails as drafts for human review — never auto-send.</statement>
      <rationale>Auto-sent close-loop emails that misquote or misdate the user's original feedback destroy trust faster than silence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/triage-feedback.sh">Bash script: pipes feedback items to Claude Haiku triage agent, emits JSONL with type/topic/segment/sentiment/confidence per item.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/feedback-log.md">Feedback log template with by-category summary, top requests, and trends section.</reference>
</text>
