<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Feedback Management Examples">
  <summary>Monthly feedback review cycle and app-store review response strategy as concrete worked examples of the six-stage pipeline in action.</summary>

  <section title="Monthly Feedback Review">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Total feedback: 150 items across all channels in the month.</note>
      <note>Top category by volume: Integrations (40%). Top request: Slack integration (25 mentions across support, social, and in-app).</note>
      <note>Emerging trend: mobile app requests increasing from 5% to 15% share over 3 months.</note>
      <note>Actions taken: Slack integration added to Q2 roadmap (25 Slack requesters notified by email); mobile scheduled for discovery (3 interviews booked); 3 billing bugs fixed (resolved items closed in register).</note>
      <note>Close loop: email sent to the 25 users who requested Slack integration, quoting their original verbatim and linking to the roadmap.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="App Store Review Response Strategy">
    <example type="good">
      <note>1-2 star reviews: respond within 24 hours, apologize and offer help, move to direct support channel. Log the core complaint in the feedback register.</note>
      <note>3-4 star reviews: thank, ask "what would make it 5 stars?", note the answer in the feedback log.</note>
      <note>5-star reviews: thank, consider for referral or marketing testimonial (with permission).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-creating backlog items from every feedback ticket without a clustering step.</description>
      <reason>Individual feedback tickets flood the backlog with 1-mention items; require at least 3 mentions of the same theme before issue creation to avoid noise.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Building features based on mention count from free-tier users while ignoring silent enterprise accounts.</description>
      <reason>Free-tier vocal users generate disproportionate feedback volume but represent a fraction of revenue; segment weighting by ARR corrects this bias.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Never responding to users about the fate of their requests.</description>
      <reason>Users who receive no close-loop response assume their feedback is ignored; declining to build a feature with an honest reason maintains more trust than silence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Feedback stored in multiple disconnected tools (Slack, email, Notion, support tool) with no central aggregation.</description>
      <reason>Siloed feedback prevents pattern detection; the same critical issue can appear in support, social, and NPS simultaneously without any human seeing the full picture.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
