<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="feedback-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for feedback-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM categorization drifts: same feedback labelled "billing" on Monday and "pricing" on Friday unless the taxonomy is pinned in the prompt and validated.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin the taxonomy in both the system prompt and in a JSON schema; reject any agent output with tags outside the enum.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Duplicate detection on embeddings is fragile for short messages ("doesn't work", "broken") — needs context window from the source thread.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require a length floor (~30 chars) or include thread context in the dedup agent's input.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Aggregation by mention count rewards the loud minority; weight by segment ARR + retention risk or it just reproduces the squeaky-wheel bias.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a segment-weighted secondary ranking. Top requests = [sum(mentions × weight_segment × weight_arr)].</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-generated "you asked, we built" emails sound robotic and erode trust if the user's verbatim is paraphrased away.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Keep the original quote in the email body. Close-loop drafts must reference verbatim. Keep drafts as *drafts* in the human's inbox, never auto-send.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Feedback from prospects (sales calls) and churned users cannot be replied to via the same close-the-loop flow; agents conflate them unless lifecycle stage is a required tag.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lifecycle stage must be a required input field (prospect, active, churned). Route each through different close-loop templates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
