<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-influencer-marketing Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-influencer-marketing. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start with micro-influencers (10K–100K followers). They deliver the best ROI for most brands: high audience trust, lower cost, accessible for outreach, and real engagement. Scale to mid or macro only after proving unit economics on micro.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Macro influencers have large reach but lower engagement rates and high cost. Micro-influencers in a specific niche have audiences that trust them as peers, not as celebrities — critical for purchase decisions in prosumer and SaaS products.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Gate every candidate on engagement rate before any other evaluation. Below-average engagement for the platform is disqualifying regardless of follower count.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Follower count can be purchased; engagement cannot be faked at scale without detection. A 100K-follower account with 0.8% engagement has a smaller real audience than a 20K-follower account with 4% engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Flag and reject any candidate with: a sudden follower spike in the past 30 days, engagement rate below platform good-threshold, generic bot-pattern comments ("Nice post!", single emoji), or more than 30% sponsored content in the last 30 posts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">These are reliable signals of purchased followers or audience burnout. Paying for reach that doesn't exist produces zero conversions regardless of brief quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference a specific recent post by URL in every outreach message. Generic "I love your work on [TOPIC]" openers are flagged as mass outreach and ignored. Include a specific line from their content and explain why it resonated.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Creators receive dozens of generic pitches daily. Proof of genuine engagement raises response rates 3–5x over templated outreach. Platform DM algorithms also rate-limit accounts sending identical messages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not send outreach DMs autonomously via agent. Instagram and TikTok shadow-ban accounts exceeding ~50 DMs per day. Queue outreach for human confirmation before sending.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Platform anti-spam systems cannot distinguish AI-bulk outreach from legitimate outreach. Account shadow-banning eliminates the brand's ability to reach any creator on that platform, not just the flagged campaign.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For unproven creators, start with an affiliate + gifting hybrid. Convert top performers (with 60 days of data) to flat-fee retainers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hybrid compensation aligns incentives — creators earn more when they drive results. Flat fees without performance data create risk: you are paying for reach that may not convert.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Negotiate UGC reuse rights upfront: "90-day paid-social usage rights." Creator content reused in Meta/TikTok ads delivers 3–5x ROAS because it carries authentic social proof signals that native-brand ads lack.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">UGC rights are cheapest to acquire during the original negotiation. Post-campaign rights requests are often refused or priced at 2–5x the original content fee.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every campaign brief must state: "All posts must include #ad or #sponsored in the first three hashtags or in visible text above the fold." Verify this in the post before and after go-live.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">FTC Endorsement Guides require clear and conspicuous disclosure. #ad buried in 30 hashtags or disclosed only in caption overflow does not meet the "conspicuous" standard. Non-compliance creates FTC investigation risk for both brand and creator.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign a unique discount code per creator (e.g., SARAH15). Codes survive iOS 14.5 tracking loss and cookie deprecation, provide clear per-creator attribution, and double as a customer incentive.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">UTM links break when users navigate between apps or share links. A creator-specific code is the most reliable cross-channel attribution signal available without third-party SDKs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Focus on conversions and ROI as primary metrics, not reach and impressions. "2M impressions" with zero conversions means audience did not match ICP.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vanity reach metrics inflate program perception but do not reflect business value. A 230K-reach campaign that produced 130 conversions outperforms a 2M-reach campaign with 20 conversions at any LTV.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
