<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-discovery-and-vetting" title="Influencer Discovery and Vetting">
  <summary>Finding micro-influencers and vetting them by engagement quality, audience match, and fraud signals before outreach.</summary>

  <section title="Influencer Tiers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with micro-influencers (10K–100K followers). They deliver the best ROI for most brands: high audience trust, lower cost, accessible for outreach, and real engagement. Scale to mid or macro only after proving unit economics on micro.</statement>
      <rationale>Macro influencers have large reach but lower engagement rates and high cost. Micro-influencers in a specific niche have audiences that trust them as peers, not as celebrities — critical for purchase decisions in prosumer and SaaS products.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Tier reference: Nano (1K–10K, high engagement, limited reach), Micro (10K–100K, best ROI starting point), Mid (100K–500K, good reach but higher cost), Macro (500K–1M, expensive), Mega (1M+, very expensive, less engaged).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Vetting Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Gate every candidate on engagement rate before any other evaluation. Below-average engagement for the platform is disqualifying regardless of follower count.</statement>
      <rationale>Follower count can be purchased; engagement cannot be faked at scale without detection. A 100K-follower account with 0.8% engagement has a smaller real audience than a 20K-follower account with 4% engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Engagement rate benchmarks: Instagram good 2–3% / great 4%+; TikTok good 3–5% / great 8%+; Twitter/X good 1–2% / great 3%+; YouTube good 2–4% / great 5%+.</p>
    <p>Evaluation criteria weights: audience match (30%), engagement rate (25%), content quality (20%), brand safety (15%), professionalism/reliability (10%).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag and reject any candidate with: a sudden follower spike in the past 30 days, engagement rate below platform good-threshold, generic bot-pattern comments ("Nice post!", single emoji), or more than 30% sponsored content in the last 30 posts.</statement>
      <rationale>These are reliable signals of purchased followers or audience burnout. Paying for reach that doesn't exist produces zero conversions regardless of brief quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Discovery Methods">
    <p>Manual: search relevant hashtags, look at who your existing customers follow, check competitor collaboration credits.</p>
    <p>Tools: Modash, HypeAuditor, Upfluence for discovery and fraud detection; BuzzSumo for content creators; SparkToro for audience research.</p>
    <p>Outbound: Twitter/X bio search for niche terms, YouTube channel search, newsletter directories.</p>
    <reference path="templates/score-creator.py">Creator scoring script: engagement rate + audience match + niche fit + content quality; flags suspect accounts</reference>
  </section>
</text>
