<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-outreach-and-execution" title="Influencer Outreach, Compensation, and Campaign Execution">
  <summary>Personalized outreach structure, compensation models, campaign brief requirements, and FTC compliance rules.</summary>

  <section title="Outreach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reference a specific recent post by URL in every outreach message. Generic "I love your work on [TOPIC]" openers are flagged as mass outreach and ignored. Include a specific line from their content and explain why it resonated.</statement>
      <rationale>Creators receive dozens of generic pitches daily. Proof of genuine engagement raises response rates 3–5x over templated outreach. Platform DM algorithms also rate-limit accounts sending identical messages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not send outreach DMs autonomously via agent. Instagram and TikTok shadow-ban accounts exceeding ~50 DMs per day. Queue outreach for human confirmation before sending.</statement>
      <rationale>Platform anti-spam systems cannot distinguish AI-bulk outreach from legitimate outreach. Account shadow-banning eliminates the brand's ability to reach any creator on that platform, not just the flagged campaign.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Compensation">
    <rule>
      <statement>For unproven creators, start with an affiliate + gifting hybrid. Convert top performers (with 60 days of data) to flat-fee retainers.</statement>
      <rationale>Hybrid compensation aligns incentives — creators earn more when they drive results. Flat fees without performance data create risk: you are paying for reach that may not convert.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Compensation models: gifting (product awareness, free product), flat fee (specific deliverables), affiliate (commission per sale, performance-based), revenue share (% ongoing for long-term), hybrid (flat + affiliate).</p>
    <p>Approximate rate benchmarks (Instagram post / YouTube video): Nano $50–250 / $200–500; Micro $250–1K / $500–2K; Mid $1K–5K / $2K–10K; Macro $5K–25K / $10K–50K.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Negotiate UGC reuse rights upfront: "90-day paid-social usage rights." Creator content reused in Meta/TikTok ads delivers 3–5x ROAS because it carries authentic social proof signals that native-brand ads lack.</statement>
      <rationale>UGC rights are cheapest to acquire during the original negotiation. Post-campaign rights requests are often refused or priced at 2–5x the original content fee.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="FTC Compliance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every campaign brief must state: "All posts must include #ad or #sponsored in the first three hashtags or in visible text above the fold." Verify this in the post before and after go-live.</statement>
      <rationale>FTC Endorsement Guides require clear and conspicuous disclosure. #ad buried in 30 hashtags or disclosed only in caption overflow does not meet the "conspicuous" standard. Non-compliance creates FTC investigation risk for both brand and creator.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/campaign-brief.md">Campaign brief template including FTC disclosure requirement and approval process</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Attribution">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign a unique discount code per creator (e.g., SARAH15). Codes survive iOS 14.5 tracking loss and cookie deprecation, provide clear per-creator attribution, and double as a customer incentive.</statement>
      <rationale>UTM links break when users navigate between apps or share links. A creator-specific code is the most reliable cross-channel attribution signal available without third-party SDKs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/tracking-sheet.md">Influencer tracking spreadsheet template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
