<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="growth-influencer-marketing Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for growth-influencer-marketing as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs hallucinate engagement rates and follower counts when asked to "check" a creator.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models have no real-time data. Always pull live data via API (Modash, HypeAuditor) or scraping. Never trust a model's asserted metrics.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-generated personalization produces generic patterns even when prompted for specificity ("I love your work on [TOPIC]").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require the agent to quote a specific post URL and a specific line from that post. Generic pattern outputs are worse than no outreach — they create negative brand impressions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping brand-safety filtering before approving a creator for outreach.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Scan last 30 post captions for political, NSFW, or controversy-adjacent terms before any outreach or content approval. One brand-safety incident can override a full quarter of positive campaign results.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Quoting USD-only rates to creators in India, Brazil, or the Philippines without local-currency equivalent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mismatched expectations from currency confusion break deals. Agents should output both USD and local currency for any creator outside the US, EU, or UK.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
