<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-measurement-and-examples" title="Influencer Campaign Measurement and Case Examples">
  <summary>Key metrics with targets, SaaS and e-commerce case examples with ROI, and AI-agent limitations for influencer workflows.</summary>

  <section title="Key Metrics">
    <p>Metrics and targets: Reach (audience exposure, goal-dependent), Engagement rate (content resonance, above platform average), Click-through (interest signal, above 1%), Conversions (business impact, goal-dependent), CPM (cost efficiency, below $20), ROI (overall return, above 2x).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Focus on conversions and ROI as primary metrics, not reach and impressions. "2M impressions" with zero conversions means audience did not match ICP.</statement>
      <rationale>Vanity reach metrics inflate program perception but do not reflect business value. A 230K-reach campaign that produced 130 conversions outperforms a 2M-reach campaign with 20 conversions at any LTV.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/campaign-report.md">Post-campaign report template with per-influencer and summary metrics</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>SaaS product launch: 10 micro-influencers in productivity niche, YouTube video reviews, affiliate codes. Budget $15,000. Results: 800K total reach, 620 trial signups, $24 cost per acquisition, 2.5x ROI factoring LTV. Key driver: YouTube format enables extended demos that drive qualified signups.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>E-commerce product: 50 nano/micro Instagram influencers, gifting + affiliate (10% commission), UGC reuse rights negotiated. Budget $5,000 (product + fees). Results: 2M impressions, $75K in attributed sales, 15x ROI. Key driver: gifting hybrid + UGC reuse in paid ads amplified reach without proportional spend.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs hallucinate engagement rates and follower counts when asked to "check" a creator.</description>
      <reason>Models have no real-time data. Always pull live data via API (Modash, HypeAuditor) or scraping. Never trust a model's asserted metrics.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-generated personalization produces generic patterns even when prompted for specificity ("I love your work on [TOPIC]").</description>
      <reason>Require the agent to quote a specific post URL and a specific line from that post. Generic pattern outputs are worse than no outreach — they create negative brand impressions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping brand-safety filtering before approving a creator for outreach.</description>
      <reason>Scan last 30 post captions for political, NSFW, or controversy-adjacent terms before any outreach or content approval. One brand-safety incident can override a full quarter of positive campaign results.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Quoting USD-only rates to creators in India, Brazil, or the Philippines without local-currency equivalent.</description>
      <reason>Mismatched expectations from currency confusion break deals. Agents should output both USD and local currency for any creator outside the US, EU, or UK.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
