<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-trend-lifecycle" title="Trend Lifecycle and STEEP Framework">
  <summary>Trend types, lifecycle stages, optimal entry timing, and the STEEP scoring rubric for evaluating trend viability.</summary>

  <section title="Trend Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every trend as Fad (weeks-months), Trend (2-5 years), Megatrend (decades), or Shift (permanent) before scoring it — solopreneur sweet spot is the Trend category.</statement>
      <rationale>Fads do not sustain a business. Megatrends and Shifts are too broad to carve a defensible niche quickly. 2-5 year trends offer the largest opportunity window relative to required investment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Fad: weeks to months (fidget spinners, NFT art)</item>
      <item>Trend: 2-5 years (remote work tooling, no-code platforms)</item>
      <item>Megatrend: decades (aging population, climate adaptation)</item>
      <item>Shift: permanent (internet adoption, mobile-first)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Lifecycle Stages and Timing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enter just before mainstream adoption — after the Early Adopter stage confirms demand but before incumbents have locked distribution.</statement>
      <rationale>Innovator stage: too early, no market. Late mainstream: commoditization and shrinking margins. The Early-to-Mainstream inflection is where CAC is still low and pricing power exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Innovator: define category — risk: too early, no market</item>
      <item>Early adopter: high margins — risk: must educate the market</item>
      <item>Early mainstream: growth — risk: competition increasing (optimal entry point)</item>
      <item>Late mainstream: volume — risk: commoditization</item>
      <item>Decline: niche/legacy — risk: shrinking market</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="STEEP Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the STEEP framework (Social, Technology, Economic, Environmental, Political) to every trend before scoring; accept "n/a" for irrelevant dimensions rather than padding.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents fill all five STEEP cells even when Environmental is irrelevant — forcing irrelevant cells produces noise that inflates the score. Explicit "n/a" is honest and faster to audit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Social: How are behaviors and values changing? Which demographics are shifting?</item>
      <item>Technology: What new tech enables this trend? What capabilities became cheap enough?</item>
      <item>Economic: What financial forces drive it? What cost arbitrages exist?</item>
      <item>Environmental: How does sustainability affect adoption? Are there regulatory tailwinds?</item>
      <item>Political: What regulations impact it? Which governments are accelerating or blocking?</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Trend Strength Score">
    <rule>
      <statement>Compute the weighted Trend Strength Score (growth rate 25%, adoption stage 20%, incumbent count 15%, investment activity 20%, personal fit 20%) before the counter-signal critic runs; treat any score above 4.0 as requiring an adversarial review pass.</statement>
      <rationale>Bullish-only pipelines recommend "pursue" on every trend. A high score without a counter-signal critic is a confirmation bias loop.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>AI Agents trend scored in 2024: Google Trends +500% in 6 months (growth 5/5), Early mainstream stage (stage 4/5), 50+ incumbents (incumbents 2/5), $2B+ funding (investment 5/5), personal fit varies by team (fit 3/5). Weighted total: 4.1/5 — triggers adversarial review.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Accepting a 5/5 score on all criteria without a single cited source URL — the rubric becomes a self-reinforcing fantasy, not a decision tool.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
