<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-signal-sources" title="Signal Sources for Trend Analysis">
  <summary>Technology, market, and consumer signal sources with known biases and collection tools for each.</summary>

  <section title="Technology Signals">
    <list>
      <item>Hacker News (Algolia API): developer sentiment and new-tool discussion — free, no key, 30-day window</item>
      <item>Product Hunt (GraphQL API): new products and category emergence — free tier available</item>
      <item>GitHub (REST API): star velocity as adoption proxy — filter by created date, sort by stars</item>
      <item>arXiv (pip install arxiv): paper counts as research-momentum signal — category + date filter</item>
      <item>VC blogs (RSS): investment thesis patterns — lagging but high-signal (a16z Big Ideas, etc.)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use GitHub star velocity (new repos in last 180 days + top star count) as an early technology-trend signal, not absolute star count.</statement>
      <rationale>Absolute star count rewards incumbents. Star velocity captures acceleration — the signal that matters for timing entry.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Market Signals">
    <list>
      <item>Google Trends (pytrends): search interest over time — smoothed on low-volume terms, splits on term renames</item>
      <item>Exploding Topics: curated emerging topics with growth rate — good seed source, Pro plan has API</item>
      <item>Crunchbase / PitchBook: funding velocity — paid API, hard gate if key missing (fail loudly)</item>
      <item>LinkedIn Jobs / Indeed: skill keyword volume — hiring volume is strongest lagging-validation signal</item>
      <item>Gartner Hype Cycle / Forrester: authoritative for B2B but lag inflection by 12-18 months</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Score deltas, not absolutes: last-month vs this-month change in HN hits / star velocity beats raw counts.</statement>
      <rationale>Absolute counts reward historical incumbents. Month-over-month deltas surface accelerating momentum regardless of baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Consumer Signals">
    <list>
      <item>Reddit (PRAW): subreddit subscriber growth and post velocity — free API, strong for validating intensity</item>
      <item>TikTok Creative Center: emerging consumer behaviors — limited API, scrape with care</item>
      <item>Amazon bestsellers: product category shifts — no API, manual or Playwright scrape</item>
      <item>App Store rankings: category leader emergence — Apptopia/Sensor Tower API for trend data</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Source Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Letting the agent pick its own sources for numeric evidence.</description>
      <reason>Unconstrained source selection collapses to "search Google, cite first SEO-spam page". Pin the allow-list of authoritative sources in the system prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using Google Trends on a low-volume term without checking if the term was recently renamed.</description>
      <reason>"AI agent" and "agentic AI" split the trend curve. Synonym-merge before scoring to avoid treating the same trend as two different signals.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating a single viral HN or Reddit thread as a trend confirmation.</description>
      <reason>Require &gt;= 3 independent sources before stage-promoting a trend. One viral post is a data point, not a trend.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
