<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="search-everywhere-optimization">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>content-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Multi-platform visibility for Google, ChatGPT, Perplexity, YouTube, TikTok. GEO = being cited by AI; AEO = AI-extractable content structure.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>geo</tag>
      <tag>aeo</tag>
      <tag>ai-search</tag>
      <tag>content-optimization</tag>
      <tag>schema-markup</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Search Everywhere Optimization (GEO / AEO)</title>

    <summary>Multi-platform visibility strategy targeting Google, ChatGPT, Perplexity, YouTube, and TikTok simultaneously. GEO (Generative Engine Optimization) focuses on being the source AI engines cite; AEO (Answer Engine Optimization) structures content so AI systems extract and surface it. The core rule: every H2/H3 heading should be a question answered directly in the first paragraph beneath it.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Traditional SEO targets only Google ranked links. LLM-powered engines (ChatGPT, Perplexity) now handle 400M+ weekly queries and are projected to overtake traditional search by 2027. Content that AI engines cannot extract and cite loses share regardless of Google rank. Content updated within 30 days gets 3.2x more AI citations (Semrush research).</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Publishing content that should be cited by AI engines in addition to ranking in Google.</item>
        <item>Auditing existing content library for GEO/AEO readiness.</item>
        <item>Creating new content targeted at AI Overview inclusion or featured snippets.</item>
        <item>Building brand entity presence across the web (schema, consistent mentions).</item>
        <item>Monitoring AI share of voice and citation frequency for a brand or product.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Purely transactional/local content (restaurant menu, service area page) — local SEO dominates.</item>
        <item>Audience is exclusively on Amazon or TikTok — GEO/AEO has no lift there.</item>
        <item>Domain authority is near-zero — AI engines won't cite content without established presence.</item>
        <item>No content publishing cadence — GEO is a content strategy layer, not a substitute for content.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="geo-principles">
      <p>Multi-platform search landscape, GEO vs traditional SEO distinction, and core citation optimization principles.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Optimize for AI engine citation in addition to Google rank — treat them as separate but complementary signals.</statement>
        <rationale>ChatGPT and Perplexity handle 400M+ weekly queries combined. Semrush projects LLM traffic to overtake traditional Google search by end of 2027. Content invisible to AI engines loses share regardless of Google rank.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Google: 90% market share, 30% of queries now trigger AI Overviews.</item>
        <item>ChatGPT/Perplexity: 400M+ weekly users, citation-based results.</item>
        <item>YouTube: second-largest search engine, video SEO rules apply.</item>
        <item>TikTok: primary search for Gen Z, short-form video format.</item>
        <item>Amazon: product search, A9 algorithm, voice commerce ($80B by 2026).</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>GEO targets being the source AI engines cite, not just the link at position 1-10 in results.</statement>
        <rationale>Traditional SEO optimizes for ranked links. GEO optimizes for inclusion in AI-generated answers. These are different mechanisms: citations are based on authority, entity clarity, and content extractability.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Traditional SEO: rank in positions 1-10 for a keyword.</item>
        <item>GEO: get cited, referenced, or recommended in AI-generated answers.</item>
        <item>Topic targeting over keyword targeting (broader subject authority).</item>
        <item>Brand visibility and mentions over position rankings.</item>
        <item>Structured, extractable content over flowing prose.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Update content within 30 days — fresh content receives 3.2x more AI citations than stale content (Semrush research).</statement>
        <rationale>AI engines weight recency as an authority signal. Content that has not been updated signals potential staleness, reducing citation probability regardless of original quality.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Become an authoritative source: earn citations, backlinks, and earned media.</item>
        <item>Provide clear, structured information with direct answers.</item>
        <item>Use schema markup for machine readability.</item>
        <item>Create comprehensive, well-researched original content.</item>
        <item>Build consensus across owned and earned media.</item>
        <item>Focus on original insights, frameworks, and proprietary data.</item>
        <item>Build entity consistency: same brand name, product names, author names everywhere.</item>
      </list>

      <list>
        <item>AI Visibility Score: frequency of brand appearance in AI responses.</item>
        <item>Source Citations: times AI models reference or link to content.</item>
        <item>AI Share of Voice: % of relevant AI answers mentioning the brand.</item>
        <item>Time-to-Citation: days from publishing to first AI citation.</item>
      </list>

      <note>AI citation tracking requires paid tools (Otterly.AI, Profound, Semrush AI Visibility Toolkit). No free API tier exists for monitoring. Set up Google Alerts for brand mentions as a low-cost proxy.</note>
    </section>

    <section name="aeo-practices">
      <p>Content structure, schema types, and platform-specific practices for AI engine answer inclusion.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Structure every content page so each H2/H3 heading is a question and the first paragraph directly answers it within 2 sentences.</statement>
        <rationale>This is the highest-impact single change for AEO. AI engines extract the question-answer pair as a unit. Content that buries answers in the third paragraph is rarely cited even when technically correct.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Q&amp;A content structure">
        <note>H2: "What is GEO?" followed immediately by: "GEO (Generative Engine Optimization) is the practice of optimizing content to be cited by AI-powered search engines. It differs from traditional SEO by targeting inclusion in AI-generated answers rather than ranked link positions."</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Poor content structure">
        <note>H2: "Understanding GEO" followed by three paragraphs of background context before a definition appears. AI engines skip this content for cleaner sources.</note>
      </example>

      <list>
        <item>Short paragraphs (2-4 lines), bullet points, and tables for key data.</item>
        <item>Proper heading hierarchy (H1, H2, H3) — no skipped levels.</item>
        <item>Target featured snippets and AI Overviews on Google.</item>
        <item>Match "People Also Ask" query formats in subheadings.</item>
        <item>Provide direct, concise answers immediately after headings.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Implement FAQPage schema on all Q&amp;A content and HowTo schema on all tutorial content — these are explicitly consumed by voice search and AI engines.</statement>
        <rationale>FAQPage and HowTo schema are in the Speakable category that Google explicitly uses for voice search and AI Overview sourcing. They create a machine-readable signal that the content is answer-structured.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>FAQPage: Q&amp;A sections, "People Also Ask" content.</item>
        <item>HowTo: step-by-step tutorials, instructions.</item>
        <item>Article/BlogPosting: all editorial content with author and date.</item>
        <item>Organization + Person: brand and author entity definitions.</item>
        <item>BreadcrumbList: topic relationship signals.</item>
      </list>

      <reference path="templates/faq-schema.json">JSON-LD FAQPage schema template</reference>

      <list>
        <item>Google: SEO readiness + Helpful Content signals + schema markup.</item>
        <item>Perplexity: clarity, recency (within 30 days), external citations in content.</item>
        <item>ChatGPT: authority signals (backlinks, brand mentions) — behavior varies by model.</item>
      </list>

      <note>AI citation behavior is non-deterministic and changes with model updates. Optimizations made today may not hold in 3-6 months. Focus on durable signals: content quality, entity consistency, schema markup.</note>
    </section>

    <section name="implementation">
      <p>GEO audit criteria, schema deployment workflow, monitoring approach, and agent-specific gotchas.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Audit each content page on five criteria before publishing or updating. Fail on any criterion triggers a specific fix, not a general "improve content" note.</statement>
        <rationale>Vague audit feedback ("make it better") produces no action. Specific fail criteria produce specific fixes that can be verified and retested.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>1. Does each heading have a direct answer within 2 sentences? (Pass/Fail)</item>
        <item>2. Are there FAQ sections with question-format headings? (Pass/Fail)</item>
        <item>3. Is entity language consistent (brand name, product names, author name)? (Pass/Fail)</item>
        <item>4. Are there tables, bullet points, or numbered lists for key data? (Pass/Fail)</item>
        <item>5. Is there original data, framework, or insight an AI would cite? (Pass/Fail)</item>
      </list>

      <reference path="templates/prompt-geo-audit.txt">LLM prompt to run GEO/AEO audit on a content page</reference>

      <rule>
        <statement>Validate all JSON-LD schema with Google Rich Results Test before deployment — never deploy agent-generated schema without validation.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents produce syntactically plausible but semantically incorrect schema: wrong @type values, missing required fields, incorrect nesting. Invalid schema produces no rich results and may trigger Search Console errors.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Generate schema from template or agent.</item>
        <item>Validate JSON syntax (jsonlint.com or IDE).</item>
        <item>Test with Google Rich Results Test.</item>
        <item>Verify no conflicting schema definitions on the page.</item>
        <item>Deploy and monitor Search Console for errors.</item>
      </list>

      <list>
        <item>Otterly.AI or Profound: monthly AI citation check (paid).</item>
        <item>Google Alerts for brand name: free proxy for citation monitoring.</item>
        <item>Google Search Console: AI Overviews impression data (limited).</item>
        <item>Semrush AI Visibility Toolkit: AI share of voice tracking (paid).</item>
      </list>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent recommends "publish more content" without specifying content gaps as article titles and target queries.</description>
        <reason>Vague content volume recommendations are not actionable. Require the agent to output specific gaps as: article title, target query, and format (FAQ, HowTo, comparison).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent updates publication dates in metadata without updating the actual content.</description>
        <reason>AI engines and Google both detect content freshness via substantive changes, not metadata timestamps. A date update without content change provides no citation benefit.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent suggests entity relationships (brand associated with specific concepts or people) without verifying what AI engines currently associate with the brand.</description>
        <reason>Suggested entity relationships may not match the brand's current knowledge graph representation. Incorrect associations can confuse AI engine entity resolution.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/faq-schema.json" purpose="JSON-LD FAQPage schema template."/>
      <template path="templates/llms-txt.txt" purpose="llms.txt file template for AI crawler guidance."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-geo-audit.txt" purpose="LLM prompt to audit a content page for GEO/AEO readiness."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-faq-schema.txt" purpose="LLM prompt to generate FAQ schema from Q&amp;A pairs."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.semrush.com/blog/ai-visibility/"/>
      <link href="https://otterly.ai/"/>
      <link href="https://perplexity.ai/"/>
      <link href="https://schema.org/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
