<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="regulatory-compliance-2026 Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for regulatory-compliance-2026. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Inventory all product surfaces (site, app, kiosk, e-book) and map each to applicable regulations: ADA Title II (US, WCAG 2.1 AA, effective April 2026), EAA (EU, EN 301 549 / WCAG 2.1 AA, effective June 2025), AODA (Ontario, WCAG 2.0 AA, now), Section 508 (US Federal, WCAG 2.0 AA, now). Identify the earliest deadline and responsible team. Document applicability per surface.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Regulatory applicability varies by jurisdiction and product type (e-commerce vs. government vs. public sector). Mapping forces explicit decisions about which surfaces fall under which rules. The earliest deadline is your constraint.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat WCAG 2.2 AA as the design baseline even where 2.1 AA is the legal minimum. Automated checkers (axe-core, pa11y, Lighthouse) catch only 30–40% of WCAG issues. Human + assistive-technology (AT) testing with real users is mandatory. Never claim conformance without documented testing (manual + automated + AT user sessions).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">2.2 AA is the newer standard; upgrading later is more expensive than designing to it now. Automated tools miss context-dependent failures (form labels, reading order, focus management) that only humans testing with AT catch. Courts scrutinize "conformance" claims without testing evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Publish a dated accessibility statement that declares WCAG version + level, describes the testing methodology (manual, automated, AT users), provides a feedback channel (email, form, phone, TTY), and commits to remediation timeline. Update the statement quarterly or after major releases. Require legal/compliance review before publication.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dated statement shows good-faith effort and provides legal protection. Methodology specificity (not vague "we test") is critical for litigation defense. Feedback channel and commitment to remediation demonstrate ongoing care. Legal review prevents overstatement.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drive Claude to inventory product surfaces (sites, apps, e-books, kiosks), map each to applicable regulations, and produce a remediation backlog ordered by deadline + risk. A second agent runs axe-core / pa11y / Lighthouse against staging URLs and merges results into the backlog. A legal-review checkpoint validates the accessibility statement language before publication.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automation scales regulatory mapping and backlog generation. But legal sign-off on the statement (the public-facing artifact) prevents overstatement and liability.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
