<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Regulatory Compliance 2026 Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the 2026 accessibility-regulation compliance report. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="jurisdiction-mapping" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product surface (web, native app, kiosk, e-book) MUST be mapped to applicable regulations with named jurisdictions: ADA Title II (US public entities, WCAG 2.1 AA, April 2026), EAA (EU, EN 301 549 / WCAG 2.1 AA, June 2025), AODA (Ontario, WCAG 2.0 AA), Section 508 (US federal procurement, WCAG 2.0 AA). The earliest deadline is the constraint.</statement>
      <rationale source="ADA Title II Final Rule 2024; Directive (EU) 2019/882">Regulatory applicability varies by jurisdiction and product type; explicit mapping forces decisions about which surfaces fall under which rules and surfaces the binding deadline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="wcag-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>WCAG 2.2 AA is the design baseline; WCAG 2.1 AA is the legal minimum. Documents MUST cite the version and level explicitly; "AA-compliant" without version is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="W3C WCAG 2.2 Recommendation Oct 2023">Designing to 2.2 now avoids gap-closing later when regulations advance; un-versioned claims are unenforceable and litigation-exposed.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="statement-publication" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A dated accessibility statement MUST be published per public-facing surface, naming WCAG version + level, the testing methodology (manual + automated + AT-user), a feedback channel (email + phone + form), and a remediation commitment. Update quarterly or after every major release.</statement>
      <rationale source="ADA Title II Final Rule §35.200; EAA Annex V">Courts and regulators read the published statement as the surface's compliance posture; absence or staleness is treated as bad faith.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="methodology-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Conformance claims MUST be backed by documented testing: automated scan logs (axe / pa11y / Lighthouse), manual screen-reader/keyboard records, and at least one assistive-technology user session per major release. Automated-only conformance is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="WebAIM 2024 — automated tools detect 30-40% of WCAG issues">Automated tools cannot evaluate context-dependent failures (label clarity, reading order, focus management); claiming conformance without manual + AT evidence creates legal exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="overlay-prohibition" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Accessibility overlay widgets (AccessiBe, UserWay, audioEye in auto-fix mode) MUST NOT be deployed as a compliance strategy. Disable any inherited overlay before publishing the statement.</statement>
      <rationale source="2023-2024 US court rulings — Murphy v. Eyebobs et al.">Overlays have repeatedly lost in court and frequently break real assistive technology; they create liability rather than reducing it.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="cms-author-training" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Content authors (marketing, support, legal) MUST receive WCAG basics training (alt-text, heading order, link labels, color contrast) and be measured on a11y defects per release. Engineering alone cannot enforce.</statement>
      <rationale source="WebAIM Million 2024 — &gt;95% of homepages with violations">Most a11y violations enter through CMS-edited content, not engineering code; training is the lowest-cost gate.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
