<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Regulatory Compliance 2026 Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>4 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="jurisdiction-blind-spot" severity="high">
      <symptom>Compliance report covers ADA + EAA but the product also serves UK or Australian users; UK Equality Act 2010 or AU DDA 1992 obligations missed; regulator complaint after launch.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="GTM blind-spot — author assumed US/EU coverage = global">Author treated the US/EU snapshot as the universe; jurisdictional inventory was not derived from GTM.</root-cause>
      <fix>Pull active-market list from GTM / billing. Add UK-EQA, AU-DDA, JP-JIS-X-8341, CA-AODA rows whenever those markets ship. Default to inclusion; require justification to exclude.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="checkbox-conformance" severity="high">
      <symptom>WCAG 2.1 AA passes axe-core but real screen-reader users cannot complete primary tasks; lawsuit filed despite green dashboard.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="WebAIM 2024">Automated tools detect 30-40% of WCAG issues; context-dependent failures (focus order, label clarity, error recovery) only show up in manual + AT-user testing.</root-cause>
      <fix>Mandate manual screen-reader sweep per release and at-least-one AT-user session per major release. Conformance claims without that evidence are forbidden by the rule set.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="overlay-as-fix" severity="high">
      <symptom>Team installs AccessiBe / UserWay banner overlay and ticks "WCAG 2.1 AA". Real users disable the overlay; lawsuit cites broken keyboard nav introduced by the overlay.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Murphy v. Eyebobs 2023; multiple 2024 ADA suits">Overlays cannot fix structural a11y issues; they often break AT and create stronger legal evidence of negligence.</root-cause>
      <fix>Disable any overlay before publishing the statement. Set `overlay_widgets_disabled: true` in the report. Fix issues in source code, not via DOM overlay.</fix>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern id="statement-without-evidence" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Accessibility statement on the site claims "fully WCAG 2.1 AA compliant" but no testing methodology, dated audit, or feedback channel is named. Counsel flags this as bad-faith liability.</symptom>
      <root-cause source="Internal — legal-review checkpoint">Marketing wrote the statement; legal + a11y lead did not sign off; methodology + evidence were never inserted.</root-cause>
      <fix>Require `statement_published.methodology.{automated,manual,at_user}` flags + last_updated + feedback_channels. Block publication via validator when any required field is missing.</fix>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
