<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="regulatory-compliance-2026 Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for regulatory-compliance-2026 as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Regulations are jurisdictional; this methodology gives a US/EU snapshot but ignores UK Equality Act, Japanese JIS X 8341, Australian DDA, etc.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If your product serves Australia, Japan, or UK, research those standards separately. This methodology covers the largest markets (US + EU); add region-specific rules as your user base expands.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>The compliance checklist is necessary but not sufficient — passes don't preclude lawsuits.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Conformance certification provides evidence of good-faith effort, but does not guarantee immunity. Courts focus on whether the product is actually usable by disabled users, not checkbox compliance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>WCAG 2.1 AA is a floor; some agencies (US federal contracts, EU public sector) require 2.2 AA or AAA in places.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>High-risk surfaces (election sites, healthcare portals, financial services) may have stricter requirements. Check your sector's guidance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>"Statement published" can be a false-comfort metric — wrong claims of conformance increase legal exposure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An accessibility statement claiming WCAG 2.1 AA conformance without evidence of testing is worse than no statement (it's evidence of intent to deceive). Stake claims to actual testing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
