<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Accessibility Basics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Accessibility Basics methodology. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="pour-as-frame-not-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use POUR (Perceivable / Operable / Understandable / Robust) as a categorisation frame for findings — not as a 4-item checklist. Each finding is tagged with its POUR principle.</statement>
      <rationale source="w3.org/WAI/fundamentals/accessibility-intro/">Treating POUR as a checklist produces shallow audits because the four principles are categories of failure, not discrete tests.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pin-wcag-version-and-level" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every quick-check report pins WCAG version + level (default: &apos;WCAG 2.2 AA&apos;). Agents and humans MUST cite SC numbers (e.g., 1.4.3).</statement>
      <rationale source="w3.org/TR/WCAG22/">Agents conflate WCAG levels and produce mixed-level audits that obscure compliance status; WCAG 2.2 adds four AA criteria not in 2.1.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="automated-only-catches-30pct" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When reporting scanner findings, the report MUST also state &apos;scanner catches ≈30% of issues; manual + AT + user testing required&apos;. Standalone scanner reports are forbidden as the only artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="Deque + WebAIM coverage studies 2023">Agents overweight scanner output; the 30% ceiling is the empirical anchor for this rule.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="five-minute-quick-check" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-PR quick-check covers exactly 5 steps: tab through, 200% zoom, alt-text on one image, label on one input, axe DevTools run. Output is one report.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — a11y onboarding metrics">A bounded 5-step routine is what survives team adoption; longer checklists are skipped.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="placeholder-is-not-a-label" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Form inputs MUST have a visible, programmatically-associated `&lt;label for&gt;`. Placeholder text MUST NOT be used as the label substitute.</statement>
      <rationale source="w3.org/WAI/tutorials/forms/labels/">Screen readers announce the associated label on focus; placeholder disappears on input and fails SC 1.4.3 contrast.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent's context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-a11y-basics.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
