<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-wcag-principles" title="WCAG POUR Principles, Conformance Levels, and Evaluation Types">
  <summary>POUR framework, A/AA/AAA conformance requirements, four evaluation types and their coverage, and a five-minute quick-check protocol.</summary>

  <section title="POUR principles">
    <p>POUR is a teaching frame for categorizing accessibility issues, not a checklist. Treating it as a checklist produces shallow audits.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Perceivable: can users perceive all content? Examples: alt text for images, captions for video, colour contrast of 4.5:1 for text and 3:1 for UI components.</item>
      <item>Operable: can users operate all controls? Examples: full keyboard access, no keyboard traps, sufficient time limits, no seizure-inducing flashes.</item>
      <item>Understandable: can users understand content and UI? Examples: clear language, predictable navigation, error identification and suggestion.</item>
      <item>Robust: does it work with current and future assistive technology? Examples: valid HTML, correct ARIA usage, name-role-value on all custom components.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Conformance levels">
    <list>
      <item>Level A: minimum accessibility — must have. Blocking issues for all users with disabilities.</item>
      <item>Level AA: standard for most products — legal requirement in most jurisdictions (ADA, Section 508, AODA, EN 301 549). Target for all public-facing products.</item>
      <item>Level AAA: enhanced accessibility — ideal but not always achievable for all content types; target where possible.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin "WCAG 2.2 AA" in every prompt and audit specification. Agents conflate WCAG levels and produce mixed-level audits that obscure compliance status.</statement>
      <rationale>WCAG 2.2 adds four new success criteria not in 2.1; specifying the version prevents auditing against an outdated standard.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Evaluation types and coverage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Automated scanning catches approximately 30% of accessibility issues. Manual testing catches approximately 50%. Assistive-technology testing and user testing with disabled users are required for the remaining issues.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents overweight scanner output; the 30% ceiling is explicit and must be stated whenever scanner results are reported.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Automated testing (axe, pa11y, Lighthouse): continuous, catches structural issues (missing alt, label, contrast, heading order, duplicate IDs).</item>
      <item>Manual testing with keyboard-only navigation: catches focus traps, invisible focus indicators, interaction-order issues.</item>
      <item>Assistive technology testing (NVDA, VoiceOver, TalkBack): catches ARIA misuse, dynamic content not announced, custom widget behavior.</item>
      <item>User testing with disabled participants: catches task-completion barriers that no tool or heuristic predicts.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Five-minute quick-check protocol">
    <p>Run before any PR that touches UI:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Tab through the page: can you reach every interactive element? Is the focus indicator always visible?</item>
      <item>Zoom to 200%: is everything still usable? Does content reflow without horizontal scroll?</item>
      <item>Check one image: does the alt text convey the same information as the image?</item>
      <item>Check one form: are all labels visible, connected to inputs, and descriptive?</item>
      <item>Run axe DevTools: are there any critical or serious violations?</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
