<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-common-issues" title="Common Accessibility Issues with Code Examples">
  <summary>The most frequent accessibility failures in web code — form labels, image alt text, keyboard access, ARIA misuse — with before/after examples and antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Form labels">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every form input must have a visible, programmatically associated label. Placeholder text is not a label substitute: it disappears when typing and has insufficient contrast.</statement>
      <rationale>Screen readers announce the associated label on focus; without it, blind users cannot determine the field's purpose. Low-contrast placeholders fail SC 1.4.3.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="html"><![CDATA[
<input type="text" placeholder="Email">
]]></code>
      <note>No label; placeholder disappears on input; screen reader announces only type.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="html"><![CDATA[
<label for="email">Email address</label>
<input type="text" id="email" name="email" aria-describedby="email-hint">
<span id="email-hint">We'll never share your email.</span>
]]></code>
      <note>Visible label, programmatic association, hint text linked via aria-describedby.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Image alt text">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decorative images: empty alt="" plus role="presentation". Informative images: concise description of the information conveyed. Complex images: short alt plus a long description linked via aria-describedby.</statement>
      <rationale>Alt text must convey the same information as the image to a user who cannot see it; the correct pattern depends on the image's role in the page.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="html"><![CDATA[
<!-- Decorative image -->
<img src="decorative-line.png" alt="" role="presentation">

<!-- Informative image -->
<img src="chart.png" alt="Sales increased 25% in Q3 compared to Q2">

<!-- Complex image -->
<figure>
  <img src="diagram.png"
       alt="System architecture diagram"
       aria-describedby="diagram-desc">
  <figcaption id="diagram-desc">
    Three layers: presentation, business logic, and data.
    [Full description follows...]
  </figcaption>
</figure>
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="ARIA misuse antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding aria-label to a native element that already has an accessible name from its label element.</description>
      <reason>Duplicate accessible names confuse screen readers; the aria-label overrides the visible label, causing inconsistency for sighted screen-reader users.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using role="button" on a div element.</description>
      <reason>Native &lt;button&gt; provides keyboard activation (Enter and Space), implicit role, and focus management for free; div + role requires manual keyboard handler and is frequently incomplete.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding ARIA attributes to fix scanner failures without understanding the semantic model.</description>
      <reason>Bad ARIA is worse than no ARIA; it creates a false accessible name or role that misleads assistive technology into announcing incorrect information.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="CI gate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Wire axe-core into PR CI. A failing PR for a missing label is cheaper than a post-launch fix. Lint with eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y to catch issues at type time.</statement>
      <rationale>Accessibility debt compounds; catching issues at PR time costs minutes, at QA costs hours, and post-launch can cost litigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/a11y-ci.js">Playwright + axe-core CI gate for WCAG 2.2 AA across defined routes</reference>
  </section>
</text>
