<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-sections" title="Implementation Plan Required Sections">
  <summary>All required sections of an implementation-plan.md with purpose and structure for each.</summary>

  <section title="Document Header">
    <list>
      <item>Version, Design path, Status (Draft/In Progress/Complete), Author, Date, Project</item>
      <item>Reference Documents table: Constitution, Spec, Design, Contracts — same pattern as design.md</item>
      <item>Overview: 1-2 paragraphs with total tasks, token estimate, critical path complexity, wave count</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Prerequisites">
    <rule>
      <statement>List infrastructure, environment, code, and documentation prerequisites as explicit checkboxes before defining any tasks.</statement>
      <rationale>Executor agents that start task execution without checking prerequisites fail mid-execution when a database migration or auth middleware does not exist. Explicit prerequisites enable pre-flight validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Infrastructure: database running, Redis configured, external API keys obtained</item>
      <item>Environment: dev environment set up, env vars configured, access permissions</item>
      <item>Code Dependencies: base service class exists, auth middleware exists, test framework configured</item>
      <item>Documentation: spec.md status=Approved, design.md status=Approved</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dependency Graph">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build the dependency graph before the wave analysis table — the graph is the input to wave grouping; inverting the order produces incorrect waves.</statement>
      <rationale>Wave analysis groups tasks by dependency level. Without a correct dependency graph, tasks end up in waves that assume non-existent outputs, producing runtime failures when the executor tries to import from a file not yet created.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>FS (Finish-to-Start): TASK-002 starts when TASK-001 finishes (most common)</item>
      <item>SS (Start-to-Start): TASK-002 can start when TASK-001 starts</item>
      <item>FF (Finish-to-Finish): TASK-002 finishes when TASK-001 finishes</item>
      <item>Use arrow notation (TASK-001 → TASK-003) for agent-generated graphs; ASCII box diagrams are copied incorrectly</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Wave Analysis">
    <p>Table format: Wave | Tasks | Parallel | Dependencies | Est. Tokens
Wave 1: tasks with no dependencies — all can run in parallel.
Wave 2: tasks depending only on Wave 1 outputs.
Continue until all tasks assigned to a wave.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Each task entry must have: wave number, complexity (simple/normal/complex), token estimate, traces to AD-X and FR-X, depends-on list, blocks list, acceptance criteria, files table.</statement>
      <rationale>Executor agents reading sparse task entries make up missing context. The task entry in the implementation plan is the authoritative source the TASK_NNN.md file is generated from; missing fields produce incomplete task files.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Risk Assessment and Rollout">
    <list>
      <item>Risk table: Risk | Likelihood (Low/Med/High) | Impact (Low/Med/High) | Mitigation (concrete action)</item>
      <item>Contingency buffer: 20% added to token estimates</item>
      <item>Rollout: pre-deployment checklist, deployment steps, rollback plan, success criteria</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Risk mitigations must be concrete actions, not vague hedges ("monitor for errors" vs "alert on error rate &gt; 0.5% for 5 minutes").</statement>
      <rationale>Vague mitigations provide no actionable guidance when the risk materializes. Concrete mitigations specify the trigger condition, the response action, and who is responsible.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/impl-plan-template.md">Canonical implementation-plan.md template with all sections</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/validate-deps.sh">Topological sort validator — detect dependency cycles</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/extract-waves.py">Extract wave → tasks mapping from wave analysis table</reference>
</text>
