<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="vr-design-patterns Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the vr-design-patterns methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="stable-horizon-ground" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every VR scene MUST have a visible ground plane AND a stable horizon. Horizonless or constantly-rotating scenes are forbidden as the default.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta Quest comfort docs; Oculus VRC.PC.UX">Vestibular system anchors to ground + horizon; their absence is the leading cause of nausea.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="teleport-first-locomotion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default locomotion MUST be teleportation for novice or general audiences. Smooth locomotion MAY be available as a user-selectable option, never the default for new users.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta Quest comfort docs">Smooth locomotion triggers nausea in ~40% of novice users; teleport rates ~5%.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="world-anchored-ui" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Primary UI MUST be world-anchored or body-anchored, NOT head-locked. Head-locked HUD is reserved for safety telemetry only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple visionOS HIG; Meta Quest UI guidelines">Head-locked UI breaks immersion and triggers vestibular conflict.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="seated-mode-and-one-hand" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>App MUST ship a seated-mode toggle AND a one-handed control path. Both MUST be reachable from the main menu.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta VRC.PC.UX">Seated and one-handed paths are mandatory for accessibility and store approval.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="subtitles-default-on-discoverable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Subtitles MUST be available and discoverable via the comfort menu. Audio descriptions for visually-encoded meaning MUST be authored.</statement>
      <rationale source="XR Access Initiative; Apple visionOS HIG">Subtitles are an accessibility floor; absence excludes deaf and HoH users.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="snap-turn-default-comfort" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Turning MUST default to snap-turn for novice settings. Smooth turn MUST be user-selectable with documented angular-velocity cap.</statement>
      <rationale source="Meta Quest comfort docs">Smooth turn triggers more nausea than smooth locomotion; snap-turn is the safer default.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
