<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="seo">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>seo-manager</domain>
    <summary>Dual-optimization for search engines and AI assistants: technical SEO, on-page, hreflang, schema, llms.txt, Core Web Vitals, accessibility.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>seo</tag>
      <tag>aeo</tag>
      <tag>search-optimization</tag>
      <tag>schema-markup</tag>
      <tag>e-e-a-t</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>SEO &amp; AEO Mastery</title>
    <summary>Comprehensive SEO and AEO (Answer Engine Optimization) methodology covering technical SEO, on-page optimization, multilingual hreflang, schema markup, llms.txt, Core Web Vitals, accessibility, and social meta tags. Optimizes content for both traditional search engines (Google, Bing) and AI assistants (ChatGPT, Perplexity, Claude).</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Modern traffic comes from two distinct discovery paths: traditional crawl-index-rank and AI-assisted answer generation. Sites optimized for only one path miss the other entirely. The dual-optimization approach ensures visibility in both — the same structural clarity, authoritative content, and proper markup that satisfies Google's E-E-A-T also enables AI crawlers to cite and reference your content.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Running a full SEO audit on a new or existing site</item>
        <item>Implementing technical SEO foundations (robots.txt, sitemap, HTTPS, Core Web Vitals)</item>
        <item>Setting up multilingual sites with hreflang</item>
        <item>Adding schema markup (Article, Organization, FAQ, BreadcrumbList)</item>
        <item>Creating llms.txt for AI crawler guidance</item>
        <item>Optimizing for AI Overviews and featured snippets</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Content strategy decisions (use content-marketer methodology instead)</item>
        <item>Paid search campaigns (use ppc-manager)</item>
        <item>Link building (use growth-seo-link-building)</item>
        <item>When the site has no indexable pages yet — fix technical blockers first</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="dual-optimization-strategy">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Optimize content for both traditional search engines (Google, Bing) AND AI assistants (ChatGPT, Perplexity, Claude) simultaneously.</statement>
        <rationale>Both paths require clear structure, authoritative content, proper markup, and fast loading. The same technical quality that satisfies Google also enables AI crawlers to cite the content.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Coverage areas and key elements:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Technical: robots.txt, sitemap.xml, crawl budget, Core Web Vitals</item>
        <item>On-Page: semantic HTML, schema markup, headings, meta tags</item>
        <item>Multilingual: hreflang, URL structure, x-default</item>
        <item>AI/AEO: llms.txt, structured data, entity optimization</item>
        <item>Social: Open Graph, Twitter Cards, LinkedIn</item>
        <item>Accessibility: WCAG 2.2, ARIA, screen readers, semantic markup</item>
        <item>Performance: LCP &lt; 2.5s, INP &lt; 200ms, CLS &lt; 0.1</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="e-e-a-t-framework">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Signal Experience, Expertise, Authoritativeness, and Trustworthiness in content and site structure.</statement>
        <rationale>Google uses E-E-A-T as a quality evaluator. Missing any dimension — particularly Trustworthiness (HTTPS, contact info, privacy policy) — reduces ranking potential regardless of content quality.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Experience: first-hand knowledge, case studies, original data</item>
        <item>Expertise: author credentials, depth of content, citations</item>
        <item>Authoritativeness: backlinks, brand mentions, industry recognition</item>
        <item>Trustworthiness: HTTPS, contact info, privacy policy, no deceptive patterns</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools">
      <list>
        <item>Google Search Console — indexing, Core Web Vitals, coverage errors</item>
        <item>PageSpeed Insights — performance analysis and CWV scoring</item>
        <item>Rich Results Test — schema markup validation</item>
        <item>Ahrefs / Semrush — backlinks, keywords, competitive audits</item>
        <item>Screaming Frog — technical crawling and link audit</item>
        <item>WAVE — accessibility testing</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-selection">
      <list>
        <item>Keyword research and data extraction: haiku — list compilation, lookup tasks</item>
        <item>Analyzing SEO metrics and patterns: sonnet — comparative analysis</item>
        <item>Developing SEO strategy and market positioning: opus — complex strategy formulation</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </content>
</methodology>
