<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-overview" title="Overview and core principle">
  <summary>The orchestrator coordinates phase-specific subagents by handing each one a path to a versioned prompt file plus a small parameter block, instead of re-typing instructions inline.</summary>

  <section title="Core principle">
    <rule>
      <statement>The orchestrator MUST NOT inline long instructions into the `Agent` tool's `prompt` argument. It dispatches the subagent with a short message that points at a file under `prompts/` and supplies a small key-value parameter block.</statement>
      <rationale>Behaviour drifts when the same instructions are paraphrased every run. Versioned prompt files make each phase a deterministic capability and let prompts be reviewed, diffed in git, and improved over time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Each subagent prompt file MUST be self-contained — it briefs the subagent like a colleague who has not seen the parent conversation.</statement>
      <rationale>Subagents spawned via the `Agent` tool do not inherit the parent's context window. A prompt that assumes shared state silently degrades into vague instructions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Role split">
    <p>The orchestrator does three things only: decides which phase runs next, decides what can run in parallel, and confirms sensitive actions (push, deploy, destructive ops) with the user. Everything else lives in subagents.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Orchestrator: composition, parallelism decisions, user confirmations, quota gating.</item>
      <item>Subagents: domain work behind a single prompt file each.</item>
      <item>Reference docs: cross-cutting knowledge (git conventions, screenshot strategy, delivery channel auth).</item>
      <item>Playbooks: per-delivery-surface specializations (faion-net-be, faion-net-fe, knowledge, storybook, mediamanager-fe, ETL).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Tracker shape (faion-network)">
    <p>The pattern uses the project's `.aidocs/` SDD lifecycle as the source of truth. Each "ticket" is a feature folder whose status is its location in the lifecycle:</p>
    <list>
      <item>`.aidocs/&lt;project&gt;/backlog/&lt;feature-id&gt;/` — accepted but not started.</item>
      <item>`.aidocs/&lt;project&gt;/todo/&lt;feature-id&gt;/` — ready for planning / execution.</item>
      <item>`.aidocs/&lt;project&gt;/in-progress/&lt;feature-id&gt;/` — currently being worked.</item>
      <item>`.aidocs/&lt;project&gt;/done/&lt;feature-id&gt;/` — merged locally, awaiting push or already pushed.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Each feature folder contains the SDD artifact set: `spec.md`, `plan.md` (merged `## Design` + `## Execution Plan` per plan-md-structure), conditional `user-flows.md` (user-facing) and `ui-ux-design.md` (UI), atomic `TASK_*.md` files, `readiness.md` (gate before move to done/), and a `clarifications.md` produced by the CLARIFY phase. The orchestrator never hard-codes a vendor tracker.</p>
    <reference path="../../../../../docs/directory-structure.md">Repo-wide layout including the SDD lifecycle folders.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Language convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>User-facing strings (clarification questions, delivery captions, AskUserQuestion payloads) use Ukrainian. Code, commit messages, prompt files, reference docs, and CHANGELOG entries use English.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed-language code is hard to grep; mixed-language conversation is impolite. The split is consistent across runs because it is encoded in the prompt files.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
