<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="08-recapture-and-deliver" title="Visual recapture and out-of-band delivery">
  <summary>For visual fixes, the final phase produces a focused before/after image pair (red outline before, green outline after) and posts them to a delivery channel (`tg-send` to Telegram, or attachment in the SDD `done/` folder) with explanatory captions in Ukrainian.</summary>

  <section title="Why focused, not full-page">
    <rule>
      <statement>Screenshots MUST be element-focused with roughly 200 pixels of context above and below the bug element. Width about 1400 px; height auto, capped around 1500 px.</statement>
      <rationale>Full-page captures of long pages (faion.net, longlife.faion.net articles, storybook stories) are unreadable when delivered through Telegram or an inline preview. The reviewer's eye must land on the bug area in under one second.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/focused-screenshot.py">Playwright Python helper that locates an element, injects a CSS outline, and clips the screenshot to the element's neighbourhood.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Before/after symmetry">
    <list>
      <item>BEFORE: render the pre-fix state (worktree at the parent commit) and outline the buggy element in red (`#d50000`).</item>
      <item>AFTER: render the post-fix state (worktree at the merged feature commit) at the same viewport and scroll position; outline the same element in green (`#1b8a3a`).</item>
      <item>Defensive fix (no visible diff in current data): outline the touched element with both red and green so the reviewer sees the changed area, and the caption explicitly says the diff manifests only once corresponding data appears.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Caption convention">
    <p>Captions are not decorative. Each caption explains, in Ukrainian, what the bug was (BEFORE) or how the fix solves it (AFTER), in two or three sentences. Captions like `&lt;feature-id&gt; before` are forbidden — they carry zero information the file name does not already convey.</p>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Adding a coloured banner with English description at the top of the screenshot instead of outlining the actual element.</description>
      <reason>It hides the visual proof. The whole point is the reviewer's eye landing on the changed pixels, not on a label.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Delivery channels (faion-network)">
    <list>
      <item>`tg-send --photo &lt;path&gt; "&lt;caption&gt;"` — primary channel for batches under active human review (Ruslan's Nero bot, chat 267619672).</item>
      <item>`tg-send --photo &lt;path&gt; --chat-id &lt;id&gt;` — content-pipeline channels (neromedia, pashtelka, longlife, ender) only when the feature is the channel's own visual change.</item>
      <item>SDD-only delivery: drop the PNG pair into `.aidocs/&lt;project&gt;/done/&lt;feature-id&gt;/screenshots/` and reference them from the feature's `summary.md`. Use this when the run is silent or batched for later review.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Channel choice and credentials live in the playbook's `reference/delivery-channel.md` (where present); the orchestrator never hard-codes a chat ID.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Capture isolation">
    <rule>
      <statement>The recapture subagent MUST work in a dedicated worktree at the relevant commit, not in the main working tree.</statement>
      <rationale>Generating the BEFORE state requires checking out the parent commit. Doing this in the main working tree corrupts user state and races with other agents.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
