<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="onboarding-60-90-day Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for onboarding-60-90-day. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Contribute phase ends when the hire has owned and completed at least one project end-to-end; "participating" or "contributing to" a team project does not satisfy this criterion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">End-to-end ownership reveals planning, execution, communication, and handoff capability. Participation in a team project reveals only the ability to execute a defined slice; it does not demonstrate the full delivery loop that the Execute phase depends on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Confirm all five day-60 success criteria are met before allowing the hire to enter the Execute phase; missing criteria require a plan for resolution, not a deferral to day-90.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Deferring unmet 60-day criteria to the 90-day review compresses the Execute phase into the remaining time and produces a rushed, low-evidence review. Addressing gaps at day 60 while there is still 30 days of execution time is the correct intervention point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Execute phase measures independence: the hire must handle most responsibilities without needing guidance; if guidance is still required for familiar tasks at day 90, the hire has not met the ramp bar.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The 90-day review is the formal transition from onboarding to standard performance management. A hire who still requires frequent guidance at day 90 is on an extended ramp that must be named explicitly and managed differently than the standard onboarding conclusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include a mentorship milestone only if there is a confirmed newer hire to mentor; never add it as a generic aspiration.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generic mentorship milestones at day 90 fail when there are no newer hires; the milestone becomes unfulfillable and the review is forced to waive it, undermining the credibility of the other criteria.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a skip-level check-in at day 45; the manager is not the only signal source and may have blind spots the skip-level surfaces.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manager-only feedback produces biased signals: managers unconsciously minimize problems they contributed to and amplify successes they credit themselves for. The skip-level provides an independent calibration point mid-ramp.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
