<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-contribute-phase" title="Days 31-60: Contributing Phase">
  <summary>Objectives, activity categories, success criteria, and antipatterns for the Contribute phase of new-hire onboarding (days 31-60).</summary>

  <section title="Phase Objective">
    <rule>
      <statement>The Contribute phase ends when the hire has owned and completed at least one project end-to-end; "participating" or "contributing to" a team project does not satisfy this criterion.</statement>
      <rationale>End-to-end ownership reveals planning, execution, communication, and handoff capability. Participation in a team project reveals only the ability to execute a defined slice; it does not demonstrate the full delivery loop that the Execute phase depends on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Activity Categories">
    <section title="Projects">
      <p>Own first project end-to-end. Scope must be achievable within weeks 5-8 — not so small it is trivial, not so large it requires extensions. Project selection is a manager decision made at the day-30 review.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Collaboration">
      <p>Contribute actively in meetings — not just attend. Contribution is measurable: made a decision, raised a risk, proposed a solution. Meeting presence without contribution is not a milestone completion criterion.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Relationships">
      <p>Build cross-functional connections beyond the immediate team. Identify 3-5 stakeholders in adjacent teams and schedule introductions in weeks 5-6. Goal: the hire knows who to contact for decisions outside their team boundary before the day-60 review.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Feedback">
      <p>Receive feedback from at least two sources (manager and peer or cross-functional stakeholder) and demonstrate acting on it. "Acting on it" requires a visible artifact: changed approach, updated doc, adjusted behavior noted by the feedback giver.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Day-60 Success Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Confirm all five day-60 success criteria are met before allowing the hire to enter the Execute phase; missing criteria require a plan for resolution, not a deferral to day-90.</statement>
      <rationale>Deferring unmet 60-day criteria to the 90-day review compresses the Execute phase into the remaining time and produces a rushed, low-evidence review. Addressing gaps at day 60 while there is still 30 days of execution time is the correct intervention point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Completed first project successfully (artifact exists: PR merged, doc published, milestone delivered).</item>
      <item>Receives positive feedback from team (at least one unsolicited or structured peer feedback).</item>
      <item>Works with minimal supervision on familiar tasks within role scope.</item>
      <item>Demonstrates core job competencies at the level expected for the role and level.</item>
      <item>Has documented goals for days 61-90 in a shared artifact, agreed with manager.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Defining "contributing" as meeting attendance or activity counts rather than outcome delivery.</description>
      <reason>Activity-based milestones (attended 10 standups, joined 3 cross-team meetings) create false completion signals. A hire who attends all meetings but delivers nothing has not demonstrated contribution — they have demonstrated availability.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Assigning a project so small it provides no meaningful evidence of delivery capability.</description>
      <reason>A 2-hour task completed in week 5 does not demonstrate the planning, execution, and communication behaviors the phase is designed to reveal. Scope the first project to require 1-2 weeks of sustained effort.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
