<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-execute-phase" title="Days 61-90: Execute Phase and 90-Day Review">
  <summary>Objectives, independence criteria, 90-day review checklist, check-in structure, and metrics for the Execute phase of new-hire onboarding.</summary>

  <section title="Phase Objective">
    <rule>
      <statement>The Execute phase measures independence: the hire must handle most responsibilities without needing guidance; if guidance is still required for familiar tasks at day 90, the hire has not met the ramp bar.</statement>
      <rationale>The 90-day review is the formal transition from onboarding to standard performance management. A hire who still requires frequent guidance at day 90 is on an extended ramp that must be named explicitly and managed differently than the standard onboarding conclusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Execute Phase Activities">
    <section title="Independence">
      <p>Handle responsibilities with minimal guidance. The target is: manager is a resource, not a required step. The hire should seek guidance for novel or high-stakes decisions, not for repeating tasks within their scope.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Delivery">
      <p>Complete a major project or milestone — larger in scope than the day-60 project. For engineering: medium-complexity feature. For sales: first closed deal. For PM: shipped feature with usage data. Milestone must be documented before the Execute phase begins.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Initiative">
      <p>Proactively identify at least one opportunity, risk, or improvement not assigned by the manager. Initiative evidence: raised the issue in a meeting or 1:1, proposed a solution, and either implemented it or passed it through the appropriate channel.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Mentorship">
      <rule>
        <statement>Include a mentorship milestone only if there is a confirmed newer hire to mentor; never add it as a generic aspiration.</statement>
        <rationale>Generic mentorship milestones at day 90 fail when there are no newer hires; the milestone becomes unfulfillable and the review is forced to waive it, undermining the credibility of the other criteria.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Day-90 Success Criteria">
    <list>
      <item>Meets or exceeds performance expectations on primary job responsibilities.</item>
      <item>Works autonomously on 80%+ of tasks without requiring guidance from manager or peers.</item>
      <item>Has delivered a major project or milestone with a verifiable artifact.</item>
      <item>Has a documented development plan for the next quarter, co-authored with the manager.</item>
      <item>Is integrated into team culture — participates in social and professional rituals without prompting.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Check-In Structure (Days 31-90)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run a skip-level check-in at day 45; the manager is not the only signal source and may have blind spots the skip-level surfaces.</statement>
      <rationale>Manager-only feedback produces biased signals: managers unconsciously minimize problems they contributed to and amplify successes they credit themselves for. The skip-level provides an independent calibration point mid-ramp.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Day 45: skip-level check-in (hire meets manager's manager; format is a conversation, not a review). Day 60: manager review with documented outcomes against day-60 success criteria. Day 90: formal performance review with documented outcomes; transition to standard performance management cycle.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Metrics">
    <p>60-day project completion: 100% (tracked by manager). 90-day retention: target above 95% (track voluntary departures in this window). Time to productivity: role-dependent; defined in the plan before Day 1 and assessed by manager at day 90. Onboarding satisfaction: target above 4.0 out of 5 (survey at day 90). 90-day review scores: target above 3.5 out of 5 on primary competency rubric.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using the same milestone pace for all hires regardless of role level or prior experience.</description>
      <reason>A senior hire from an adjacent company may complete the Contribute phase in 3 weeks rather than 4-8. Rigidly enforcing the standard cadence frustrates fast ramps and signals the organization cannot adapt to individual capability.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping the day-45 skip-level because the manager reports the hire is doing well.</description>
      <reason>The skip-level's purpose is precisely to check when the manager reports success. Confident reports from the manager are the highest-risk scenario for a blind-spot review at day 90.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
