<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="onboarding-60-90-day Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for onboarding-60-90-day as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Defining "contributing" as meeting attendance or activity counts rather than outcome delivery.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Activity-based milestones (attended 10 standups, joined 3 cross-team meetings) create false completion signals. A hire who attends all meetings but delivers nothing has not demonstrated contribution — they have demonstrated availability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Assigning a project so small it provides no meaningful evidence of delivery capability.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A 2-hour task completed in week 5 does not demonstrate the planning, execution, and communication behaviors the phase is designed to reveal. Scope the first project to require 1-2 weeks of sustained effort.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Using the same milestone pace for all hires regardless of role level or prior experience.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A senior hire from an adjacent company may complete the Contribute phase in 3 weeks rather than 4-8. Rigidly enforcing the standard cadence frustrates fast ramps and signals the organization cannot adapt to individual capability.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping the day-45 skip-level because the manager reports the hire is doing well.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The skip-level's purpose is precisely to check when the manager reports success. Confident reports from the manager are the highest-risk scenario for a blind-spot review at day 90.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
