<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-security" title="GitHub Actions Security">
  <summary>Action pinning to commit SHA, minimal GITHUB_TOKEN permissions, OIDC cloud auth, and injection prevention.</summary>

  <section title="Action Pinning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin every third-party action to a full 40-character commit SHA, never a mutable tag like @v4 or @main.</statement>
      <rationale>Tags are mutable — an action author or attacker who compromises the account can push malicious code to a tag. SHA references are immutable and cannot be changed after the fact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- uses: actions/checkout@v4          # mutable tag
- uses: some-action/deploy@main      # branch reference
]]></code>
      <note>Both can be replaced by the action publisher at any time.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- uses: actions/checkout@b4ffde65f46336ab88eb53be808477a3936bae11  # v4.1.1
]]></code>
      <note>Add a comment with the tag name for readability. Use Dependabot for automatic SHA updates.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="GITHUB_TOKEN Permissions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set permissions: at workflow or job level with only the scopes actually needed, defaulting contents: read.</statement>
      <rationale>The implicit default grants read access to all scopes and write to some (contents). Explicit minimal permissions limit blast radius if a malicious action runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
permissions:
  contents: read       # default safe baseline

jobs:
  docker:
    permissions:
      contents: read
      packages: write  # only this job needs GHCR push
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="OIDC Cloud Authentication">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use OIDC (id-token: write permission + aws-actions/configure-aws-credentials with role-to-assume) instead of storing AWS/GCP/Azure credentials as repository secrets.</statement>
      <rationale>OIDC tokens are short-lived (15 minutes), scoped to the specific workflow run, and require no rotation. Stored access keys are long-lived and rotate-or-breach scenarios are common.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
permissions:
  id-token: write
  contents: read

steps:
  - uses: aws-actions/configure-aws-credentials@v4
    with:
      role-to-assume: arn:aws:iam::123456789012:role/GitHubActionsRole
      aws-region: us-east-1
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Checkout Safety and Injection Prevention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set persist-credentials: false on actions/checkout unless subsequent steps explicitly need the token.</statement>
      <rationale>Default checkout persists the GITHUB_TOKEN in the git config. Any later script that runs git commands can exfiltrate the token.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pass GitHub event context to shell commands via environment variables, not inline expression interpolation.</statement>
      <rationale>Inline ${{ github.event.pull_request.title }} in a run: step is interpreted before the shell executes, enabling command injection if the value contains shell metacharacters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- run: echo "${{ github.event.pull_request.title }}"
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- env:
    PR_TITLE: ${{ github.event.pull_request.title }}
  run: echo "$PR_TITLE"
]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use pull_request_target with code from the fork without explicit trust verification.</statement>
      <rationale>pull_request_target runs with write permissions and access to secrets. Checking out fork code in this context lets untrusted PRs exfiltrate all secrets.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
