<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="content-audit Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for content-audit. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always cross-reference remove/archive decisions with inbound link data before deletion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A low-traffic page with high inbound links should be redirected, not deleted; removing it breaks third-party links and harms SEO.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define evaluation criteria explicitly before scoring begins; do not score against implicit criteria.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Subjective quality judgments without written criteria produce inconsistent scores across auditors and audit passes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign a human owner to each "Update" action item before the audit is considered complete.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent recommendations without human ownership stall; unowned tasks do not get done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store the audit in a versioned spreadsheet; keep it for at least one full content cycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Version history enables tracking governance effectiveness and provides baseline for the next audit pass.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require the agent to declare confidence level per row when it has only URL/title and no body content.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent may confidently score pages based on insufficient information; explicit confidence flags prevent false precision in low-data rows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Flag agent accuracy scores on specialized content (technical, medical, legal) for human expert review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent accuracy judgments on specialized topics are unreliable without domain context; these categories require subject-matter expertise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Batch large sites into topical groups and audit each group with domain-appropriate criteria.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Context window limits mean approximately 200-400 page rows per call; consistent criteria across batches requires the same prompt for each group.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Generate a redirect mapping before any deletion; "Remove" recommendations must include redirect destination.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Removing pages without redirects breaks inbound links and search rankings; agent should output redirect pairs, not just removal decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Final Keep/Remove decisions must be approved by a content owner or PM, not executed automatically.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automated content deletion without human sign-off carries irreversible SEO and user-trust risk; agent output is advisory.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
