<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Content Audit Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Rules for agent-assisted scoring, redirect risk management, batching large sites, and common audit mistakes.</summary>

  <section title="Agent Scoring Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require the agent to declare confidence level per row when it has only URL/title and no body content.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent may confidently score pages based on insufficient information; explicit confidence flags prevent false precision in low-data rows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag agent accuracy scores on specialized content (technical, medical, legal) for human expert review.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent accuracy judgments on specialized topics are unreliable without domain context; these categories require subject-matter expertise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Batch large sites into topical groups and audit each group with domain-appropriate criteria.</statement>
      <rationale>Context window limits mean approximately 200-400 page rows per call; consistent criteria across batches requires the same prompt for each group.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Redirect and Deletion Risk">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate a redirect mapping before any deletion; "Remove" recommendations must include redirect destination.</statement>
      <rationale>Removing pages without redirects breaks inbound links and search rankings; agent should output redirect pairs, not just removal decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Final Keep/Remove decisions must be approved by a content owner or PM, not executed automatically.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated content deletion without human sign-off carries irreversible SEO and user-trust risk; agent output is advisory.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Incomplete inventory — missing PDFs, gated content, JavaScript-rendered pages.</description>
      <reason>An audit of 70% of content produces decisions that may conflict with unreviewed items; the inventory must be complete before scoring begins.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-time audit without ongoing governance.</description>
      <reason>Content decays continuously; a single audit snapshot becomes stale within months without a review schedule and owner assignments.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>All-or-nothing approach — auditing the entire site before taking any action.</description>
      <reason>Large audits stall on completion anxiety; start with priority areas (core pages, high-traffic content) to generate early wins.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/merge-audit.sh">Merge Screaming Frog crawl CSV with GA pageview data</reference>
</text>
