<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="spec-writing Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for spec-writing. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A complete spec must contain: Overview, Problem Statement, Goals (with current/target metric table), Non-Goals, User Stories, Functional Requirements (FR-N IDs), Non-Functional Requirements, Acceptance Criteria, Out of Scope, Open Questions. Missing any section is a reject signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each section prevents a specific class of delivery failure: Non-Goals prevent scope creep, Open Questions prevent false confidence, Acceptance Criteria prevent untestable scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every goal must have a measurable current baseline and a numeric target. "Improve UX" is not a goal. "Reduce time-to-find-product from 3 min to 30 sec" is a goal.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unmeasurable goals cannot be verified at launch and cannot drive prioritization decisions during delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>List everything explicitly excluded from this spec. Non-Goals section must be non-empty for any feature touching more than one surface.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The absence of Non-Goals is the leading cause of scope creep. Every unspecified behaviour becomes "obviously included" during implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every story uses the format: "As a [named persona], I want to [action] so that [measurable benefit]." Use persona IDs (not "the user") in every story. Include the "so that" clause—it encodes motivation and validates the story is worth building.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Stories without persona IDs cannot be traced to a validated user segment. Stories without "so that" cannot be evaluated for user value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Functional requirements use "FR-N: The system shall [do X]" format. Cap at ~15 FRs per spec; larger features must be split. Keep implementation details out: no library names, DB schemas, or UI component names.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Specs mixing what and how box in engineers and are ignored. Implementation decisions belong in the design document, linked from the spec.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Open Questions section must be non-empty. A spec with zero open questions signals false confidence. List technical unknowns, pending business decisions, and user research gaps with an owner per question.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs in particular will "answer" every question rather than acknowledge uncertainty. Explicitly requiring a non-empty Open Questions section forces intellectual honesty.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Target 1-3 pages (or ~15 FRs). Use Mini-Spec for features under one sprint. Track decisions made post-approval as a versioned addendum—never silently rewrite the original spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Beyond 5 pages, nobody reads the spec. Silent rewrites destroy the audit trail that later resolves scope disputes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assign a unique ID to every FR (FR-1, FR-2, ...) and reference that ID in the corresponding acceptance criteria. An FR without a linked AC is an orphan—reject the spec.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without ID-based traceability, FRs and ACs drift apart during revisions. Orphan FRs produce untested scope at launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Label every FR with a priority: Must (MVP blocker), Should (high value, deferrable), Could (nice-to-have). Pair with a co-signer for any FR labelled Must.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unprioritized requirements produce all-or-nothing scope debates at sprint planning. Must-level FRs need sign-off because they encode strategic decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every NFR must specify a measurable criterion. "The system shall be fast" is not an NFR. "FR-2 latency: results visible within 200ms at p95 for up to 50K concurrent users" is an NFR.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unmeasurable NFRs cannot be verified in QA and become perpetual technical debt claims.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every FR must have at least one Given/When/Then acceptance criterion. Each AC row must reference the FR ID. AC must be unique—never a restatement of the FR.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AC that restates the FR cannot be used for test case authoring or sprint review verification. "FR-2 search works → AC: search works" tells testers nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
