<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-requirements" title="Requirements Authoring: FR/NFR Rules and Acceptance Criteria Format">
  <summary>How to write functional requirements, non-functional requirements, and Given/When/Then acceptance criteria with traceability between them.</summary>

  <section title="Functional Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign a unique ID to every FR (FR-1, FR-2, ...) and reference that ID in the corresponding acceptance criteria. An FR without a linked AC is an orphan — reject the spec.</statement>
      <rationale>Without ID-based traceability, FRs and ACs drift apart during revisions. Orphan FRs produce untested scope at launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Label every FR with a priority: Must (MVP blocker), Should (high value, deferrable), Could (nice-to-have). Pair with a co-signer for any FR labelled Must.</statement>
      <rationale>Unprioritized requirements produce all-or-nothing scope debates at sprint planning. Must-level FRs need sign-off because they encode strategic decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
| ID   | Requirement                              | Priority |
|------|------------------------------------------|----------|
| FR-1 | Search bar visible on all pages          | Must     |
| FR-2 | Results appear as user types             | Must     |
| FR-3 | Show top 10 results with product images  | Should   |
| FR-4 | "No results" shows similar products      | Could    |
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Non-Functional Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every NFR must specify a measurable criterion. "The system shall be fast" is not an NFR. "FR-2 latency: results visible within 200ms at p95 for up to 50K concurrent users" is an NFR.</statement>
      <rationale>Unmeasurable NFRs cannot be verified in QA and become perpetual technical debt claims.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Generic NFR boilerplate: "99.99% uptime", "GDPR compliant" pasted without source or justification.</description>
      <reason>Generic NFRs fabricated without contractual or regulatory basis waste engineering effort on unnecessary hardening.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Acceptance Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every FR must have at least one Given/When/Then acceptance criterion. Each AC row must reference the FR ID. AC must be unique — never a restatement of the FR.</statement>
      <rationale>AC that restates the FR cannot be used for test case authoring or sprint review verification. "FR-2 search works → AC: search works" tells testers nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### FR-1 Acceptance
- Given I'm on the product listing page, when the page loads, then I see a search bar in the header.
- Given I'm on the checkout page, when the page loads, then I see the same search bar.

### FR-2 Acceptance
- Given I type "chair" in the search bar, when I type the 3rd character, then product results appear within 200ms.
- Given I type "chiar" (typo), when I submit, then I see "Did you mean: chair?" suggestion.
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-structure.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/prd.md"/>
    <link path="templates/validate-spec.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
