<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-pipeline-and-scoring" title="Product Development Trends (Market-Side): Pipeline and Signal Scoring">
  <summary>Three-stage pipeline for market-side trend research, signal JSONL schema, recency/evidence/applicability scoring rubric, and the market-implication output format that distinguishes this methodology from the product-side sibling.</summary>

  <section title="Three-Stage Pipeline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run in three sequential stages: (1) wide signal collection — sonnet subagent does WebSearch + WebFetch and dumps to .aidocs/research/raw/signals.jsonl; (2) scored synthesis — opus subagent scores each signal on recency × evidence × applicability and proposes a market implication; (3) human checkpoint — accept/reject before writing into .aidocs/product_docs/trend-report.md.</statement>
      <rationale>Paying for opus synthesis on unfiltered signals is wasteful and overwhelms context. The scoring pass (cheap) before synthesis (expensive) reduces token cost and improves output quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Persist signals.jsonl as an audit trail. Next-quarter run must diff against it rather than re-scraping from scratch.</statement>
      <rationale>Re-scraping each quarter misses the delta — the change between quarters is more informative than the absolute list. Diffing the raw signal log provides both the delta and a reproducibility record.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Signal JSONL Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each signal row must contain: trend (string), source (URL), published (YYYY-MM-DD), primary_source (bool), citations (int), applicability (0-3), region (US|EU|APAC|global), market_impl (market implication string). Drop signals with total score below 5.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a schema enforced at ingest, signals arrive in heterogeneous shapes that make batch scoring and quarterly diffing unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Rubric">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each signal: recency (3 if ≤30 days, 2 if ≤90 days, 1 if ≤180 days, 0 if older) + evidence (3 if primary_source, 2 if citations ≥3, 1 otherwise) + applicability (0-3 as provided). Threshold ≥5 to include in synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale>The threshold prevents paying for opus synthesis on stale, low-evidence signals. A signal scoring 4 or below is too weak to anchor a market implication.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Market Implication Output">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each passing trend, write the MARKET implication (TAM shift, pricing power, positioning) — not product/roadmap implications. Product implications belong in researcher/product-development-trends.</statement>
      <rationale>The two sibling methodologies are distinct deliverables. Mixing market and product implications in the same document produces a document that satisfies neither the investor audience nor the product team.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a kill-list: for every adopted trend, name one current GTM/pricing assumption to retire. Trend memos without subtractions are theater.</statement>
      <rationale>Adding new trend implications without retiring stale ones creates an ever-growing list of "things to do" with no prioritization signal. The kill-list forces explicit trade-offs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate consumer trends (slow, demographic) from platform trends (fast, technology) into two tables. Mixing them is the most common failure mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Consumer trends (sustainability, "brands that do good") operate on 5-10 year cycles; platform trends (AI-native tooling) operate on 6-18 month cycles. Mixing cadences produces misleading urgency signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/signal-scorer.py">Score signals.jsonl on recency/evidence/applicability, drop below threshold, render markdown table</reference>
  <reference path="templates/trend-report.md">Trend report skeleton with market implications, kill-list, and separated consumer vs platform trend tables</reference>
</text>
