<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules-and-gotchas" title="Product Development Trends (Market-Side): Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Source-freshness, regional-bias guards, kill-list requirement, consumer vs platform separation, and AI-agent failure modes for the market-side trend brief.</summary>

  <section title="Source and Freshness Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor every macro trend to one quantifiable market datapoint — funding round, traffic-share delta, review-count trajectory. Label trends without such an anchor as "watch", not "act".</statement>
      <rationale>"Trend" articles are written for SEO. Without a quantifiable anchor, a trend claim is indistinguishable from a well-cited opinion piece.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Force at least one EU and one APAC primary source per trend or reject the brief as regionally biased. Never blend US + EU + APAC CPC into one number.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs over-index on US/SF sources; training data overweights US benchmarks. For non-US markets, a US-only brief actively misleads decision-making.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Date-stamp at the bullet level, not just the document. Future agents diff bullet-dates to detect staleness without re-reading the full document.</statement>
      <rationale>Document-level dates hide which specific bullets have gone stale. Bullet-level dates let a quarterly diff agent flag individual claims without a full re-research pass.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scope Guardrails">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not run this methodology less than 90 days after the previous run unless a triggering event occurred (funding round, regulatory shift, major launch). Trend churn faster than 90 days is noise.</statement>
      <rationale>Macro market trends do not materially change week-to-week. Running more frequently produces re-confirmation of the last snapshot at significant token cost without new information.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep each trend's executive summary to ≤3 sentences. Long entries always indicate weak evidence padded with adjectives.</statement>
      <rationale>Evidence-dense trend claims are short by nature. If you cannot express the market implication in 3 sentences, the evidence is not strong enough to warrant a claim.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>WebSearch ranked by SEO not freshness — sorting by published date is skipped, producing stale results summarized as current.</description>
      <reason>Sort by published date in the signal scraper before summarizing. Freshness of source is the primary quality signal in trend research.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>"Rapid pivots, quarterly cycles" added as an unsourced cadence claim generated from LLM defaults rather than evidence.</description>
      <reason>Treat any unsourced cadence claim as hallucinated. Require a named study (DORA, Stack Overflow) with cohort label before accepting a cadence benchmark.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Three citations to the same secondary article (HBR, McKinsey blog) inflating confidence for a claim.</description>
      <reason>Multiple citations to the same source ≠ multiple sources. Require independent primary sources; citations to the same base article count as one.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Human-in-the-loop checkpoint missing before the synthesis lands in .aidocs/product_docs/.</description>
      <reason>Without the gate, hallucinated vendor names and fabricated market data points land in deliverables that get circulated to investors and boards. The checkpoint is non-negotiable.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Token cost blowup: synthesis on opus with 50+ raw signals exceeds 100k tokens.</description>
      <reason>Pre-filter with the signal-scorer.py script before paying for opus synthesis. A scored and trimmed set of signals produces better output at 20% of the cost.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Duplicate-content trap: both market and product sibling methodologies produce a file called trend-report.md and one silently overwrites the other.</description>
      <reason>Explicitly namespace files: market side writes to trend-report-market.md, product side to trend-report-product.md. Ask "is the deliverable a market memo or a product memo?" before running.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
