<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-development-trends Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-development-trends as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>WebSearch ranked by SEO not freshness — sorting by published date is skipped, producing stale results summarized as current</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Sort by published date in the signal scraper before summarizing. Freshness of source is the primary quality signal in trend research.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Rapid pivots, quarterly cycles added as an unsourced cadence claim generated from LLM defaults rather than evidence</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Treat any unsourced cadence claim as hallucinated. Require a named study (DORA, Stack Overflow) with cohort label before accepting a cadence benchmark.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Three citations to the same secondary article (HBR, McKinsey blog) inflating confidence for a claim</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multiple citations to the same source ≠ multiple sources. Require independent primary sources; citations to the same base article count as one.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-the-loop checkpoint missing before the synthesis lands in .aidocs/product_docs/</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without the gate, hallucinated vendor names and fabricated market data points land in deliverables that get circulated to investors and boards. The checkpoint is non-negotiable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Token cost blowup: synthesis on opus with 50+ raw signals exceeds 100k tokens</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-filter with the signal-scorer.py script before paying for opus synthesis. A scored and trimmed set of signals produces better output at 20% of the cost.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Duplicate-content trap: both market and product sibling methodologies produce a file called trend-report.md and one silently overwrites the other</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicitly namespace files: market side writes to trend-report-market.md, product side to trend-report-product.md. Ask "is the deliverable a market memo or a product memo?" before running.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
