<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Tailwind Design Tokens Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every tailwind-design-tokens application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-primitives-vs-semantics" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Separate primitive tokens (raw values: #1A73E8, 16px) from semantic tokens (color.action.primary, spacing.md). Tailwind config exposes ONLY semantic tokens; primitives stay in CSS variables.</statement>
      <rationale source="Style Dictionary docs; design-tokens W3C">Primitive-only configs make rebranding impossible without code churn; semantic-only configs lose the raw layer required for theming.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-css-var-bridge" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tailwind theme values MUST reference `var(--token-name)`. Hardcoded hex or pixel values in tailwind.config.js are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tailwind docs — Customizing Colors">Hardcoded values require a build for any change and cannot be overridden at runtime for theming.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-rgb-channel-for-opacity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>To support Tailwind opacity modifiers (`bg-primary/50`), colour CSS variables MUST be declared in RGB channel format (e.g. `--color-primary: 26 115 232`) and Tailwind colors MUST use the RGB variable with `&lt;alpha-value&gt;`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tailwind docs — Using CSS variables">Opacity modifiers require channel-form values; hex strings break opacity silently.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-dark-mode-layer" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Light-mode tokens declared at `:root`; dark-mode tokens declared under `[data-theme="dark"]` OR `@media (prefers-color-scheme: dark)`. NEVER mix Tailwind's `dark:` variant with raw CSS-variable tokens without explicit alpha-channel setup.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tailwind docs — Dark mode">Mixing strategies causes silent failures where dark mode is detected but tokens never switch.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-safelist-dynamic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any token-mapped class assembled dynamically (string concatenation like `bg-${color}`) MUST be added to Tailwind's safelist. JIT cannot statically analyse template strings.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tailwind docs — JIT mode">Without safelist the class is purged at build and the runtime style does not exist.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-tailwind-major-version" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tailwind major version MUST be known and matched. v3 uses `tailwind.config.js`; v4 uses CSS-first `@theme` directive. Cross-version configs are silently ignored.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tailwind v4 docs">v3 config in a v4 project ships nothing and produces no error.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
