<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-frameworks" title="Modern BA Framework — Candidate Catalog and Selection Criteria">
  <summary>Eight candidate BA reference frameworks with selection scoring criteria and known limitations of purely descriptive framework tables.</summary>

  <section title="Candidate Frameworks">
    <list>
      <item>BABOK v3 (IIBA, 2015) — most comprehensive; 6 knowledge areas; dominant in regulated and enterprise contexts; ECBA/CCBA/CBAP certs</item>
      <item>BA Standard 2025 (IIBA) — modernizes BABOK v3 with agile, hybrid, and transformational org context; SFIA v9 integration; replaces some BABOK guidance</item>
      <item>IREB CPRE (Foundation + Advanced) — engineering-grade requirements; strong in automotive (ASPICE), aerospace, medical; CPRE-FL/AL certs</item>
      <item>PMI-PBA / Business Analysis for Practitioners — bridging doc + waterfall; PMBOK-aligned; PMI-PBA cert</item>
      <item>BCS Diploma in Business Analysis — practitioner-focused; common in UK public sector; certificate ladder</item>
      <item>SAFe Business Analyst — maps BA competencies to SAFe roles; best for scaled agile (LeSS, PI planning); not audit-grade</item>
      <item>Agile Extension to BABOK v2 (IIBA) — bridge from BABOK KAs to Scrum/SAFe ceremonies; pairs with BABOK v3</item>
      <item>SWEBOK v4 KA: Software Requirements (IEEE) — engineering-centric; most useful for software-only programs; no certs</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Selection Scoring Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each candidate on six dimensions before selecting: regulatory_fit, team_maturity_fit, vocabulary_overlap_with_existing, tooling_support, certification_availability, agile_friendliness. Let regulatory_fit veto agile-friendly choices in regulated settings.</statement>
      <rationale>Without structured scoring, LLMs default to BABOK regardless of context; explicit scoring surfaces IREB in automotive and PMI-PBA in hybrid-portfolio orgs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick ONE primary framework and at most two extension frameworks. Two co-equal primaries always produce vocabulary thrash and audit ambiguity.</statement>
      <rationale>Common failure: BABOK v3 + Agile Extension treated as equal primaries; extensions supplement, they do not co-govern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cache PDFs of BABOK v3, BA Standard 2025, IREB CPRE-FL/AL, and PMI-PBA as a local fact-source; require the agent to cite from the cache, not from training data.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents confabulate clause numbers, KA boundaries, and version dates; a pinned cache is the only defense.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Framework Table Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating the "Modern Application" tables as procedures.</description>
      <reason>The tables are descriptive (e.g., "AI/ML literacy" under Analytical Thinking); they have no inputs, outputs, or acceptance tests. Agents that treat them as instructions produce hand-wavy plans.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using certification tier (ECBA, CCBA, CBAP) as a capability proxy.</description>
      <reason>Certs measure exam pass rate, not analyst quality with LLM tools, RAG, or evals; treat the cert ladder as procurement signaling, not skill assurance.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying SAFe BA framework in regulated industries (pharma, automotive, aerospace).</description>
      <reason>SAFe BA is not audit-grade; ASPICE, IEC 62304, DO-178C auditors require IREB or BABOK-aligned artifact vocabulary.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Vocabulary Glossary Requirement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before producing any artifact, build a vocabulary glossary mapping chosen-framework terms to org existing terms and to sibling methodology slugs; persist as glossary.md next to ba-framework-decision.md.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a shared glossary, downstream artifacts in different hands redefine terms silently, breaking traceability across the program.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/ba-framework-select.sh">Shell script that scaffolds ba-framework-decision.json with all scoring fields</reference>
</text>
