<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="modern-ba-framework Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for modern-ba-framework as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating the "Modern Application" tables as procedures.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The tables are descriptive (e.g., "AI/ML literacy" under Analytical Thinking); they have no inputs, outputs, or acceptance tests. Agents that treat them as instructions produce hand-wavy plans.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using certification tier (ECBA, CCBA, CBAP) as a capability proxy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Certs measure exam pass rate, not analyst quality with LLM tools, RAG, or evals; treat the cert ladder as procurement signaling, not skill assurance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying SAFe BA framework in regulated industries (pharma, automotive, aerospace).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>SAFe BA is not audit-grade; ASPICE, IEC 62304, DO-178C auditors require IREB or BABOK-aligned artifact vocabulary.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs default to BABOK because it is the most-tokenized BA reference in training data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force structured candidate scoring or you'll never see IREB / PMI-PBA / BCS picked. Without explicit scoring on all 8 frameworks, BABOK wins by default regardless of context fit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Models confabulate clause numbers, KA boundaries, and IIBA version dates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin a fact-source file (cached BABOK ToC + BA Standard ToC + IREB CPRE syllabi) and require citations. Reject any structural claim not present in the cached files.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>"BA Standard (2025)" wording will go stale; agent must check current IIBA publication titles before quoting versions to humans.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Update publication title checks when standards are released. Agents that quote outdated version numbers lose credibility in procurement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>The Agent Selection table is advisory. Cost regressions appear when the planner downgrades opus → sonnet for "gap analysis" or regulatory mapping.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Lock the model per task in the decision JSON. Do not let cost optimizations degrade output on critical signals like regulatory mapping.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-the-loop checkpoint is skipped; auto-execution bypasses the only place a real PO/BA can correct framework bias.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The mandatory checkpoint between selection and routing is where humans correct the default-BABOK pull. Never auto-execute through this gate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Vocabulary glossary is sensitive: in M&amp;A or vendor contexts it can leak commercial terms.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run password-scrubber-agent and tag the doc as confidential before persisting outside private repos.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent edits the README's tables; it tends to "modernize" them every run, churning git history.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confine edits to agent-integration.md and .aidocs/&lt;feature&gt;/. Pin the README tables as read-only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Certification recommendations leak vendor bias (IIBA-only).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-reference IREB, PMI-PBA, BCS, and Scrum.org product-owner tracks before presenting to the user. Single-vendor lists mislead procurement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent quotes CMMI-DEV process areas as "framework" peers without flagging that CMMI is a maturity model, not a BA reference.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Mixing maturity models and BA references confuses procurement. Keep them in separate decision tracks.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM defaults to BABOK because it dominates training data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force structured candidate scoring on all 8 frameworks; without it, IREB, PMI-PBA, and BCS are never selected regardless of context fit.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent confabulates clause numbers, KA boundaries, and IIBA version dates.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin a local fact-source (cached BABOK ToC + IREB CPRE syllabi) and require citations to it; reject any structural claim not present in the cached files.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent auto-proceeds from selection to routing without a human checkpoint.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The human-in-the-loop checkpoint between selection and routing is the only place a real BA can correct the framework bias introduced by training data; auto-execution removes this control.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Certification recommendations are IIBA-only, creating vendor bias.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-reference IREB, PMI-PBA, BCS, and Scrum.org product-owner tracks before presenting to the user; single-vendor cert lists mislead procurement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent edits the framework README tables to "modernize" them on each run.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Confine edits to agent-integration.md and .aidocs/&lt;feature&gt;/; churning git history on the README tables destroys stable reference content.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
