<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="spatial-design-tools">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Four-stage design-to-dev workflow for spatial XR: 2D wireframes → ShapesXR low-fi → high-fi Unity/Unreal → production with accessibility.</summary>
    <category>spatial</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>spatial-design</tag>
      <tag>xr</tag>
      <tag>vr</tag>
      <tag>figma</tag>
      <tag>unity</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Spatial Design Tools</title>

    <summary>Tool selection guide and design-to-development workflow for spatial (XR) design. Covers the gap between 2D design tools (Figma) and native spatial tools (ShapesXR, Gravity Sketch), and defines a four-stage workflow from concept through production: 2D wireframes → low-fi headset prototype → high-fi Unity/Unreal → production.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Spatial design cannot be adequately specified or tested in traditional 2D tools. Key interaction qualities (depth, scale, arm reach, comfort) are invisible in Figma mockups and only manifest in a headset. A staged workflow that introduces the headset at the low-fi prototype stage catches spatial UX problems before costly high-fidelity development.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Selecting tools for a new spatial/XR design project</item>
        <item>Setting up a design-to-development handoff process for an XR team</item>
        <item>Deciding when to move from 2D to 3D in the design process</item>
        <item>Recommending tool investments to stakeholders</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>2D screen-based UI design — standard Figma/Sketch workflow applies</item>
        <item>XR content production (3D modeling, animation) — separate tools and skills</item>
        <item>Enterprise XR requirements specification — use enterprise-xr-applications instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="tool-landscape">
      <list>
        <item>Figma with 3D plugins: 2D wireframes with spatial annotations; suitable for concept and specification only</item>
        <item>ShapesXR: VR-native low-fidelity prototyping directly in a headset; primary tool for early spatial UX validation</item>
        <item>Gravity Sketch: VR-native 3D design and sketching; suitable for 3D form design and organic spatial layouts</item>
        <item>Unity: industry-standard XR development platform; used for high-fidelity interactive prototypes and production</item>
        <item>Unreal Engine: high-fidelity rendering for XR; suited to visualization-heavy enterprise applications</item>
        <item>Reality Composer Pro: Apple's tool for visionOS spatial content; required for Vision Pro production</item>
        <item>Spark AR: Meta AR effects and passthrough content; consumer-focused AR</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="four-stage-design-to-development-workflow">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Stage 1 (Concept): Use 2D wireframes in Figma with explicit spatial annotations — depth layers, scale references relative to human height, reach zones. Do not attempt to design spatial interactions in 2D beyond basic flow.</statement>
        <rationale>2D tools cannot represent depth, scale, or arm reach; spatial annotations communicate intent to developers without requiring 3D tooling at concept stage.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Stage 2 (Low-fi Prototype): Build a rough spatial prototype in ShapesXR or equivalent and test it in the target headset with representative users before writing any production code.</statement>
        <rationale>Key spatial UX problems — arm fatigue, uncomfortable viewing angles, depth misperception, scale errors — are invisible in 2D mockups and only manifest in the headset. Catching them at low-fi stage costs a fraction of fixing them post-development.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Stage 3 (High-fi Prototype): Implement in Unity or Unreal with real interactions, performance constraints, and target hardware. Conduct a second round of user testing in the target environment (factory floor, office, home).</statement>
        <rationale>Performance constraints (frame rate, rendering budget) affect interaction feel; high-fi prototypes in the development engine expose these issues before production optimization.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Stage 4 (Production): Include an accessibility review — check gaze+dwell fallback for motor-impaired users, voice command support, comfort for long sessions, and color contrast for passthrough AR overlays.</statement>
        <rationale>Spatial accessibility is rarely addressed in production without an explicit review gate; omitting it excludes motor-impaired users and may violate enterprise accessibility requirements.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="when-to-enter-the-headset">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Move to headset testing at Stage 2 (low-fi), not later. If the team lacks access to the target hardware, use the nearest available headset — any 6DOF device is more informative than any 2D mockup for spatial UX.</statement>
        <rationale>Delaying headset testing to high-fi or production is the most common cause of late-stage XR UX failures; the headset test must be part of the design process, not a QA activity.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use Claude as a "spatial pipeline librarian" — it picks the right tool per stage (concept → low-fi → high-fi → production), generates scaffolding (Unity C# MonoBehaviours, USDA scene files, glTF transforms), and writes the headset test plan. The headset-bound creative work (hand-sketching in ShapesXR, sculpting in Gravity Sketch) stays human; the agent prepares import scripts, file conventions, and review checklists around it. Always pair agent output with a human in-headset validation pass — pixel-perfect 2D ≠ comfortable 3D.</statement>
        <rationale>Agentic workflow separates deterministic scaffolding from creative and embodied design work, allowing agents to accelerate the pipeline without replacing human spatial intuition.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Core tools and services for spatial design pipeline:</p>
      <list>
        <item>usdpython / usdcat: Convert / inspect USD scenes (https://openusd.org/release/install.html)</item>
        <item>gltf-pipeline: glTF optimization, Draco compression (npm i -g gltf-pipeline)</item>
        <item>gltf-validator: Validate glTF before headset import (npm i -g gltf-validator)</item>
        <item>Unity -batchmode CLI: Headless Unity build for XR (https://docs.unity3d.com/Manual/CommandLineArguments.html)</item>
        <item>Unreal RunUAT.bat BuildCookRun: Headless Unreal XR packaging (https://docs.unrealengine.com/automation/)</item>
        <item>xcrun reality-composer-pro: macOS Reality Composer Pro CLI (https://developer.apple.com/documentation/realitykit)</item>
      </list>
      <p>SaaS services: ShapesXR (SaaS, no public API), Gravity Sketch (limited Figma plugin bridge), Unity Cloud Build (REST API), Reality Composer Pro (macOS GUI-only), Adobe Aero (export-only).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pin one tool per stage in the project README; agent should not switch mid-feature.</item>
        <item>Scale all assets to real-world meters at export, never "design units".</item>
        <item>Bake lighting in the design tool; runtime baking blows perf budgets on Quest 3 / Vision Pro.</item>
        <item>Ship a xr-handoff/ folder with USDZ + glTF + screenshots; agents read the manifest, not the binaries.</item>
        <item>Version 3D assets via Git LFS, not raw Git — diffs are useless and bloat the repo.</item>
        <item>Test on actual hardware every sprint; emulator comfort never matches headset comfort.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Claude can hallucinate Unity APIs that exist only in older XR Toolkit versions — pin the target version in the prompt.</item>
        <item>USDA/USDZ JSON-like syntax fools LLMs into emitting almost-valid files; always run usdchecker before import.</item>
        <item>Token-cheap output: ask for scene graphs as JSON, not prose; saves 60–80% tokens vs. natural-language scene descriptions.</item>
        <item>Human checkpoint required before headset upload — comfort, occlusion, and anchor drift cannot be predicted from text.</item>
        <item>Don't let the agent author shaders; ShaderGraph / Material X visual tooling is the source of truth.</item>
        <item>IP risk: Gravity Sketch / ShapesXR cloud may store proprietary models; agent should warn before any cloud upload.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://openusd.org/release/index.html"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/visionos/"/>
      <link href="https://developers.meta.com/horizon/"/>
      <link href="https://docs.unity3d.com/Packages/com.unity.xr.interaction.toolkit@2.5/manual/index.html"/>
      <link href="https://www.khronos.org/gltf/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
