<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Win-Loss Interview Program Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Win-Loss Interview Program application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-sample-50-50-won-lost" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview ratio MUST be 50% won deals + 50% lost deals. Lost-only is pessimism bias; won-only is sales-narrative confirmation.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Balanced samples produce materially better insights than either-only; both halves answer different questions (why we win / why we lose) that compose into roadmap signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-not-the-rep-who-sold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interviewer MUST NOT be the AE/CSM who worked the deal. Use a PM, researcher, or peer rep from a different territory.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Interviewees give socially-desirable answers to the person they negotiated with; separating interviewer from seller is the standard bias control in win/loss practice.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-script-with-evidence-anchors" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Script MUST include open + evidence-anchored prompts: 'What alternatives did you consider?', 'What would have made you go the other way?', 'What surprised you?'. Leading questions ('Was our price the issue?') are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Leading questions corrupt the signal; open + anchored questions retrieve actual purchase reasoning rather than reasoning the interviewee thinks the company wants to hear.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-timing-within-30-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Interview MUST happen within 30 days of deal close. After 30 days, memory degrades and rationalisation grows.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Empirical recall research is consistent: post-30-day interviews retrieve mostly rationalisation; the methodology preserves the recency window.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-quarterly-synthesis-three-channel" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly synthesis MUST be distributed to PM (product/roadmap), marketing (messaging/positioning), and sales (objection-handling). Single-channel synthesis is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Insights die in inboxes; three-channel distribution is the only configuration that consistently moves win-rates because each function takes a different action from the same finding.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
