<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="earned-value-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Measure project performance objectively using PV, EV, AC to derive variance indices and forecasts. Use objective % complete only — never subjective opinion.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>evm</tag>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
      <tag>performance-metrics</tag>
      <tag>forecasting</tag>
      <tag>cost-control</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Earned Value Management</title>

    <summary>EVM is an objective, formula-driven approach to project performance measurement. It combines three primary inputs (Planned Value, Earned Value, Actual Cost) to produce variance metrics (SV, CV, SPI, CPI) and forecasts (EAC, ETC, TCPI). The single biggest rule: use objective % complete only — milestones, units completed, or 0/50/100 rules — never subjective opinion, which corrupts EV and cascades into false forecasts.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>"We're 80% done" is meaningless without context. EVM converts progress claims into objective financial metrics: CPI tells you the cost efficiency of work completed; SPI tells you schedule efficiency. CPI rarely improves spontaneously — a CPI less than 0.9 sustained for two periods signals a structural problem, not noise. TCPI greater than 1.10 typically indicates the project is unrecoverable on the current budget.</p>
      <p>EVM is used across predictive and hybrid projects, government, defense, infrastructure, and large IT organizations. It is the standard for ANSI/EIA-748 compliance and provides the objective metrics necessary for credible program forecasting and sponsor communication.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Predictive/hybrid projects with a fixed scope baseline and budget.</item>
        <item>Programs with monthly/weekly steering committee status reporting that require objective trend, not narrative.</item>
        <item>Government, defense, infrastructure, large IT — contracts that require ANSI/EIA-748 or similar standards.</item>
        <item>Engagements where "% complete" claims have lost credibility and you need an objective measure.</item>
        <item>Program forecasting (EAC/ETC) for board approval of additional budget.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure agile teams shipping continuously — burndown and flow metrics are better fits.</item>
        <item>Discovery/R&amp;D phases with no stable baseline to measure against.</item>
        <item>Projects under 6 weeks or under $50k — overhead exceeds insight gained.</item>
        <item>Internal startup work where speed matters more than financial control.</item>
        <item>Soft-cost projects with no convertible-to-dollars effort tracking.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="base-metrics">
      <p>The four foundational EVM metrics are the inputs and basic calculations from which all other indices and forecasts derive.</p>

      <list>
        <item>PV (Planned Value) = BAC × % planned — how much work should be done by now.</item>
        <item>EV (Earned Value) = BAC × % complete — how much work is actually done (objective measure only).</item>
        <item>AC (Actual Cost) — money or effort actually spent to date.</item>
        <item>BAC (Budget at Completion) — total approved project budget.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use objective % complete only: 0/50/100 rule, milestone-based, or units-completed — never subjective opinion.</statement>
        <rationale>Subjective % complete (team says "80% done") corrupts EV and cascades into false SPI/CPI/EAC values. One inflated EV reading misleads stakeholders for the rest of the project.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="performance-indices">
      <p>The performance indices are derived from the base metrics and provide a normalized view of schedule and cost efficiency.</p>

      <list>
        <item>SV (Schedule Variance) = EV - PV; positive = ahead, negative = behind schedule.</item>
        <item>CV (Cost Variance) = EV - AC; positive = under budget, negative = over budget.</item>
        <item>SPI (Schedule Performance Index) = EV / PV; greater than 1 = ahead, less than 1 = behind.</item>
        <item>CPI (Cost Performance Index) = EV / AC; greater than 1 = under budget, less than 1 = over budget.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Color-code: SPI/CPI in [0.95, 1.05] = green; [0.85, 0.95) = yellow; below 0.85 = red.</statement>
        <rationale>Consistent thresholds across all reporting periods allow stakeholders to compare status at a glance without reinterpreting scales each time.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Performance index calculation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Month 3 of 5, BAC = $100,000:
  PV  = $50,000  (50% of BAC planned)
  EV  = $40,000  (40% complete × BAC)
  AC  = $55,000  (actual spend)

  SV  = EV - PV  = -$10,000 (behind schedule)
  CV  = EV - AC  = -$15,000 (over budget)
  SPI = EV / PV  = 0.80 (schedule efficiency 80%, code: yellow)
  CPI = EV / AC  = 0.73 (cost efficiency 73%, code: red)
]]></code>
        <note>Both SPI and CPI below 0.85 — project shows red status on both schedule and cost.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="forecasting-metrics">
      <p>Forecasting metrics extrapolate current performance into predictions of final project cost and schedule. They answer the questions: how much more will this cost, when will it finish, and how hard must we work to recover?</p>

      <list>
        <item>EAC (Estimate at Completion) = BAC / CPI — predicted final cost assuming current efficiency continues.</item>
        <item>ETC (Estimate to Complete) = EAC - AC — additional cost needed to finish.</item>
        <item>VAC (Variance at Completion) = BAC - EAC — expected final over/under run.</item>
        <item>TCPI (To-Complete Performance Index) = (BAC - EV) / (BAC - AC) — required future efficiency to finish on budget.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Flag TCPI greater than 1.10 as likely unrecoverable; escalate to sponsor for re-baseline or scope reduction decision.</statement>
        <rationale>TCPI greater than 1.10 means the remaining work must be completed 10% more efficiently than the project has averaged — statistically improbable without a structural intervention.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring early CPI warnings because "it will recover".</description>
        <reason>CPI rarely improves on its own — the "CPI cliff" is empirically documented. A CPI of 0.80 at 20% complete predicts a final CPI of 0.70-0.85 in most projects.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <example type="good" title="Forecast interpretation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Continuing Month 3 example:
  EAC = BAC / CPI  = $100,000 / 0.73  = $137,000
  ETC = EAC - AC   = $137,000 - $55,000 = $82,000
  VAC = BAC - EAC  = $100,000 - $137,000 = -$37,000 (over budget)
  TCPI = (BAC - EV) / (BAC - AC) = ($100,000 - $40,000) / ($100,000 - $55,000)
       = $60,000 / $45,000 = 1.33

Interpretation:
  - Final cost predicted at $137,000 (37% over budget)
  - Still need $82,000 to complete
  - TCPI = 1.33 (must run 33% more efficiently than to date) — unrecoverable without scope cut or budget increase
]]></code>
        <note>All three forecasts point to the same conclusion: escalate for re-baseline or scope decision.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="four-step-process">
      <p>EVM implementation follows a four-step cycle: establish a baseline, measure progress each period, calculate metrics, and analyze variance. Each step has specific rules and common failure modes.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Step 1 — Establish Baseline: create a time-phased PV curve (planned spend per period); freeze as BAC with sponsor sign-off.</item>
        <item>Step 2 — Measure Progress: per reporting period, collect objective % complete for each WBS element; calculate EV = BAC × %complete; record actual AC.</item>
        <item>Step 3 — Calculate Metrics: SV, CV, SPI, CPI, EAC, ETC, VAC, TCPI per WBS element and rolled up to project.</item>
        <item>Step 4 — Forecast and Act: trend analysis over 3+ periods; variance analyst flags sustained CPI/SPI below threshold; PM decides corrective action; re-baseline only with CCB approval.</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track EVM at WBS level 3-4; not at the leaf task level and not at the project summary level only.</statement>
        <rationale>Leaf-level tracking generates noise from individual task estimation error. Summary-level tracking hides which work packages are in trouble until the overall CPI collapses.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Treat re-baselining as a P1 event; log it, require CCB approval, never automate.</statement>
        <rationale>Silent re-baselining is the most common way teams game EVM. A team with CPI 0.70 can re-baseline to show CPI 1.00 overnight. Require an explicit decision record for every re-baseline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <p>EVM implementations commonly fail in the same ways. Recognizing and avoiding these patterns prevents metrics corruption and credibility loss.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Re-baselining to "fix" red metrics without CCB approval.</description>
        <reason>Hides true variance. A project that has re-baselined three times has three sets of lies as its history. Future forecasts become meaningless.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Reporting SPI/CPI numbers without a 3-period trend line.</description>
        <reason>A single-period metric value tells you nothing about direction. Stakeholders need trajectory, not a snapshot. Always show the last 3 periods together.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Running both MegaLinter and the underlying native tool (e.g., ruff) twice in the same CI workflow because "the agent fixes faster from the SARIF".</description>
        <reason>Effort-driven scopes (consulting hours) can show CPI greater than 1 while the deliverable rots. Hours × rate; must pull rate-per-role.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <p>Automated EVM pipelines encounter specific pitfalls that human EVM analysts would catch. These gotchas are empirically documented across agentic deployments.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Enforce single base currency; agents must not silently mix USD/EUR/GBP in AC.</statement>
        <rationale>Currency mixing produces nonsense CPI values. Multi-currency programs need FX-hedged EAC with explicit conversion date and rate.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>% complete from PR counts or story point burn is a proxy — calibrate against milestone-based EV gates.</item>
        <item>AI tooling cost (token spend) is a real AC component; meter it and include in AC if material.</item>
        <item>Effort vs cost confusion: hours × role rate; agents must pull rate-per-role, not a flat blended rate.</item>
        <item>LLM narratives mask negative variance with euphemism; require numeric thresholds before any positive wording is permitted in status reports.</item>
        <item>EAC = BAC/CPI is pessimistic for early-stage projects; allow EAC = AC + (BAC - EV)/(CPI × SPI) for schedule-sensitive items.</item>
        <item>Garbage-in: subjective % complete corrupts EV; agents inherit and amplify the bias.</item>
        <item>Schedule-aggregator subagent must normalize progress + cost from multiple tools per WBS code.</item>
      </list>

      <note>A schedule-aggregator subagent pulls task progress (Jira/MS Project), labor + materials cost (timesheets, invoices), and computes weekly PV/EV/AC per work package. A metrics-engine produces SV/CV/SPI/CPI/EAC/ETC/TCPI with trend. A variance-analyst flags work packages with CPI less than 0.9 or SPI less than 0.9 for two consecutive periods, drafts a root-cause hypothesis, and proposes corrective actions. PM reviews; agent updates the EVM dashboard. Re-baselining always requires human approval.</note>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Use objective % complete: 0/50/100, milestone-based, or units-completed — not opinion.</item>
        <item>Lock baseline; require formal re-baseline (CCB) — never silent re-baseline by agent.</item>
        <item>Track at WBS level 3-4, not lowest leaf — too granular = noise, too coarse = blind.</item>
        <item>Pair EVM with risk register; risk events explain CPI/SPI shifts.</item>
        <item>For agile-hybrid: EVM at release (or PI) level, story burndown intra-iteration.</item>
        <item>TCPI greater than 1.10 typically signals project is unrecoverable on current budget — escalate honestly.</item>
        <item>Color-code: SPI/CPI in [0.95, 1.05] green, [0.85, 0.95) yellow, less than 0.85 red — consistency aids stakeholders.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>EVM can be implemented via specialized project management software, spreadsheets with custom formulas, or bespoke calculation pipelines. The choice depends on scale, integration requirements, and automation needs.</p>

      <list>
        <item>Microsoft Project (Plan 5) — EVM fields native, Graph API available.</item>
        <item>Primavera P6 — Heavy, EVM-strong, REST API limited.</item>
        <item>Smartsheet Resource Mgmt — EVM via custom columns and API.</item>
        <item>Deltek Cobra — Defense-grade EVMS, ANSI/EIA-748 certified.</item>
        <item>OpenProject — EVM via plugin/extension, open-source.</item>
        <item>GanttPRO — Lightweight, REST API available.</item>
        <item>Toggl Track + custom EVM — Pull AC from Toggl, compute EVM in code.</item>
        <item>Python (numpy/pandas) — EVM math, curves, Monte Carlo simulations.</item>
        <item>gnuplot / matplotlib — Render PV/EV/AC trend charts.</item>
        <item>Jira CLI — Pull WBS-coded issue progress.</item>
        <item>Tempo API — Worklog to AC mapping.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A production EVM pipeline distributes work across multiple specialized subagents, each responsible for one step in the data flow.</p>

      <list>
        <item>schedule-aggregator — Normalizes progress + cost from multiple tools per WBS code.</item>
        <item>evm-calculator — Pure function: inputs PV/EV/AC, outputs full EVM metric set.</item>
        <item>variance-analyst — Interprets metrics, references historical patterns, proposes actions.</item>
        <item>forecast-revisor — Runs 3-point estimates and Monte Carlo on EAC under uncertainty.</item>
        <item>evm-reporter — Emits stakeholder-ready dashboard (markdown/PDF/dashboard JSON).</item>
      </list>

      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Prompt pattern for evm-calculator:
You are an evm-calculator. Inputs: WBS state {wbs.yaml} with {bac, percent_complete,
actual_cost} per package, planned curve {pv_curve.json}. Compute and return JSON
per package: {pv, ev, ac, sv, cv, spi, cpi, eac, etc, vac, tcpi}. Use BAC/CPI for
EAC unless cpi < 0.6 (flag for human re-baseline review).

Prompt pattern for variance-analyst:
You are a variance-analyst. Given metrics {evm.json} for last 6 periods, identify
packages with CPI<0.9 or SPI<0.9 sustained ≥2 periods. For each, draft root-cause
hypothesis citing schedule/risk/scope-change events. Propose 2 corrective actions
with expected impact. Output JSON, do NOT propose re-baselining.
]]></code>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/evm-dashboard.md" purpose="EVM status report template with metrics table, variances, forecasts, and status color coding."/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/evm.py" purpose="Pure EVM calculator: inputs WP bac/pct_planned/pct_complete/ac, outputs full metric set (PV, EV, AC, SV, CV, SPI, CPI, EAC, ETC, VAC, TCPI)."/>
      <script path="scripts/eac-montecarlo.py" purpose="Three-point EAC under uncertainty via triangular Monte Carlo simulation."/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.acq.osd.mil/asda/dpc/cp/policy/evm.html">DOD EVMS Guidance</link>
      <link href="https://www.dau.edu">DAU EVM Gold Card (cheat sheet)</link>
      <ref slug="wbs-structure"/>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
      <ref slug="schedule-management"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
