<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cloud Commitment Discounts: RIs, Savings Plans, and Spot Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the finops-devops-cost-commitments methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="savings-plan-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before purchasing Savings Plans, calculate the minimum hourly On-Demand compute spend over the previous 90 days (5th percentile, not average) and commit to 50-60% of that minimum.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">The 5th percentile floor is the safest commitment basis; starting at 50-60% leaves buffer for workload reduction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ri-coverage-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Analyse 3+ months of stable workload data before purchasing RIs and target 60-80% RI coverage of the baseline instance count; choose Convertible RIs when the family may change.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">RI underutilisation wastes the discount premium; Convertible RIs trade a small premium for the right to exchange families.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="spot-eligibility" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Spot only for batch processing, CI/CD runners, ML training (with 30-minute checkpointing) and stateless services behind a load balancer; never for stateful databases or coordination services.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Spot interruption with 2-minute notice is incompatible with graceful database shutdown; checkpointing makes batch and ML tolerant of reclaim.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="multi-pool-diversification" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure Spot fleets across at least 3 instance type pools and 2 AZs and alert when commitment utilisation drops below 80% in any quarter.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Diversification reduces fleet-wide interruption below 1%; utilisation below 80% inverts the discount into waste.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="post-rightsize-commit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Commit to the rightsized baseline, never the pre-rightsize footprint; re-evaluate commitments quarterly against the rightsizing output.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Locking commitments to oversized instances guarantees underutilisation for the full term.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
