<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="finops-devops-cost-commitments Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for finops-devops-cost-commitments. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before purchasing Savings Plans, calculate the minimum hourly On-Demand compute spend over the previous 90 days (use the 5th percentile, not the average). Commit to 50-60% of that minimum as the first Compute Savings Plan. Increase coverage quarterly by reviewing utilization reports — target 70-80% baseline coverage, never exceed 85%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The 5th percentile floor is the amount spent in the cheapest hours of the last 90 days — the safest commitment. Starting at 50-60% coverage leaves buffer for workload reduction. Exceeding 85% coverage risks underutilization if business scales down.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Analyze 3+ months of stable workload data before purchasing RIs. Calculate RI coverage target as 60-80% of baseline (minimum steady-state) instance count. Choose Convertible RIs when the instance family may change within the commitment term; Standard when locked to a specific family. Monitor RI utilization weekly — underutilization below 80% indicates over-purchase.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">RI underutilization wastes the discount premium. Convertible RIs cost slightly more but allow exchanges — worth the premium during architectural evolution.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Spot instances for: batch processing, CI/CD runners, ML training jobs (with checkpointing every 30 minutes), and stateless web services behind a load balancer. Spot MUST NOT be used for: stateful databases, coordination services (ZooKeeper, etcd), or any service without automated restart handling. Always configure multi-AZ diversification with at least 3 instance type pools to reduce interruption probability.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Diversification across instance types and AZs reduces Spot interruption rate from ~5% to under 1% — the provider rarely reclaims capacity across all pools simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For multi-cloud environments, purchase provider-native commitment instruments per cloud rather than relying on third-party aggregators. Track commitment coverage quarterly via a coverage report: total spend, committed portion (RI/SP/CUD), On-Demand portion, Spot portion, and utilization of purchased commitments. Alert when RI/SP utilization drops below 80%.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Commitment utilization below 80% means you are paying for reserved capacity you do not use — the inverse of the intended discount. Quarterly review catches underutilization before the commitment renews.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
