<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-hook-model" title="Hook Model and Retention Loop Types">
  <summary>The Hook model (Trigger → Action → Variable Reward → Investment) maps each product flow to concrete retention mechanics; retention loop type must be identified before applying the Hook model.</summary>

  <section title="Retention Loop Types">
    <p>A retention loop is a self-reinforcing cycle where using the product creates reasons to return. Identify the primary type before designing any retention mechanic.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Content loop: new content from creators or algorithm draws users back (Netflix, TikTok)</item>
      <item>Social loop: activity from connections motivates return (Facebook, Slack)</item>
      <item>Progress loop: accumulating value makes leaving costly (Duolingo streaks)</item>
      <item>Stored value loop: data or content the user created lives only here (Notion, Evernote)</item>
      <item>Habit loop: triggered by a recurring routine (morning news app)</item>
      <item>Network loop: others depend on the user's presence (team collaboration tools)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Hook Model Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the trigger first; all other Hook components depend on it being reliable.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a trigger the action never starts. External triggers (push, email) are controllable but decay; internal triggers (boredom, loneliness, uncertainty) are durable but must be cultivated by associating the product with an existing emotional state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reduce the action to the minimum possible behavior between trigger and reward.</statement>
      <rationale>Every extra step between trigger and reward is friction that causes drop-off. The action should be the simplest behavior in anticipation of the reward — one tap, one swipe, one scan.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Rewards must be variable; predictable rewards become boring and stop driving return.</statement>
      <rationale>Variable schedules of reinforcement (unpredictable reward magnitude or timing) sustain engagement longer than fixed schedules. Three reward types: Tribe (social validation — likes, comments), Hunt (searching for content — scrolling), Self (personal achievement — level-up, streak).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Each Investment must increase future value and load the next trigger.</statement>
      <rationale>Investment creates stored value (data, preferences, social ties, reputation) that raises the cost of switching and makes the next session more valuable. Examples: following accounts, completing a profile, creating content, learning a shortcut.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trigger Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Taper external triggers over time; the goal is internal trigger formation.</statement>
      <rationale>External triggers (email, push) have open-rate decay and fatigue risk. The lifecycle plan should reduce trigger frequency as internal triggers form — measure internal trigger adoption by tracking unprompted direct opens vs notification-driven opens.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Best: internal trigger (user thinks of you when stimulus X occurs)</item>
      <item>Good: event-based trigger (real activity to show — "John commented")</item>
      <item>OK: time-based trigger (routine — 9 AM digest)</item>
      <item>Weak: generic reminder with no contextual anchor</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying streak mechanics to work tools or finance products.</description>
      <reason>Streaks work for habit/learning categories but backfire in contexts where users want predictability. Breaking a streak punishes power users who take vacations. Provide streak-freeze mechanics or choose a different Investment type.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using variable reward to drive engagement through anxiety triggers (infinite scroll, fear-of-missing-out notifications).</description>
      <reason>Manipulative designs face regulatory risk (EU DSA, UK Online Safety Act, AU eSafety) and destroy long-term trust. Variable reward must be net-positive in expectation; users who feel cheated uninstall and leave negative reviews.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Measuring retention with DAU/MAU for all products regardless of use-case cadence.</description>
      <reason>DAU/MAU is appropriate for habit products (daily news, social). For tools (weekly), utilities (monthly), or B2B workflows, the metric is misleading. Define "active" operationally per product type before measuring.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/hook-loop.txt">Fill-in-the-blank Hook sentence template per product flow</reference>
  <reference path="templates/retention-curves.py">DAU/MAU ratio + 8-week cohort curve script</reference>
</text>
