<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-workspace-setup" title="ClickUp Workspace Architecture">
  <summary>Hierarchy design, ClickApps configuration, custom status workflow, view setup, and custom field placement rules.</summary>

  <section title="Hierarchy Design">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep hierarchy to 3–4 levels: Workspace → Space → Folder → List. Add Task/Subtask levels but never create a 6th level of nesting via checklists as a hierarchy substitute.</statement>
      <rationale>Deeper hierarchies require more navigation clicks and degrade API query complexity; checklists cannot be queried as first-class items via API.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Spaces for department/product isolation with separate permissions and workflows; use Folders for project grouping, not timeline grouping.</statement>
      <rationale>Permissions are set at Space level; timeline-based folders (Q1, Q2) become stale and require migration; project-based folders (Feature Dev, Bug Tracking) remain stable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Field Placement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create custom fields at the highest applicable level (Workspace &gt; Space &gt; Folder &gt; List) so they inherit downward.</statement>
      <rationale>Fields created at List level must be recreated for every new list; Space-level fields are available to all lists in the Space automatically.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document all created custom field IDs in a config file — field IDs are UUIDs, not human-readable names, and are required for API updates.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents must match custom fields by ID, not name; names can be renamed by users, breaking agent queries silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/status-config.json">Custom status definitions JSON for development workflow</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Essential ClickApps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable at workspace level: Time Tracking (with estimates), Custom Fields, Priorities (Urgent/High/Normal/Low), Multiple Assignees. Enable Sprints at space level with 2-week duration and auto-close.</statement>
      <rationale>Workspace-level ClickApps apply uniformly; space-level Sprints allow engineering spaces to use cycles while marketing spaces use continuous flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Views Setup">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create six standard views per space: List (detailed, group by status), Board (kanban, WIP limits), Gantt (timeline, show dependencies), Calendar (due dates), Workload (capacity, requires estimates), Dashboard (metrics).</statement>
      <rationale>Each view serves a distinct PM function; missing the Workload view makes capacity planning invisible until tasks are already overdue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/folder-structure.yaml">Software project folder and list hierarchy example</reference>
  </section>
</text>
