<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automations" title="ClickUp Automations and Integrations">
  <summary>Native automation patterns, GitHub/Slack/Toggl integration setup, and automation governance rules.</summary>

  <section title="Native Automations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use native ClickUp automations for mechanical flows before building agent-driven automations: auto-assign on status change, notify on overdue, create subtasks from template on task creation.</statement>
      <rationale>Native automations run instantly, do not consume API rate limit, and require no infrastructure; agents should handle logic that native automations cannot express.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document all active automations in a shared "Automation Registry" list inside the workspace; review monthly for unused or conflicting automations.</statement>
      <rationale>Automation loops (trigger A fires action that triggers B which fires action back to A) cause infinite execution and exhaust the monthly automation limit; a registry makes circular dependencies visible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Automation: "When status changes to In Progress → assign Developer" + automation "When Developer assigned → set status to In Progress" — these two automations loop infinitely.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Integrations">
    <rule>
      <statement>GitHub integration: set branch naming to "clickup-{task_id}-{task_name}" and enable auto-status-on-merge to "Complete"; link PRs to tasks via branch name convention.</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent branch naming enables bidirectional traceability between code and tasks; auto-status on merge eliminates manual "mark as done" steps.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Archive tasks (set to "Won't Do") rather than deleting — deleted tasks cannot be recovered and break any rollup or reporting that referenced them.</statement>
      <rationale>ClickUp has no bulk undo; deletions are permanent. Won't Do status keeps historical data intact and preserves rollup counts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="API Rate Limits">
    <rule>
      <statement>ClickUp API v2: use Authorization header with token directly (no "Bearer" prefix); implement exponential backoff on 429 responses; bulk custom field updates require one POST per task per field.</statement>
      <rationale>The non-standard Authorization header format is a frequent agent bug; 100 req/min limit is hit quickly during workspace bootstrap; no bulk custom field endpoint exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-bootstrap.txt">Prompt for agent to create workspace hierarchy via API</reference>
  </section>
</text>
