<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="argocd-gitops Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for argocd-gitops as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Managing raw YAML manifests directly in ArgoCD without Helm or Kustomize.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Raw YAML duplicates configuration across environments. Updating an image tag requires editing the same value in every environment's YAML directory. Kustomize patches and Helm values files centralize shared config and allow per-env overrides without duplication.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using Git branches for environment promotion (e.g., a staging branch and a production branch for the same app).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Branch-per-environment causes merge conflicts and forces manual cherry-pick workflows. When the staging branch diverges from production, it is unclear what is actually deployed. Folder-per-environment (apps/myapp/overlays/staging vs overlays/production) keeps all environments in the same branch for easy comparison.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Storing application source code and Kubernetes manifests in the same repository.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A code commit triggers CI, which would push to the same repo, triggering ArgoCD, which triggers CI again — an infinite loop. Separate repos break this cycle: code repo triggers CI, CI updates the GitOps config repo, ArgoCD watches the config repo only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Placing plain Kubernetes Secrets (base64-encoded) in the GitOps repository.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Base64 is not encryption. Any repository reader can decode the values. Use External Secrets Operator, Sealed Secrets, or SOPS to encrypt secret values before committing to Git.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>App code and manifests in same repo — every code commit triggers a manifest sync; CI loop on the same repo causes infinite churn.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Separate "app repo" from "config repo" to break the trigger cycle.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Branches per environment — hot-fix in prod-branch must be back-ported to dev-branch; merge conflicts forever.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use folder-per-env in one branch.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Raw YAML for everything — drift across dev/, staging/, prod/ because someone hand-edited one.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use Helm or Kustomize with overlays.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>kubectl edit in production — ArgoCD detects drift and either reverts (auto-sync) or reports OutOfSync (manual sync).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Either way the change is undocumented. Lock down with RBAC.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>automated.selfHeal: true + flapping resources — a Job that creates a TTL'd resource looks like drift; ArgoCD keeps re-creating.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use ignoreDifferences or annotate argocd.argoproj.io/compare-options: IgnoreExtraneous.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>ApplicationSet template explosion — generators × clusters × envs = thousands of Applications; one bad template breaks them all simultaneously.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Test with --dry-run and use progressive sync.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Sync waves misordered — agents add a wave to make CRDs deploy before CRs but forget that hooks (PreSync) run before all waves; result: hook fails on missing CRD.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Order waves correctly: CRDs before CRs, hooks before both.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Sharded controller misconfig — with 100+ clusters, single controller OOMs; sharding via replicas requires correct argocd-application-controller env.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Default config silently single-shards.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Helm + ArgoCD value precedence — values from valueFiles, values, helm.parameters merge in non-obvious order.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents add a parameters block expecting override but valueFiles wins.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>syncPolicy.automated.prune: true mass-deletes resources when manifests are accidentally moved/renamed.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always pair with prune: false until tested, then enable behind feature-flag.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>No sync windows — auto-sync at 3 AM Saturday during a security incident → uncontrolled changes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Configure syncWindows to block prod changes during business-hours-only or freeze periods.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Notifications missing — sync fails, no one sees it for hours.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Configure argocd-notifications with Slack/Teams/PagerDuty and per-app subscriptions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
