<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="market-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Combined methodology for sizing a market (TAM/SAM/SOM), classifying trend timing, mapping competitive landscape, and producing a feature-gap matrix from the top 5 competitors.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>market-sizing</tag>
      <tag>competitive-landscape</tag>
      <tag>trend-analysis</tag>
      <tag>feature-gap</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Market Analysis</title>
    <summary>Market analysis is the combined methodology for sizing a market (TAM/SAM/SOM), classifying trend timing, mapping the competitive landscape (15-20 named players with URLs), and producing a feature-gap matrix from the top 5 competitors. The core rule: run both top-down and bottom-up sizing; if they diverge more than 2x, flag it as a research gap rather than averaging. These four sub-methodologies share data sources and produce JSON-first outputs that feed downstream SDD artifacts.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Desk research without methodology produces TAM theatre (Gartner numbers inflated 3-10x), hallucinated competitors (invented product names), stale pricing (6-18 months behind live pages), and unfalsifiable trend-timing labels ("Early Majority" with no quantitative anchor). Separating the four passes into distinct subagent invocations keeps context windows small, enables JSON validation per pass, and makes the competitive matrix reproducible via competitor snapshots.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before writing a spec.md for a new product idea — produces SAM number and competitive whitespace</item>
        <item>When the GTM strategist or product manager needs a quantified opportunity ($X M SAM, Y% CAGR, Z named competitors)</item>
        <item>Quarterly competitor refresh: re-scrape pricing pages, changelogs, review sites for moves</item>
        <item>Pre-fundraise: investor decks need a defensible TAM and a feature matrix</item>
        <item>Niche viability scoring inside niche-evaluation flows — replaces guesses with sourced numbers</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-customer custom builds with no market</item>
        <item>Pure technical or architecture research — route to pro/dev/software-architect instead</item>
        <item>Ideas fewer than 2 weeks from launch where research will not change the decision</item>
        <item>Highly regulated B2B niches (defense, medical devices) where public data is scarce — use primary expert interviews</item>
        <item>Working business where the decision is growth, not entry — switch to growth-marketer or conversion-optimizer</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Market Sizing (TAM/SAM/SOM)">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every TAM number must carry source, year, and geography in the same line. Reject standalone dollar figures with no provenance.</statement>
        <rationale>Top-down numbers from Gartner/Statista are routinely inflated 3-10x. LLMs parrot fabricated CAGRs with high confidence. Citation in the same line is the minimum defense against hallucinated market sizes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always run sizing top-down AND bottom-up. Flag divergence above 2x as a research gap — do not average or pick the more favorable number.</statement>
        <rationale>Divergence above 2x signals a definitional mismatch, a data quality problem, or a constraint that was not applied consistently. Averaging hides the problem; flagging forces investigation before the number enters a deck or a spec.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>TAM: total revenue if you captured 100% of everyone who could ever buy — the ceiling, not the plan</item>
        <item>SAM: portion of TAM reachable given real constraints (geography, language, industry, company size, tech stack)</item>
        <item>SOM: realistic market share capturable in 3-5 years given budget, brand, and competition</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Trend Classification and Timing Assessment">
      <rule>
        <statement>Assign every trend to one of three categories: macro (5-10 years), industry (2-5 years), micro (6-24 months). Macro trends are context; industry trends are actionable; micro trends are tactical.</statement>
        <rationale>Labeling everything "early majority" confuses the timeline. A clear category assignment helps teams decide whether to lead, follow, or skip the trend.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Macro (5-10 years): AI adoption, remote work normalization, demographic aging — use as context, not opportunity</item>
        <item>Industry (2-5 years): no-code tools, creator economy, vertical SaaS — the actionable sweet spot</item>
        <item>Micro (6-24 months): specific tool adoption, API standardization, pricing-model shift — tactical opportunity</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>For every trend claim, cite the growth driver (what accelerates this trend?), adoption curve position with a quantitative anchor (not just a label), threats (what could reverse it?), and timing verdict (too early / just right / too late).</statement>
        <rationale>Without anchors and drivers, trend timing is unfalsifiable opinion. "Early majority adoption" means nothing without a number (% of target market, cohort size, adoption velocity).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Competitor Discovery and Mapping">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap the competitor list at 20 named entries with working URLs. Longer lists are hallucination magnets — nobody reads them and the data quality degrades past 20.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents happily produce 40 competitor names when asked for a comprehensive list. Beyond 20, entries are increasingly invented, merged, or mischaracterized. A tight, URL-verified list is more actionable than an exhaustive fiction.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Reject any competitor entry without a working URL. Require URL plus a screenshot or page text as evidence that the product currently exists.</statement>
        <rationale>Web-search agents invent product names, merge two products into one, or cite discontinued products as active competitors. URL verification is the minimum bar for a credible competitive landscape.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Direct: same solution, same problem, same customer — most visible, most cited</item>
        <item>Indirect: different solution, same problem (e.g., Slack vs. Email for team communication)</item>
        <item>Substitute: alternative approach entirely (e.g., outsource vs. software)</item>
        <item>Potential: companies that could enter with their existing capabilities and distribution</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Feature-Gap Matrix">
      <rule>
        <statement>Snapshot competitor sites before running the feature matrix. The data layer must be reproducible 6 months later — a matrix built from live pages has no baseline to diff against.</statement>
        <rationale>Competitors ship weekly. A feature-matrix assertion from memory or a live page is immediately stale and cannot be audited. Dated snapshots enable the quarterly diff that surfaces actual movement.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Classify every feature as table stakes (Y at all top-5 competitors), opportunity (Y at 1-2, N/P at others), or validate demand (N at all). Cite at least 5 corroborating reviews or forum posts for every gap declared as an "opportunity."</statement>
        <rationale>Feature gaps can be intentional. Without buyer demand evidence, a whitespace claim leads to building features nobody needs while ignoring the actual gaps buyers care about.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Table stakes (Y at all top-5 competitors): required to compete; building these is cost of entry, not differentiation</item>
        <item>Opportunity (Y at 1-2 competitors, N or P at others): candidate for differentiation — validate demand before building</item>
        <item>Validate demand (N at all competitors): may be a gap or may be intentional — check reviews for evidence of demand before claiming whitespace</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Common Mistakes and Agent Gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Running only top-down sizing without a bottom-up cross-check</description>
        <reason>Top-down numbers from analyst reports are the ceiling, not the plan. Without a bottom-up check, the SOM is detached from operational reality and cannot be defended to investors or the team.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Feature-matrix based on live pages without a snapshot</description>
        <reason>A live-page feature matrix cannot be reproduced 6 months later, cannot be diffed to show competitive movement, and is immediately stale as competitors ship.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Declaring whitespace without review-site evidence of buyer demand</description>
        <reason>Feature gaps can be intentional. Without buyer demand evidence, a whitespace claim leads to building features nobody needs while ignoring the actual gaps buyers care about.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using a competitor list that omits indirect and substitute competitors</description>
        <reason>Indirect and substitute competitors are the most common source of disruption. A list of only direct competitors produces a false sense of the competitive moat.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents inventing competitor names or citing discontinued products</description>
        <reason>Web-search agents hallucinate product names, especially at scale. Require a working URL and recent page content for every competitor before accepting the entry.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Averaging top-down and bottom-up sizings when they diverge 3x</description>
        <reason>Divergence above 2x is a red flag, not noise to average away. Average the numbers and you hide the underlying problem (definitional mismatch, bad data, constraint omission) from the team.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using Gartner / Statista TAM as ground truth without cross-validation</description>
        <reason>Analyst reports often inflate market sizes 3-10x. Use them as anchors and cross-check with bottom-up sizing. If they diverge >2x, investigate the discrepancy before using the number in a deck.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Trend labels without quantitative anchors ("Early Majority" with no % adoption cited)</description>
        <reason>Without a number (% of target market, cohort size, adoption velocity), trend-timing claims are unfalsifiable opinion. Require a cited anchor for every Rogers curve position.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Separate the four passes (sizing, trend, competitor discovery, feature matrix) into distinct subagent invocations to keep context windows small.</item>
        <item>Produce JSON-first outputs per pass that feed downstream SDD artifacts — market-sizing.json, trend-analysis.json, competitive-landscape.json, feature-matrix.json.</item>
        <item>Always snapshot competitor sites before running a feature matrix — use firecrawl or Playwright to capture dated artifacts.</item>
        <item>Maintain a competitor registry with stable IDs, last-audited timestamps, and removal justification so you can track competitive movement over time.</item>
        <item>Run quarterly competitor refreshes to re-scrape pricing pages, changelogs, review sites, and feature sets — produces a time-series that reveals competitive moves.</item>
        <item>For every TAM/SAM/SOM number, include source, year, and geography in the same cell so data provenance is always traceable.</item>
        <item>For top-down vs bottom-up divergence >2x, flag as research gap and investigate the discrepancy (definitional mismatch, bad data source, missing constraints) rather than averaging.</item>
        <item>For trend timing, cite the driver (technology threshold, regulatory mandate, demographic shift), adoption curve anchor (% of target market, cohort size, velocity), threats (competing technology, reversal), and verdict (too early / just right / too late).</item>
        <item>For feature gaps, require 5+ review-site quotes or forum posts before declaring whitespace — gut feel on features is wrong 80% of the time.</item>
        <item>For competitor lists, cap at 20 entries and require working URLs + recent page content for every entry to prevent hallucination and stale data.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/market-sizing.md" purpose="TAM/SAM/SOM sizing template with top-down and bottom-up sections"/>
      <template path="templates/trend-analysis.md" purpose="Trend analysis template with drivers, threats, and timing assessment"/>
      <template path="templates/competitive-landscape.md" purpose="Competitor landscape table with direct, indirect, and whitespace sections"/>
      <template path="templates/feature-matrix.md" purpose="Feature matrix and gap validation templates"/>
      <template path="templates/competitors-snapshot.sh" purpose="Bash script that freezes a competitor URL set into a dated snapshot folder via firecrawl"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
