<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Objection FAQ Library Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Objection FAQ Library MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="objection-mined-not-invented" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Objections MUST come from real lost-deal artifacts (&gt;=10). Invented or assumed objections are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — lost-deal audit Q4 2025">Real-customer language is what closes; agency-generated FAQ blocks read as marketing fluff.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-per-rebuttal" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each rebuttal MUST cite evidence (case study, customer quote, benchmark, screenshot). Un-backed rebuttals are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sales-rebuttal effectiveness studies">Without evidence, rebuttals are claims vs. claims; evidence shifts the burden of proof.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="funnel-stage-tagged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every entry MUST tag funnel-stage (ToFu / MoFu / BoFu). Stage-blind libraries waste copy at wrong stages.</statement>
      <rationale source="Operational practice — sales enablement">ToFu objections (trust, fit) differ from BoFu (timing, budget); tagging routes copy correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pre-empt-format" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Library MUST include &gt;=2 copy variants per objection (proposal-inline + landing-page FAQ). Single-variant libraries cannot serve both surfaces.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sales enablement practice">Proposal copy and FAQ-block copy differ in voice + length; one-variant libraries force rewrite at use.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-refresh" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Library MUST be refreshed monthly with new lost-deal evidence. Stale libraries drift from current objections.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — lost-deal velocity tracking">Buyer objections shift with market conditions (recession / AI hype / category-creation); monthly refresh keeps copy live.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
