<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Register Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the stakeholder-register methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="groups-as-groups" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify groups as groups (e.g. 'Security Council', 'Beta Customers') when a single person is not authoritative.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Splitting a group into individuals loses the fact that authority is collective.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-not-gut-feel" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use evidence (org chart, budget authority, RACI) for Power rating — not gut feel.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — register-bias audits">Two PMs produce different ratings without anchored evidence; anchoring to org-chart and budget makes ratings defensible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="verify-attitude-in-conversation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Verify attitude through direct conversation, not from written communication inference.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">Written communication is systematically polite; agents reading transcripts over-classify as 'Supportive'.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="attitude-unknown-without-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store attitude as 'unknown' when no evidence exists in inputs — never invent an attitude.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — register-bias audits">An agent that infers 'supportive' from polite tone produces a false register.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pii-separated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep PII (email, phone, salary) in a separate access-controlled file; the in-repo register holds only ID and role.</statement>
      <rationale source="Privacy practice (GDPR Art. 9 if attitude implies political opinion)">A register committed to a shared repo exposes sensitive contact and compensation data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="refresh-after-stage-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Refresh the register after each stage gate; archive the previous version.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-trail practice">A stakeholder who was Low-Low at kickoff can become High-High at launch; archived history shows when and why.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Fully internal personal-tool project with only you and your manager</item>
      <item>Pure agile team building for itself with one PO and no external dependencies</item>
      <item>Pre-discovery exploration where stakeholders are not yet defined</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
