<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-stakeholder-framework" title="Stakeholder Register Framework">
  <summary>Five-step process for identifying, analyzing, mapping, and engaging project stakeholders using the Power-Interest grid.</summary>

  <section title="Identification">
    <p>Identify every person or group who affects or is affected by the project. Include indirect stakeholders often missed:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Project team members and leads</item>
      <item>Management, executives, sponsors</item>
      <item>Customers and end users (often listed as a group, not individuals)</item>
      <item>Suppliers and vendors</item>
      <item>Regulatory bodies, security council, data privacy, accessibility</item>
      <item>"Who can stop this project for 2+ weeks?" — the most important identification question</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify groups as groups (e.g., "Security Council", "Beta Customers") when a single person is not authoritative.</statement>
      <rationale>Splitting a group into individuals loses the fact that the authority is collective. An agent that lists "Alice, Bob, Carol from Security" implies any one of them can unblock — they cannot.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Power-Interest Grid">
    <list>
      <item>Manage Closely (High Power, High Interest) — active engagement, involve in decisions; weekly or more frequent contact</item>
      <item>Keep Satisfied (High Power, Low Interest) — regular updates, no surprises; bi-weekly contact</item>
      <item>Keep Informed (Low Power, High Interest) — regular communication, gather feedback; weekly status</item>
      <item>Monitor (Low Power, Low Interest) — minimal effort, watch for quadrant changes; monthly summary</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use evidence (org chart, budget authority, RACI) for Power rating — not gut feel.</statement>
      <rationale>Two PMs produce different power ratings for the same stakeholder. Anchoring to org-chart position and budget authority makes ratings defensible and consistent across project phases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Verify attitude through direct conversation, not from written communication inference.</statement>
      <rationale>Written communication (email, Slack) is systematically polite. Agents reading written transcripts will over-classify stakeholders as "Supportive". Only direct conversation reveals resistance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Register Maintenance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Refresh the register after each stage gate; archive the previous version to track attitude changes over time.</statement>
      <rationale>A stakeholder who was Low-Low at kickoff can become High-High at launch (e.g., security team). The archived history shows when and why the quadrant shifted — valuable for post-mortems.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Track last_touch field; automated weekly diff vs comms log flags Manage-Closely stakeholders with zero recent contact</item>
      <item>Use the register as input to RACI, Communications Plan, and Risk Register</item>
      <item>Privacy: keep PII in a separate access-controlled file; the in-repo register holds only ID and role</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/stakeholders.yaml">YAML register schema with all required fields</reference>
    <reference path="templates/stakeholder-profile.md">Individual stakeholder profile with engagement history</reference>
  </section>
</text>
