<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-stakeholder-data" title="Stakeholder Register Data Schema and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>YAML data schema for the stakeholder register, privacy handling rules, and agent-specific pitfalls in stakeholder identification and attitude classification.</summary>

  <section title="YAML Schema">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
- id: S-01
  name: Olena Kravchenko
  role: VP Engineering
  dept: Engineering
  interests:
    - delivery cadence
    - tech-debt reduction
  influence: H        # H | M | L
  impact: H
  attitude: supportive  # supportive | neutral | resistant | unknown
  quadrant: manage-closely  # manage-closely | keep-satisfied | keep-informed | monitor
  comms:
    cadence: weekly
    channel: 1:1 + Slack DM
  notes: Sponsor for Q2 platform initiative.
  last_touch: 2026-04-22

- id: S-02
  name: Security Council
  role: Group
  dept: Security
  interests: [compliance, audit-trail]
  influence: H
  impact: M
  attitude: resistant
  quadrant: keep-satisfied
  comms:
    cadence: bi-weekly
    channel: review meeting
  last_touch: 2026-04-15
]]></code>
      <note>Quadrant is auto-computed from influence × interest but stored explicitly so changes are visible in diffs.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store attitude as "unknown" when no evidence exists in inputs — never invent an attitude.</statement>
      <rationale>An agent that infers "supportive" from polite email tone produces a false register. Unknown flags the PM to gather direct evidence before trusting the classification.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Privacy Handling">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep PII (email, phone, salary) in a separate access-controlled file; the in-repo register holds only ID and role.</statement>
      <rationale>A stakeholder register committed to a shared repo exposes sensitive contact and compensation data. Separation allows broad repo access while restricting PII to those who need it.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Do not publish the full register to stakeholders themselves — attitude fields are internal; redact before sharing</item>
      <item>Apply the same access control tier as the project charter (executive-only for High-Power stakeholders)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require attitude evidence as a quoted string from source material; reject any attitude assignment without a quote.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents systematically over-classify as "Supportive" because meeting transcripts and emails are written in professional, polite language. Requiring a quoted source prevents pattern-matching on tone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Agents extract names from email signatures and infer seniority from job title — many blockers are mid-level gatekeepers (procurement, security review)</item>
      <item>Group stakeholders get split into individuals if you ask the LLM to "list people" — preserve the group when authority is collective</item>
      <item>Stale registers go undetected: build a last_touch field and a weekly cron diff vs comms logs</item>
      <item>Mid-level "influencer" stakeholders are systematically under-rated; explicitly prompt for "who has a veto even if not in the org chart?"</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
