<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Agency Rebrand Methodology Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Agency Rebrand Methodology application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-client-notice-30-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Notify active clients ≥30 days before public rebrand via personal email from founder. Include: new name, why, what changes (contract addendum), what does not (team, work, contacts).</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Surprise rebrands trigger churn cycles; 30-day notice converts uncertainty into routine admin.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-contract-addenda-not-renewals" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Issue addenda assigning existing contracts to the new entity. Do NOT force renewal. Renewals expose every term to renegotiation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Standard M&amp;A practice: assign, don't re-paper, to preserve commercial terms.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-301-redirect-map" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build a 1:1 redirect map for every URL with traffic &gt; 0. Deploy 301s the day the new domain goes live; keep ≥24 months.</statement>
      <rationale source="Moz / Ahrefs case studies">Without 301s, 60-80% of accrued SEO equity is lost in 90 days (Moz / Ahrefs case studies).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-portfolio-migration" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Migrate top 10 case studies to new domain BEFORE launch. New site goes live with a working portfolio, not 'coming soon'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Empty portfolio at launch resets credibility to zero (first-impression weight).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-post-launch-audit-30-days" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>30 days post-launch, audit redirect coverage, organic traffic, churn vs baseline, brand mentions. Surface deltas explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale source="Industry consensus + practitioner experience">Most rebrand failures show up at day 30-60; explicit audit catches them in the recoverable window.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>