<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="information-architecture">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Organize content by user tasks and goals. Produces category structure, taxonomy, sitemap. Validate with card sorting and tree testing.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>information-architecture</tag>
      <tag>navigation</tag>
      <tag>taxonomy</tag>
      <tag>card-sorting</tag>
      <tag>tree-testing</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Information Architecture</title>

    <summary>Organize content by user tasks and goals. Produces category structure, taxonomy, sitemap. Validate with card sorting and tree testing.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Navigation organized around internal product logic or org charts fails users who search by task or topic. A structured IA process (research → organize → validate) prevents the most common failure: building navigation that makes sense to the team but not to the user. 4-7 top-level categories is the validated sweet spot for scannability.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating a sitemap or taxonomy from a product spec, feature list, or content inventory</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing IA against card sort or tree test data to identify mismatches</item>
        <item>Drafting an IA strategy document from user research findings and business requirements</item>
        <item>Proposing navigation label alternatives when current labels test poorly with users</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Validating a proposed IA — agents draft structure but cannot replace card sorting and tree testing with real users</item>
        <item>Real-time search relevance tuning — IA shapes browse; search ranking is a separate discipline</item>
        <item>Micro-level layout decisions — IA governs content organization, not component placement within a page</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="organization-schemes">
      <rule>
        <statement>Organize content around user tasks and goals, not internal product structure or org chart.</statement>
        <rationale>Internal organization reflects how the team thinks, not how users search. Task-based IA (Shop, Learn, Get Help) maps to user intent; feature-based IA (Products, Platform, Resources) maps to company structure and fails navigation findability tests.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Topic-based: organize by subject matter (most common for content-heavy sites)</item>
        <item>Task-based: organize by what users want to do (best for tool/application navigation)</item>
        <item>Audience-based: organize by user type (use only when audiences have truly distinct needs)</item>
        <item>Chronological: organize by time (logs, news, events)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="navigation-depth-and-breadth">
      <rule>
        <statement>Target 4-7 top-level categories; keep navigation to 3 levels maximum depth.</statement>
        <rationale>Below 4 categories feels sparse and forces overloaded categories. Above 7 exceeds comfortable visual scanning range (Miller's Law). Deeper than 3 levels buries content in paths users cannot remember or navigate back from.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="labeling-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write labels in user vocabulary; never use internal codenames, acronyms, or "Misc" / "Other" / "Resources" without specific scope.</statement>
        <rationale>User-language labels require no translation. Internal terminology forces users to learn your vocabulary before they can navigate. "Resources" with no scope defined is the most common navigation label failure — it can contain anything and therefore signals nothing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Validate labels with 5 users before running a tree test — a wrong label makes tree test data uninterpretable.</statement>
        <rationale>If a label is misunderstood, users take wrong paths not because the structure is bad but because the label failed. Label validation is cheaper than rerunning a full tree test.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="scalability">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define rules for where new content types will go before launch; do not add categories reactively when content accumulates.</statement>
        <rationale>Reactive category creation produces inconsistent depth and "miscellaneous" buckets. Pre-defined taxonomy rules keep the IA coherent as content grows.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="mega-menu-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use mega menus for sites with 40+ pages organized into 4+ top-level categories with meaningful subcategories at L2.</statement>
        <rationale>Mega menus expose L2 content without requiring navigation into L1 first, reducing clicks for users who already know their destination category. Overuse on small sites creates visual complexity without benefit.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Mega menu for e-commerce site">
        <note>E-commerce with Products, Solutions, Resources, Company: each top-level item expands to show 3-6 subcategories in columns, with a featured content block. Users can jump directly to "Enterprise Solutions" without clicking "Solutions" first.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="hub-and-spoke-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use hub-and-spoke for task-focused applications where users complete one task per session, then return to a central dashboard.</statement>
        <rationale>Hub-and-spoke minimizes navigation complexity by removing the need for cross-spoke navigation. Users go from hub to task and back — no need to find "related" content or browse.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="flat-structure-pattern">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use flat structure (1-2 levels) for small sites with under 20 pages, marketing sites, and portfolio sites.</statement>
        <rationale>Small sites with deep hierarchies bury content unnecessarily. Flat structure keeps all content within 2 clicks of home, reducing navigation overhead for simple content sets.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="validation-workflow">
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow this mandatory validation sequence: card sort → proposed IA → label validation (5 users) → tree test → refined IA → build.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent-generated or team-designed IA without validation produces navigation that makes sense to the team but fails with real users. Each validation step has a different failure mode; all three are required.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Card sort: discovers how users group content (inputs IA structure)</item>
        <item>Label validation: confirms users interpret category labels as intended (prevents tree test corruption)</item>
        <item>Tree test: confirms users can find specific content in the proposed hierarchy (validates findability)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never treat agent-generated IA as final without tree testing — the most common IA failure mode.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents generate internally consistent structures that may not match user mental models. Tree testing with real users is the only way to validate that users can navigate the structure, not just that the structure is logically coherent.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="ecommerce-ia-example">
      <example type="good" title="Organization scheme: task-based">
        <note>Shop, Learn, Get Help. Shop → By Category, By Brand, Sale Items. Learn → Buying Guides, Style Tips, Product Reviews. Get Help → Order Status, Returns, Contact Us. Labels use user verbs, not company nouns. Maximum 2 levels deep.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="saas-ia-example">
      <example type="good" title="Organization scheme: user journey">
        <note>Discover, Build, Grow. Discover → Features, Solutions, Pricing. Build → Documentation, API Reference, Tutorials. Grow → Case Studies, Best Practices, Community. L1 names reflect user intent stages, not product feature categories.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-ia-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Navigation structure mirrors org chart (Marketing, Product, Engineering, Support as L1 categories)</description>
        <reason>Users do not know or care about internal org structure. They navigate by their goals. Org-based IA forces users to guess which department owns the content they need.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Category named "Resources" or "Miscellaneous" without specific scope</description>
        <reason>"Resources" signals nothing about what it contains. Users cannot predict its contents and skip it in navigation. Everything needs a specific, content-accurate label.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>IA change that affects URL structure shipped without SEO review</description>
        <reason>URL structure changes break search engine indexing and user-bookmarked links. Any IA change touching URLs requires human sign-off and redirect planning before deploy.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Agent receives product spec or feature list. Produces: (1) proposed category structure at L1 and L2, (2) taxonomy document defining content types and tag groups, (3) sitemap skeleton in markdown, (4) validation plan specifying card sort type and tree test scope. Second agent pass takes card sort results and tree test failure data and produces revised sitemap with changes justified by data.</p>
      <reference path="templates/ia-strategy.md">IA strategy document template</reference>
      <reference path="templates/sitemap.md">Sitemap skeleton template</reference>
      <reference path="templates/taxonomy.md">Taxonomy document template</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="where-ia-fails">
      <p>Agents generating IA from a feature list will produce an internally consistent structure that may not match user mental models — always validate with card sorting or tree testing before building. Taxonomy decisions involve business, legal, and content governance constraints that are invisible to the agent without explicit input. Navigation depth vs. breadth trade-offs (2 levels wide vs. 4 levels deep) require user task data the agent rarely has access to; it will default to shallow and broad, which is usually right but not always. Large-scale IA (thousands of content items) requires faceted taxonomy and search architecture that goes well beyond what a markdown sitemap can represent. Agents will not proactively identify "orphan" content (pages with no logical parent) without a complete content inventory as input.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow-detailed">
      <p>A Claude agent receives a product spec or feature list and produces: (1) a proposed category structure at L1 and L2, (2) a taxonomy document defining content types, attributes, and tag groups, (3) a sitemap skeleton in markdown, and (4) a validation plan recommending which card sort type and tree test scope to run. A second agent pass takes card sort results and tree test failure data and produces a revised sitemap with specific changes justified by the data.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents generating sitemaps from feature lists will create IA that mirrors the feature roadmap, not the user's mental model</description>
        <reason>Explicitly instruct to use user goal framing in prompts</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Navigation label generation tends toward corporate-speak ("Solutions", "Resources", "Platform")</description>
        <reason>Require plain-language alternatives in the prompt</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents do not spontaneously account for SEO implications of URL/category structure</description>
        <reason>If SEO matters, add a constraint to the prompt ("categories should be primary keywords")</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Human sign-off required before any IA change that affects URL structure</description>
        <reason>Broken URLs cause SEO damage and user-bookmarked links to fail</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Tree test validation is non-optional; treating agent-generated IA as final without testing</description>
        <reason>The most common IA failure mode</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Start with user tasks, not content types — IA should be organized around what users want to do, not how your team organizes work internally</item>
        <item>4-7 L1 categories is the sweet spot for top-level navigation; below 4 feels sparse, above 7 exceeds comfortable scanning range</item>
        <item>Validate labels with 5 users before committing to a tree test — a wrong label makes tree test data uninterpretable</item>
        <item>Design for growth: define rules for where new content types will go before launching, not after content starts accumulating</item>
        <item>Document the IA in version-controlled markdown (not only in Figma) so engineering, SEO, and content teams can reference and diff it</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ia-strategy.md" purpose="Strategy document: research summary, organization approach, navigation design, labeling, search, validation plan"/>
      <template path="templates/sitemap.md" purpose="Sitemap skeleton with page inventory table"/>
      <template path="templates/taxonomy.md" purpose="Taxonomy document: content types, categories, tags, naming conventions"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/information-architecture/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/mental-models/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
