<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="experimentation-at-scale Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for experimentation-at-scale. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Idea-triager (sonnet): On idea intake. Input: Idea text, opportunity tree, traffic estimate. Output: Testability score + tier (A/B, prototype, qual, irreversible). Cheap models for collection and triage.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sonnet for structured task decomposition. Triage gates ideas before PM invests in hypothesis authoring.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hypothesis-author (sonnet): Per candidate idea. Input: Idea, opportunity tree node, prior experiments. Output: experiment-doc.md with if-then-because, primary metric, MDE. Reject if hypothesis names a feature instead of a behavior change. Reject if MDE is missing or &gt; likely effect by 3x. Require prior_evidence: field with at least 2 sources.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sonnet for structured authoring. Hypothesis-author must enforce behavioral framing and evidence requirements before any sample-size math runs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ice-rice-ranker (haiku): Weekly slate. Input: Hypothesis pool, eng dep graph, current OKRs. Output: Ranked slate with confidence, effort, reach, dep flags. Feed eng dep graph; ranker will otherwise ignore 6-week blockers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Haiku for ranking math. Dep awareness prevents surface of ready-to-ship ideas that actually depend on long-running work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assumption-mapper (sonnet): Pre-launch. Input: Hypothesis, surface. Output: Falsifiable assumptions + stop conditions + decision rule. Pair every experiment with a kill criterion before launch.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sonnet for structured writing. Stop-conditions make the kill threshold explicit and prevent PM bias toward shipping.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Readout-interpreter (opus): At decision point. Input: Ops readout JSON, hypothesis doc, segment cuts. Output: Verdict (ship/iterate/kill/extend) + caveats. Check SRM and power before reading lift. Fail fast on invalid experiments. Surface guardrail breaches BEFORE primary metric. Surface novelty risk if runtime less than 14 days OR engagement metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opus for verdict synthesis where misreading is expensive. Fail-fast on validity checks prevents nicely worded ship memos on broken assignments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stakeholder-narrator (sonnet): At decision point. Input: Verdict, OKR map, audience. Output: Exec memo, slack blurb, ticket update. Force verbatim copy of CI low/high; never paraphrase. Never round confidence intervals ("4% lift, 95% confidence") into clean numbers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sonnet for narrative writing. Verbatim numbers prevent stakeholders from misinterpreting precision.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Learning-curator (opus): Monthly. Input: All closed experiments. Output: Opportunity-tree edits, "patterns we found", "patterns we killed". Require N&gt;=5 with shared opportunity-tree branch before emitting a "pattern" claim. Do not hallucinate patterns from N=2 experiments.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opus for synthesis. Monthly curation links experiments back to the discovery tree, building org memory and preventing local-maxima drifts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Roadmap-impact-modeler (sonnet): Quarterly. Input: Closed experiments, OKR tree. Output: Adjusted forecast for next quarter's roadmap. Emit ranges and label assumptions; never single-number forecasts. Do not compound point estimates into 4-quarter forecasts and report as fact.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sonnet for structured writing. Range forecasts prevent the illusion of precision and flag assumptions explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-register the decision rule, not just the metric — written, signed by sponsor, archived in Notion. Without this, "we won" becomes negotiable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Decision rules encode what "victory" means before the data arrives. Otherwise, post-hoc interpretation drifts based on leadership politics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tie every experiment to one opportunity-tree node; if it doesn't link, it's a CTA test, not product work — schedule, but cap to ≤25% of slate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Opportunity-linked experiments build strategic learning. Capping CTA tests prevents drift into micro-optimizations that look productive but don't inform roadmap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep one primary metric per experiment. PM agents will be tempted to add "secondary primary"; reject in review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Multiple primary metrics introduce p-hacking risk and bury the main hypothesis in noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r12" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-register segment cuts (max 5). Post-hoc segments are exploratory only and labelled as such — never drive ship decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pre-registration prevents p-hacking. Exploratory segments are valid for hypothesis generation but not for decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r13" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat null results as findings, not failures. Add to learning-curator inputs; over time, a pattern of nulls in a region of the opportunity tree means rethink the opportunity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Null results rule out hypotheses and redirect discovery effort. Patterns of nulls in one branch signal the team is chasing a mirage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r14" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a quarterly "decisions we got wrong" memo with sponsor — single highest-leverage org-learning loop.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quarterly calibration prevents the team from repeating mistakes and surfaces systemic issues (e.g., "we keep over-weighting novelty effects").</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r15" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cap PM time on experiment ops to less than 20%. If it's higher, the platform isn't mature enough; push work back to product-ops or invest in tooling.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Experiment ops is overhead; it should not dominate PM cycles. If it does, it signals weak tooling or governance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r16" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always pair an experiment with a kill criterion before launch. PMs are biased to ship; the kill rule is the only thing that keeps the slate honest.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Kill criteria make the downside explicit and prevent sunk-cost fallacy from extending dead-end experiments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r17" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain a living opportunity-tree map; learning-curator edits it after every closed experiment so future PMs see why a path was abandoned.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Org memory prevents the same hypothesis from being re-tested in 18 months. Documented abandonment is as valuable as documented wins.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
