<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-maturity-and-stack" title="Experimentation Maturity and Platform Stack">
  <summary>Defines the four maturity levels for organizational experimentation and the 2026 tool stack required to reach Level 3 (Scaled) with statistical rigor.</summary>

  <section title="Maturity Levels">
    <list>
      <item>Level 1 — Ad-hoc: individual experiments, no standardization, no shared tooling.</item>
      <item>Level 2 — Structured: defined process, shared tools, reproducible setup.</item>
      <item>Level 3 — Scaled: 100+ experiments/year, statistical rigor, guardrail metrics on every test.</item>
      <item>Level 4 — Culture: every significant product decision is backed by an experiment; results are organization-wide knowledge.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Target Level 3 before claiming "we are an experimentation culture." Level 3 requires: a pre-registration log, a guardrail metric registry, SRM checks on every experiment, and a closed learning repository.</statement>
      <rationale>Organizations claiming culture without Level 3 infrastructure run experiments that cannot be trusted; results are theater, not evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Modern Experiment Stack (2026)">
    <list>
      <item>Feature Flags: LaunchDarkly, Statsig — safe rollouts and kill-switches.</item>
      <item>A/B Testing: GrowthBook (developer-first, OSS), Statsig (1T+ events/day), Eppo (warehouse-native, statistical rigor).</item>
      <item>Analytics: Amplitude, Mixpanel — behavioral data for hypothesis authoring and readout context.</item>
      <item>Warehouse: Snowflake, BigQuery — source of truth for primary metric computation.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never compute experiment statistics in the analytics tool (Amplitude, Mixpanel). Delegate all statistical computation to the A/B platform (GrowthBook, Statsig, Eppo) which controls assignment randomization and sample integrity.</statement>
      <rationale>Analytics tools are designed for exploration, not causal inference; computing lift in an analytics tool produces biased estimates due to peeking and non-randomized cohort cuts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AI in Experimentation (2026)">
    <list>
      <item>AI-generated test hypotheses from behavioral clusters and support themes.</item>
      <item>Automated variant creation for copy and layout tests.</item>
      <item>Predictive winner detection to reduce runtime for clear signals.</item>
      <item>Natural language result summaries for stakeholder communication.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use AI to accelerate hypothesis generation and result narration, never to make ship/kill decisions autonomously. The final verdict must be a human-reviewed application of the pre-committed decision rule.</statement>
      <rationale>AI narrators round confidence intervals, paraphrase null results as directionally positive, and defer to the PM's prior. Human review of the verbatim statistical output is the only guard.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scale Benchmarks">
    <list>
      <item>Microsoft: ~100,000 experiments/year.</item>
      <item>GoDaddy: 1,700+ experiments/year.</item>
      <item>Enterprise average (Level 3): 500-1,000 experiments/year.</item>
    </list>
    <p>The competitive gap between ad-hoc (Level 1) and scaled (Level 3) orgs compounds with each roadmap cycle — Level 3 orgs run 10x more tests and accumulate 10x more validated learnings per year.</p>
  </section>
</text>
