<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-pm-practices" title="PM Experimentation Practices">
  <summary>Behavioral hypothesis framing, pre-registration requirements, decision rules, and the failure modes that prevent experiments from producing genuine organizational learning.</summary>

  <section title="Hypothesis Framing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every experiment hypothesis must follow the if-then-because structure: "If [behavior change], then [metric M] will [move direction] by [delta], because [mechanism]." Reject solution-shaped hypotheses that name a feature instead of a behavior change.</statement>
      <rationale>Solution-shaped hypotheses ("add a banner") carry the answer in the question, preventing genuine learning. Behavioral if-then-because forces articulation of the causal mechanism, which can be falsified.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Hypothesis: "We should add a progress bar to onboarding."</note>
      <note>Failure: names a feature, not a behavior. If the experiment fails, you learn nothing about the underlying problem.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Hypothesis: "If we show users a 3-step progress indicator during onboarding, then Day-7 activation will increase by &gt;= 4% (relative), because users who see how close they are to completion are less likely to abandon mid-flow."</note>
      <note>Primary metric: d7_activation_rate. MDE: 4% relative. Decision rule: SHIP if lift &gt;= 4% with no guardrail breach; ITERATE if 0-4% lift; KILL if &lt;= 0% or guardrail breach.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Pre-Registration Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-register the decision rule before any traffic is exposed. The rule must name the primary metric, the threshold, guardrail metrics, and what to do if guardrails breach. A decision rule that allows "we'll see" is not a rule.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a pre-committed decision rule, the ship/kill call becomes negotiable post-readout; HiPPO override rates are near 100% when no rule exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-register segment cuts — maximum 5 — before launch. Post-hoc segment analysis is exploratory only and labelled as such; it never drives a ship decision.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc segment cuts are p-hacking by another name. Pre-registration is the only defense against finding a "winning" segment after 47 cuts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>HiPPO override: a clean readout is available but leadership ships the loser because the experiment contradicts a prior conviction.</description>
      <reason>Without a written decision rule co-signed by the exec sponsor before launch, "the data wins" is aspirational, not operational.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Local maxima: 18 months of CTA color tests yield 6% cumulative lift and zero strategic learning.</description>
      <reason>Without an opportunity-tree-rooted experiment slate, experimentation drifts to micro-optimizations that do not compound into competitive advantage.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reading "p=0.08, directionally positive" as a ship signal.</description>
      <reason>Inconclusive results (power &lt; 0.7 or p &gt; alpha) must produce "extend or kill," never "ship directionally." The pre-registered decision rule handles this automatically when applied verbatim.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating null results as failures and suppressing them from the learning repository.</description>
      <reason>A pattern of nulls in a region of the opportunity tree means rethink the opportunity. Suppressed nulls cause the same failed experiment to be re-run by the next PM cycle.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/hypothesis-doc.yaml">Full hypothesis intake schema with if-then-because, primary metric, guardrails, decision rule, and stop conditions.</reference>
  <reference path="scripts/triage-idea.py">30-line Python: scores idea testability and routes to tier (A/B, prototype, qual, irreversible-strategic).</reference>
</text>
