<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="experimentation-at-scale Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for experimentation-at-scale as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>HiPPO override: even with a clean readout, leadership ships the loser anyway. Without a written decision rule pre-committed by the exec sponsor, experimentation becomes theatre.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-register the decision rule, not just the metric — written, signed by sponsor, archived in Notion. Without this, "we won" becomes negotiable.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>"Experiment to launch, not to learn": PM ships the variant once it crosses 95% CI without checking guardrails — guardrails fail, ops gets paged, trust in the platform erodes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Surface guardrail breaches BEFORE primary metric in the narrative. All readouts must enumerate stop-conditions and check SRM and power before reading lift.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Solution-shaped hypotheses: "we should add a banner" — the hypothesis carries the answer. PM agents must rewrite to behavioral if-then-because before any sample-size math runs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force a behavioral if-then-because hypothesis. "Try a banner" is rejected; "If we surface plan upgrades in-context, then trial-to-paid will move +3% because friction at the upgrade moment is the bottleneck" is accepted.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Metric tunnel-vision: PM optimizes the KPI in their OKR; the experiment moves the KPI but cannibalizes a sibling team's metric. Cross-team guardrails are the fix, not heroic monitoring.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every experiment MUST enumerate guardrail metrics that represent adjacent team outcomes. Surface guardrail breaches before concluding the experiment won.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Local maxima: 18 months of CTA color tests yield 6% lift and zero strategic learning. Without an opportunity-tree-rooted slate, experimentation drifts to micro-optimizations.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tie every experiment to one opportunity-tree node; if it doesn't link, it's a CTA test, not product work — schedule, but cap to ≤25% of slate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Prioritization blind spot: agents will rank by ICE without checking dependency on long-running platform work, then surface a "ship-now" candidate that needs a 6-week migration first.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feed the eng dep graph into the ranker prompt. ICE/RICE rankers will rank a 6-week dependency-locked experiment above a ready-to-go one because they ignore deps.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Reading outcomes wrong: "p=0.08, directionally positive" → ship. PM agents will defer to whichever framing matches the PM's prior unless forced to copy verbatim framework output.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin temperature ≤0.1 and force JSON output with explicit verdict enum. Readout-interpreter must check SRM and power before reading lift; reorder prompt to fail fast on invalid experiments.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Communication failure: a clean win in one segment, flat overall — PM ships globally citing "the win." Segmented readout is mandatory; segment cuts must be pre-registered to avoid p-hacking.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-register segment cuts (max 5). Post-hoc segments are exploratory only and labelled as such — never drive ship decisions. Surface all segment cuts in the decision narrative.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents will turn ambiguous PM intent ("can we improve activation?") into a hypothesis without flagging missing evidence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require a prior_evidence: field with at least 2 sources; hypothesis-author refuses to output if missing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Readout-interpreter under temperature &gt; 0.2 will narrate "directionally positive" on null results.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pin temperature ≤0.1 and force JSON output with explicit verdict enum.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Decision rules drift between hypothesis-doc and readout — narrator agent should compute a hash of the hypothesis-doc at launch and refuse to render a ship memo if the hash changed.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hypothesis immutability is critical. If PM rewrites the decision rule after seeing the readout, the experiment is invalid.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>ICE/RICE rankers will rank a 6-week dependency-locked experiment above a ready-to-go one because they ignore deps.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feed the eng dep graph into the ranker prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Stakeholder-narrator will round confidence intervals into clean numbers ("4% lift, 95% confidence").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force verbatim copy of CI low/high; never paraphrase.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Learning-curator will hallucinate a pattern from N=2 closed experiments.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require N&gt;=5 with shared opportunity-tree branch before emitting a "pattern" claim.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>HiPPO leak: if the agent has access to leadership chat, it will weight comments as "evidence".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Keep prior_evidence sources to artifact links only (Dovetail study IDs, prior experiments, prototype tests). No Slack or email.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Readout-interpreter must check SRM and power before reading lift; reorder prompt to fail fast on invalid experiments.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Otherwise opus will write a nicely worded ship memo on a broken assignment.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Roadmap-impact-modeler will compound point estimates into 4-quarter forecasts and report them as fact.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require it to emit ranges and to label assumptions, never single-number forecasts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>PM-only ship/kill: agents must not auto-execute the ship action; gate at the flag-deployer step.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If autonomy is dialed up, require dual-key approval from PM and sponsor.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>Translation drift (Ukrainian PM input ↔ English experiment doc): hypothesis-author should round-trip-translate the if-then-because and surface differences before approval.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Otherwise nuance about "first-value" or "activation" gets lost.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-20" severity="medium">
      <description>Token cost: readout-interpreter on a 12-segment readout balloons.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cap at 50k tokens; otherwise summarize segments first, then interpret.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
