<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-content-strategy" title="Threads Content Strategy and Agent Rules">
  <summary>Content pillar mix, posting cadence, cross-posting rules, and agent-specific gotchas for Threads.</summary>

  <section title="Content Pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every draft with its content pillar; reject pillar-less drafts. Cap agent-generated posts at 50% of weekly volume.</statement>
      <rationale>Without pillar tags, agents drift toward whatever style won last week. The other 50% must come from the operator's lived context (replies, real-time reactions) because the algorithm rewards authentic conversation, not publishing volume.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Opinions: industry takes, hot takes (2-3/day).</item>
      <item>Value: tips, insights, learnings (1-2/day).</item>
      <item>Questions: engagement drivers (1/day).</item>
      <item>Personal: behind the scenes, stories (1/day).</item>
      <item>Curated: interesting finds, quotes (1/day).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Posting Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Post minimum 3 times/day; optimal 7-10 times/day. Reply within the first hour of each post for algorithm boost.</statement>
      <rationale>Threads' algorithm rewards reply velocity, not just post volume. Accounts that post but do not reply plateau within weeks. Replies drive reach more than the post itself.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep agent-generated posts under 500 characters; validate length programmatically after generation.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs are unreliable at character-count limits. Over-length posts fail silently or look unprofessional on Threads' compact format. Include a hard length constraint in every prompt and check post-generation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cross-Posting Anti-Pattern">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Cross-posting X/Twitter threads verbatim to Threads.</description>
      <reason>Twitter irony, link references, and thread formatting do not translate. Threads rewards warmth and conversational register; verbatim X content reads as out-of-place and suppresses engagement. Force a register-shift rewrite step.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent auto-posts to Threads on a schedule.</description>
      <reason>No stable scheduling API exists as of 2026. Meta is aggressive about automation detection. Best practice: agent drafts and ranks 20 candidates, operator picks 7-10 and posts manually within prime windows.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent uses identical hook phrases across drafts ("Hot take:", "Honest question:").</description>
      <reason>Hook repetition reduces engagement. Enforce banned-bigram lists in the prompt to force variety across a content pack.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent includes engagement-bait phrases: "comment X for Y", "tag a friend", "follow for more".</description>
      <reason>These phrases are flagged by Meta and suppress reach. Explicitly prohibit them in every prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/prompt-ideation.txt">Daily content pack ideation prompt</reference>
  <reference path="templates/daily-posts.txt">Post format templates</reference>
</text>
