<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SERP Movement Alert Rules Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `SERP Movement Alert Rules` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="impressions-wow-30pct-alert" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger alert when week-over-week impressions for a keyword (or query group) drop &gt;= 30%. Compare against 4-week rolling average to filter noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="GSC alerting practice; Search Engine Land 2024">30% WoW drop is outside normal seasonal noise; comparable to a manual penalty or core update hit. Smaller thresholds produce too many false positives.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="position-delta-3-rank-alert" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger alert when a tracked keyword&apos;s average position degrades by &gt;= 3 ranks in a 7-day window. Rank-tracker daily data; smoothing via 7-day average.</statement>
      <rationale source="Ahrefs / Semrush alert config docs">3-rank drop on a top-10 keyword is loss of 50%+ click share. Smaller drops are within normal SERP volatility; bigger thresholds miss early signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ai-overview-appearance-alert" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger alert any time an AI Overview (SGE / AIO) starts appearing on a tracked keyword&apos;s SERP. Detection via rank-tracker SERP feature flag or scraping.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SGE rollout monitoring 2024">AI Overview typically halves click-through for the first organic result. Late detection = weeks of CTR collapse before team notices.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ctr-collapse-50pct-alert" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger alert when CTR for a query drops &gt; 50% relative to its 4-week rolling average AND impressions stable. Filters out genuine traffic drops.</statement>
      <rationale source="GSC analyst playbooks">Stable impressions + collapsing CTR means SERP layout changed (AI Overview, featured snippet steal, ad block expansion). Different fix than ranking drop.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="48-hour-review-sla" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every alert MUST have a documented 48-hour review SLA with a named owner. Alerts without owner are ignored within weeks.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal SRE alerting discipline applied to SEO">Unowned alerts = noise. Named owner + SLA forces triage decision: real → investigate, noise → adjust threshold.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
