<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SERP Alert Rules — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every SERP alerting setup must satisfy. Skipping any one produces either alarm fatigue or the dreaded six-day-late discovery of a traffic collapse.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-four-signal-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Alerting MUST evaluate four signals nightly: (a) impressions week-over-week delta for tracked queries, (b) position delta for tracked queries, (c) AI Overview presence/absence on tracked queries, (d) CTR delta on stable impressions. Missing any signal leaves a blind spot.</statement>
      <rationale source="Search Console API documentation; post-2024 SERP feature literature">Impressions catch broad visibility changes. Position catches algorithm hits per query. AI Overview catches the new dominant feature shift. CTR catches snippet / title changes. A monitor that only watches impressions misses the AI Overview that just appeared on the head query.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-sustained-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An alert fires only if the threshold is breached for ≥2 consecutive days (or ≥7 days for weekly seasonality). Single-day spikes do not fire — they often reflect Google data-pipeline noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Search Console data-pipeline behaviour; rank-tracker SLA variability">Search Console reporting lags 1-3 days and sometimes back-fills. A single-day -25% drop is often a partial-data artefact that resolves the next day. The sustained-window rule eliminates the most common false positive.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-ai-overview-first-class" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>AI Overview presence on a tracked query is its own alert class (not folded into position) AND its appearance/disappearance triggers an investigation regardless of whether traffic changed yet.</statement>
      <rationale source="post-2024 SERP feature observations; AI Overview adoption literature">AI Overviews change CTR before they change impressions and may compress positions silently. The alert must fire on the structural change, not wait for downstream traffic damage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-query-priority-weighting" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tracked queries are tagged by priority band (head = revenue-driving, body = supporting, long-tail = exploration). Alerts on head queries route to immediate-review; body to daily digest; long-tail to weekly summary.</statement>
      <rationale source="80/20 SEO impact distribution; field experience">Treating every query equally produces digest sprawl. Head queries deserve interruption; long-tail movement is informational. The priority band is the difference between a usable inbox and an ignored one.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-no-weekend-pages" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Alerts fire only Mon-Fri 09:00-19:00 operator local time unless the affected query is critical (head + revenue path). Saturday-night SERP volatility is real but rarely actionable in real time.</statement>
      <rationale source="alerting-philosophy; sustainable-pace marketing operations">A Saturday alert on a long-tail query is noise. The operator cannot publish content fixes over the weekend in most agencies. Hard quiet-hours protect attention; the Monday digest covers the gap.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Default thresholds">
    <list>
      <item><b>impressions_wow_drop</b>: head queries -20%, body -30%, long-tail -50%</item>
      <item><b>position_drop</b>: head -3, body -5, long-tail -8</item>
      <item><b>ai_overview_appeared</b>: any tracked query — always fires</item>
      <item><b>ai_overview_disappeared</b>: any tracked query — always fires</item>
      <item><b>ctr_drop_on_stable_impressions</b>: -30% over 7 days, impressions ±10%</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="AI Overview appearance triggers an investigation">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tuesday 03:00 — nightly pull. Query "best CRM for freelancers" (head, priority 1)
    has new AI Overview snippet citing 3 competitors, not us.
Tuesday 09:00 — alert fires; investigation log opened.
Tuesday 11:00 — content team identifies our page lacks the structured comparison
    section the AI Overview pulls from. Update drafted.
Wednesday — update published.
Friday — AI Overview now cites us; CTR partially recovers.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r3 (AI Overview as first-class signal), r4 (head priority), r5 (work hours). Caught within 6 hours of the SERP change.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="The weekly-review-only failure">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Monday weekly review: impressions down 32% from previous week.
Investigation: AI Overview appeared Thursday last week and has been
showing competitors for 5 days. By the time the fix ships, recovery
takes 3 weeks instead of 1.
      ]]></code>
      <note>r1, r3 violated. Weekly review is too slow for AI Overview shifts.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
