<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="What You Don't Know About Launch Pre-Mortem Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every What You Don't Know About Launch Pre-Mortem application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="surface-enumerated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-mortem enumerates ≥6 launch surfaces (billing, auth, data, support, abuse, retention). Skipping a surface requires a named reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Launch-surface coverage practice">Unknown-unknowns hide in the surface that was never named.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-fix-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every identified failure mode names a single accountable fix owner (handle + role). Placeholder values or 'team' are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI accountability discipline">Pre-mortem with anonymous owners produces no fixes; the failure is just re-documented post-mortem.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="detector-per-failure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every failure mode names a concrete detector signal (log, alert, metric, ticket pattern) the team can monitor.</statement>
      <rationale source="Observability practice">Failures with no detector are unrecoverable; the detector pins which failures we can survive.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kill-criterion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The pre-mortem report carries a launch-kill criterion: a single sentence that, if true, blocks GO. No-kill-criterion launches turn pre-mortems into theatre.</statement>
      <rationale source="Pre-mortem methodology (Gary Klein)">Kill criteria force the team to define what 'not safe' means before pressing GO.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="revisit-on-launch-week" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-mortem is refreshed within 24h of launch-week start. Pre-mortems older than 14 days are flagged stale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Launch context drifts fast; an old pre-mortem misses the surfaces that changed last week.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
