<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="strategy-analysis-business-need Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for strategy-analysis-business-need. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The business need statement MUST be outcome-shaped, not solution-shaped. Any statement containing "implement", "deploy", "build", "buy", or "migrate" MUST be recast as a measurable outcome before proceeding.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Solution-shaped needs hard-code a choice before the problem is understood. The BA and agents must refuse them because they collapse the solution space before the gap analysis has been done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every driver MUST cite a primary-source verbatim quote with document name and date. Drivers without evidence MUST be flagged as unverified and excluded from the signed need statement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generic driver prose ("AI is disrupting industries") is ignored in steering reviews. Evidence-backed drivers survive scrutiny and give the BA standing to defend the need.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The consequence of inaction MUST be falsifiable and quantified where possible. Aspirational language ("things will deteriorate") MUST be rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a measurable consequence of inaction, leadership cannot see the cost of doing nothing; the strategy reads as advocacy rather than analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A named decision-maker MUST be identified before need-framing is complete. If no decision-maker is named, the need frame is not signed off; downstream agents MUST NOT begin current-state work.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without a decision-maker, change strategy recommendations have no authority; the analysis floats until someone with budget and mandate takes ownership.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
