<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Sprint Demo Script Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn a senior-dev-runs-the-demo session into a defensible per-AC acceptance log.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-sprintdemoscripttemplate" testable="true">
      <statement>The demo MUST iterate one acceptance criterion at a time using the loop: read AC verbatim → demonstrate on staging → ask the three-option prompt → log decision → move to next AC. No multi-AC "round-up" demonstrations.</statement>
      <rationale>Multi-AC demonstrations let a client accept a "general feel" without signing off on each criterion, which is exactly the ambiguity that fuels later disputes. One AC at a time forces explicit per-item decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-sprintdemoscripttemplate" testable="true">
      <statement>The accept prompt MUST present exactly three options, named verbatim: "Accept", "Accept with defect (log + ship)", "Reject". No free-form "what do you think?" framing is allowed. The dev MUST wait for the client to pick one of the three before logging.</statement>
      <rationale>Open-ended feedback collapses into "looks great, but..." which is unrecorded in any binary acceptance state. Three labelled options force a categorical answer the log can store and an invoice line can reference.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-sprintdemoscripttemplate" testable="true">
      <statement>Each AC decision MUST be logged in `demos/sprint-NN-decisions.md` with the fields: AC ID, decision (Accept | Accept-with-defect | Reject), named decider, defect ticket ID (if applicable), and verbatim quote when the decider qualified the answer. The log is appended live during the meeting, not reconstructed afterwards.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc reconstruction is the failure mode the script exists to eliminate. Live append + named decider is what makes the log invoicable and defendable when memories diverge a month later.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-sprintdemoscripttemplate" testable="true">
      <statement>Before the demo starts, the dev MUST confirm in writing (chat or quick verbal-then-logged statement) that the attending client is authorised to sign acceptances on behalf of the company for this sprint. If signer authority cannot be confirmed, the demo proceeds but decisions log as "preliminary — pending sign-off by [named role]" rather than final.</statement>
      <rationale>A junior or non-authorised signer accepting on behalf of the company is unenforceable. Confirming authority upfront prevents the engagement manager from later finding the "signed-off" demo has no commercial weight.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-sprintdemoscripttemplate" testable="true">
      <statement>Any "Reject" decision MUST trigger an immediate change-request entry: the dev records the reason, the affected requirement ID, and the proposed disposition (defect-fix in current scope | new CR | scope renegotiation). No "Reject" is allowed to leave the meeting unattached to one of these three dispositions.</statement>
      <rationale>"Reject" without a follow-up channel is the most expensive outcome of a demo — work that lands in limbo while the team keeps building. Forcing immediate disposition routes the rejection into a tracked path before the team disperses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Skip-If clause from AGENTS.md fires OR any precondition fails, STOP applying this methodology and route to the correct one. Producing an artefact when the methodology does not apply is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network skill-authoring docs">Mis-application is the most common methodology-routing failure observed in audits. An explicit STOP rule prevents the agent from synthesizing outputs for the wrong instrument.</rationale>
    </rule>


  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Sprint 14 — Demo Decision Log
# Decider: Maria Lopes (VP Operations) — authority confirmed via Slack 2026-05-19

| AC ID  | Decision               | Defect ticket | Decider quote |
|--------|------------------------|----------------|----------------|
| AC-014 | Accept                 | —              | "Yes, this is what we asked for." |
| AC-015 | Accept-with-defect     | BUG-2031       | "Ship it; the timezone glitch can wait for next sprint." |
| AC-016 | Reject                 | CR-018 opened  | "Mobile UX feels wrong; needs a redesign pass." |
      ]]></code>
      <note>Each AC has a categorical state, a named decider, a defect/CR linkage. Invoicing on AC-014 and AC-015 is now defensible; CR-018 is tracked.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Sprint 14 — Demo Notes

The client seemed happy with most things. The mobile screen needs work.
We'll fix the small issues next sprint.
      ]]></code>
      <note>No AC IDs, no categorical decision, no named decider, no defect linkage. Worthless for invoicing or change tracking.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
