<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="recognition-over-recall">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Make elements, actions, and options visible. Minimize memory load. Users should not need to remember information from one part of the interface to another.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>usability-heuristic</tag>
      <tag>cognition</tag>
      <tag>ux</tag>
      <tag>memory-load</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Recognition Rather Than Recall</title>

    <summary>Users must remember information from one part of the interface to use in another. They need to recall command syntax or codes. Options are hidden until users know to look for them. Instructions disappear before users can follow them. Memory becomes a barrier to use. Without recognition support: cognitive overload, slower task completion, more errors, frustration.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Usability Heuristic #6: Minimize the user's memory load by making elements, actions, and options visible. The user should not have to remember information from one part of the interface to another. Information required to use the design should be visible or easily retrievable.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>UI audit: reviewing an existing interface for cognitive load issues</item>
        <item>Design review: checking new component designs before implementation</item>
        <item>Accessibility review: recognition aids are disproportionately important for users with cognitive disabilities</item>
        <item>Command-palette or search interface design: autocomplete and suggestions are the primary recognition mechanism</item>
        <item>Onboarding flow design: new users have zero recall of your UI; every step must surface what to do next</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When the interface is exclusively for expert power-users who have internalized shortcuts (e.g., vim, git CLI) — recall is the design intent</item>
        <item>When screen real estate is genuinely constrained (e.g., mobile watch apps) — some hiding is unavoidable; add tooltips</item>
        <item>When adding recognition aids would create visual noise that harms scannability — balance with aesthetic simplicity</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="recognition-vs-recall">
      <p>The fundamental difference:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Recognition: See and choose (menu selection, autocomplete, visual cues) — lower cognitive load</item>
        <item>Recall: Remember and type (command line, blank field, hidden options) — higher cognitive load</item>
      </list>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Common actions must be visible, not hidden in menus. Navigation should use visible tabs for main sections instead of hidden hamburger menus.</statement>
        <rationale>Recognition requires only identifying the right option from visible choices. Recall requires users to remember what exists and where it is, adding cognitive burden and errors.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Design principles for recognition:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Make options visible - Show rather than hide</item>
        <item>Provide context - Keep relevant info visible</item>
        <item>Use recognition aids - Icons, labels, thumbnails</item>
        <item>Support retrieval - Recent items, search, suggestions</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="implementation-patterns">
      <p>Practical patterns for reducing recall load:</p>

      <example type="good" title="Visible Navigation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: Hidden hamburger menu (must remember what is inside)
Good: Visible tabs for main sections
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Visible Actions">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: Right-click for all actions
Good: Visible toolbar with common actions
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Forms with reference data must show the context in a sidebar. When editing an order, show order details so the user cannot forget what they are editing. In multi-step processes, show a summary of previous selections.</statement>
        <rationale>Context visibility prevents cognitive load of remembering earlier decisions. Multi-step forms without a summary force users to mentally track their previous entries.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Recognition aids must replace recall requirements: file browser shows thumbnails for images (not just filenames); recent items are shown prominently; search includes autocomplete and suggestions; icons are paired with text labels (or tooltips if space-constrained).</statement>
        <rationale>Thumbnails, recent items, and search suggestions let users recognize what they want instead of recalling it. Icons without labels force memorization; labels reduce recall load to near-zero.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="File Browser with Visual Recognition">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: List of filenames only
Good: Thumbnails for images, previews for documents
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Search with Suggestions">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: Empty search box
Good: Search with autocomplete, recent searches, suggestions
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Icon with Label">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Bad: Icon only (user must remember meaning)
Good: Icon + text label
Or: Icon + tooltip on hover (for space-constrained areas)
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="advanced-patterns">
      <p>Advanced techniques for reducing memory load:</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Progressive disclosure: show essential options always, reveal advanced options on demand. Users do not need to remember what is available.</statement>
        <rationale>Novice users see only what they need; expert users can access advanced features. No one has to memorize the full feature set.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Smart defaults: pre-fill forms with likely values (from user history or profile). Users recognize and confirm rather than recall and enter.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-filled values reduce typing and recall. Users verify rather than generate; recognition of correct values is faster and more reliable than recalling what to type.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Search and filter: instead of asking users to browse hundreds of options or recall item locations, let users search and see results. Recognition of results is easier than recall of location.</statement>
        <rationale>Search and filter shift the cognitive model from recall (where is it?) to recognition (which one is it?).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>History and recents: show recent documents, recent searches, frequently used items, and favorites. Consistent placement keeps elements in the same location so users recognize location without recalling where to look.</statement>
        <rationale>Recency and frequency are strong recognition cues. Consistent placement becomes predictable after a few uses.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="where-it-fails">
      <p>Common failure modes when implementing recognition-based design:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding too many recognition aids (labels, tooltips, recent items, suggestions) simultaneously creates visual clutter</description>
        <reason>Recognition support has diminishing returns. Balance recognition with aesthetic simplicity and scannability.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Autocomplete systems surfacing wrong suggestions erode trust faster than blank fields</description>
        <reason>Poor suggestions are worse than no suggestions. Test autocomplete logic with real user data.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recent items panels can expose sensitive data to shared-device users</description>
        <reason>Consider privacy implications; offer session-scoped history rather than persistent history on shared devices.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recognition aids add implementation complexity (state management for recents, fuzzy matching for search)</description>
        <reason>Teams often deprioritize these under time pressure. Plan complexity budget for recognition features upfront.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Static checklist audits miss dynamic state transitions where recognition fails</description>
        <reason>A multi-step wizard with no summary panel is harder to audit than visible UI. Test with real user flows and state transitions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Claude subagents can perform recognition audits against provided screenshots or component code, generating a filled Recognition Audit template with ranked issues and recommended fixes. Agents can also generate autocomplete suggestion logic or "recent items" component specs.</p>

      <note>Code-level audits (checking for aria-label presence, tooltip implementation, icon-only buttons) are reliable. Visual judgment about whether recognition support is sufficient requires human validation.</note>

      <note>Recommended subagents: faion-usability-agent (runs recognition audit against UI descriptions or component specs; generates issue table with severity and fix); faion-sdd-executor-agent (implements recognition pattern fixes in code: adds labels, tooltips, recent items state).</note>

      <example type="good" title="Recognition Audit Prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Audit this UI for violations of the Recognition Rather Than Recall heuristic (Nielsen #6).
For each violation:
1. Describe what the user must remember
2. Rate severity: High (blocks task) / Medium (slows task) / Low (friction only)
3. Propose a specific recognition-based alternative

UI description / component list:
{ui_description_or_code}
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Recent Items Component Spec">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Generate a recent-items component specification for the following context.
Requirements:
- Show last N items (configurable)
- Each item: icon, label, timestamp
- Click restores the item's context
- Clear history option
- No PII stored in localStorage; session-scoped only

Context: {app_context}
Items represent: {item_type}
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-services">
      <p>Tools for automated recognition audits:</p>
      <list>
        <item>axe-core CLI: Automated accessibility audit (detects missing labels) (npm i -g axe-cli; deque.com/axe)</item>
        <item>pa11y: Automated a11y scanner including label checks (npm i -g pa11y; pa11y.org)</item>
        <item>eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y: Linter rule to flag icon-only buttons missing aria-label (npm i -D eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y)</item>
        <item>storybook-addon-a11y: Per-component a11y audit in Storybook (storybook.js.org/addons/@storybook/addon-a11y)</item>
        <item>playwright: Automated UI regression + a11y assertions (playwright.dev)</item>
      </list>

      <p>Services and platforms for recognition features:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Axe DevTools (SaaS + OSS, Yes): API for automated scans in CI; flags missing labels</item>
        <item>Deque WorldSpace (SaaS, Yes): Enterprise a11y management platform; API available</item>
        <item>Fuse.js (OSS, Yes): Client-side fuzzy search for recognition-based filtering</item>
        <item>Algolia (SaaS, Yes): Search-as-a-service with autocomplete API</item>
        <item>Typesense (OSS, Yes): Self-hosted; typo-tolerant search for autocomplete</item>
        <item>FullStory (SaaS, Partial): Session recordings to observe recall failures in the wild</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="inline-script">
      <p>Detect icon-only buttons in HTML (no label, no tooltip):</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[
from bs4 import BeautifulSoup

def find_recall_violations(html: str) -> list[dict]:
    soup = BeautifulSoup(html, "html.parser")
    violations = []

    for btn in soup.find_all(["button", "a"]):
        text = btn.get_text(strip=True)
        aria_label = btn.get("aria-label", "")
        title = btn.get("title", "")
        has_img = bool(btn.find("img") or btn.find("svg"))

        if has_img and not text and not aria_label and not title:
            violations.append({
                "element": str(btn)[:80],
                "issue": "Icon-only control: user must recall meaning",
                "severity": "High",
                "fix": "Add aria-label or visible text label",
            })

    return violations

violations = find_recall_violations(open("component.html").read())
for v in violations:
    print(v)
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Audit with icon-only buttons as your first filter — they are the most common recognition failure and easiest to fix (add aria-label + visible tooltip)</item>
        <item>Implement recent items with a maximum of 5-7 entries; more than that shifts the cognitive pattern back to recall (scanning a long list)</item>
        <item>Search autocomplete should show results after 2 characters, not 0 (no query) or 3+ (too slow to provide recognition)</item>
        <item>In multi-step forms, show a persistent summary sidebar of all prior inputs — users filling out step 4 should not need to remember what they entered on step 1</item>
        <item>Smart defaults (pre-filled from user history or profile) reduce recall load more effectively than helper text</item>
        <item>Test recognition support specifically with users who are new to the interface — expert users compensate with recall; new users expose recognition gaps</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas">
      <p>When working with agents on recognition audit and implementation, be aware of these failure modes:</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents auditing UI from text descriptions will miss visual recognition failures</description>
        <reason>Two similar icons adjacent to each other look the same; text descriptions cannot capture this. Provide annotated screenshots or component names with their icon descriptions.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents implementing "recent items" tend to use localStorage without considering session isolation or PII implications</description>
        <reason>Specify storage scope explicitly (session-scoped, no PII) in the implementation prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Autocomplete suggestions generated by agents may not account for the latency cost</description>
        <reason>Specify debounce timing (typically 150-300ms) in the implementation prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recognition audit severity ratings by agents default to "Medium" for everything</description>
        <reason>Require explicit criteria: High = task cannot be completed without recall, Medium = slows task, Low = friction only.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents can identify technical violations but not judge visual design balance</description>
        <reason>Human checkpoint required for visual design decisions — whether added labels harm the aesthetic balance of the layout.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-connection">
      <p>Recognition-based design disproportionately helps users with specific needs:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Users with cognitive disabilities</item>
        <item>Older users</item>
        <item>Occasional users (who have not internalized UI patterns)</item>
        <item>Users in stressful situations</item>
        <item>Users on mobile (divided attention)</item>
      </list>

      <p>Measuring recognition support effectiveness:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Task completion time: Faster with recognition aids</item>
        <item>Error rate: Fewer recall errors</item>
        <item>Help requests: Less "where is X?"</item>
        <item>User confidence: Self-reported ease</item>
        <item>Learnability: Time to proficiency</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/recognition-audit.md" purpose="Recognition audit checklist: recall requirements, hidden information, icon labels, recommendations"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/recognition-and-recall/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/human-memory"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/foundations/navigation"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/navigation"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/dequelabs/axe-core"/>
      <link href="https://www.fusejs.io"/>
      <link href="https://typesense.org"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
