<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Information Architecture — Framework Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Information Architecture — Framework. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-user-research-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Start IA work from user research and content inventory; never from internal org chart or product team boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Norman Group — Information Architecture 101">Org-chart-derived IA is the most common failure mode and predicts low findability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-scheme-justified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick a single primary organization scheme — topic, task, audience, alphabetical, chronological, or geographic — and document why; mixing schemes ad-hoc breaks predictability.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rosenfeld, Morville, Arango — Information Architecture for the Web and Beyond">A documented scheme prevents downstream contributors from inventing competing patterns.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-depth-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Navigation depth is capped at three levels for task-based UIs and four for content-heavy sites; deeper hierarchies require explicit justification and breadcrumbs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — tree-test studies">Beyond four levels users lose orientation and retreat to search.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-label-test" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every top-level and second-level label is tested with at least five external users via first-click or tree testing before commit; jargon labels are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Optimal Workshop — Treejack and Chalkmark guides">Internal teams lose perspective on jargon; external testing surfaces it before launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-taxonomy-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A single taxonomy owner with veto authority is named; changes to top-level categories require their sign-off and a written rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — taxonomy drift audits">Without an owner taxonomies become internally inconsistent within six to twelve months.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-cards-then-trees" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Card sorting precedes tree testing precedes implementation; skipping card sorting biases the tree test toward the team's draft taxonomy.</statement>
      <rationale source="Optimal Workshop methodology guides">Card-sort first prevents validating only the team's prior assumption.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-ia-framework.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
