<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ia-framework Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ia-framework as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Org chart navigation — using internal reporting structure (Product, Engineering, Sales, Marketing sections) instead of user mental models (Features, Documentation, Community, Support).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Org-chart navigation mirrors how the company is structured, not how users think about the product. Users do not know which internal team owns a feature; they search by feature or task.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Too deep hierarchy — more than 3-4 levels in navigation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Beyond 3 levels, users lose context of where they are and retreat to search. Each level adds a decision point and a chance for wrong turns.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Too many choices — more than 7 items per navigation level (Miller's Law).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Humans cannot comfortably hold more than 7 items in working memory while making a choice. Above 7 items, navigation becomes a search task in itself.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Jargon labels — using internal terminology (API Keys, Service Tiers, Webhook Integrations) in public navigation without translation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users working with the product understand jargon through repeated exposure, but first-time visitors and occasional users will not recognize terms. Test labels with people outside your company.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>No testing — assumptions about navigation not validated with users.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Even experienced designers misjudge label clarity and category groupings. Card sorting and tree testing reveal mismatches; assumptions should not drive IA.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>IA designed without user input reflects the organization's mental model, not users' — org-chart navigation is the most common failure.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Internal teams lose perspective on their own jargon. Org-chart navigation matches internal reporting structure, not user mental models of the product. Users do not think "engineering," "product," "sales" — they think about their jobs and the tools that solve them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Tree testing validates findability of a specific label structure but not the navigation experience (visual design, microcopy, discoverability).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tree testing strips visual design, making all navigation equally visible. In practice, visual design, color, proximity, and font size affect findability dramatically. A label that scores well in tree testing may still fail in visual UI if it is de-emphasized or buried.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Deep hierarchies (5+ levels) test well in tree testing but fail in practice because users lose context of where they are.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tree testing asks discrete questions ("find this item") without context. Real navigation requires users to hold their location in the hierarchy in memory. Five levels exceeds working memory; users cannot remember where they are and give up.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
