<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ada-title-ii-compliance-2026 Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ada-title-ii-compliance-2026. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only to public entities under 28 CFR Part 35: US state, local, and territorial governments and their contractors delivering digital services on their behalf.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Title II scope is narrower than ADA Title III (private sector); applying Title II requirements to private commercial sites misstates the legal obligation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Implement WCAG 2.1 Level AA — not 2.2 — as the required standard; apply 2.2 success criteria only as recommended enhancements.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The DOJ final rule pins to WCAG 2.1 AA. Auto-applying 2.2 SCs as required misrepresents the legal standard and may misprioritize remediation effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not assume archived content is exempt; the archived-content exemption requires: unaltered, clearly marked as archived, not used for current agency activity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The exemption is intentionally narrow; pre-existing PDFs must still be remediated on request even if created before the deadline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not advise clients to use the "undue burden" defense without legal counsel; it is far narrower under Title II than Title III.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agents lack the legal standing and financial-analysis capability to make undue-burden determinations; premature reliance creates litigation exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Crawl and tag every digital surface (web pages, mobile apps, PDFs, multimedia, forms, third-party widgets) before running any accessibility tests.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Unknown surfaces cannot be remediated; inventory gaps produce incomplete VPAT documentation and ongoing litigation risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run automated tools (axe-core, Pa11y) first, then add manual checkpoints for captions, audio descriptions, accessible PDFs, and keyboard-only navigation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Automated tools catch approximately 30-40% of WCAG failures; captions, audio descriptions, and PDF tagging require human or specialized tool review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prioritize high-traffic, high-impact pages first; document remediation priority and owner for every issue found.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Remediation resources are finite; demonstrating good-faith prioritized effort matters under DOJ enforcement review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Wire automated accessibility checks into CI/CD pipelines so regressions are caught at pull-request time, not post-launch.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Manual-only monitoring cannot scale; new content and code changes continuously introduce new violations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce a VPAT 2.5 INT or ACR for each covered product; legal counsel must sign off on conformance claims and undue-burden assertions — never delegate these to an agent.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">VPAT/ACR conformance statements carry legal weight; incorrect agent-generated claims increase enforcement and litigation risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reference WCAG 2.1 AA as the required standard in all remediation guidance; flag WCAG 2.2 additions as recommended, not required.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The DOJ rule is pinned to WCAG 2.1 AA; conflating it with 2.2 creates inaccurate compliance assessments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
