<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-requirements" title="ADA Title II 2026 — Scope, Deadlines, and Covered Content">
  <summary>Legal scope, compliance deadlines, and the full list of digital content types covered by 28 CFR Part 35 (DOJ final rule, April 24 2024).</summary>

  <section title="Who Is Covered">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply this methodology only to public entities under 28 CFR Part 35: US state, local, and territorial governments and their contractors delivering digital services on their behalf.</statement>
      <rationale>Title II scope is narrower than ADA Title III (private sector); applying Title II requirements to private commercial sites misstates the legal obligation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Covered: state and local government agencies, public universities, transit authorities, libraries, court systems, public utility portals.</item>
      <item>Covered as vendor: SaaS or custom software delivered to a covered entity under contract.</item>
      <item>Not covered by Title II: federal government (Section 508 applies), private-sector commercial sites (Title III), private employer internal tools (Title I).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Deadlines">
    <list>
      <item>Large entities (population 50,000 or more): April 24 2026.</item>
      <item>Smaller entities: April 26 2027.</item>
      <item>Special district governments: April 26 2027.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Standard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement WCAG 2.1 Level AA — not 2.2 — as the required standard; apply 2.2 success criteria only as recommended enhancements.</statement>
      <rationale>The DOJ final rule pins to WCAG 2.1 AA. Auto-applying 2.2 SCs as required misrepresents the legal standard and may misprioritize remediation effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Covered Content Types">
    <list>
      <item>All public-facing websites and web applications.</item>
      <item>Mobile applications (native iOS, Android, and web-based).</item>
      <item>Multimedia content: video (captions required), audio (transcripts), accessible media players.</item>
      <item>PDF documents, Word, Excel, and PowerPoint files created by or for the covered entity.</item>
      <item>Interactive forms.</item>
      <item>Third-party content embedded in covered entity sites (can still trigger compliance obligation).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Exemption Limits">
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not assume archived content is exempt; the archived-content exemption requires: unaltered, clearly marked as archived, not used for current agency activity.</statement>
      <rationale>The exemption is intentionally narrow; pre-existing PDFs must still be remediated on request even if created before the deadline.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not advise clients to use the "undue burden" defense without legal counsel; it is far narrower under Title II than Title III.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents lack the legal standing and financial-analysis capability to make undue-burden determinations; premature reliance creates litigation exposure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
