<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="ADA Title II Compliance Workflow">
  <summary>Six-step workflow from digital inventory to conformance documentation, with agent responsibilities and human checkpoints.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Inventory All Digital Surfaces">
    <rule>
      <statement>Crawl and tag every digital surface (web pages, mobile apps, PDFs, multimedia, forms, third-party widgets) before running any accessibility tests.</statement>
      <rationale>Unknown surfaces cannot be remediated; inventory gaps produce incomplete VPAT documentation and ongoing litigation risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Gap Analysis Against WCAG 2.1 AA">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run automated tools (axe-core, Pa11y) first, then add manual checkpoints for captions, audio descriptions, accessible PDFs, and keyboard-only navigation.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated tools catch approximately 30-40% of WCAG failures; captions, audio descriptions, and PDF tagging require human or specialized tool review.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Create Remediation Roadmap">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prioritize high-traffic, high-impact pages first; document remediation priority and owner for every issue found.</statement>
      <rationale>Remediation resources are finite; demonstrating good-faith prioritized effort matters under DOJ enforcement review.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Implement Fixes">
    <list>
      <item>Add captions to all video content; provide audio descriptions for visual-only information.</item>
      <item>Tag all PDFs with proper heading structure, alt text, and reading order.</item>
      <item>Ensure all forms have programmatic labels, error identification, and error suggestions.</item>
      <item>Verify keyboard navigation order, focus visibility, and skip-nav links.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Establish Ongoing Monitoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Wire automated accessibility checks into CI/CD pipelines so regressions are caught at pull-request time, not post-launch.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual-only monitoring cannot scale; new content and code changes continuously introduce new violations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Document Conformance (VPAT / ACR)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce a VPAT 2.5 INT or ACR for each covered product; legal counsel must sign off on conformance claims and undue-burden assertions — never delegate these to an agent.</statement>
      <rationale>VPAT/ACR conformance statements carry legal weight; incorrect agent-generated claims increase enforcement and litigation risk.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
