<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules" title="ADA Title II — Agent Rules and Limitation Flags">
  <summary>Testable agent rules and known limitation flags that prevent common compliance errors.</summary>

  <section title="Standard Pinning">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reference WCAG 2.1 AA as the required standard in all remediation guidance; flag WCAG 2.2 additions as recommended, not required.</statement>
      <rationale>The DOJ rule is pinned to WCAG 2.1 AA; conflating it with 2.2 creates inaccurate compliance assessments.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Known Limitation Flags">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent auto-applies WCAG 2.2 success criteria as required under Title II.</description>
      <reason>WCAG 2.2 SCs are not part of the DOJ final rule; marking them required overstates the legal obligation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent marks pre-existing PDFs as exempt from all accessibility requirements.</description>
      <reason>Pre-existing PDFs must still be remediated on request even if created before the compliance deadline; the exemption is not blanket.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent claims embedded third-party content is not in scope for the covered entity.</description>
      <reason>Third-party content embedded in a covered entity's site can still trigger the covered entity's compliance obligation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent drafts an undue-burden claim without legal and financial analysis.</description>
      <reason>Undue-burden defenses under Title II require entity-level financial analysis; an agent lacks the standing and data to make this determination.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Human Checkpoints">
    <list>
      <item>Legal counsel must review and sign VPAT/ACR conformance statements.</item>
      <item>Manual AT (assistive technology) walkthroughs by a qualified evaluator are required for captions, audio descriptions, and complex form interactions.</item>
      <item>Validation with real AT users (screen reader, voice control, switch access) before declaring compliance.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
