<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Discovery Research Handoff Template Core Rules">
  <summary>The one-page contract every discovery-to-build handoff must satisfy so downstream design and engineering stop re-deriving the problem.</summary>
  <section title="Required sections">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The handoff is a single page (≤500 words, ≤2 figures) with exactly five sections, in order: Problem, Target User, Jobs-to-be-Done, Evidence, Success Metric. Sections may not be added, removed, or reordered; over-length handoffs are rejected by the gate, not silently accepted.</statement>
      <rationale>A standardised shape is the only way design and engineering can scan the artefact in 60 seconds and act. Adding sections invites scope-creep ("can we add competitor analysis?"); removing sections is how teams ship without a success metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The Problem section states one user-observable problem in one sentence, in the user's voice, with no solution words. Statements containing the words "we should build", "the feature", "the solution", or naming a UI element are rejected and rewritten.</statement>
      <rationale>Solution-shaped problem statements pre-commit the team to the first idea and starve later alternatives. The "user voice + no solution words" rule keeps the problem open for design exploration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Target User is named as a specific cohort with a measurable definition (e.g. "PMs at companies 10-50 people using Notion for product docs"), not a marketing persona. Definitions vague enough to match anyone ("startup founders") are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague personas let every downstream decision invoke "well a founder might…", which approves any direction. A measurable cohort definition forces tradeoffs and enables instrumentation to verify the cohort actually exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Evidence cites at least three concrete data points: an interview quote (with consent + source), a measurement (analytics, support volume, NPS verbatim), and one competitor or alternative-tool observation. Each citation has a link or file-path; evidence without a source is removed and the claim weakened.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-source claims (one customer call) drive products into edge-case features. Triangulation across interview + measurement + market makes the problem real; sourced citations make the artefact defensible in roadmap pushback.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Success Metric names one leading indicator and one lagging indicator with current baselines, target values, and the measurement instrument. "More engaged users" is rejected; "weekly active checkout completions, baseline 12%, target 18%, measured via metrics.events.checkout_complete" is the shape required.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a baselined metric and instrument, "did we win?" is unanswerable; the team ships features and never closes the discovery loop. Forcing baseline+target+instrument at handoff time is the cheapest moment to set the bar.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Problem
"I keep losing track of which Notion page is the latest project plan."

## Target User
PMs at companies 10-50 people using Notion as the primary doc tool.

## Jobs-to-be-Done
- When starting a meeting, find the canonical plan in <30s.
- When updating a plan, leave a clear pointer for the next reader.

## Evidence
- 6/9 interviewees described "the right page" search failure (transcripts/...)
- Support volume "lost page" up 40% YoY (dashboards/...)
- Coda, ClickUp show pinned-doc patterns (notes/competitor-2026-05.md)

## Success Metric
- Leading: pinned-page count per workspace; baseline 0.4, target 2.0
- Lagging: weekly "lost page" support tickets; baseline 38, target ≤20
- Instrument: events.workspace.pinned_page_view; events.support.ticket_lost_page
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
We talked to some founders and they want better document organization.
We should build a pinned-pages feature.
KPI: engagement up.
]]></code>
      <note>Solution-shaped, vague cohort, no evidence, no instrumented metric — design will re-derive, engineering will ask for an AC, the loop never closes.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
