<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Indie Mini-CRM (Notion) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Indie Mini-CRM (Notion) application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-four-databases" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Workspace MUST be exactly 4 databases (Contacts, Outreach, Partners, Touches) with linked relations. Single-table CRMs are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Indie flows are many-to-many; a single table collapses past ~50 contacts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-closed-contact-type-enum" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Contacts.Type MUST be a closed select (subscriber / customer / partner / prospect / VIP). Free-text type fields are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Open enums become folklore; closed enums make filter views deterministic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-last-touch-date-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every contact MUST carry a last_touch_date populated by ritual. Missing dates are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Stalling detection depends on the date; without it the CRM becomes a graveyard.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-three-rituals-scheduled" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Spec MUST schedule the 3 rituals (morning outreach batch, weekly partner review, monthly community pulse) as recurring tasks.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Unscheduled rituals decay within 4 weeks; calendar entries protect them.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-templated-outreach" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Outreach DM / email MUST use templates with response-rate tracking columns. Free-form outreach is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Without templates response rate cannot be optimised; templates also halve drafting cost.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
