<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Indie Portfolio Scorecard Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Indie Portfolio Scorecard application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="five-columns-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product row MUST populate all five columns: MRR, growth %, support hours, founder hours, joy. Missing columns invalidate the row.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scorecard-discipline research">Scorecard-discipline research — anchors Indie Portfolio Scorecard rule `five-columns-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ninety-day-growth-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Growth % MUST be computed over a 90-day window. Shorter windows are noise; longer windows lag too much.</statement>
      <rationale source="Time-series research">Time-series research — anchors Indie Portfolio Scorecard rule `ninety-day-growth-window`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hours-self-report-honest" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Founder hours/week MUST be honestly self-reported; &apos;less than I think&apos; bias inflates ROI estimates. Calibrate against 1 week of time tracking before the first run.</statement>
      <rationale source="Self-reporting calibration">Self-reporting calibration — anchors Indie Portfolio Scorecard rule `hours-self-report-honest`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="monthly-review-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The scorecard MUST be reviewed monthly. Quarterly = signal lags too long; weekly = noise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cadence-research practice">Cadence-research practice — anchors Indie Portfolio Scorecard rule `monthly-review-cadence`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="explicit-decision-per-product" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each scorecard review MUST emit one decision per product: grow / maintain / kill. No-decision rows are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-record discipline">Decision-record discipline — anchors Indie Portfolio Scorecard rule `explicit-decision-per-product`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
