<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="a11y-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Entry-level accessibility layer: WCAG POUR principles, conformance levels, evaluation types, quick-check protocol, and pre-commit gate criteria.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>wcag</tag>
      <tag>a11y</tag>
      <tag>inclusion</tag>
      <tag>compliance</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>beginner</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Accessibility Basics</title>
    <summary>The entry-level accessibility layer for web products: WCAG POUR principles, A/AA/AAA conformance levels, four evaluation types, five-minute quick-check protocol, and pre-commit gate criteria. Automated scanners catch only ~30% of issues; manual and assistive-tech testing is required.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Products without accessibility baseline exclude users with disabilities, create legal compliance risk (ADA, Section 508, AODA), and accumulate expensive late-stage fixes. Wiring axe-core into CI catches regressions at PR time, where fixing a failing input label costs minutes rather than hours in a QA cycle. The POUR framework gives teams a shared vocabulary for categorizing and prioritizing issues.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Onboarding a team or codebase to accessibility for the first time</item>
        <item>Pre-launch sanity sweep on a small site or feature where a full WCAG 2.2 conformance audit is overkill</item>
        <item>Wiring CI to catch the obvious 30% automated tools find: missing alt, unlabelled inputs, contrast failures, heading skips</item>
        <item>Educating a new agent or developer before they edit UI code</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Final compliance sign-off — use wcag-22-compliance and regulatory-compliance-2026</item>
        <item>Real assistive-technology testing flows (NVDA/VoiceOver/TalkBack) — use testing-with-assistive-technology</item>
        <item>Procurement / VPAT-ACR generation — use regulatory-compliance-2026</item>
        <item>XR/spatial experiences — use vr-design-patterns, ar-design-patterns, spatial-accessibility</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="WCAG POUR Principles">
      <p>POUR is a teaching frame for categorizing accessibility issues, not a checklist. Treating it as a checklist produces shallow audits.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Perceivable: can users perceive all content? Examples: alt text for images, captions for video, colour contrast of 4.5:1 for text and 3:1 for UI components.</item>
        <item>Operable: can users operate all controls? Examples: full keyboard access, no keyboard traps, sufficient time limits, no seizure-inducing flashes.</item>
        <item>Understandable: can users understand content and UI? Examples: clear language, predictable navigation, error identification and suggestion.</item>
        <item>Robust: does it work with current and future assistive technology? Examples: valid HTML, correct ARIA usage, name-role-value on all custom components.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Conformance Levels">
      <list>
        <item>Level A: minimum accessibility — must have. Blocking issues for all users with disabilities.</item>
        <item>Level AA: standard for most products — legal requirement in most jurisdictions (ADA, Section 508, AODA, EN 301 549). Target for all public-facing products.</item>
        <item>Level AAA: enhanced accessibility — ideal but not always achievable for all content types; target where possible.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pin "WCAG 2.2 AA" in every prompt and audit specification. Agents conflate WCAG levels and produce mixed-level audits that obscure compliance status.</statement>
        <rationale>WCAG 2.2 adds four new success criteria not in 2.1; specifying the version prevents auditing against an outdated standard.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Evaluation Types and Coverage">
      <rule>
        <statement>Automated scanning catches approximately 30% of accessibility issues. Manual testing catches approximately 50%. Assistive-technology testing and user testing with disabled users are required for the remaining issues.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents overweight scanner output; the 30% ceiling is explicit and must be stated whenever scanner results are reported.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Automated testing (axe, pa11y, Lighthouse): continuous, catches structural issues (missing alt, label, contrast, heading order, duplicate IDs).</item>
        <item>Manual testing with keyboard-only navigation: catches focus traps, invisible focus indicators, interaction-order issues.</item>
        <item>Assistive technology testing (NVDA, VoiceOver, TalkBack): catches ARIA misuse, dynamic content not announced, custom widget behavior.</item>
        <item>User testing with disabled participants: catches task-completion barriers that no tool or heuristic predicts.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Five-Minute Quick-Check Protocol">
      <p>Run before any PR that touches UI:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Tab through the page: can you reach every interactive element? Is the focus indicator always visible?</item>
        <item>Zoom to 200%: is everything still usable? Does content reflow without horizontal scroll?</item>
        <item>Check one image: does the alt text convey the same information as the image?</item>
        <item>Check one form: are all labels visible, connected to inputs, and descriptive?</item>
        <item>Run axe DevTools: are there any critical or serious violations?</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Form Labels">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every form input must have a visible, programmatically associated label. Placeholder text is not a label substitute: it disappears when typing and has insufficient contrast.</statement>
        <rationale>Screen readers announce the associated label on focus; without it, blind users cannot determine the field's purpose. Low-contrast placeholders fail SC 1.4.3.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="html"><![CDATA[<input type="text" placeholder="Email">]]></code>
        <note>No label; placeholder disappears on input; screen reader announces only type.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="html"><![CDATA[<label for="email">Email address</label>
<input type="text" id="email" name="email" aria-describedby="email-hint">
<span id="email-hint">We'll never share your email.</span>]]></code>
        <note>Visible label, programmatic association, hint text linked via aria-describedby.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Image Alt Text">
      <rule>
        <statement>Decorative images: empty alt="" plus role="presentation". Informative images: concise description of the information conveyed. Complex images: short alt plus a long description linked via aria-describedby.</statement>
        <rationale>Alt text must convey the same information as the image to a user who cannot see it; the correct pattern depends on the image's role in the page.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="html"><![CDATA[<!-- Decorative image -->
<img src="decorative-line.png" alt="" role="presentation">

<!-- Informative image -->
<img src="chart.png" alt="Sales increased 25% in Q3 compared to Q2">

<!-- Complex image -->
<figure>
  <img src="diagram.png"
       alt="System architecture diagram"
       aria-describedby="diagram-desc">
  <figcaption id="diagram-desc">
    Three layers: presentation, business logic, and data.
    [Full description follows...]
  </figcaption>
</figure>]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="ARIA Misuse Antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding aria-label to a native element that already has an accessible name from its label element.</description>
        <reason>Duplicate accessible names confuse screen readers; the aria-label overrides the visible label, causing inconsistency for sighted screen-reader users.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using role="button" on a div element.</description>
        <reason>Native &lt;button&gt; provides keyboard activation (Enter and Space), implicit role, and focus management for free; div + role requires manual keyboard handler and is frequently incomplete.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adding ARIA attributes to fix scanner failures without understanding the semantic model.</description>
        <reason>Bad ARIA is worse than no ARIA; it creates a false accessible name or role that misleads assistive technology into announcing incorrect information.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="CI Gate">
      <rule>
        <statement>Wire axe-core into PR CI. A failing PR for a missing label is cheaper than a post-launch fix. Lint with eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y to catch issues at type time.</statement>
        <rationale>Accessibility debt compounds; catching issues at PR time costs minutes, at QA costs hours, and post-launch can cost litigation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <code lang="javascript"><![CDATA[// tests/a11y.spec.js — `npm exec playwright test tests/a11y.spec.js`
const { test, expect } = require('@playwright/test');
const AxeBuilder = require('@axe-core/playwright').default;

const ROUTES = ['/', '/pricing', '/login', '/dashboard'];
for (const route of ROUTES) {
  test(`a11y: ${route}`, async ({ page }) => {
    await page.goto(route, { waitUntil: 'networkidle' });
    const results = await new AxeBuilder({ page })
      .withTags(['wcag2a', 'wcag2aa', 'wcag22aa'])
      .analyze();
    const critical = results.violations.filter(v => v.impact === 'critical' || v.impact === 'serious');
    expect(critical, JSON.stringify(critical, null, 2)).toEqual([]);
  });
}]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Integration">
      <p>Use as the on-ramp / triage layer: a fast agent runs axe-core + pa11y over routes, plus heuristic checks against the quick checklist (Tab path, 200% zoom, alt text sanity, label binding, heading order). It produces a categorized issue list (perceivable / operable / understandable / robust), routes critical issues to fix-PR agents, and escalates anything ambiguous (ARIA, complex components, dynamic regions) to human accessibility review or to testing-with-assistive-technology.</p>
      <section name="Recommended Subagents">
        <list>
          <item>faion-accessibility-specialist-agent — POUR-categorized triage and remediation suggestions.</item>
          <item>faion-frontend-developer-agent — apply fixes (alt, label, contrast, heading hierarchy, focus styles).</item>
          <item>faion-testing-developer-agent — wire axe-core / pa11y-ci / lighthouse-ci into CI; gate PRs on regressions.</item>
          <item>faion-ux-ui-designer-agent — design-token review for contrast, focus indicator, target size before code lands.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Prompt Patterns">
        <p>Role: a11y triage.</p>
        <p>Input: URL list or HTML snapshot.</p>
        <p>Run conceptual checks against POUR: missing alt, unlabelled inputs, contrast &lt;4.5:1 (text) / 3:1 (UI), heading skips, keyboard-only path broken, focus invisible, duplicate IDs, language not set. Return JSON {issue_id, principle, severity: critical/major/minor, selector, fix, wcag_ref}.</p>
        <p>Role: 5-minute test runner.</p>
        <p>Walk these routes: &lt;list&gt;. For each:</p>
        <list>
          <item>1) Tab from top → list focus path + first unreachable element.</item>
          <item>2) Zoom 200% → list reflow breakages.</item>
          <item>3) Pick one img → critique alt text.</item>
          <item>4) Pick one form → list label/aria-describedby gaps.</item>
          <item>5) axe scan → report critical violations only.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="CLI Tools">
        <list>
          <item>axe-core — Programmatic a11y checks (in-browser, Node, Playwright, Puppeteer). npm i -D axe-core @axe-core/playwright</item>
          <item>pa11y / pa11y-ci — CLI runner over URLs, JSON output, CI integration. npm i -D pa11y-ci</item>
          <item>lighthouse-ci — Aggregate perf + a11y + SEO with budgets in CI. npm i -D @lhci/cli</item>
          <item>axe-cli — CLI-only axe runner. npm i -g @axe-core/cli</item>
          <item>wcag-zoo — Heading-order + skip-link checks, simple Python. pip install wcag-zoo</item>
          <item>eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y — Lint React/JSX for known a11y mistakes. npm i -D eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y</item>
          <item>eslint-plugin-vuejs-accessibility — Same for Vue. npm i -D eslint-plugin-vuejs-accessibility</item>
          <item>headingsmap (browser ext) — Manual heading-tree review. Chrome/Firefox stores</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Services &amp; SaaS">
        <list>
          <item>Deque axe DevTools / Auditor — SaaS + browser ext. Yes — REST + CLI. Most accurate scanner; paid tiers expand coverage</item>
          <item>WAVE (WebAIM) — SaaS + browser ext. Limited — UI-centric. Strong educational visualization</item>
          <item>SiteImprove — SaaS. Yes — REST. Enterprise crawl + remediation tracking</item>
          <item>Tenon — SaaS. Yes — REST. API-first scanner</item>
          <item>Accessibility Insights for Web (Microsoft) — OSS. Partial — assessment-driven. Guided manual + automated</item>
          <item>Pa11y Dashboard — OSS, self-host. Yes. Tracks scans over time</item>
          <item>Tota11y — OSS bookmarklet. Manual. Visual overlay for first-pass review</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="Best Practices">
        <list>
          <item>Wire axe-core into PR CI early; failing PR is cheaper than a lawsuit.</item>
          <item>Lint with eslint-plugin-jsx-a11y (or framework equivalent) in editor — catch issues at type time.</item>
          <item>Build the team habit: every PR that touches UI runs the 5-minute manual test before review.</item>
          <item>Use semantic HTML first; reach for ARIA only when no semantic equivalent exists.</item>
          <item>Keep an a11y backlog separate from feature backlog — visible debt, owned, not buried.</item>
          <item>Train designers on contrast (4.5:1 text, 3:1 UI) and focus visibility — most bugs originate in design tokens.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
        <list>
          <item>Agents add aria-label to native elements that already have accessible names — duplicates and confuses screen readers.</item>
          <item>Agents recommend role="button" on &lt;div&gt; instead of using &lt;button&gt; — keyboard handlers go missing.</item>
          <item>Agents conflate WCAG levels (A vs. AA vs. AAA); pin "WCAG 2.2 AA" in every prompt.</item>
          <item>Color-contrast checks fail on text over images / gradients; agents miss this — escalate to manual review.</item>
          <item>Generated alt text from filenames is bad; require model to read surrounding context before authoring alt.</item>
          <item>Agents skip cognitive accessibility; explicitly include "plain language, predictable, error-prevention" in audit scope.</item>
          <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: ARIA additions, custom-component patterns (combobox, tabs, modal), focus-management refactors, anything dynamic with live regions.</item>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/a11y-ci.js" purpose="Playwright + axe-core CI gate for WCAG 2.2 AA across defined routes"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG22/quickref/"/>
      <link href="https://webaim.org/intro/"/>
      <link href="https://www.a11yproject.com/checklist/"/>
      <link href="https://dequeuniversity.com/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Accessibility"/>
      <link href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/ARIA/apg/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
