<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitOps — Repository Structure Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="base-plus-overlays" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Repo layout MUST follow `base/` + `overlays/&lt;env&gt;/` per workload. Flat env-specific copies of manifests are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kustomize convention">Flat copies drift; base-plus-overlays keeps the differences explicit and small.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="tenant-folder-per-team" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Multi-team repos MUST allocate `tenants/&lt;team&gt;/` with its own RBAC + Kustomization. Shared global namespaces across teams are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Multi-tenancy isolation">Shared namespaces create cross-team blast radius; tenant folders enforce ownership boundaries.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="promotion-via-pr-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Promotion from env N to env N+1 MUST be a PR that moves the image tag / chart version. Direct edits to the prod overlay outside a PR are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit + review">PRs are the only auditable promotion artefact; direct edits bypass review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kustomize-or-helm-not-both-inline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per workload choose Kustomize OR Helm; do not mix Helm-template-then-Kustomize-patch inline. (Cross-tool wrapping via Flux HelmRelease + post-render is acceptable.)</statement>
      <rationale source="Tool clarity">Inline mixing produces unreadable diffs; pick a primary tool per workload.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="readme-per-overlay" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every `overlays/&lt;env&gt;/` MUST contain a README.md describing the env's purpose, approvers, and divergence rationale from base.</statement>
      <rationale source="Self-documenting repo">Without a README, future operators reverse-engineer the overlays; README codifies the why.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when single-env single-tenant OR Helm-only with per-env values is sufficient.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">Overlays cost cognitive overhead; below thresholds they are pure overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
