<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Behavior-Triggered Onboarding Emails Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Behavior-Triggered Onboarding Emails application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-trigger-on-behavior" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each email in the sequence MUST fire on a tracked user behavior (action OR inaction), not on time alone. Pure day-N drips are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Behavior triggers outperform time triggers by 15-40% on activation rate.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-one-cta-per-email" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each email MUST carry exactly one CTA matching the next activation step. Multi-CTA onboarding is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Confused users do not activate; one ask per email holds focus.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-escalation-ladder" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sequence MUST include an escalation ladder: nudge → help → human-offered for users stuck at the same step ≥3 times.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Stuck users churn silently; escalation surfaces them before churn.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-activation-event-defined" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sequence MUST name a single activation event the whole ladder targets. Without it, success cannot be measured.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Without a named event, retention attribution collapses and the sequence cannot be optimised.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-stop-on-activation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sequence MUST suppress remaining emails immediately on activation. Continuing the drip post-activation is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Post-activation drips read as spam and depress long-term engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
