<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Value Stream Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules grounding VSM. Each rule pairs a binary check + empirically anchored rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="customer-anchored-boundary" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lead Time MUST be measured from "user filed request" to "user received value" — NOT from "ticket created" to "merged". Reports that use internal endpoints are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mik Kersten — Project to Product (2018); Forsgren/Humble/Kim — Accelerate (2018)">Internal pipeline metrics (commit-to-deploy) can look elite while the customer waits weeks for spec, design, and compliance stages that precede the first commit. Only customer-anchored boundaries reveal actual flow.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="work-type-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Flow data MUST be split by Kersten's four work types: feature, defect, risk, debt. Single-number flow metrics are rejected as misleading.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kersten Flow Framework; DevOps Research and Assessment cohort studies">A team shipping 100% defect work has high throughput but zero feature velocity; aggregating disguises this. Four-type split is the minimum granularity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pair-dora-metrics" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never optimise one DORA metric in isolation. Reports MUST always show the full four-tuple (DF, CLT, CFR, MTTR) AND pair DF with CFR. Single-metric optimisation is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Accelerate (Forsgren/Humble/Kim); DORA State of DevOps reports 2019-2023">Deployment frequency can be gamed by deploying trivial changes. AI productivity that lifts DF while raising CFR erases the gain. The four-tuple interacts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="fifty-item-minimum-before-constraint" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A constraint MUST NOT be declared with &lt; 50 items per work type in the analysis window. With insufficient data, emit `insufficient_data: true` and stop.</statement>
      <rationale source="Little's Law statistical-validity research; DORA panel-size guidance">Constraint identification flips month-to-month with low data volume. >= 50 items per type is the minimum sample for Little's Law to hold within reasonable noise.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-elite-label-without-trend" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The report MUST NOT publish a DORA tier label ("Elite", "High") without trend context (>= 2 quarters of data + delta vs prior period). Static-label reports are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Accelerate methodology — levels are improvement benchmarks, not badges; Goodhart's Law cohort observations">Publishing static levels invites teams to optimise for the scorecard, destroying the signal. Trend context preserves the diagnostic value.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="ai-pr-bot-split" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When AI-generated PRs are present in the dataset, the report MUST report `human_prs` and `bot_prs` counts separately for DF and Throughput. Mixed totals are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitHub copilot-impact studies 2024; faion-network internal AI-flood audit">AI commits can flood the repo with micro-PRs that inflate DF and Throughput without raising Earned Value. Splitting preserves comparability across quarters.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
