<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-doc-model" title="Requirements Documentation — Model and EARS Patterns">
  <summary>Requirements hierarchy, document-set boundaries, SMART attributes, EARS phrasing patterns, and standard selection rule.</summary>

  <section title="Requirements Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain BRD (BR- prefix), URS (UR- prefix), and SRS/FRD (FR-/NFR- prefix) as separate files with distinct ID namespaces. One requirement per file remains the source-of-truth. Never blend BRD and FRD content into a single document.</statement>
      <rationale>BRD = why (business); URS = what users need (operational); SRS/FRD = what the system shall do (functional + NFR). Teams that produce overlapping content lose traceability between levels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Business Requirements (BR-) — why are we doing this? example: "Increase revenue by 20%"</item>
      <item>Stakeholder/User Requirements (UR-/SR-) — what do users need? example: "Sales reps need to create quotes faster"</item>
      <item>Functional Requirements (FR-) — what shall the system do? example: "The system shall calculate quote total"</item>
      <item>Non-Functional Requirements (NFR-) — how shall the system perform? example: "Pages shall load in less than 2 seconds"</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Standard Selection Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick one standard per project — IEEE 830-1998 or ISO/IEC/IEEE 29148:2018 — and freeze it in constitution.md before any requirement is written. Mixing standards produces section-name skew and audit ambiguity.</statement>
      <rationale>IEEE 830 is more prescriptive on document structure; ISO 29148 is more process-oriented and better for systems engineering. Mixing them silently creates incompatible section numbering.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="SMART Requirement Attributes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every requirement must be: Specific (only one interpretation), Measurable (testable against acceptance criteria), Achievable (technically feasible), Relevant (traces to a business need), and free of subjective terms (fast, user-friendly, easy, robust, intuitive, seamless).</statement>
      <rationale>Subjective terms cannot be tested; a requirement containing them is a deferred conflict with QA.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="EARS Patterns for Functional Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write all functional requirements in one of the six EARS patterns. Default to Ubiquitous only when no trigger or state condition applies; always ask whether the requirement is actually event-driven or state-driven first.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents and teams default every FR to Ubiquitous ("The system shall..."), producing unconditional requirements that under-specify state machines and generate ambiguous test conditions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Ubiquitous: "The system shall {response}." — unconditional</item>
      <item>Event-driven: "When {trigger}, the system shall {response}." — maps to test: given-when-then</item>
      <item>State-driven: "While {state}, the system shall {response}." — maps to test: given-setup-when-then</item>
      <item>Optional: "Where {feature included}, the system shall {response}." — feature-flag gated</item>
      <item>Unwanted-behaviour: "If {trigger}, then the system shall {response}." — error/exception handling</item>
      <item>Complex: combine two patterns; one per sentence</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using "should", "may", or "might" in an SRS that mandates "shall".</description>
      <reason>RFC 2119 and IEEE 830 conventions differ; an agent trained on RFC documents writes MAY/SHOULD in a "shall"-only SRS. Lint with the conformance schema; reject modal-verb drift.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Document Versioning Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Version the document, not just the requirements: patch for typos, minor for added requirements, major for scope or baseline changes requiring re-sign-off. Approval block must name role + individual + date + Git tag (e.g., approved-2026-04-15-srs-v1.0). Never edit an Approved document in place; any change must bump version and reset status to Draft.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents editing Approved docs in place silently destroy the audit chain; CI-checked status invariants prevent this.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/brd-template.md">Business Requirements Document template with IEEE-aligned sections</reference>
  <reference path="templates/srs-conformance.yaml">IEEE 830 conformance schema for CI validation</reference>
  <reference path="templates/srs_conform.py">Python validator that fails CI on missing sections and forbidden words</reference>
</text>
