<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Positioning Diff Log Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules every positioning-diff-log entry must satisfy. The discipline is the only thing keeping the log useful 12 months in.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-adr-style-header" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each entry has a stable header: `entry_id` (sequential), `date`, `trigger` (one of: competitor-move, customer-call, persona-recalibration, support-pattern, metric-degradation, founder-insight), `expected_effect` (one sentence), `success_metric` (the metric and the threshold that would prove the change worked), `status` (draft / live / rolled-back). The body is the old-vs-new diff.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nygard ADR pattern; calibration research on hypothesis-tracking">Without a stable header, the log devolves into a journal that nobody can query. The fixed header lets the founder filter for "all changes triggered by competitor moves" or "all changes with status=rolled-back", which is the basis for learning what kinds of positioning iterations actually pay off.</rationale>
      <example type="good" title="Diff entry">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Entry 014 — 2026-05-12
trigger: support-pattern (3 of last 5 demo requests asked "is this for me?")
expected_effect: clarify audience in hero so demo-request quality rises
success_metric: demo-to-trial conversion rises from 32% to 40%+ by 2026-07-15
status: live

### OLD
"Faion ships SDD-grade methodology to your coding agent."

### NEW
"Faion ships SDD-grade methodology to your coding agent — built for solo
SaaS builders shipping their first paying product."

### Source signals
- Support ticket #4421: "is this for agencies or individuals?"
- Demo 2026-05-09: "we are 80-person co-op, not really your customer right?"
- Competitor scan: 2 competitors lead with team-size segmentation

### 30-day check (due 2026-06-11)
[unchecked]

### 90-day check (due 2026-08-10)
[unchecked]
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-trigger-required-and-categorised" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every entry's `trigger` field must be one of a closed list of 6 trigger types. Free-text triggers are rejected. An entry without a trigger is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="taxonomy-anchored learning research">A closed trigger list lets the monthly review answer "which trigger types produce the highest hit rate". Free-text triggers cannot be aggregated. Without categorisation, the founder cannot learn whether their positioning iterations are reactive (chasing competitors) or proactive (founder insight backed by data).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-source-quotes-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each entry includes at least one verbatim source signal: a support ticket excerpt, a demo-call quote, a competitor headline screenshot URL, or a metric chart with the relevant numbers. Synthetic source signals (paraphrased, reconstructed from memory) are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="anti-revisionism in decision logs; ADR best practice">Source quotes anchor the entry in observable reality. Without them, the founder rewrites the trigger to fit the change in retrospect. Verbatim sources prevent the log from becoming a self-justifying narrative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-thirty-and-ninety-day-checks" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each entry has a `30-day check (due YYYY-MM-DD)` and `90-day check (due YYYY-MM-DD)` section. By the due date, the section must be populated with the actual metric value, the threshold the entry expected, and a verdict: confirmed / not-observed / inconclusive. Unpopulated past-due sections are blockers on any new positioning change.</statement>
      <rationale source="hypothesis-test discipline; positioning-iteration burnout patterns">Without the check sections, every positioning change is a fire-and-forget event. The 30/90-day rhythm forces the founder to confront the data, distinguishing positioning changes that worked from those that did not. The blocker rule prevents the founder from churning positioning without ever evaluating prior changes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-monthly-review-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On the first Monday of each month, the founder runs the monthly review: surfaces all entries past their due checks, fills in the missing checks (or explicitly marks them inconclusive with reason), and posts a one-page summary to the marketing channel including any positioning-rollbacks the data justifies.</statement>
      <rationale source="async-team review cadence patterns">Without a forced review event the log rots into a write-only file. The monthly review is the moment the data feeds back into the next positioning decision; skipping it makes the entire discipline a costume.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="What does NOT belong here">
    <list>
      <item>Copy edits below the hero / sub-hero level (button copy, microcopy) — too granular</item>
      <item>Pricing-page changes — track in the pricing experiment runbook</item>
      <item>Feature announcement copy — track in the launch / release notes</item>
      <item>Internal team renaming or org-structure shifts — track elsewhere</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
