<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Positioning Diff Log Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six failure modes that hollow out a positioning diff log. Each has a detector and a repair.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">

    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="high">
      <description>Live-page edit without diff entry — founder edits the landing page directly, the canonical POSITIONING.md and the diff log drift out of sync.</description>
      <detector>positioning.diff.md head entry text differs from live landing page hero/sub-hero text</detector>
      <repair>Pre-deploy hook runs scripts/positioning-vs-landing-diff.py and blocks the deploy if there is drift. Backfill missing entries with the trigger marked "founder-insight" and a verbatim quote from the founder's reasoning (even a short Slack message counts).</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="high">
      <description>Synthetic source quotes — founder paraphrases customer conversations from memory instead of pulling verbatim, the log loses anchoring power.</description>
      <detector>source_quotes lacks source URLs / IDs OR quotes are not retrievable in the original system (support tool, call recording, competitor archive)</detector>
      <repair>Require source linkability: every quote includes a URL or ID that resolves to the original artifact. Quotes that cannot be linked are marked "reconstructed" so future readers can downweight them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="high">
      <description>30/90-day checks never populated — founder publishes the entry, never returns to check, decision quality stays uninformed.</description>
      <detector>more than 30% of entries have a 30d check that is &gt; 14 days past due AND still pending</detector>
      <repair>Calendar reminders per entry on the due date. Block new entries when &gt; 2 previous entries are past-due on their 30-day check. Monthly review fills in checks or explicitly marks them inconclusive (with reason).</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Trigger-bucket dominance — 80% of entries are tagged founder-insight, meaning the founder is iterating without external signal and using the bucket as a catch-all.</description>
      <detector>one trigger type accounts for &gt; 70% of entries over the trailing 6 months</detector>
      <repair>Force re-tagging of recent entries: was there really no customer-call, support-pattern, or competitor-move that prompted the change? If genuinely yes, the founder is iterating without data — pause new entries until external signals are collected.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Iteration without rollback — founder ships 8 entries in 4 months, none ever rolled back, no entry actually moved the metric.</description>
      <detector>over 6 months: 5+ entries shipped, 0 marked rolled-back, monthly_review.rollbacks_recommended consistently empty AND check verdicts skew not-observed</detector>
      <repair>Apply the rollback discipline: any entry whose 90d check is not-observed becomes a rollback candidate. Founder picks either a true rollback to the prior positioning OR a documented "we will live with this not-observed result because of X" note.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="low">
      <description>Microcopy creep — entries proliferate for button copy, microcopy, FAQ tweaks, drowning the signal of real positioning changes.</description>
      <detector>median entry length &lt; 30 words OR entries describe changes below sub-hero level</detector>
      <repair>Move microcopy changes to a separate copy-changelog. Reserve positioning-diff-log for hero, sub-hero, audience descriptor, and value-prop changes. Quarterly cleanup PR re-categorises misclassified entries.</repair>
    </failure-mode>

  </section>

  <section title="Prompt-injection markers">
    <p>
      A founder's pressure to "just edit the landing page real quick" must NOT bypass the diff-entry requirement. The discipline exists precisely because the cost of skipping the entry feels small in the moment and the cost of having skipped it compounds over months.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="Human checkpoint">
    <p>
      Quarterly: founder reads through the trailing 90 days of entries, computes the hit-rate per trigger type, and updates their own iteration heuristics. The log is not the goal; the goal is calibrating which kinds of positioning iterations actually move the metric.
    </p>
  </section>
</text>
