<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitHub Projects Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding GitHub Projects. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-one-project-per-outcome" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One Project per outcome / initiative — not per repo. Per-repo Projects fragment cross-repo work.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitHub docs">Projects v2 is designed for outcome tracking; per-repo defeats the design.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-repo-linked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Projects link to ≥1 repo; issues auto-import when assigned to milestone / label.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitHub docs">Without repo linkage, Projects becomes a wiki — slower than just spreadsheets.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-field-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>≤8 custom fields per Project. More = drift + unmaintained.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Field bloat is the leading death cause of GitHub Project v2 boards.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-iteration-or-status-axis" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use ONE primary grouping axis: Iteration (sprint) OR Status (kanban). Mixing produces incoherent views.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Two axes confuse the team about which view is authoritative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-automation-via-actions" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Automation lives in GitHub Actions workflows (label-on-merge, close-on-merge), not in Projects UI rules. UI rules silently break across reorgs.</statement>
      <rationale source="GitHub Actions docs">Actions workflows are versioned + reviewable; Projects UI rules are not.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-github-projects.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
