<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-project-setup" title="GitHub Projects Setup Rules">
  <summary>Rules for configuring GitHub Projects v2: custom fields, views, and built-in workflow automation.</summary>

  <section title="Project Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create organization-level projects for cross-repo work. Repo-level projects are limited to one repository and cannot be used for portfolio tracking.</statement>
      <rationale>Organization-level projects support items from any repo under the org and can be set to public for open-source visibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define standard custom fields at project creation: Status (single_select: Backlog/Todo/In Progress/In Review/Done), Priority (single_select: P0/P1/P2/P3), Estimate (number), Sprint (iteration, 2-week duration), Team (single_select). These cannot be created via API — configure in the GitHub UI before agent automation begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Iteration fields (sprints) and their options cannot be created via the GitHub Projects GraphQL API as of 2025. Pre-creating them in the UI is mandatory for agent sprint planning to work.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Views">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create three standard views: Table (all issues, sortable by priority), Board (grouped by Status, filtered to current sprint), Roadmap (grouped by Release, zoom level month). Each view serves a distinct audience — do not create redundant views.</statement>
      <rationale>Redundant views become stale. Three views covers planning (Table), execution (Board), and stakeholder communication (Roadmap).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Built-in Workflows">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable these four built-in workflows in project settings: Item added → Status=Backlog, Item reopened → Status=Todo, Item closed → Status=Done, Pull request merged → Status=Done. Do not build GitHub Actions equivalents for these — the built-in workflows are more reliable.</statement>
      <rationale>Built-in workflows run as project-level automation without requiring GitHub Actions tokens or YAML maintenance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable "Auto-add items" workflow for the primary repo with label filters. This eliminates manual issue-to-project linking for standard issue types.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual linking is the most common workflow gap — developers forget to add issues to the project, creating invisible work.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Issue Templates">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create YAML-form issue templates in .github/ISSUE_TEMPLATE/ for feature requests and bugs. Templates must include a dropdown for Priority (P0/P1/P2/P3) and auto-assign the issue to the project via the projects key. This gives agents consistently structured issues to parse.</statement>
      <rationale>Free-text issue bodies have no schema. YAML form templates enforce structure that agents can reliably parse for triage and field assignment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/issue-feature.yml">Feature request issue template (YAML form)</reference>
  <reference path="templates/workflow-project-automation.yml">GitHub Actions for adding issues to project</reference>
</text>
