<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Stakeholder Engagement Framework">
  <summary>The five engagement levels, assessment matrix, level-transition strategies, and warning signs that signal engagement degradation.</summary>

  <section title="Engagement Levels">
    <p>Each stakeholder is assessed at a point in time against five levels:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Unaware (U) — stakeholder does not know the project exists or does not understand its relevance.</item>
      <item>Resistant (R) — aware but actively or passively opposed; may block decisions or withhold resources.</item>
      <item>Neutral (N) — aware but indifferent; neither advances nor hinders the project.</item>
      <item>Supportive (S) — aware and positively engaged; provides inputs, advocates informally.</item>
      <item>Leading (L) — actively champions the project; removes barriers, drives adoption, takes public ownership.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every engagement level assessment must cite at least one behavioral signal; "seems supportive" without evidence defaults to "unknown", not Supportive.</statement>
      <rationale>Label-based assessments without behavioral grounding create false confidence; a PM who believes a stakeholder is Supportive based on polite email responses misses the resistance that surfaces at the critical decision gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Level-Transition Strategies">
    <p>Strategies differ by the transition being targeted:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Unaware to Neutral — inform; tailor message to their specific interests; use trusted intermediaries.</item>
      <item>Resistant to Neutral — listen first, document concerns in the stakeholder's own words; involve in problem-solving; give veto power on specific concerns to build trust; find common ground.</item>
      <item>Neutral to Supportive — demonstrate benefits relevant to their personal goals; ask for their input to generate ownership; show quick wins early.</item>
      <item>Supportive to Leading — assign visible roles (launch spokesperson, steering committee seat); recognize contributions publicly; share strategic information; empower specific decisions.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>For Resistant stakeholders, document their concerns verbatim before designing the strategy; strategies built on assumed concerns miss the real objection and waste engagement effort.</statement>
      <rationale>PM assumptions about why someone is resistant are often wrong; the actual concern (a personal risk, a process implication, an unmet need) requires direct conversation to surface, and addressing the stated concern produces visible trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Warning Signs">
    <p>Observable signals that indicate engagement is degrading — requires immediate outreach:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Declining meeting attendance — sends delegate or stops attending entirely.</item>
      <item>Response latency increases — emails taking days to answer that previously received same-day replies.</item>
      <item>Negative comments in public forums — criticism raised in steering meetings rather than 1:1.</item>
      <item>Going around the project team — raising concerns directly with the executive sponsor.</item>
      <item>Silence in meetings — previously vocal stakeholder becomes passive.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a 30-day rolling engagement log per high-power stakeholder; level changes must be confirmed by two independent signals, not a single interaction.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-signal level changes based on one meeting or one email are unreliable; cross-cultural communication differences, temporary workload spikes, and politeness norms all produce false signals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
