<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Engagement Rules and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Rules for observable behavioral indicators, confidentiality of the engagement plan, cultural context, and safe agentic engagement signal extraction.</summary>

  <section title="Observable Behavioral Indicators">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every "desired level" target with a specific observable behavioral indicator: not "Sales Director is Leading" but "Sales Director mentions the project in the Q3 QBR without being prompted."</statement>
      <rationale>Labels like "Leading" are ambiguous; a behavioral indicator is pass/fail and verifiable by any team member, which eliminates subjective level inflation and creates accountability for the engagement strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Schedule low-effort touchpoints (brief email, brief mention in a shared meeting) with Supportive stakeholders at least monthly; Supportive without maintenance regresses to Neutral within one quarter of neglect.</statement>
      <rationale>Engagement is a relationship that requires maintenance; Supportive stakeholders who feel forgotten do not escalate — they quietly disengage, and the regression is invisible until a critical decision reveals it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Confidentiality">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never share the engagement matrix or per-stakeholder strategies with the stakeholders themselves; it is a working PM artefact, not a communication deliverable.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders who see their attitude categorized as "Resistant" with a strategy to "address their concerns" are likely to feel manipulated; the exposure destroys trust and makes honest future assessment impossible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the engagement plan in a restricted-access location; encrypt if the repo is shared beyond the core project team.</statement>
      <rationale>Engagement plans contain candid assessments of individuals' motivations, concerns, and influence; broader exposure damages relationships and may create legal liability depending on jurisdiction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Cultural Context">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a cultural_context note to the system prompt for international programs; engagement tactics calibrated to Western individualist norms misfire in high-context or collectivist cultures.</statement>
      <rationale>Tactics like "give a visible role" or "recognize publicly" improve engagement in low-context cultures but create unwanted attention in high-context cultures where public singling-out is uncomfortable; agents trained predominantly on Western PM content cannot infer this without explicit instruction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using identical engagement strategies for all stakeholders across a global program without cultural context.</description>
      <reason>A one-size engagement approach produces active resistance in cultures where the approach signals disrespect for hierarchy or group norms; differentiation by cultural context is not optional for multinational programs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Engagement Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>The engagement signal agent ingests meeting notes, status emails, and interaction logs; it proposes level updates with confidence (low/medium/high) and never updates the plan autonomously — all level changes require human review.</statement>
      <rationale>Automated level changes based on sentiment analysis of a single email are unreliable; the agent surfaces the evidence, the PM applies judgment, and the human-in-loop on every change maintains accountability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The meeting-prep agent receives only the active stakeholder profile and the last N interactions; the full engagement plan history is not passed to the LLM to avoid PII leakage and context bloat.</statement>
      <rationale>Full plan history in the prompt expands context unnecessarily and passes sensitive assessments of other stakeholders to a model that only needs information about the current conversation target.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/engagement_diff.py">Engagement level diff script between two YAML snapshots</reference>
    <reference path="templates/engagement-plan.md">Stakeholder engagement plan template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/meeting-prep.md">Pre/post-meeting stakeholder prep sheet</reference>
  </section>
</text>
