<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-sdd-and-docs" title="SDD and Living Documentation Trends 2025-2026">
  <summary>SDD as dominant paradigm for AI-assisted development, docs-as-code patterns, LLM-optimized documentation, and developer portal landscape.</summary>

  <section title="Specification-Driven Development">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the specification as the source of truth; code is its output, not the input to understanding.</statement>
      <rationale>SDD emerged as the dominant paradigm for AI-assisted development in 2025. The core principle — intent is the source of truth — reverses the traditional relationship where code is read to understand intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Core workflow: Intent (human) → Spec (human + LLM draft) → Plan (LLM + human review) → Execute (LLM) → Review (human).</p>
    <list>
      <item>SDD effectiveness by scenario:</item>
      <item>Feature work in existing systems (N to N+1): highest effectiveness</item>
      <item>Greenfield with clear requirements: high</item>
      <item>Legacy modernization: medium-high</item>
      <item>Exploratory/R&amp;D work: medium</item>
      <item>Vibe coding / rapid prototypes: low (use different approach)</item>
    </list>
    <p>Key SDD tools as of 2025: Amazon Kiro (full SDD workflow with hooks), Spec Kit (GitHub/Microsoft open-source), Tessl (framework and registry), Claude Code (native SDD support).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Living Documentation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat documentation as first-class code: version-controlled, CI/CD pipelines, automated testing.</statement>
      <rationale>Documentation that is not in version control becomes stale immediately. Docs-as-code enables the same quality gates applied to code to be applied to documentation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Docs-as-code core stack: Markdown/MDX format, Git storage, static site generators (Docusaurus, MkDocs, Mintlify), automated linting and link checking in CI/CD.</p>
    <list>
      <item>LLM-optimized documentation patterns:</item>
      <item>Clear heading hierarchy: better LLM parsing</item>
      <item>Explicit context sections: reduced hallucination</item>
      <item>Code blocks with language tags: accurate code generation</item>
      <item>API contracts in specs: type-safe integration</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Developer Portal Landscape">
    <p>Developer portals are UI; platforms are the backend. The portal is not the platform.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Backstage (89% market share): large orgs, extensibility, TechDocs integration</item>
      <item>Port (rising): service catalogs, workflows, REST API for agent registration</item>
      <item>Cortex (growing): service ownership, scorecards</item>
      <item>Roadie (SaaS leader): Backstage without ops overhead</item>
      <item>Mintlify: llms.txt standard; Anthropic uses for Claude docs</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Load this trends document at the start of quarterly roadmap sessions; do not load it per-task.</statement>
      <rationale>Trend documents are orientation resources, not per-task guides. Loading per-task wastes context tokens and produces over-confident recommendations based on trend data that should be treated as directional.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
