<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GCP Network Architecture Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the gcp-network-architecture methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="shared-vpc-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Shared VPC for any environment with more than one GCP project; the VPC lives in a dedicated host project.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Shared VPC centralises subnet + firewall control with the network team while letting service projects deploy workloads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cidr-allocation-plan" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Allocate /16 per environment VPC; within each VPC reserve /20-/24 for primary subnets, /18-/20 for GKE pod ranges, /24 for GKE services, /28 for GKE master CIDR.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">A documented plan prevents the future GKE-pod-range collisions that block adding new clusters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="psc-for-google-apis" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Private Service Connect for projects without public IPs that call Google APIs; add private DNS zones for googleapis.com and gcr.io.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">PSC plus private DNS lets workloads reach Google without an internet egress path.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cloud-nat-with-min-ports" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure Cloud NAT per region with explicit min-ports-per-VM and dynamic-port-allocation; alert on NAT-port exhaustion.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">NAT-port exhaustion looks like silent connection failures; explicit sizing + alert detects it before user impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hierarchical-firewall" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply hierarchical firewall policies at folder level with explicit deny-all egress and per-tier allow rules.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Folder-level policies cannot be over-ridden by a project-level mistake — the only durable network guard rail.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
