<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Decompose top-line goals into 2-4 product outcomes with 4-week leading indicators and confidence levels, then generate four synchronized audience views from one source of truth.</summary>
    <category>roadmap</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
    <updated>2026-05-01</updated>
    <tags>
      <tag>outcome</tag>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>leading-indicators</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Outcome-Based Roadmaps Advanced</title>

    <summary>Decompose a top-line business goal into 2-4 product outcomes, each with a leading indicator measurable within 4 weeks, a confidence level (low/med/high) backed by evidence, and 2-3 candidate experiments. Maintain one source-of-truth roadmap, then generate four audience views from it: theme-based (customers, no dates), outcome-metric (board, quarterly targets), outcome-plus-options (engineering, sprint-level when known), and problem-solution (sales, only confirmed items get timing). Confidence inflation — defaulting to "medium" without evidence — is the primary failure mode.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Stakeholders who demand feature timelines despite an outcome-first culture are solving a communication problem, not a roadmap-format problem. Audience-tailored views from a single source of truth provide the narrative each audience needs without creating four diverging documents. Breaking a business goal into product outcomes with leading indicators is the highest-leverage PM skill for 2026: it forces explicit evidence requirements and surfaces "what we still need to learn" before committing to solutions.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Stakeholders keep demanding feature timelines; you need audience-tailored views per cohort (board, sales, eng, customers).</item>
        <item>Translating a top-line business goal into a tree of product outcomes with leading indicators.</item>
        <item>Quarterly re-planning where confidence levels shift and the same roadmap must be presented to different audiences.</item>
        <item>A PM transitioning from feature owner to "architect of impact" who needs scaffolding for the new role.</item>
        <item>Trigger phrase: agent or human says "we need a roadmap that says when feature X ships" while leadership has formally adopted outcome-based planning.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Early-stage product (pre-PMF) where outcomes are unstable and discovery dominates — use a "now/next/later" theme list.</item>
        <item>Single-stakeholder context (just you and your co-founder) — the audience-matrix overhead has zero ROI.</item>
        <item>Enterprise with hard-deadline contractual commitments — use a hybrid (outcome theme plus dated milestones).</item>
        <item>Org with no metrics infrastructure — you cannot operate confidence levels without measurement.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <how-to>
      <step>Collect inputs. Gather the single business goal (one sentence with a number and a date), the named audiences (default: customers, board, engineering, sales), the metrics layer access (warehouse, BI URL, query language), and the kill-criteria appetite (how much movement counts as "moving"). If any input is missing, stop and ask the human PM.</step>
      <step>Draft the outcome tree. Decompose the goal into exactly 2-4 product outcomes. For each outcome write: outcome statement (in user-impact voice, not feature voice), leading indicator (must be observable inside 4 weeks), evidence-we-have (link to query/dashboard or "TO BE INSTRUMENTED"), what-we-still-need-to-learn, 2-3 candidate experiments, confidence level (low/medium/high) with mandatory evidence pointer, and a kill criterion ("if X does not move by Y by date Z, drop this outcome"). Save to source-of-truth file (`roadmap.yaml`).</step>
      <step>Validate the outcome tree against the schema and the cap rules. Run `python templates/validate-outcome-tree.py roadmap.yaml`. Fix every reported issue before generating any audience view.</step>
      <step>Generate four audience views from the source-of-truth file. Use the audience-rewriter prompt below. Save outputs as `views/customers.md`, `views/board.md`, `views/engineering.md`, `views/sales.md`. Never edit a view directly; always regenerate from the source.</step>
      <step>Run the view-drift diff. Diff each view against the source and flag any line in a view without a source-of-truth row id. Fail the build if drift exists.</step>
      <step>Schedule cadence. Weekly: leading-indicator monitor pulls metrics and proposes promote/demote/replace per outcome. Quarterly: re-decompose the entire goal tree from scratch. Re-version the roadmap (bump SemVer minor) only on real signal — a sustained metric move greater than 10% of the kill threshold for two consecutive weeks.</step>
      <step>Hand off. Human PM signs off on outcome decomposition before any audience view is published. Customer-facing view requires human edit before publication to strip jargon. Sales view publishes only items with confidence=high.</step>
    </how-to>

    <section name="outcome-decomposition-rules">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Decompose one business goal into exactly 2-4 product outcomes. More than 4 outcomes from a single goal signals lack of focus and must be collapsed.</statement>
        <rationale>Outcome trees with 6-8 branches dilute team attention and make experiment planning incoherent. Hard cap at 4 forces strategic prioritization before committing to measurement.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every outcome must have a leading indicator measurable within 4 weeks. An outcome whose leading indicator requires more than 4 weeks to observe cannot support fast learning.</statement>
        <rationale>Slow leading indicators mean the team runs for a quarter before knowing if the outcome is moving. The 4-week constraint forces selection of leading (not lagging) metrics.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every outcome must list 2-3 candidate experiments, not committed solutions. Listing solutions at the decomposition stage locks in an answer before the problem is understood.</statement>
        <rationale>Outcome roadmaps fail when they become feature roadmaps with outcome labels. Experiments must remain tentative until evidence promotes them.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every outcome must include an "evidence we have" line and a "what we still need to learn" line. Confidence=high requires existing shipped data, not just a strong hypothesis.</statement>
        <rationale>Confidence inflation — defaulting to "medium" or "high" without evidence — is the primary failure mode of outcome roadmaps. The evidence requirement makes confidence a checkable claim.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="source-of-truth-and-audience-views">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Maintain one source-of-truth roadmap. Generate four audience views from it: theme-based (customers, no dates, no internal metrics), outcome-metric (board, quarterly targets, confidence column), outcome-plus-options (engineering, sprint-level when known), problem-solution (sales, only confirmed items get timing).</statement>
        <rationale>Four independent roadmap documents diverge immediately. Views generated from a single source remain synchronized and each line is traceable to a source row.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Customer-facing view stays at theme level for at least 2 quarters out ("better collaboration", not "real-time presence v2"). No internal metrics appear in the customer view.</statement>
        <rationale>Specific feature names in customer-facing roadmaps create commitment expectations the team may not be able to meet. Theme-level language preserves flexibility while communicating direction.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Sales view is the only view that mentions specific solutions, and only for items at high confidence. The other three views must not name solutions for items below high confidence.</statement>
        <rationale>Sales commitment to a specific feature creates a contractual obligation in customer minds. Naming solutions only for high-confidence items limits the blast radius of delivery misses.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="roadmap-cadence">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run the leading-indicator monitor weekly and propose promote/demote/replace actions to the PM. Quarterly, re-decompose the full goal tree. Re-version the roadmap only on real signal, not on every metric blip.</statement>
        <rationale>Rewriting the roadmap on every data point destroys stakeholder trust. The weekly/quarterly cadence separates tactical adjustments from strategic re-decomposition.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pair every roadmap presentation with a kill criterion: "if X does not move by Y, we drop this outcome." Forces honest stakes and prevents zombie outcomes.</statement>
        <rationale>Outcomes without kill criteria become permanent features of the roadmap regardless of evidence. An explicit kill criterion makes the outcome falsifiable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="confidence-management">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Outcomes assigned confidence=medium or confidence=high without cited evidence. Agent defaults to "medium" because it sounds reasonable.</description>
        <reason>Uncalibrated confidence is opinion. Every confidence assertion must reference a query, dashboard URL, or an explicit "TO BE INSTRUMENTED" flag. Without it, the confidence column provides false precision that misleads planning.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use exactly three confidence levels: low, medium, high. More levels create false precision. Confidence=high requires shipped data on the surface; confidence=medium requires some data or reasonable analogues; confidence=low is hypothesis only.</statement>
        <rationale>A 5-level scale devolves into splitting hairs between "medium-high" and "high." The 3-level scale forces clean categorization.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="view-drift-prevention">
      <antipattern>
        <description>An audience view is edited directly rather than regenerated from the source of truth, causing the four views to diverge and contradict each other.</description>
        <reason>Direct edits to views break the single-source principle. When board and engineering views disagree, stakeholders lose confidence in all four. Run a daily diff job to flag lines in views without a source-of-truth trace.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="outcome-count-and-focus">
      <antipattern>
        <description>A business goal decomposed into 6-8 outcomes because every stakeholder's priority gets included.</description>
        <reason>More outcomes = less focus = slower experiments = longer time-to-learn. The hard cap at 4 exists precisely because stakeholder pressure tends toward expansion. A PM must own the decomposition decision and defend the cap.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="sales-pressure-mitigation">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Sales pressure causes specific features and dates to appear in the board view or customer view for items that are below high confidence.</description>
        <reason>Sales pressure is a political problem, not a roadmap format problem. Outcome framing reduces but does not eliminate it. Solving it requires agreement on which view each audience receives and enforcement of view boundaries by the PM.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Board-facing roadmap leads with the metric movement, not the activity list. If a board member asks "where is the chat feature?", redirect to the outcome metric the feature is meant to move.</statement>
        <rationale>Boards skim metrics and ask about named features because named features feel concrete. Leading with the metric reframes the conversation to impact, not output.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A decomposition agent takes one business goal and produces 2-4 candidate product outcomes with leading indicators and an experiment menu, plus an honest "we don't know" branch when evidence is weak. A second agent generates the audience views (theme-based for customers, outcome-metric for board, options-with-confidence for engineering, problem-solution for sales) from the same source. A third agent monitors the leading indicators on a weekly cadence and proposes "promote/demote/replace" actions to the human PM. Human owns final decomposition and audience-view sign-off.</p>

      <list>
        <item>An outcome-decomposition agent (Opus) — strategy work; needs the highest reasoning model.</item>
        <item>An audience-rewriter agent (Sonnet) — reformats one source-of-truth into 4 views without losing fidelity.</item>
        <item>A leading-indicator monitor agent — pulls metrics weekly, flags drift greater than 10%.</item>
        <item>faion-mlp-impl-planner-agent — once an outcome is committed, plans experiments under it.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools for outcome roadmap automation: dbt (define and version leading-indicator metrics with lineage), metabase or superset API (programmatic dashboard creation per audience view), mermaid-cli (render outcome-tree diagrams), pandoc (convert one source markdown into 4 audience PDFs/HTML), gh project (manage outcome roadmap as GitHub Projects with custom fields).</p>

      <p>Services (SaaS/OSS, agent-friendly): ProdPad (outcome-roadmap UX is best-in-class; "now/next/later" with confidence), Airfocus (configurable view per audience from one source), Productboard (strong customer-feedback linkage; audience-specific portals), Aha! Roadmaps (multiple "views" per roadmap is native), Jira Plans / Advanced Roadmaps (engineering-execution audience view; weak for outcome semantics), Notion + dbt + Hex (DIY outcome roadmap that integrates metric layer; cheap and flexible), OpenProject (self-hostable; supports custom outcome fields).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs love to invent plausible-but-wrong leading indicators. Require that every metric has a query/dashboard URL or a flag of "TO BE INSTRUMENTED".</item>
        <item>Outcome decomposition tends toward 6-8 outcomes per goal; force the agent to a hard cap of 4. More than 4 = lack of focus.</item>
        <item>Audience-rewriter agents drift from source over time; run a daily diff job that flags lines in views without traceability.</item>
        <item>Confidence inflation: agents default to "medium" because it sounds safe. Force evidence-based justification per confidence assertion.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoint: outcome trees are strategic; a human PM owns the final decomposition before any audience view is generated.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoint: customer-facing view requires human edit before publication — agent-generated phrasing leaks internal jargon.</item>
        <item>Do not let the agent rewrite the roadmap on every metric blip. Cadence: weekly metric monitor, quarterly re-decomposition, only re-version on real signal.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="source-of-truth-schema">
      <p>The source-of-truth roadmap is one YAML file (`roadmap.yaml`) with stable row ids. All audience views must trace each printed line back to a row id. The schema below is the minimum every row must satisfy; the validator script enforces it.</p>
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
goal:
  statement: "Reduce 90-day churn from 18% to 12% by Q4 2026"
  metric: "churn_rate_d90"
  current: 0.18
  target: 0.12
  due: "2026-12-31"

outcomes:
  - id: O1
    statement: "New users reach the 'aha' moment within first session"
    leading_indicator:
      name: "first_session_aha_pct"
      observable_within_days: 28
      query_url: "https://metabase.example.com/question/142"
      current: 0.34
      target: 0.55
    confidence: medium
    evidence_we_have:
      - "Funnel data shows 34% reach feature X in session 1 (q142)"
    what_we_still_need_to_learn:
      - "Whether tooltip variant lifts feature-X first-touch"
    candidate_experiments:
      - id: O1.E1
        title: "Inline tooltip on first empty state"
        status: "candidate"
      - id: O1.E2
        title: "Sample-data prefill for new accounts"
        status: "candidate"
    kill_criterion: "If first_session_aha_pct does not exceed 0.40 by 2026-06-30, drop O1"
]]></code>
    </section>

    <commands>
      <command name="validate-tree">python skills/faion/knowledge/solo/product/product-manager/outcome-based-roadmaps-advanced/templates/validate-outcome-tree.py path/to/roadmap.yaml</command>
      <command name="render-tree-diagram">mermaid-cli -i outcome-tree.mmd -o outcome-tree.svg</command>
      <command name="generate-views">python tools/render_views.py --source roadmap.yaml --out views/</command>
      <command name="diff-view-drift">python tools/view_drift.py --source roadmap.yaml --views views/ --fail-on-drift</command>
      <command name="weekly-monitor">python tools/leading_indicator_monitor.py --source roadmap.yaml --threshold 0.10 --notify pm@example.com</command>
      <command name="bump-version">git tag -a roadmap-v$(date +%Y.%m).$(git rev-list --count HEAD) -m "real-signal re-version"</command>
    </commands>

    <prompt purpose="outcome-decomposition (Opus)"><![CDATA[
You are an outcome-decomposition agent. Decompose ONE business goal into 2-4 product outcomes.

INPUTS
- business_goal: <one sentence with metric + target + date>
- current_metrics: <list of accessible metrics with query URLs>
- evidence_pool: <links to past experiment results, surveys, dashboards>

HARD RULES
- Exactly 2-4 outcomes. Refuse to output 1 or 5+; ask the user to collapse or focus.
- Each outcome MUST have:
  * statement in user-impact voice (NOT feature voice)
  * leading_indicator with observable_within_days <= 28
  * evidence_we_have (1+ items, each with a real URL or "TO BE INSTRUMENTED")
  * what_we_still_need_to_learn (1+ items)
  * 2-3 candidate_experiments tagged status="candidate"
  * confidence in {low, medium, high}; high requires shipped data; medium requires
    "some data or reasonable analogue"; low is hypothesis only
  * kill_criterion (specific metric, threshold, date)
- Add an explicit "we_dont_know" branch if evidence is weak.
- Output STRICT YAML matching the source-of-truth schema. No prose outside YAML.
]]></prompt>

    <prompt purpose="audience-rewriter (Sonnet)"><![CDATA[
You are an audience-rewriter. Read roadmap.yaml and produce four files:

views/customers.md  — theme-level only; no dates closer than current quarter; no
                      internal metric names; no solution names; >= 2 quarters
                      stay theme-level (e.g. "better collaboration").
views/board.md      — outcome-metric table: outcome | metric | current | target |
                      due | confidence. Lead each section with the METRIC, not
                      the activity list.
views/engineering.md — outcome + options menu + sprint window when an experiment
                       has status=committed; status=candidate items show NO date.
views/sales.md      — problem-solution view. Mention a specific solution ONLY
                      when its parent outcome confidence == "high" AND the
                      experiment status == "committed". Otherwise refer to the
                      outcome theme only.

Every printed line MUST end with a hidden HTML comment <!-- src:<row_id> -->
referencing the source-of-truth row. Lines without a row id will be flagged
and rejected by the drift-checker. Do not invent rows.
]]></prompt>

    <checklist>
      <check>Goal is one sentence with a number and a date.</check>
      <check>Outcome count is 2, 3, or 4 — never 1 or 5+.</check>
      <check>Every outcome's leading indicator has observable_within_days within 28 days.</check>
      <check>Every confidence value cites a query URL, dashboard, or explicit "TO BE INSTRUMENTED".</check>
      <check>Every outcome has 2-3 candidate experiments at status=candidate.</check>
      <check>Every outcome has a kill_criterion with metric, threshold, and date.</check>
      <check>Source-of-truth file (roadmap.yaml) exists and validates against schema.</check>
      <check>All four views regenerate from source; no view edited by hand.</check>
      <check>view_drift.py reports zero drift before publication.</check>
      <check>Customer view contains no internal metric names and no specific solution names.</check>
      <check>Sales view names a solution only when parent outcome confidence == high AND experiment status == committed.</check>
      <check>Board view leads with metric movement, not feature names.</check>
      <check>Human PM has signed off on the outcome decomposition before any view is published.</check>
      <check>Customer view has been human-edited before publication.</check>
      <check>Weekly leading-indicator monitor is scheduled and routes promote/demote/replace proposals to PM.</check>
    </checklist>

    <verify>
      <step>Run `python templates/validate-outcome-tree.py roadmap.yaml`. Expect exit 0 and zero violations on cap (2-4), evidence presence, confidence-evidence pairing, and 2-3 experiments per outcome.</step>
      <step>Run the drift-checker `python tools/view_drift.py --source roadmap.yaml --views views/ --fail-on-drift`. Expect exit 0. Any flagged line means an audience view drifted from source — regenerate, do not patch.</step>
      <step>Confirm the customer view contains zero occurrences of internal metric names: `grep -nE 'first_session_aha_pct|churn_rate_d90' views/customers.md` must return empty.</step>
      <step>Confirm the sales view names solutions only for confidence=high committed items. Cross-check against `roadmap.yaml` with `python tools/check_sales_view_solutions.py views/sales.md roadmap.yaml`.</step>
      <step>Confirm cadence is wired: `crontab -l | grep leading_indicator_monitor` returns a weekly entry, and a quarterly re-decomposition reminder exists in the team calendar.</step>
      <step>Confirm a human-PM sign-off marker exists: `roadmap.yaml` has `signed_off_by:` field with a name and an ISO date within the last 90 days.</step>
      <step>Success criteria for the methodology output: validator PASS, drift PASS, audience boundaries PASS, sign-off present, cadence scheduled. If any of the five fails, the methodology has not been applied — block publication.</step>
    </verify>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/validate-outcome-tree.py" purpose="Python validator: fails outcomes missing leading indicators, high confidence without evidence, or fewer than 2 experiments."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.prodpad.com/blog/now-next-later-roadmap/"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog/roadmap"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/p/the-ultimate-guide-to-product-roadmaps"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
