<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="seven-performance-domains">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>PMBoK 8 organises project management into seven domains: Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk. Each maps to artefacts and measurable outcomes. Fixed canonical list.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>pmbok</tag>
      <tag>domains</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
      <tag>project-planning</tag>
      <tag>audit</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Seven Performance Domains (PMBoK 8)</title>
    <summary>PMBoK 8 reorganises project management into seven performance domains: Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk. Quality, Communications, and Procurement are integrated throughout rather than standalone domains. Each domain maps to observable artefacts and measurable outcomes. The canonical domain list is fixed — agents must never invent an 8th domain or reintroduce "Integration Management" or "Quality" as standalone items.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Domains are the smallest mental model that covers the full scope of a project. Each project artefact belongs under exactly one domain, making gap analysis mechanical: walk the seven, check artefact presence, flag missing ones as risks. PMBoK 8 replaces PMBoK 7's eight domains (Stakeholder, Team, Development Approach, Planning, Project Work, Delivery, Measurement, Uncertainty) and PMBoK 6's ten knowledge areas, so teams migrating between editions need a translation layer.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Structuring a project charter or status pack around a known taxonomy (charter → closure)</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing project plan: walk each domain and surface missing artefacts</item>
        <item>Building a weekly project status dashboard (one panel per domain, RAG per outcome)</item>
        <item>Tailoring methodology selection — domains are stable; processes inside them vary by approach</item>
        <item>Onboarding a PM agent: seven domains is the smallest anchor that still covers everything</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure-Scrum teams with Product Owner / Scrum Master where Scrum events already cover domains implicitly — domain mapping is busywork</item>
        <item>Solopreneur projects under 1 week with a single deliverable — governance and finance collapse to "did I ship, did I get paid"</item>
        <item>Shops still on PMBoK 6 (process groups + knowledge areas) in mid-project — switching narrative mid-project confuses sponsors</item>
        <item>Domain-driven design conversations — the word "domain" overloads the term</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Canonical Seven Domains">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always use exactly these seven domain names — never add an 8th, never reintroduce "Integration Management", "Quality", or "Communications" as standalone domains.</statement>
        <rationale>PMBoK 8 explicitly integrates Quality, Communications, and Procurement. LLMs trained on PMBoK 6 data will hallucinate these as standalone domains; the canonical seven must be pinned in system prompts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Governance — oversight, decision frameworks, value realisation; replaces Integration Management; includes sustainability as a core metric</item>
        <item>Scope — define and control what is included and excluded; enhanced definition and traceability</item>
        <item>Schedule — plan and manage timelines, milestones, and dependencies</item>
        <item>Finance — budgets, costs, financial performance; replaces Cost Management; pairs with EVM</item>
        <item>Stakeholders — identify, analyse, and engage all stakeholders; now includes Communications</item>
        <item>Resources — acquire and manage team members and physical resources; enhanced focus on team development</item>
        <item>Risk — identify, analyse, and respond to uncertainties including threats and opportunities</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Key Artefacts per Domain">
      <p>Minimal artefact set that satisfies each domain. A missing artefact is a risk in the Risk domain.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Governance: charter.md, decision-log.md</item>
        <item>Scope: scope.md, wbs.md, requirements-traceability.md</item>
        <item>Schedule: schedule.md, milestones.md</item>
        <item>Finance: budget.md, cost-baseline.md</item>
        <item>Stakeholders: stakeholder-register.md, comms-plan.md, engagement-plan.md</item>
        <item>Resources: raci.md, team-charter.md</item>
        <item>Risk: risk-register.md</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="PMBoK 7 to 8 Delta">
      <list>
        <item>Principles: 12 (PMBoK 7) → 6 streamlined (PMBoK 8): Stewardship and Ethics, Collaboration, Value Optimisation, Systems and Complexity, Adaptability, Sustainability</item>
        <item>Domains: 8 (PMBoK 7) → 7 (PMBoK 8): Team + Project Work collapsed into Resources + Governance; Planning + Delivery merged into Scope/Schedule/Finance; Measurement absorbed into respective domains; Uncertainty → Risk</item>
        <item>Sustainability: mentioned in PMBoK 7, core principle in PMBoK 8 — needs a measurable proxy (e.g. CO2 per release, accessibility pass rate)</item>
        <item>AI Coverage: none in PMBoK 7, dedicated appendix in PMBoK 8</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Audit Workflow">
      <rule>
        <statement>Walk the seven domains in fixed order (Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk) and for each emit: artefact_path (or MISSING), owner (or UNASSIGNED), last_updated (ISO date or never), status (green/amber/red), next_action (one imperative sentence).</statement>
        <rationale>Fixed domain order makes diffs across weekly runs stable — status changes are visible as line-level changes in version control without noise from reordering.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run the domain audit before every steering committee meeting. The output is the status pack, not a separate document that the PM then summarises manually.</statement>
        <rationale>Separate manual summarisation introduces optimism bias and lag. An automated audit from source artefacts is objective and current.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Map each missing domain artefact directly to a risk entry in the Risk domain register. A missing artefact is not a process gap — it is a project risk with a probability and impact.</statement>
        <rationale>Risk registers that do not include process gaps undercount project risk systematically. Governance gaps are often higher-impact than delivery risks.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Constraints">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM output contains "Integration Management" or "Quality Management" as a domain name.</description>
        <reason>These are PMBoK 6 terms; in PMBoK 8 they are integrated. Any output containing these names is anchored to the wrong edition and must be rejected.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent output lists eight domains (adding Quality or Communications as a standalone).</description>
        <reason>Validate output length == 7 domains. An 8th domain signals PMBoK 6 training bias; reject and re-prompt with the canonical seven in the system prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Domain status colours drift to "green" over time without human sampling.</description>
        <reason>Agents self-validate by confirming artefact existence, not artefact quality. Calibrate by sampling 1 in 5 domains for human review each cycle.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Use the seven domains as a top-level rubric the agent walks linearly: for each domain, the agent asks "what artefact exists, who owns it, what is the current state?". Output is a markdown matrix (domain × artefact × owner × status × next-action). Re-run weekly; diff drives the status report. Never let the agent invent domain names — pin them to the canonical seven (Governance, Scope, Schedule, Finance, Stakeholders, Resources, Risk).</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: pm-domain-auditor (define inline) walks the seven domains against a project workspace and produces a gap matrix. faion-sdd-executor drives implementation of domain gaps through quality gates. brainstorm generates initial artefacts for a new domain. nero-improve feeds the gap matrix into periodic remediation loops.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Limitations">
      <p>Domains are descriptive, not generative: knowing "Risk" is a domain does not produce a risk register; it points you at the methodology. "Governance replaces Integration Management" is not a 1:1 swap; portfolio-level governance was previously implicit and now leaks into PM scope, surprising old PMP holders. "Quality integrated throughout" sounds elegant but hides quality work; agents skip explicit quality plans because the domain is invisible.</p>
      <p>Stakeholder + Communications fusion drops dedicated comms artefacts (comms plan, RACI for messages); teams forget to recreate them. Procurement moved to appendix → agents under-emphasize vendor risk on contractor-heavy projects. Sustainability is named but unmeasured in PMBoK 8 itself; teams need external frameworks (GHG Protocol, B-Corp) to operationalize.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools and Services">
      <p>Key tools for domain auditing and management:</p>
      <list>
        <item>gh — Pull issues / PRs as scope + schedule signal</item>
        <item>jira-cli — Read epics / stories per domain</item>
        <item>linear CLI / API — Stakeholder + scope sync</item>
        <item>monday-cli (community) — Resources + risk boards</item>
        <item>gitleaks / trufflehog — Governance / sec hygiene per domain audit</item>
        <item>notion-sdk (Python/JS) — Pull domain artefacts from a project workspace</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli — Render domain interaction diagrams</item>
      </list>
      <p>SaaS platforms: Jira Premium / Advanced Roadmaps (Scope + Schedule + Resources), ClickUp (Stakeholders + Resources), Smartsheet (Governance forums + Finance dashboards), Monday.com (Risk + Resources boards), Notion / Confluence (Domain charter + status doc), Power BI / Looker / Metabase (Finance + Measurement dashboards), MS Project / Project for the Web (Schedule + Resources baseline), Asana Portfolios (Governance roll-up).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Treat domains as the project's table of contents; every artefact lives under exactly one domain</item>
        <item>Pair each domain with a measurable outcome (e.g. Finance → "CPI ≥ 0.95 at every gate"), not just an activity</item>
        <item>Run the seven-domain audit before every steering committee — drives the status pack automatically</item>
        <item>When a process feels homeless, default to Governance; do not invent a new domain</item>
        <item>Map domain gaps to risks: a missing artefact = a risk in the Risk domain</item>
        <item>For PMBoK 7 → 8 transitions, keep a translation table next to the audit so old PMs do not wave the integration-management flag</item>
        <item>Track domain coverage as a project KPI (e.g. "7/7 green" by gate 2)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs blur Stakeholders + Communications back into separate domains because PMBoK 6 is heavily represented in training data; pin the canonical seven in the system prompt</item>
        <item>Agents will silently rename Governance to "Integration Management"; reject any output containing the old name</item>
        <item>"Quality" is integrated, not a domain — agents keep adding an 8th domain. Validate output length == 7</item>
        <item>Sustainability creeps into Stakeholders or Risk inconsistently; either keep it under Governance or as an explicit sub-criterion in every domain — pick one and lock it</item>
        <item>Agents underweight Procurement on vendor-heavy projects because PMBoK 8 demoted it; force a vendor-risk question into the audit</item>
        <item>Domain status colors drift over time (every artefact "green") — calibrate by sampling 1 in 5 domains for human review</item>
        <item>Output ordering matters: list domains in fixed sequence so diffs across runs are stable</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/domain-audit.py" purpose="Python: walk seven domains against a project root, emit JSON gap matrix"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="project-integration"/>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/learning/library/pmbok-guide-7th-edition-performance-domains"/>
      <link href="https://www.praxisframework.org/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
