<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Active Listening Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the RASA practice. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="rasa-full-cycle" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every substantive conversation MUST cover all four RASA steps in order: Receive (full attention, no phone), Appreciate (verbal acknowledgment), Summarize (paraphrase back), Ask (one open follow-up).</statement>
      <rationale source="Center for Creative Leadership — RASA Framework">Skipping Summarize is the most common failure; without paraphrasing, the speaker cannot confirm understanding and will either repeat or withhold detail.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="open-question-discipline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Questions in the generated script MUST open with What, How, or Tell-me-about. Openers Is, Do, Did, Are, Were, Will, Would are forbidden because they produce yes/no answers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — interview audits Q1 2026">Closed questions cap exploration; open questions give the speaker control of scope and surface information the interviewer did not know to ask about.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="level-5-target" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For high-stakes conversations the script MUST include at least one explicit reflective-listening prompt of the form "It sounds like you're [FEELING] because [CONTENT]." targeting Level 5 empathic listening.</statement>
      <rationale source="Stephen R. Covey — 7 Habits of Highly Effective People">Levels 1-4 process words; Level 5 processes meaning and feeling. Decision-makers under stress communicate 40-60% of their actual concern through emotional register, not explicit words.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="reflective-formula" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reflective statements MUST use the formula "It sounds like you're [FEELING] because [CONTENT]." Pre-generated reflections without observed signal context are forbidden — the script must mark them as response-only, not opener.</statement>
      <rationale source="MindTools Active Listening">Naming the feeling signals Level 5 attention; the speaker either confirms (and feels understood) or corrects (providing higher-quality signal). Out-of-context reflection lands as condescending.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="mirror-only-no-interpretation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mirroring prompts MUST repeat the last 1-3 words of the speaker as a question and MUST NOT add interpretation. Generated examples must not embed assumptions about why the speaker said it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Chris Voss — Never Split the Difference">Mirroring is the lowest-friction technique with the highest elaboration rate. Adding interpretation converts it into a leading question and kills the elaboration effect.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="silence-3-to-5s" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The script MUST include an explicit "pause 3-5 seconds after speaker finishes" cue before any follow-up. For async/text contexts the substitute MUST be a "Is there anything you'd like to add?" prompt because text cannot encode silence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — coaching transcripts review">People add the most important information after the first pause. Immediate response signals waiting-to-speak rather than listening. In text the explicit second-pass prompt closes the same gap.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
