<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-paid-acquisition">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>ppc-manager</domain>
    <summary>Test-and-scale framework for paid ads: calculate LTV:CAC ratio, start with one channel, kill underperformers by CTR and CPA rules, scale winners gradually with human checkpoints.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>paid-acquisition</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>ltv-cac</tag>
      <tag>cpa-optimization</tag>
      <tag>test-and-scale</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Paid Acquisition: Unit Economics and Test-and-Scale Framework</title>

    <summary>A test-and-scale framework for profitable paid advertising: calculate LTV:CAC before spending, start with one channel, run 3-5 audience and creative variations with $20-50 per ad before judging, kill ads with CTR below 0.5% after 1,000 impressions, and scale only when CPA stays below target for 3+ consecutive days.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Most paid acquisition failures share the same root causes: spending before knowing unit economics, testing too few variations, and scaling before statistical confidence. The LTV:CAC ratio (minimum 3:1) is the decision gate that prevents burning budget on campaigns that can never be profitable.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Launching the first paid acquisition campaign for a product</item>
        <item>Choosing which ad platform to start on (Google, Meta, LinkedIn, TikTok)</item>
        <item>Building a weekly optimization routine for an active campaign</item>
        <item>Diagnosing why an existing campaign is unprofitable</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Product does not yet have measurable LTV — fix pricing/retention first</item>
        <item>No conversion tracking installed — set up pixels and events before spending</item>
        <item>Organic channels not yet tested — paid amplifies a working message; it does not create one</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="unit-economics">
      <title>Paid Acquisition Unit Economics</title>

      <p>LTV, CAC, and target CPA calculation rules — the prerequisite for any paid acquisition spend.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Calculate LTV:CAC ratio before spending any budget. If LTV:CAC is below 3:1, fix product pricing or retention before launching paid acquisition.</statement>
        <rationale>Paid acquisition at an unfavorable LTV:CAC ratio compounds losses. Every dollar spent accelerates cash burn without building a sustainable business.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>SaaS: ARPU $50/mo x 12 months average lifetime = $600 LTV. Target CAC = $600 / 3 = $200. If conversion rate is 3%, max CPA = $200 x 0.03 = $6. Any campaign delivering CPA above $6 is unprofitable.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad">
        <note>B2C app: LTV $10, CAC $8 = 1.25:1 ratio. Scaling this campaign burns cash — each conversion costs 80% of the customer's lifetime value before accounting for product costs.</note>
      </example>

      <title>Metric Formulas</title>
      <list>
        <item>LTV = ARPU x Average customer lifetime (months or years)</item>
        <item>Target CAC = LTV / 3</item>
        <item>Max CPA = Target CAC x Conversion rate</item>
        <item>ROAS = Revenue / Ad Spend (minimum target: 3:1)</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Do not launch paid acquisition until pixel/conversion tracking is installed and conversion events are firing correctly.</statement>
        <rationale>Without tracking, you cannot measure CPA or ROAS, making optimization impossible and budget decisions arbitrary.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="channel-selection-and-testing">
      <title>Channel Selection, Testing Framework, and Creative</title>

      <p>Platform comparison by use case and budget, testing structure, ad copy formulas, and kill/scale decision rules.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Start with ONE channel. Master it before adding more. Spreading budget across multiple channels at low spend prevents any single channel from generating enough data to optimize.</statement>
        <rationale>Each platform has a learning phase requiring minimum conversion volume. Split budgets delay learning and produce inconclusive data on all channels simultaneously.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Google Ads: high intent (search), $500/mo minimum — best for solution-aware buyers</item>
        <item>Meta Ads: B2C, broad demographic targeting, $500/mo minimum — best for awareness to conversion</item>
        <item>LinkedIn Ads: B2B by job title and company size, $1000/mo minimum — best for enterprise leads</item>
        <item>TikTok Ads: young demographic, viral content, $500/mo minimum — high creative demand</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Give each ad a minimum of $20-50 spend and 1,000 impressions before judging performance. Killing ads earlier produces random results.</statement>
        <rationale>Ad delivery needs a learning period. Decisions made on fewer than 1,000 impressions have 15-30% random variance in CTR.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Start with 3-5 audiences per campaign</item>
        <item>Run 3-5 ad variations per audience</item>
        <item>Kill: CTR below 0.5% after 1,000 impressions</item>
        <item>Kill: CPA above 2x target after $50 spend</item>
        <item>Kill: zero conversions after 5x expected CPA spend</item>
        <item>Scale: CPA below target for 3+ consecutive days with consistent volume</item>
      </list>

      <title>Ad Copy Formulas</title>
      <list>
        <item>PAS: "Tired of [problem]? [Amplify pain]. [Product] solves this by [benefit]."</item>
        <item>Before/After: "Before [Product]: [pain state]. After: [desired state]."</item>
        <item>Social Proof: "Join [N]+ [audience] who [benefit]."</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use real product screenshots over stock photos. Ads with faces outperform faceless creative on Meta by 15-30% on average CTR.</statement>
        <rationale>Authenticity signals reduce ad skepticism. Stock imagery is pattern-matched as advertising and ignored faster.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="tracking-and-optimization">
      <title>UTM Structure, Conversion Events, and Weekly Optimization Routine</title>

      <p>UTM parameter naming convention, the 5 essential conversion events to track, and the weekly optimization cadence for managing active campaigns.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Use consistent UTM parameters on every paid link. Inconsistent UTM naming makes attribution analysis unreliable across campaigns.</statement>
        <rationale>When utm_source values vary (meta vs Meta vs facebook), GA4 aggregates them as separate sources and understates channel performance.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>?utm_source=meta&amp;utm_medium=paid&amp;utm_campaign=summer-sale-2026&amp;utm_content=video-v1. Use lowercase, hyphens not underscores, consistent source names per channel.</note>
      </example>

      <title>Essential Conversion Events</title>
      <list>
        <item>1. Page View — baseline traffic measurement</item>
        <item>2. Lead — signup or form submission</item>
        <item>3. Trial Start — product trial initiated</item>
        <item>4. Purchase — transaction completed</item>
        <item>5. Subscription — recurring revenue started</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Implement server-side Conversion API in addition to pixel tracking. Pixel data degrades with ad blockers and iOS privacy changes; server-side fills the gap.</statement>
        <rationale>Without server-side tracking, Meta and Google can miss 20-40% of conversions, causing the algorithm to optimize on incomplete signals.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <title>Weekly Optimization Routine</title>
      <list>
        <item>Monday: review last week's CPA, ROAS, CTR by campaign and ad set</item>
        <item>Tuesday: pause underperformers, increase budget on winners by 20-30%</item>
        <item>Wednesday: create new ad variations based on winning angles</item>
        <item>Thursday: test new audience segments</item>
        <item>Friday: analyze and document learnings; plan next week</item>
      </list>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Increasing campaign budget by more than 30% in a single adjustment.</description>
        <reason>Large budget increases (50%+) trigger the platform learning phase, resetting algorithm optimization and causing temporary CPA spikes.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <title>Key Metrics</title>
      <list>
        <item>CTR (Clicks / Impressions): target 1%+ for healthy ad relevance</item>
        <item>CPC (Cost / Clicks): varies by platform and industry</item>
        <item>CVR (Conversions / Clicks): target 2-5%</item>
        <item>CPA (Cost / Conversions): must be below LTV/3</item>
        <item>ROAS (Revenue / Ad Spend): target 3:1 minimum</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/campaign-plan.md" purpose="Campaign planning template: goals, audience, creative, tracking, success criteria"/>
      <template path="templates/weekly-ads-report.md" purpose="Weekly ads report: spend, conversions, CPA, ROAS, learnings, next actions"/>
    </templates>

    <section name="limitations-and-gotchas">
      <title>Where This Fails and AI-Agent Gotchas</title>

      <p>Understanding the limitations of this framework is critical for avoiding costly mistakes.</p>

      <title>Methodology Limitations</title>
      <list>
        <item>The methodology assumes platform conversion data is correct; iOS ATT, ad-blockers, and walled-garden self-reporting silently distort it.</item>
        <item>LTV:CAC of 3:1 is a heuristic, not a law — subscription churn, refunds, fraud can flip a "winner" in month 3.</item>
        <item>"Kill after 1000 impressions" works for high-intent search, fails for upper-funnel video where 10k impressions is the minimum signal.</item>
        <item>Weekly cadence is too slow for fast-moving e-com promotions (Black Friday) and too fast for B2B with 90-day sales cycles.</item>
        <item>Cross-channel attribution is hand-waved here — pair with ads-attribution-models for a defensible rollup.</item>
        <item>Budget benchmarks ($500/mo Meta minimum) are channel-defaults; specific verticals (legal, finance) need 5-10x that.</item>
      </list>

      <title>AI-Agent Gotchas</title>
      <list>
        <item>LLMs love to "optimize" winning ads by tweaking copy mid-flight, killing performance. Lock winners for ≥7 days.</item>
        <item>"Conversions" reported by platforms double-count; agents that sum across platforms report inflated revenue. Use GA4 / warehouse total.</item>
        <item>Models often skip the LTV gate if the user gives them a budget directly. Hard-code the gate as a precondition.</item>
        <item>Human-in-loop checkpoints: enabling a campaign, increasing daily budget by >25%, expanding to a new channel, opening a new geo.</item>
        <item>Time-based reasoning is weak: agents will compare a 3-day-old campaign to a 90-day baseline. Force "min-data" assertions before judging.</item>
        <item>Creative tone drift: agent-written ad copy on its 5th iteration becomes generic. Reset the creative agent with fresh brand-voice context.</item>
        <item>Currency / FX: multi-region accounts mix USD/EUR/GBP cost rows; agents must normalize before computing CPA.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://brianbalfour.com/quick-takes/ltv-cac"/>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/programs/growth-series"/>
      <link href="https://www.wordstream.com/blog/ws/2023/02/20/ppc-benchmarks"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift"/>
      <link href="https://andrewchen.com"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
