<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="threads-growth">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>smm-manager</domain>
    <summary>Conversation-first growth for Threads: post 5+ punchy posts daily, reply to large accounts, adapt from Twitter/Instagram. No links; suppress promotional content. No write API; all posting manual.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>threads</tag>
      <tag>conversation</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>social-media</tag>
      <tag>meta</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Threads Growth</title>

    <summary>A conversation-first growth system for Threads: post 5+ short punchy posts per day, reply thoughtfully to large accounts to drive discovery, and adapt content from Instagram or Twitter to Threads' casual tone. No links in posts — Threads suppresses promotional content. No official third-party posting API as of 2026; all posting is manual.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Threads rewards authenticity signals — genuine disagreement, admitted uncertainty, and follow-up questions outperform polished takes. One early, thoughtful reply on a 100K-follower post outperforms five standalone posts for discovery.</p>
      <p>The platform is tied to Instagram: cross-promoting from Instagram Stories ("join the conversation on Threads") is the fastest follower import mechanism, and any Instagram account restriction affects Threads access.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Generating daily post batches (20-30 drafts) across hot takes, this-or-that, fill-in-blank, experience stories, and predictions</item>
        <item>Drafting reply templates for a specific niche (to be edited and sent by a human)</item>
        <item>Planning a cross-platform content flow from Instagram or Twitter to Threads</item>
        <item>Repurposing Twitter/X thread content into Threads-native conversational format</item>
        <item>Writing a Month 2-3 optimization plan: which post types to double down on</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Automated posting or replying — no official API for write access; all posting is manual</item>
        <item>Engagement pod coordination — Threads community strongly penalizes inauthentic engagement</item>
        <item>Generating long-form content — Threads punishes long posts; max 300 characters is target</item>
        <item>Accounts without an Instagram presence — Threads account depends on Instagram; fix that first</item>
        <item>Generating posts that mimic trends without knowing current platform culture</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="reply-first-growth">
      <rule>
        <statement>Reply to large accounts first — one early, thoughtful reply on a 100K-follower post outperforms five standalone posts for discovery.</statement>
        <rationale>Threads surfaces engaged replies to the original post's audience. Early replies get the most exposure; late replies are buried.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use the [Agree/Disagree] + [Add perspective] + [Question] reply formula. Never write "Great point!" as a reply.</statement>
        <rationale>Generic agreement adds no value and signals low-quality engagement. Questions invite the original poster to respond, creating a visible conversation thread.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Reply to a post about shipping fast: "This is so true. I found the same thing when building [X] — the constraint of a hard deadline produced better decisions than open-ended sprints. What made you realize this?"</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Reply: "Great point! So insightful. Totally agree." — No perspective added, no question, no reason for the original poster or their audience to engage further.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="conversation-starter-post-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Post 5+ short punchy posts per day across these types: hot takes, this-or-that, fill-in-blank, experience prompts, and predictions.</statement>
        <rationale>Threads rewards high volume of conversational posts. Each post type generates a different engagement pattern — questions drive replies, hot takes drive quote posts.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Hot take: "Unpopular opinion: [bold statement]. Change my mind."</item>
        <item>This or that: "[A] or [B]?" (e.g., "Notion or Obsidian?")</item>
        <item>Fill in blank: "The best [X] is ___"</item>
        <item>Experience: "Raise your hand if you've ever [relatable struggle]"</item>
        <item>Prediction: "In [year], [specific prediction about your niche]"</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not include links in Threads posts. Threads does not render links and promotional posts are heavily suppressed.</statement>
        <rationale>Threads's algorithm suppresses posts that look promotional or are designed to drive traffic off-platform. Use the bio link for all external CTAs.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="cross-platform-synergy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cross-promote from Instagram Stories by sharing a specific Threads post with "join the conversation on Threads" — this is the fastest follower import mechanism.</statement>
        <rationale>Instagram followers already trust the account. Directing them to Threads via Stories converts at a much higher rate than organic Threads discovery.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When adapting Twitter/X content for Threads: shorten to 1-3 posts, remove thread numbering, make it conversational, add a genuine question at the end, remove promotional language.</statement>
        <rationale>Twitter content is declarative and formal. Threads culture rewards rough edges, admitted uncertainty, and genuine curiosity. Verbatim cross-posts underperform.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="metrics-benchmarks">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track follower growth rate (target 5-10% weekly), replies per post, and profile visits per day as primary Threads KPIs.</statement>
        <rationale>Threads provides almost no exportable analytics. Manual tracking in a spreadsheet is required. These three metrics are observable without API access.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Followers: starting = building, 100+/week = growing, 500+/week = established</item>
        <item>Post views: 100 = starting, 1K = growing, 10K+ = established</item>
        <item>Replies per post: 2-5 = starting, 10-20 = growing, 50+ = established</item>
        <item>Profile visits: 10/day = starting, 50/day = growing, 200+/day = established</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Just cross-posting content from Twitter without adaptation.</description>
        <reason>Twitter content is declarative and polished. Threads culture rewards casual, curious, rough-edged posts. Verbatim cross-posts feel out of place and underperform.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Being too promotional — product pitches in posts.</description>
        <reason>Threads's algorithm heavily penalizes promotional content. The platform norms are 95% value, 5% promo. Any promotional feel reduces distribution.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Posting once a day instead of 5+ posts daily.</description>
        <reason>Threads requires higher post volume than LinkedIn or Twitter because the feed is highly active and content decays quickly. One daily post is not enough for the algorithm.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using a formal or corporate tone.</description>
        <reason>Threads culture is conversational and casual. Corporate language signals inauthenticity and the audience does not engage.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-limitations-on-threads">
      <rule>
        <statement>Batch-generate 35+ post drafts per week but post only what feels genuinely on-voice. Volume generation is useful; volume posting without editing is harmful.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent output defaults to polished and authoritative. Threads requires rough edges and genuine curiosity. Always rewrite agent output before posting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>As of 2026, Threads has no official write API. All posting must be done manually by a human. Agent output is drafts only.</statement>
        <rationale>Meta's Threads API (2024) is read-only. Any tool claiming to post to Threads on your behalf is violating ToS and risks account suspension.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Use the agent as a content ideation and adaptation engine, not an execution tool. Given the week's content pillars and ICP, produce 20-30 post draft options across all conversation-starter types. The human selects, edits for personal voice, and posts manually. For cross-platform adaptation, feed the agent the original Twitter or Instagram caption and ask it to rewrite in Threads tone (conversational, lower-stakes, question-ending). No agent subagents are needed for posting; all execution is human.</p>
      <p><term name="Recommended subagents">faion-sdd-executor-agent — for planning and tracking the Month 2-3 Threads growth SDD tasks</term></p>
    </section>

    <section name="prompt-pattern">
      <p>Content generation prompt:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are a Threads content strategist for <niche>. ICP: <icp>. Tone: casual, direct, curiosity-driven.

Generate 20 Threads post drafts. Distribute across:
- 5 hot takes ("Unpopular opinion: ...")
- 5 this-or-that questions
- 5 fill-in-the-blank prompts
- 3 personal experience stories (2-3 sentences)
- 2 predictions for <year>

Each post: max 300 characters, no hashtags, end with an implicit or explicit invitation to respond.
      ]]></code>

      <p>Adaptation prompt:</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Adapt this Twitter/X thread for Threads:
<twitter_thread>

Rules:
- Shorten to 1-3 posts max
- Remove thread numbering
- Make it conversational, not declarative
- Add a genuine question at the end
- Remove any promotional language
      ]]></code>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p><term name="CLI tools">Meta Graph API (Threads) — Read public Threads posts and basic profile data (https://developers.facebook.com/docs/threads); requests (Python) — Call Threads API endpoints (pip install requests); Buffer — Schedule Threads posts (added Threads support 2024) (https://buffer.com/threads)</term></p>

      <p><term name="Services">Threads (Meta, SaaS, partial agent-friendly) — Official API is limited; write access via Meta partnership only; Buffer (SaaS, agent-friendly API) — Added Threads scheduling in 2024; basic analytics; Metricool (SaaS, agent-friendly API) — Threads analytics + scheduling where API permits; Later (SaaS, partial) — Limited Threads support; check current API status; Meta Business Suite (SaaS, agent-friendly Graph API) — Threads insights at account level</term></p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Post volume on Threads (5+ posts/day) is higher than any other text platform; batch-generate 35+ posts per week but only post what feels genuinely on-voice</item>
        <item>Replies to large accounts drive disproportionate discovery — one early, thoughtful reply on a 100K-follower post outperforms 5 standalone posts</item>
        <item>Threads rewards authenticity signals: genuine disagreement, admitted uncertainty, and follow-up questions outperform polished takes</item>
        <item>Do not include links in posts — Threads does not render links and promotional posts are heavily suppressed</item>
        <item>Cross-promote from Instagram Stories by sharing a specific Threads post with "join the conversation on Threads" — this is the fastest follower import mechanism</item>
        <item>Build reply conversations by replying to your own posts with follow-up thoughts; algorithmic signals treat thread-style self-replies as active conversations</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p><term name="Tone overfitting">Agent defaults to polished, authoritative voice; Threads culture rewards rough edges and genuine curiosity — always rewrite agent output before posting</term></p>
      <p><term name="No posting API">Agent cannot schedule or post to Threads autonomously; all output is drafts for human posting</term></p>
      <p><term name="Analytics gap">Threads provides almost no exportable analytics data; growth measurement requires manual tracking in a spreadsheet</term></p>
      <p><term name="Platform immaturity">Threads features and algorithms were still evolving rapidly as of early 2026; agent knowledge of "best practices" should be treated as provisional</term></p>
      <p><term name="Instagram account dependency">Threads account is tied to Instagram; any Instagram account issue (ban, restriction) affects Threads access — do not treat them as independent</term></p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/prompt-post-batch.txt" purpose="Agent prompt: 20 Threads post drafts across all conversation-starter types"/>
      <template path="templates/adapt-twitter-thread.py" purpose="Strip tweet numbering, split into ≤3 Threads-native posts, append question"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://threads.net/"/>
      <link href="https://about.instagram.com/blog/announcements/threads"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
