<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Messaging House Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Messaging House Template application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-one-root-line" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>House MUST have exactly one root value statement at the top. Multiple root lines are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Multiple roots collapse the structure into a positioning grab-bag; the house exists to enforce one.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-exactly-three-pillars" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>House MUST have exactly 3 pillars supporting the root line. 2 or 5 pillars are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Three is the documented cognitive floor for memorability; the closed constraint forces prioritisation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-evidence-per-proof-point" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each pillar MUST carry 2-4 proof points; every proof point MUST cite evidence (data / quote / asset). Empty proof points are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Un-evidenced proof points are marketing wishlist; downstream copy collapses without backing.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-per-channel-variants" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each pillar MUST produce per-channel variants (X tweet, LinkedIn post, email subject, ad copy, landing-page hero). Pillars without variants are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Without variants the house stays abstract; concrete variants are what channel teams actually consume.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>House MUST have a single named owner accountable for updates. Group-owned houses are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Group-owned artefacts decay; named ownership creates an update ritual.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-27 chunk-03 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
