<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="backup-kubernetes-velero Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for backup-kubernetes-velero as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent emits `--default-volumes-to-restic` or `--use-restic` for Velero v1.15+ installations.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Restic path is deprecated in Velero v1.15. Use --use-node-agent and --default-volumes-to-fs-backup with Kopia. Anchor the prompt to the exact installed Velero version to avoid this.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates Velero Schedule with cron expression "0 2 * * *" without noting the timezone, causing the schedule to run at 2 AM UTC regardless of the team's local time — potentially during peak traffic hours for non-UTC teams.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Velero schedules run in UTC by default. "0 2 * * *" stomps on traffic peaks for teams in UTC+3 to UTC+8 time zones. Add a comment documenting the UTC schedule and its local equivalent for the ops team.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent generates Velero Backup that includes kube-system, velero, and other platform namespaces in the includedNamespaces wildcard without explicitly excluding them.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Backing up kube-system and velero namespaces adds noise, inflates backup size, and can cause restore conflicts. Always exclude them with excludedNamespaces in wildcard schedules.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent treats Velero CSI snapshot as equivalent to an off-cluster backup — "snapshot = backup".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CSI snapshots live on the same storage system. If the storage system fails (cloud provider outage, cluster deletion), all snapshots go with it. Always configure a BackupStorageLocation in a separate account/region that copies backup data off the cluster's storage.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
