<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Google Ads Reporting and Optimization Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules grounding the ads-google-reporting methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="conversion-not-vanity" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Optimize on conversion-tied metrics (CPA, ROAS, conversion count). Clicks, impressions, CTR are diagnostic — never targets.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: ads-google-reporting common-mistakes">More clicks at higher CPA destroys margin; optimizing on vanity metrics is the dominant cause of budget waste.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="weekly-search-terms" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The Search Terms report is reviewed weekly cost-descending; every term over $5 is classified keep / negate / promote.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: ads-google-reporting search-terms-analysis">Irrelevant searches accumulate weekly; Search Terms is the earliest detector of waste.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-daily-churn" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Major structural changes (bids ±25%, ad-group restructure, new bidding strategy) MUST be limited to monthly cadence with ≥2 weeks of stable data after each change.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: ads-google-reporting common-mistakes">Google's bidding models need stable signal; daily churn resets the learning phase.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="segment-before-judging" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before judging a campaign healthy/unhealthy, segment by device, network, location, audience, time. Aggregate averages MUST NOT be used in isolation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: ads-google-reporting segment-analysis">Campaign-level averages hide high- and low-performing slices.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="quality-score-as-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keywords with Quality Score under 5 are flagged for ad-group split, ad copy rewrite, or landing-page realignment before any bid change.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source: ads-google-reporting key-metrics">Low QS multiplies effective CPC; fixing QS is cheaper than out-bidding the competition.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
