<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="competitive-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>A structured method for examining 3-5 direct competitors, 2-3 indirect, and 1-2 aspirational examples against consistent evaluation criteria (features, user flows, UI patterns, IA, error handling, mobile experience). Output is a feature comparison matrix, per-competitor profiles, and recommendations bucketed into: must-have (table stakes), parity (match), and differentiation (opportunity). Analysis requires actually using the products through key user flows, not just looking at screenshots.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>competitive-analysis</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>ux-design</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Competitive Analysis</title>

    <summary>A structured method for examining 3-5 direct competitors, 2-3 indirect, and 1-2 aspirational examples against consistent evaluation criteria (features, user flows, UI patterns, IA, error handling, mobile experience). Output is a feature comparison matrix, per-competitor profiles, and recommendations bucketed into: must-have (table stakes), parity (match), and differentiation (opportunity). Analysis requires actually using the products through key user flows, not just looking at screenshots.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Designing without competitive context means reinventing existing solutions, missing user expectations set by other products, and failing to see differentiation opportunities. Competitors' UX patterns represent accumulated product decisions — understanding them reveals what users now expect as baseline behavior, what problems are unsolved across the market, and what mistakes to avoid.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before a new feature spec is written — understand what exists before designing something that already exists</item>
        <item>Quarterly product reviews — market and competitor UI patterns shift faster than annual reviews capture</item>
        <item>When a stakeholder asks "what do others do?" — answer with evidence, not opinion</item>
        <item>Before a positioning or pricing decision — competitor UX quality is part of the market landscape</item>
        <item>When user research reveals users compare your product to specific competitors — study those products</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>As a substitute for user research — tells you what others built, not what users actually need</item>
        <item>When all target competitors are behind closed paywalls inaccessible for legal analysis</item>
        <item>For internal tooling with no external market — no competitors means no competitive analysis</item>
        <item>When the product intentionally defies conventions — conventional analysis anchors you to patterns you're breaking</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="competitor-taxonomy">
      <rule>
        <statement>Analyze a minimum of 3-5 direct competitors, 2-3 indirect competitors, and 1-2 aspirational examples outside the direct category. Do not limit analysis to direct competitors only.</statement>
        <rationale>Direct competitors reveal table stakes and parity requirements. Indirect competitors show alternative approaches to the same user problem. Aspirational examples outside the category (e.g., studying Airbnb's onboarding for a B2B SaaS) produce the most differentiated ideas.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Direct: same problem, same target user (Uber vs Lyft)</item>
        <item>Indirect: same problem, different approach (Uber vs public transit apps)</item>
        <item>Partial: overlapping features (Google Maps vs Waze)</item>
        <item>Aspirational: best-in-class for a specific pattern, not a direct competitor</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="six-step-process">
      <rule>
        <statement>Step 1: Define scope. Identify the specific product or feature being analyzed, which competitors to include and why, which dimensions matter most, and how findings will be used.</statement>
        <rationale>Undefined scope produces unfocused analysis. "Analyze the market" yields a report too broad to act on. "Analyze checkout flow across 5 direct competitors" yields actionable findings for a specific design decision.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 2: Create evaluation criteria before gathering data. Criteria must be based on research questions, not what is easy to observe. Rate each criterion consistently using a fixed scale (Excellent/Good/Fair/Poor) before writing narrative.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc criteria selection introduces confirmation bias — you find evidence for what you already believe. Consistent ratings prevent rationalization: if you score before writing narrative, the data leads the conclusion, not the conclusion the data.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 3: Gather data by actually using each product. Create accounts, complete full user flows, try edge cases, contact support, test on mobile. Do not rely on screenshots of marketing pages.</statement>
        <rationale>Marketing pages show the product's best-case presentation. Real usage reveals friction, error handling quality, mobile experience, and edge-case behavior — the factors that differentiate good UX from poor UX.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 4: Document with screenshots and annotations immediately during research. Competitor UIs change; documentation is the historical record.</statement>
        <rationale>Memory of observed UIs decays and blurs. Annotated screenshots capture exact wording, layout, interaction patterns, and the date of observation. Without them, analysis findings cannot be reproduced or compared to later versions.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 5: Analyze patterns across competitors to find: baseline (what all do), best practices (what top performers do), common problems (what to avoid), and gaps (what none do).</statement>
        <rationale>Pattern analysis across multiple products reveals market consensus vs differentiation opportunities. A feature present in all competitors is table stakes; a feature no competitor does well is an opportunity.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Step 6: Generate insights as actionable recommendations in three buckets: "We should..." (adopt), "We could differentiate by..." (opportunity), and "We should avoid..." (competitor failures).</statement>
        <rationale>Observations without recommendations are notes, not insights. The three-bucket structure maps directly to roadmap prioritization: must-have, opportunity, and anti-patterns.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="analysis-dimensions">
      <list>
        <item>Features: what can users do?</item>
        <item>User flows: how do users accomplish key goals? Count steps, measure time to value</item>
        <item>UI patterns: navigation, forms, error handling, empty states</item>
        <item>Information architecture: how is content organized?</item>
        <item>Content and tone: messaging strategy, voice</item>
        <item>Accessibility: WCAG compliance level, screen reader behavior</item>
        <item>Mobile experience: mobile-first or responsive-degraded?</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="priority-buckets-and-examples">
      <rule>
        <statement>Categorize all competitive findings into three priority buckets: Must Have (table stakes — competitors all have it), Should Have (parity — match the best), and Could Differentiate (opportunity — nobody does it well).</statement>
        <rationale>These three buckets map directly to roadmap prioritization. Table stakes go to P0; parity goes to the next cycle; differentiation opportunities go to experimentation or innovation tracks. Avoid mixing all findings in a flat list — stakeholders cannot prioritize a flat list.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good">
        <note>E-commerce checkout analysis — table stakes finding</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Finding: All 5 direct competitors offer guest checkout.
Insight: Guest checkout is table stakes.
         Not having it is a competitive disadvantage.
Action:  Must have → add to P0 backlog.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <note>E-commerce checkout analysis — differentiation opportunity</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Finding: Only 1 of 5 competitors shows estimated delivery
         on the product page. Others show it only at checkout.
Insight: Opportunity to differentiate by showing delivery
         estimate earlier in the purchase funnel.
Action:  Could differentiate → test in next sprint.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good">
        <note>SaaS onboarding analysis — data-driven priority finding</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Competitor | Onboarding Steps | Time to Value | App Store Rating
A          | 8 steps          | 15 min        | 3.8
B          | 3 steps          | 2 min         | 4.7
C          | 5 steps          | 8 min         | 4.2

Insight: Competitor B's minimal onboarding correlates with
         highest ratings. Reducing our 7-step flow is a priority.
        ]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Only analyzing direct competitors — missing inspiration from adjacent industries</description>
        <reason>Cross-industry patterns produce the most differentiated ideas. A fintech product studying Airbnb's trust signals or Duolingo's onboarding may find patterns no direct competitor has tried.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Copying competitor features without understanding why they made that design decision</description>
        <reason>A competitor's feature may exist due to legacy technical constraints, regulatory requirements, or past A/B test results that no longer apply. Copying without context means inheriting their tradeoffs.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>One-time analysis treated as permanent truth</description>
        <reason>Competitor products update continuously. An analysis from 6 months ago may reflect a product that no longer exists. Schedule quarterly lightweight checks and annual deep analyses.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating industry consensus as validated best practice</description>
        <reason>If all competitors share a bad pattern, the analysis surfaces a shared bad practice, not a best practice. App store reviews and user research are needed to determine whether the consensus pattern actually works for users.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/analysis-plan.md" purpose="Analysis plan: objective, competitor list (type + rationale), criteria, flows to analyze, deliverables"/>
      <template path="templates/comparison-matrix.md" purpose="Feature comparison matrix with legend (Yes/No/Partial + ratings)"/>
      <template path="templates/competitor-profile.md" purpose="Per-competitor profile: overview, target users, key screens, flows, friction points, strengths/weaknesses, opportunities"/>
      <template path="templates/summary-report.md" purpose="Executive summary report: key findings, industry standards, best practices, opportunities, recommendations (must/should/could/avoid)"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/competitive-usability-evaluations/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/how-to-do-a-competitive-analysis-in-ux-design"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2018/04/competitive-analysis-ux-design/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
