<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cost Estimation Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding Cost Estimation. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="wbs-decomposition" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cost estimate MUST decompose to WBS leaves with named success criteria. Estimating at higher levels is forbidden for projects ≥25k.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Estimating">Top-down estimates hide variance and resist defence. Bottom-up forces discovery of hidden work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="three-point-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each WBS leaf MUST carry three-point estimates (optimistic, most-likely, pessimistic) feeding a PERT mean.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Quantitative Estimation">Single-point estimates produce false precision; PERT exposes the variance the project actually carries.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="contingency-risk-driven" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Contingency reserve MUST be sized from the risk register, not as a flat 10/15/20% padding. Each contingency line ties to a named risk.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Risk Management">Flat contingency is unhedged; risk-driven contingency is defensible to buyer scrutiny.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="management-reserve-separate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Management reserve (for unknown-unknowns) MUST be tracked SEPARATELY from contingency. It is approved by sponsor, not consumed by PM.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Reserve Management">Comingling reserves lets PMs spend management reserve on planned risks, leaving no buffer for genuine unknowns.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="historical-data-cited" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each three-point estimate MUST cite ≥1 historical reference (similar engagement, leaf, or industry benchmark).</statement>
      <rationale source="Hubbard, How to Measure Anything (2014)">Uncited estimates are vibes. Citations make calibration possible and resist optimism bias.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for Cost Estimation fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying Cost Estimation outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
