<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-personalization" title="Personalization, Exit Intent, and Retargeting">
  <summary>Segment-based personalization lifts (15-40%), exit-intent recovery patterns, and retargeting channel timing and conversion benchmarks.</summary>

  <section title="Personalization by Segment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Personalize messaging by segment before running A/B tests on a single message — segment lift (15-40%) typically exceeds copy optimization lift (5-15%).</statement>
      <rationale>A generic message optimized for the average user underperforms a segment-specific message for each audience.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Traffic source: match ad message to landing page — lift 15-30%</item>
      <item>Geographic: local language, currency, examples — lift 10-20%</item>
      <item>Device: mobile-optimized vs desktop layout — lift 10-25%</item>
      <item>Returning users: skip intro, show new features — lift 20-40%</item>
      <item>User intent: different CTAs per goal — lift 15-35%</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/ice-scoring-worksheet.md">Worksheet for prioritizing personalization hypotheses by expected lift</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Exit Intent">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger exit intent only when user has not already converted and has not dismissed the overlay in this session.</statement>
      <rationale>Showing exit intent to converted users or repeat dismissers is noise that damages trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Realistic recovery rate: 5-15% of abandoning users. Offer must have clear value (discount, free trial, consultation).</p>
    <reference path="templates/exit-intent-config.js">Exit intent configuration template with exclusion and tracking hooks</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Retargeting Channels">
    <list>
      <item>Email immediate (within 24h): remind of value, no hard sell — recovery 5-10%</item>
      <item>Email 24-48h: social proof + small incentive — recovery 3-8%</item>
      <item>Ad retargeting 1-7 days: social proof creative + offer — recovery 2-5%</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/retargeting-email-sequence.md">3-email retargeting sequence with timing, goals, and metric targets</reference>

    <example type="good">
      <note>Stripe-style sequence: Hour 0 — "Questions about Stripe?" (15% open, 3% conversion); Day 1 — case study (20% open, 5% conversion); Day 3 — "Start in 10 minutes" + $500 credit (18% open, 8% conversion). Overall 12% recovery rate.</note>
    </example>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Sending identical messaging to all retargeting segments regardless of where they dropped off.</description>
      <reason>A cart abandoner needs a different message than a pricing-page abandoner. Irrelevant retargeting increases unsubscribe rate and wastes ad budget.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
