<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Security as Code (Policy as Code) Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Security as Code (Policy as Code) methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-pr-gate-on-cve" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PRs MUST be blocked on critical-severity CVEs in dependencies (SCA) and container images. Block threshold is severity &gt;= 7.0 (CVSS v3) with a known fix.</statement>
      <rationale source="OWASP DevSecOps Guideline; SLSA Level 2">Catching vulns at PR-time costs minutes; catching at runtime costs hours-to-days. Threshold avoids alert fatigue from low-severity findings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-no-plain-policy-violations-merged" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Admission-controller policies (Kyverno / OPA Gatekeeper) MUST run in enforce mode for new namespaces by default. Exception requires a documented waiver with an expiry date.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kyverno production patterns">Audit-only policies provide false comfort; teams ignore violations they never see. Waivers with expiry force re-evaluation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-image-signed-and-verified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All production images MUST be signed at build (cosign) and verified at admission (cosign verify or Sigstore policy controller). Unsigned images are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="SLSA Build L3; Sigstore docs">Image signing closes the supply-chain gap between build and run; signature verification prevents typosquat / hijacked-registry attacks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-sast-on-every-pr" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every PR runs SAST (Semgrep / CodeQL) + secrets scan (gitleaks / trufflehog). Findings of severity &gt;= high block the PR.</statement>
      <rationale source="OWASP SAMM v2">SAST + secret scans catch low-hanging fruit (SQL injection, hardcoded keys) before they reach review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-runtime-policy-audit-log" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Admission-controller and runtime-policy enforcement MUST emit structured audit events to a SIEM or central log store. Logs include policy id, namespace, principal, decision, and resource.</statement>
      <rationale source="NIST SP 800-53 AU-2, AU-3">Without audit, policy violations are invisible; the same controls that block bad changes also surface attack attempts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-policy-as-code-in-repo" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Policies (Kyverno, OPA, Rego) MUST live in version control alongside infrastructure code. Changes go via PR with review; no console-level policy edits.</statement>
      <rationale source="Policy-as-Code best practices (OPA)">Policy drift is identical to config drift; PRs + review surface intent and history.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
