<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="Security as Code (Policy as Code) Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 antipatterns observed in real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">

    <antipattern id="audit-only-policies" severity="medium">
      <description>Kyverno reports 200 violations/day; nobody fixes them; same violations recur.</description>
      <reason>Policies in audit mode 'to avoid breaking the team'; no enforcement deadline.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Promote to enforce with a 2-week notice. Issue waivers for legacy workloads with 90-day expiry. Track waiver burn-down weekly.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="scanner-but-no-gate" severity="medium">
      <description>CI runs Trivy on every build; finds 50 criticals; merges anyway.</description>
      <reason>Scanner job set to continue-on-error.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Set Trivy job to fail-on critical. Require security-team override label to merge with criticals (documented exception).</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="unsigned-images-in-prod" severity="medium">
      <description>Cluster pulls images from a public registry without verification; SLSA review finds no build provenance.</description>
      <reason>Signing infra never set up; admission controller absent.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Install cosign in build pipeline; sign every image. Install Sigstore policy-controller; require signature for the prod namespace.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="policy-via-console" severity="medium">
      <description>Production Kyverno policies edited via kubectl edit; no git history.</description>
      <reason>Team treated policies as one-off configs.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Move all policies to git. Apply via ArgoCD / Flux. Lock the policy controller against console edits via RBAC.</note>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="no-audit-log" severity="medium">
      <description>Post-breach forensics: cannot determine which images ran, which admission decisions allowed them.</description>
      <reason>Admission webhook ran without log shipping.</reason>
      <note>Fix: Configure admission-controller audit log shipping to a separate-account SIEM. Replay 30 days of events; close gaps.</note>
    </antipattern>

  </section>
</text>
