<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-map-structure" title="Story Map Structure and Slicing Rules">
  <summary>Two-axis map structure, backbone/task/story definitions, walking-skeleton contract, and vertical vs horizontal slicing rules.</summary>

  <section title="Two-Axis Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Horizontal axis: backbone activities in narrative verb-phrases in the user's voice (e.g., "Find a place to stay", "Pay for the order"), ordered by user journey. Vertical axis: priority — walking skeleton stories at the top, enhancements below, nice-to-haves at the bottom.</statement>
      <rationale>Activities expressed as feature names ("Search", "Checkout") produce a 2D Jira view, not a narrative. Verb-phrases force user-voice framing and reveal journey gaps that noun-names hide.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Freeze backbone activities before adding tasks. Backbone changes invalidate everything below. Require explicit unfreeze flag to reorder activities within a planning cycle.</statement>
      <rationale>Activity churn mid-cycle forces task re-grouping and story re-assignment, wasting the most expensive agent work (the release-slicer pass).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Build one map per persona. If two personas share a journey, build two maps and derive a "shared backbone" view as a read-only overlay. Never start with a merged map.</statement>
      <rationale>Multi-persona merged maps produce one-size-fits-none stories. Persona-specific maps surface persona-specific gaps; the shared backbone derives from the union after both are stable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Walking Skeleton Contract">
    <rule>
      <statement>R1 (walking skeleton) must contain at least one story per backbone activity that delivers a complete, degraded-but-functional user journey end-to-end. Absence of any backbone activity in R1 is a contract violation, not a scope cut.</statement>
      <rationale>A release that covers 4 of 5 activities completely but skips one does not let users complete the journey. An incomplete journey produces no learning about the product's core value proposition.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>R1 capacity feasibility must be computed: sum of story points in R1 divided by (team velocity × sprint count) must be at most 1.0. Release-slicer must emit this ratio and refuse to mark R1 valid if it exceeds 1.0.</statement>
      <rationale>Capacity overrun in R1 is the most common cause of walking-skeleton failure. Explicit feasibility evidence prevents optimistic slicing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag enabler stories (auth, payment infra, telemetry, analytics) explicitly with enabler: true and pin them as dependencies of journey stories, not as journey tasks. Enablers must not count toward backbone coverage.</statement>
      <rationale>Technical enablers are a prerequisite for journey stories but are not user-observable activities. Counting them as coverage masks an incomplete journey.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Slicing Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Prefer vertical slicing (thin end-to-end slice covering all activities) over horizontal slicing (all tasks in one activity). Horizontal-first produces feature-factory releases with no complete journey.</statement>
      <rationale>Vertical slicing maximizes learning per release by enabling end-to-end user tests from day one. Horizontal slicing defers learning until all activities are complete — often much later.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Map-as-code: the canonical artifact is map.yaml in version control. Miro, Markdown tables, and FigJam exports are rendered from map.yaml; they are display surfaces, not sources of truth.</statement>
      <rationale>Visual tools are not queryable, diffable, or validatable. Tool fragmentation produces stale maps within days of a workshop. Code-as-source enables automated drift detection and Jira sync.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/map.yaml">YAML schema for story map with backbone, tasks, stories, releases, and capacity fields.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
