<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="User Story Mapping Antipatterns">
  <summary>Structural and agentic failure modes in user story mapping, with concrete mitigations.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Activities expressed as feature names ("Search", "Checkout", "Profile") instead of verb-phrases in user voice ("Find a product", "Complete purchase", "Manage account settings").</description>
    <reason>Noun-names produce a 2D Jira view. Verb-phrases reveal journey sequence, user goals, and gaps. The activity-extractor must be constrained to reject noun-only activities.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Vertical priority dimension collapses to ranks 1, 2, 3 with no forcing function. Everything ends up in R1.</description>
    <reason>Without a release line tied to capacity (story-points sum / velocity × sprints &lt;= 1.0), priority is aspirational. The release-slicer must compute and enforce the capacity constraint.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Multi-persona stories merged into one map from the start ("shoppers + admins" in the same backbone).</description>
    <reason>Merged maps produce one-size-fits-none stories. Different personas have different journey sequences and different definitions of "essential". Always start per-persona; merge only after each is stable.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Walking skeleton inflation: R1 padded with "delight" stories because they are "already built".</description>
    <reason>Walking skeleton = minimum to validate the outcome metric. Every non-essential R1 item must provide a removal justification. The opus slicer must request this justification when adding stories beyond the minimum.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Workshop produces 200 stickies; nobody transcribes them within 24 hours. Map exists only on a wall or whiteboard.</description>
    <reason>Untranscribed workshops are effectively lost within days. Digitize to map.yaml within 24 hours; the workshop is prep for the canonical artifact, not the artifact itself.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Story-rewriter emits 7 acceptance-criteria scenarios for a 1-point story.</description>
    <reason>AC inflation bloats test-plan.md and slows CI. Cap at 3 GWT scenarios per story; additional scenarios go to a nice_to_have_ac bucket for later.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Backbone activities reordered by agents on every run, causing downstream task and story churn.</description>
    <reason>Pin backbone order as immutable for the cycle. Require explicit unfreeze flag to reorder. Agents must reject re-orderings that were not explicitly requested.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
