<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Creative Brief Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules grounding the creative brief. Each pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="one-brief-per-campaign" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>One brief MUST cover exactly one paid-ads campaign instance. Multi-campaign briefs are forbidden — split into one per campaign with explicit cross-links.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-conflation pattern (faion brief audit Q1 2026)">Combined briefs lose the rationale per variant; downstream designers cannot tell which input justified which creative.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="typed-and-sourced-input" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every input field MUST have a declared type AND cite a source (URL, doc path, ticket ID). Free-form prose without a citation is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Contract-first artefact discipline">Untyped + unsourced inputs let LLMs hallucinate plausible-but-wrong values; typed + sourced inputs make the brief falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="named-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brief MUST name a single accountable owner (handle, email, or rotating role with handle). "Team", "we", or empty is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="RACI / single-throat-to-choke practice">Plural ownership = no ownership. Future readers need a named human to chase when the brief is stale.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="versioned-and-dated" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brief MUST carry a semver-style version and a last_reviewed ISO date. Briefs &gt;30 days old MUST be flagged on read.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice; faion content-aging policy">Briefs decay as audiences + ad platforms change; freshness gating forces refresh cadence.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="traceable-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every creative decision (angle, hook, CTA) MUST cite at least one input field by name. Decisions without traces are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Audit-trail discipline">Without traceability, the brief becomes opinion. Citations make the brief reviewable by a future operator with no context.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
