<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PMBoK Performance Domains Overview Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding PMBoK Performance Domains Overview. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="eight-domains-covered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Assessment MUST score all eight PMBoK 7 domains (Stakeholder, Team, Development Approach, Planning, Project Work, Delivery, Measurement, Uncertainty). Skipping a domain is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Performance Domains">Skipping domains creates blind spots; the rubric's value is portfolio-comparable coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="rag-with-evidence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each domain score (red/amber/green) MUST cite ≥1 evidence row (artefact reference, observation date, or metric).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — PMO health-check audit">Unevidenced RAG scores are vibes; evidence forces honest assessment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="recommended-action-per-amber-red" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every amber or red score MUST carry a recommended action with owner + due date.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 7 — Performance Domains">Scores without actions are diagnostic without therapeutic; the rule closes the loop.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="quarterly-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Performance-domain rubric MUST be re-run at minimum quarterly. Annual-only cadence is forbidden for projects >6 months.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMO governance best practices">Annual cadence lets domains drift unnoticed; quarterly catches early signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="scorer-independence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Scorer MUST be independent of the project (PMO, peer PM, external auditor). Self-scoring forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 21500 audit independence">Self-scoring inflates greens; independent scoring exposes signals the PM minimises.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for PMBoK Performance Domains Overview fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying PMBoK Performance Domains Overview outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
