<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="scrum-ceremonies">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>The five Scrum events with time-boxes, facilitation patterns, quality gates, and Definition of Ready discipline.</summary>
    <category>agile</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>scrum</tag>
      <tag>ceremonies</tag>
      <tag>ceremonies</tag>
      <tag>sprint</tag>
      <tag>agile</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Scrum Ceremonies</title>

    <summary>The five Scrum events — Sprint Planning, Daily Standup, Sprint Review, Sprint Retrospective, and Backlog Refinement — with time-boxes, facilitation patterns (including async/remote variants), tool configurations, and quality gates. Sprint goal must be falsifiable in one sentence; retro actions must have an owner and a linked issue or they do not exist; async standup blockers must escalate within 1 working day.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Ceremony theatre — running events without the underlying DoR/DoD discipline and action follow-through — is the most common Scrum failure mode. The five events exist to create inspect-and-adapt loops at different cadences, not to generate reports for management. Each event has a specific output and a quality gate; agents can automate prep and capture, but cannot replace facilitation.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bootstrapping Scrum for a new team and wiring ceremonies into a PM tool (Jira, Linear, GitHub Projects).</item>
        <item>Replacing free-form standups with structured cadence after onboarding or merging teams.</item>
        <item>Optimizing a remote/distributed Scrum team — async standups, retro tools, recorded reviews.</item>
        <item>Reducing ceremony time-tax (pre-refine with an agent the day before planning).</item>
        <item>Evidence collection for transformations (sprint goal achievement, retro action follow-through, velocity stability).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo developer or pair — Scrum overhead exceeds value; use Kanban with lightweight reviews.</item>
        <item>Pure research or discovery teams with no incremental delivery — use Lean Startup or Discovery Kanban.</item>
        <item>Crisis or incident periods — break glass, run incident process, restart Scrum after.</item>
        <item>Hardware-heavy programs where 2-week sprints do not match material lead times.</item>
        <item>Teams with working ceremonies and good outcomes — do not redesign for novelty.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="time-boxes-per-sprint-length">
      <p>Time-boxes scale with sprint duration. Always adhere to the time-box and end on time even if unfinished.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Sprint Planning: 2h (1-week sprint), 4h (2-week), 8h (4-week).</item>
        <item>Daily Standup: 15 min (all sprint lengths).</item>
        <item>Sprint Review: 1h (1-week), 2h (2-week), 4h (4-week).</item>
        <item>Sprint Retrospective: 45min (1-week), 1.5h (2-week), 3h (4-week).</item>
        <item>Backlog Refinement: 1-2h (1-week), 2-4h (2-week), 4-8h (4-week).</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>End every ceremony on time even if unfinished; recurring overruns indicate bad inputs (insufficient refinement, miscalculated capacity) — fix the input, not the time-box.</statement>
        <rationale>Extending ceremonies trains the team that preparation is optional. The time-box creates the pressure that drives refinement discipline upstream.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="sprint-planning">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never run sprint planning without a refined-Ready backlog of at least 1.5x sprint capacity; force a refinement session before planning if the backlog is not ready.</statement>
        <rationale>Planning against unrefined stories produces a sprint goal that collapses on Day 2 when acceptance criteria are discovered to be missing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Sprint Planning splits into two parts. Part 1 (What, first half): review sprint goal, top backlog items, acceptance criteria, and team questions. Part 2 (How, second half): break stories into tasks, estimate, identify dependencies, commit to sprint backlog.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Sprint goal must be falsifiable in one sentence; ban vague goals like "make progress on X". Reject during planning and ask the PO to reframe.</statement>
        <rationale>An unfalsifiable sprint goal cannot be assessed at review. The team can always claim they "made progress" regardless of what was delivered.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/sprint-planning.md">Sprint planning notes template for sprint info, goal, team capacity, committed backlog, stretch goals, risks/dependencies, and action items.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="daily-standup">
      <p>Three standup formats suited to different team conditions. Choose one and stick with it for the sprint; rotate formats quarterly to prevent staleness.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Classic three questions: What did I do yesterday? What will I do today? Any blockers?</item>
        <item>Walk-the-board (preferred for flow): right-to-left column sweep, focus on stale items and blockers.</item>
        <item>Async standup: post by agreed time, thread discussions, hard limit — blocker older than 1 working day escalates to sync.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Design standup for team-to-team flow visibility, not for reporting to a manager; standup output goes to the team channel, not a management dashboard.</statement>
        <rationale>Standups designed for management reporting shift the power dynamic from self-organizing team to supervised status update, eroding agile culture and psychological safety.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/standup-bot.yaml">Geekbot async standup configuration with questions and schedule settings.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="sprint-review">
      <rule>
        <statement>Sprint review requires real stakeholders with decision authority; without them it is engineering show-and-tell with no feedback loop.</statement>
        <rationale>The review's purpose is to inspect the increment and adapt the backlog based on stakeholder feedback. Without stakeholders, the inspect-and-adapt loop is broken.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/sprint-review-readiness.py">Gate script checking completion ratio, demoable items, demo environment, invited stakeholders, and escaped bug count.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="sprint-retrospective">
      <rule>
        <statement>Retro action items must have a named owner, a due date, and a linked issue — or they do not exist. Review previous sprint actions before adding new ones.</statement>
        <rationale>Unowned, unlinked actions appear identically in every retrospective. The recurring-action antipattern destroys retro credibility and team trust in the process.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Retrospective formats rotate to prevent staleness. Supported formats include Start-Stop-Continue (default), 4Ls (Liked/Learned/Lacked/Longed For), Mad-Sad-Glad, and Sailboat (goal/wind/anchor/rocks). Each format surfaces different themes and emotions.</p>
      <reference path="templates/retrospective.md">Retrospective template with metrics, format options, action table with owner/due/issue, and team health check.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="backlog-refinement-definition-of-ready">
      <p>Refinement is the ceremony where the team and PO prepare stories for upcoming sprints. Stories must reach Definition of Ready (DoR) before they can enter sprint planning.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>A story is Ready for sprint planning only when all five DoR criteria are met: acceptance criteria defined, dependencies identified, estimate provided, fits in one sprint, and is testable.</statement>
        <rationale>Stories entering planning without DoR criteria cause mid-sprint discovery of missing information, breaking the sprint goal and forcing scope changes under pressure.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="planning-poker-and-estimation">
      <p>Planning poker is a structured estimation technique that uncovers diverse thinking and prevents anchoring bias.</p>
      <p>Scale: 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, ?, coffee. Tools: planningpoker.com, scrumpoker-online.org, or Jira-integrated poker modules.</p>
      <p>Process: PO presents story → team asks questions → everyone votes secretly → reveal simultaneously → discuss outliers → re-vote if needed → consensus recorded.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep agent estimation suggestions masked until after the team's first vote; surfacing suggestions before voting anchors all estimates to the LLM's output (anchoring bias).</statement>
        <rationale>Anchoring bias on an LLM baseline eliminates the independent estimation diversity that makes planning poker useful. The value of poker is the outlier discussion, not the median.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>T-Shirt Sizing correlation: XS very small, few hours → 1 point. S small, about 1 day → 2-3 points. M medium, 2-3 days → 5 points. L large, about 1 week → 8 points. XL very large, needs splitting → 13+ points.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ceremony theatre — team runs events but DoR/DoD discipline and action follow-through are missing.</description>
        <reason>Ceremonies without underlying discipline produce the appearance of Scrum without the inspect-and-adapt value. Agents that only schedule and notify reinforce theatre by making it effortless.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Standup as management reporting — standup updates go to a manager dashboard, not the team channel.</description>
        <reason>Reporting-oriented standups shift power from the self-organizing team to the manager, eroding psychological safety and turning the event into a performance rather than a coordination mechanism.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Retros without action follow-through — same actions appear sprint after sprint with no resolution.</description>
        <reason>Repeated unresolved actions signal that the team does not believe retro actions will change anything. Trust in the retro collapses; teams stop contributing honestly.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>PO convergence in planning poker — PO names a number first and team votes to match it.</description>
        <reason>Authority-anchored poker produces uniform votes from the first round. No disagreement means no discussion, which means the only person whose estimate was real was the PO — poker served no purpose.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Async blocker rot — a blocker is posted in standup, no one responds, it ages past 24 hours in a thread.</description>
        <reason>Unresolved async blockers compound daily. A 24-hour blocker in a 10-day sprint consumes 10% of capacity silently. Hard limit: blocker older than 1 working day must trigger a sync or escalation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Hard rules for scaling Scrum ceremonies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Time-box hard. End on time even if unfinished — recurring overruns indicate bad inputs (refinement quality, capacity miscalc).</item>
        <item>Never run planning without a refined-Ready backlog ≥ 1.5× sprint capacity; force a refinement session if missing.</item>
        <item>Walk the board (right-to-left) at standup; prioritize flow over individual status. Agents that surface stale columns help.</item>
        <item>Sprint goal must be falsifiable in one sentence; ban vague goals like "make progress on X". Reject during planning.</item>
        <item>Retro action items have owner + due-date + linked issue or they do not exist; agents enforce.</item>
        <item>Rotate facilitators; standardize ceremony agendas in a runbook so rotation is cheap.</item>
        <item>Async standups: maximum blocker age = 1 working day; auto-escalate.</item>
        <item>Capture sprint review feedback in the backlog with provenance (who said what); never leave it in chat.</item>
        <item>Velocity is for forecasting, not management — never use it as a performance metric per person.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A ceremony-orchestrator agent owns the sprint clock: schedules each event in the team calendar, posts pre-reads (refined backlog, capacity, prior-sprint metrics), drafts agendas, and posts post-event summaries with action items linked to issues.</p>
      <p>A refinement-coach agent runs against the backlog mid-sprint: flags stories without acceptance criteria, oversized stories, missing estimates, hidden dependencies, then opens a refinement-ready list for the PO.</p>
      <p>A retro-synthesizer clusters retro contributions, surfaces themes, and writes a 1-page summary with new action items + status of previous ones.</p>
      <p>A standup-bot collects async updates, computes blocker age, and pages a Scrum Master after thresholds.</p>
      <p>Humans facilitate live; agents do prep + capture, never replace conversation.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents:</p>
      <list>
        <item>ceremony-orchestrator (haiku) — schedule + agenda + summary; touches calendar, PM tool, chat.</item>
        <item>refinement-coach (sonnet) — backlog quality checks, story splitting suggestions, INVEST scoring.</item>
        <item>estimation-helper (sonnet) — proposes story-point estimates from historical reference issues; never auto-applies.</item>
        <item>retro-synthesizer (sonnet) — clusters retro inputs, drafts summary, links actions to backlog.</item>
        <item>standup-bot (haiku) — async question prompts, thread-summary, blocker-age escalation.</item>
        <item>velocity-watcher (haiku) — alerts on velocity outliers, commitment ratio drift, scope creep.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>Common failure modes when wiring agents into Scrum ceremonies:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Bots that "summarize standups" to managers turn the ceremony into reporting; restrict standup-bot output to the team channel.</item>
        <item>Estimation suggestions from LLMs anchor humans (anchoring bias) — keep them masked until after first vote, or do not use.</item>
        <item>Auto-clustering retros loses context (sarcasm, sentiment) — always show original notes alongside themes.</item>
        <item>Async standup tools generate vast logs; without rotation/archive, retrieval becomes the bottleneck. Page-summarize weekly.</item>
        <item>Calendar agents schedule across time zones poorly when DST flips — always use IANA tz names, never UTC offsets.</item>
        <item>Reading sprint metrics out-of-context: the same 30-point velocity is "good" or "bad" depending on capacity, holidays, dependencies. Force the agent to include context.</item>
        <item>Auto-closing stale stories at sprint end is a foot-gun; let the team triage spillover, not a rule.</item>
        <item>Permission scope: a standup-bot writing into the issue tracker can create circular notification storms; whitelist target fields.</item>
        <item>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints (mandatory): sprint goal acceptance, story splitting, retro action commitment, sprint-end spillover decision.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/sprint-planning.md" purpose="Sprint planning notes: sprint info, goal, team capacity, committed backlog, stretch goals, risks/dependencies, action items."/>
      <template path="templates/retrospective.md" purpose="Retrospective template: sprint metrics, what went well, what to improve, action items with owner/due, previous action review, team health check."/>
      <template path="templates/standup-bot.yaml" purpose="Geekbot async standup configuration with questions and schedule settings."/>
      <template path="templates/sprint-review-readiness.py" purpose="Gate script: checks completion ratio, demoable items, demo environment, invited stakeholders, escaped bug count."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://scrumguides.org"/>
      <link href="https://pragprog.com/titles/dlret/agile-retrospectives/"/>
      <link href="https://retromat.org"/>
      <link href="https://geekbot.com"/>
      <link href="https://standuply.com"/>
      <link href="https://parabol.co"/>
      <link href="https://retrium.com"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
