<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process-and-rules" title="Writing Specifications: Process, Rules, and Common Mistakes">
  <summary>The 9-phase process for writing spec.md, document hierarchy rules, SMART/INVEST criteria for requirements, and a common mistakes table.</summary>

  <section title="Document Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>A specification answers WHAT and WHY. A design answers HOW. An implementation plan answers IN WHAT ORDER. Never mix concerns across documents.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing implementation details into spec.md causes the spec to become stale when the design changes, and breaks the clean hand-off between phases.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Document responsibility table</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Specification  → WHAT and WHY?       → Requirements, user stories, acceptance criteria
Design         → HOW?                → Architecture, file structure, API contracts
Impl Plan      → IN WHAT ORDER?      → Tasks, dependencies, token estimates
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="9-Phase Writing Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Load constitution.md and completed feature specs BEFORE writing any requirements.</statement>
      <rationale>Requirements written without constitution context violate tech stack constraints. Reviewing done/ features surfaces patterns and prevents re-inventing resolved problems.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Phase 1: Load context — read constitution.md, features/done/, related specs in todo/in-progress/</item>
      <item>Phase 2: Problem analysis — define WHO, WHAT, WHY, IMPACT using SMART criteria</item>
      <item>Phase 3: User research — define minimum 2 personas with role, goal, pain points, context</item>
      <item>Phase 4: User story mapping — backbone, walking skeleton (MVP), phase 2 stories</item>
      <item>Phase 5: Use cases — for multi-step workflows, multiple actors, or complex validations</item>
      <item>Phase 6: Functional requirements — SMART requirements with MoSCoW, FR-X IDs, US traceability</item>
      <item>Phase 7: Non-functional requirements — measurable targets (no vague words)</item>
      <item>Phase 8: Acceptance criteria — Given-When-Then covering all scenarios with specific values</item>
      <item>Phase 9: Scope definition — explicitly list what IS and IS NOT in scope</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="SMART Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every functional requirement must satisfy SMART: Specific (one interpretation), Measurable (verifiable), Achievable (technically feasible), Relevant (traces to user need), and have a testable pass/fail criterion.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague requirements cannot be tested. "System should be fast" is untestable; "response time &lt; 500ms p95" is not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Vague requirement — fails SMART</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[FR-001: System should be fast and handle user requests efficiently.]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>SMART requirement</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[FR-001: System SHALL return API responses within 500ms p95 under 100 concurrent users. [Must]]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="User Story Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every user story must include the "so that [benefit]" clause. A story without a benefit clause hides the value and cannot be prioritized.</statement>
      <rationale>The benefit clause is where business value lives. Stories without it get implemented based on assumed value, which is frequently wrong.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Missing benefit clause</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[US-001: As a user, I want to log in with my email.]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Complete user story</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[US-001: As a registered user, I want to log in with my email and password, so that I can access my personal account and saved data.]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>"System should be fast" as a non-functional requirement.</description>
      <reason>Not measurable. Rewrite as: "Response time &lt; 500ms p95".</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No user personas defined.</description>
      <reason>Requirements written without personas are not grounded in user context and tend to describe system behavior rather than user needs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Requirements without FR-X IDs.</description>
      <reason>Unidentified requirements cannot be traced to design decisions or acceptance criteria.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Out of Scope section is empty or lists only obvious exclusions.</description>
      <reason>Out of Scope must name specific features that were discussed and explicitly rejected; generic exclusions do not prevent scope creep.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>AC items are not testable: "system should handle errors gracefully".</description>
      <reason>Acceptance criteria without Given-When-Then and specific values cannot be verified by a test.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
