<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-dialog-components" title="VUI Dialog Components and Prompt Class Rules">
  <summary>Defines conversation components (intent, entity, prompt classes), dialog flow patterns, and rules for prompt copy.</summary>

  <section title="Core Components">
    <p>Every VUI turn consists of: wake word (activation), intent (user goal), entities (parameters), system prompt (question or confirmation), and response. Error handling is a first-class component, not an afterthought.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Design all four repair paths for every prompt node: no-match (unrecognized input), no-input (silence/timeout), max-retry (escalation after N failures), and escape-to-human (always available within 3 retries).</statement>
      <rationale>VUI flows without repair paths produce dead ends. The user cannot read a "Page Not Found" equivalent — they just hear silence or repeated prompts and abandon the interaction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Prompt Classes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use the correct prompt class for each node: open prompts ("How can I help?") for unconstrained input; directed prompts ("What city?") when the entity space is large; option prompts ("Red, blue, or green?") only when options are 4 or fewer; confirmation prompts ("Is that correct?") for destructive or irreversible actions only.</statement>
      <rationale>Option prompts with more than 4 choices exceed working memory. Using explicit confirmation for low-stakes actions (setting a timer) feels robotic and wastes turn budget. Implicit confirmation (just executing) is correct for low-stakes reversible actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every prompt with class, intent, and retry-count in analytics. Without this tagging, you cannot measure where the dialog fails in production.</statement>
      <rationale>Anonymous prompt firing data cannot be analyzed by failure type. Class + intent + retry-count gives the minimum dimensions needed to locate dialog bottlenecks.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Dialog Flow Patterns">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Happy path, missing-entity slot-filling, and disambiguation flow for "set timer".</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Happy path:
  User: "Set a timer for 5 minutes"
  VUI:  "5-minute timer started"

Missing entity (no duration):
  User: "Set a timer"
  VUI:  "For how long?"
  User: "5 minutes"
  VUI:  "5-minute timer started"

Disambiguation (ambiguous entity):
  User: "Set a timer for five"
  VUI:  "5 minutes or 5 hours?"
  User: "Minutes"
  VUI:  "5-minute timer started"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/dialog-flow.json">Skeleton dialog graph node structure</reference>
  </section>
</text>
