<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-repair-design" title="Repair Branch Design Rules">
  <summary>Rules for no-match, no-input, retry variation, confirmation strategy, and escalation-to-human paths.</summary>

  <section title="Retry Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap retries at 3 on any node. The third no-match transitions to human escalation or an alternative modality (text fallback, app deep link). Never loop indefinitely.</statement>
      <rationale>Users who fail 3 times in a row are in a breakdown state. Offering a different modality respects their time and preserves product trust. Looping produces frustration and abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Vary prompt copy on retry — do not repeat the same wording. Maintain at least 3 variants per node and rotate. Repeating the same prompt feels broken.</statement>
      <rationale>Identical retry prompts signal to the user that the system is stuck, increasing anxiety and reducing the chance of a successful follow-up input.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Confirmation Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use implicit confirmation for low-stakes reversible actions (executing immediately). Use explicit confirmation ("Is that correct?") only for destructive or irreversible actions.</statement>
      <rationale>Overuse of explicit confirmation creates robotic, slow interactions. Users learn to ignore confirmations when they appear too frequently. Reserve explicit confirmation for actions where a mistake has real cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Write Repair First">
    <rule>
      <statement>Author no-match, no-input, and barge-in handlers before the happy path. Happy path is written last.</statement>
      <rationale>Writing repair branches first forces honest coverage and exposes ambiguity at design time. Happy-path-first designers consistently underspecify repair branches and discover gaps in testing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Coverage Check">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run repair-coverage-checker on every dialog graph draft. LLMs producing dialog flows skip no-input and max-retry transitions reliably.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent-generated dialog graphs consistently omit timeout transitions and max-retry escalations. Automated linting after every draft catches these before human review.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/repair-check.ts">TypeScript linter for missing repair transitions</reference>
  </section>
</text>
