<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="vui-conversation-design Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for vui-conversation-design as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Disambiguation with more than one clarifying turn before falling back to directed prompt or human.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multi-turn disambiguation compounds confusion. After one failed disambiguation, transition to a directed prompt with explicit options or escalate to human assistance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using option prompts with more than 4 choices (e.g., listing 7 options).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Voice working memory holds 3-4 items. Users lose track of options mid-list and cannot re-hear. Constrain options to 4 or fewer, or use directed prompting to narrow the space.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Breaking the user's mental model on barge-in by ignoring a relevant interruption mid-prompt.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If the user starts speaking during a prompt with a relevant utterance and the system ignores it, trust breaks immediately. Accept relevant barge-in; if irrelevant, gracefully resume.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated unbounded paraphrases used as runtime prompt variants.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Runtime LLM paraphrases drift in tone and length across sessions. Pre-generate 3-5 vetted variants offline and rotate. Never generate prompt copy live in production.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM dialog flow skips no-input and max-retry transitions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs reliably omit timeout and escalation transitions. Run repair-coverage-checker on every draft before review — treat missing transitions as blocking defects.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Using the same TTS engine for test fixtures as for product output.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Same-vendor TTS inflates naturalness scores in LLM-judge evaluation. Use a different TTS engine for test utterance fixtures than for product output rendering.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
