<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="data-driven-requirements">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Evidence-based requirements engineering that anchors each requirement to business questions, quantified baselines, and success metrics. Replaces opinion-driven prioritization with usage, performance, business, and customer-feedback analytics.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>data-driven</tag>
      <tag>prioritization</tag>
      <tag>analytics</tag>
      <tag>success-metrics</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>requirements</category>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-24</created>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Data-Driven Requirements Engineering</title>

    <summary>An evidence-based approach to requirements definition that replaces opinion-driven prioritization with data analytics. Each requirement is anchored to a business question, quantified baseline metrics, and a measurable success target. Prioritization uses usage data, performance data, business metrics, and customer feedback rather than stakeholder seniority or gut feel.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Requirements based on stakeholder opinion are frequently wrong about user needs and business impact; prioritization becomes political; success metrics are defined post-implementation when the team wants to declare victory.</p>
      <p>Data-driven engineering anchors every requirement to evidence, establishes the baseline before development, and locks success criteria upfront so measurement cannot be gamed. 95% of enterprise AI projects fail without a solid data strategy underpinning requirements — the same principle applies to all feature work.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Prioritizing a backlog where features compete for limited capacity and ROI data is available.</item>
        <item>Feature validation before investment when analytics (usage, conversion, error rate) can answer the business question.</item>
        <item>Post-MVP iteration where product analytics reveal which flows users actually take.</item>
        <item>A/B test design where the requirement specifies what hypothesis is being tested and what outcome declares success.</item>
        <item>AI/ML feature scoping where business impact measurement (cycle time, CSAT, error rate) must be defined before model training.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Greenfield products with no users and no baseline — hypothesis-driven development (Lean Startup) applies before data exists.</item>
        <item>Requirements driven by compliance or legal obligation where the mandate, not ROI, is the reason to build.</item>
        <item>One-off internal tooling with a known, small user group where analytics instrumentation cost exceeds value.</item>
        <item>When the organization has no analytics tooling and instrumenting is out of scope — gather qualitative evidence instead.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="evidence-based-process">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every requirement must trace back to a business question, then to data sources, then to analysis findings before a requirement statement is written. The sequence is: Business Question → Data Collection → Analysis → Insight → Requirement → Success Metrics.</statement>
        <rationale>Requirements written before data analysis capture stakeholder opinion, not evidence. The evidence-based process delays requirement writing until after the analysis phase, flipping the order from traditional waterfall.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define success metrics — with baseline values and measurement methods — before development starts, not after. Lock metric definitions and baseline queries in the requirement document.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-implementation metric definition enables Goodhart's Law: when teams define metrics after knowing the result, definitions drift to make the number land.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>The evidence-based process flow:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Business Question — "Why do 38% of users abandon at the payment step?" (framed with time window, audience, decision it informs).</item>
        <item>Data Collection — query warehouse/BI for baseline: bounce rate, support tickets, session replays, interviews.</item>
        <item>Analysis — synthesize findings: 52% cite "too many fields", 8% fail validation, 5% session timeout.</item>
        <item>Insight — root cause identified: form complexity + insufficient validation errors.</item>
        <item>Requirement — simplify payment form to 3 required fields with inline validation.</item>
        <item>Success Metrics — baseline drop-off 38%, target 27% (11 point improvement), measured via funnel query over 30 days.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="analytics-competencies-for-bas">
      <p>Required competencies: statistical analysis (validate assumptions with data), data visualization (communicate insights), SQL/BI tools (query business data), A/B testing (validate solution options), predictive analytics (forecast feature impact).</p>

      <p>Self-service tools by category:</p>
      <list>
        <item>BI dashboards (Tableau, Power BI) for KPI monitoring.</item>
        <item>SQL interfaces (Mode, Looker) for custom queries.</item>
        <item>No-code analytics (Dataiku, Alteryx) for automated workflows.</item>
        <item>NLP query (ThoughtSpot) for natural language exploration.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="prioritization-metric-types">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Prioritize requirements using four metric types in combination: usage data (page views, feature adoption) for high-use feature improvements; performance data (error rates, load times) for bottleneck resolution; business metrics (conversion, revenue) for revenue-impacting features; customer feedback (NPS, support tickets) for high-volume pain points.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-metric prioritization is gameable; combining four independent signal types produces a prioritization that is robust to individual metric drift.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Metric types and their use:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Usage data (page views, feature adoption rate, session depth) — prioritize improvements to high-use features; deprioritize features nobody uses even if stakeholders believe they are important.</item>
        <item>Performance data (error rates, latency p95, funnel drop-off rates) — address bottlenecks that degrade user experience for the largest user segments.</item>
        <item>Business metrics (conversion rate, revenue per user, churn rate) — focus on features with direct revenue impact measurable within the evaluation window.</item>
        <item>Customer feedback (NPS verbatims, support ticket volume by category, user interviews) — address the pain points mentioned most frequently across all feedback channels.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-ml-roi-measurement-framework">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Measure AI/ML feature impact across four areas: operational efficiency (cycle time, throughput, error rate, rework percentage), experience and growth (CSAT/NPS, conversion rate, retention), financial (cost-to-serve, gross margin, working capital), and risk and compliance (policy violations avoided, audit hours saved).</statement>
        <rationale>Single-area measurement (e.g., only efficiency) misses the full value picture; AI features often have their largest impact in a different area than the one that motivated the investment.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>For each metric, define the measurement method, data source, baseline value, and target value before development — never after. Use the same query and the same data source for baseline and post-implementation measurement.</statement>
        <rationale>Changing data sources or query definitions between baseline and measurement invalidates variance calculations; the numerator and denominator must be comparable.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Industry context:</p>
      <list>
        <item>91.9% of organizations report measurable value from data and analytics investments.</item>
        <item>65% have adopted or are investigating AI for analytics.</item>
        <item>Data-driven companies are 23x more likely to acquire customers.</item>
        <item>95% of enterprise AI projects fail without a solid data strategy underpinning requirements.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="example-data-driven-requirement">
      <example type="good" title="Checkout flow optimization — requirement derived from analytics, not opinion">
        <note>Requirement: REQ-142 — Reduce cart abandonment at payment step</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Business Question:
  Why do 38% of users who reach payment step not complete checkout?

Data Sources:
| Source       | Metric                        | Value        | Confidence |
|--------------|-------------------------------|--------------|------------|
| PostHog      | Payment step drop-off rate    | 38%          | High       |
| Zendesk      | Payment error support tickets | 120/month    | High       |
| Session replay | Top exit reason at step 4   | "Too many fields" — 52% | Medium |

Analysis Summary:
  Session replay shows 52% of abandoners stop at the payment form.
  Support tickets confirm credit card field validation errors as #1 complaint.
  A/B test on a simplified 2-field form in Q3 showed +11% completion on n=2,400.

Requirement Statement:
  Simplify the payment entry form to 3 required fields (card number, expiry, CVV)
  with inline validation and auto-detection of card type.

Success Metrics:
| Metric               | Baseline | Target | Method                    |
|----------------------|----------|--------|---------------------------|
| Payment step drop-off | 38%     | 27%    | PostHog funnel, same cohort def |
| Payment support tickets | 120/mo | 80/mo | Zendesk category filter   |
| Checkout conversion  | 62%      | 73%    | Revenue analytics, 30-day window |

Validation Plan:
- A/B test: 50/50 split, minimum 2,000 users per arm, 14-day run
- Success criterion: drop-off delta > 8 percentage points, p < 0.05
- Rollback trigger: conversion drops > 2% from baseline in first 48 hours
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipattern-opinion-based-requirement">
      <example type="bad" title="Opinion-based requirement without evidence">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Requirement: Improve the checkout experience
Reason: Stakeholders think it's too complicated
Success: Users are happier
        ]]></code>
        <note>No data source, no baseline, no measurable success criterion. Cannot prioritize, cannot validate, cannot measure outcome.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow-four-pass-pipeline">
      <p>Drive data-driven requirements as a four-pass pipeline that turns telemetry into reviewable requirements.</p>

      <p>Pass 1: Question pass — a sonnet agent reads the business context and emits {business_question, hypothesis, kpi_owner, expected_direction}; no data yet.</p>

      <p>Pass 2: Baseline pass — agents query BI / warehouse / product analytics (BigQuery, Snowflake, Mixpanel, PostHog, GA4) and emit {kpi, current_value, segment, as_of_date, source_url, n}. Parallel agents per data source reduce blocking on slow warehouses.</p>

      <p>Pass 3: Requirement pass — given baseline + hypothesis, an opus agent writes the structured requirement (the README template) and the success-metric table; a separate agent runs power calculation for the validation A/B.</p>

      <p>Pass 4: Review pass — faion-sdd-executor-agent re-reads the requirement against constitution standards (no vanity metrics, has baseline + target + measurement method, validation plan defined). Humans own (a) the business question, (b) target setting (aggressive vs. realistic), (c) the go/no-go after the experiment.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations-and-failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Survivorship bias in usage data.</description>
        <reason>Heavily-used features look high-priority because users who hated them already churned. Add churn-cohort comparison or you'll over-invest in features your remaining base loves and your lost base rejected.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Vanity metric capture.</description>
        <reason>"Page views" and "DAU" feel like business signal but are easy to game. Tie every requirement to a downstream conversion / retention / revenue metric, not a top-of-funnel proxy.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Baseline drift.</description>
        <reason>The "current value" cell ages out fast (seasonality, marketing campaigns, releases). Stamp every metric with as_of_date and a query/dashboard URL; reject baselines older than ~30 days for active surfaces.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Sample-size theater.</description>
        <reason>A/B plans that don't pre-calculate MDE (minimum detectable effect) and required N produce "no significant difference" results that are actually underpowered. Use a power calculator before, not after.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Simpson's paradox in cohort rollups.</description>
        <reason>Aggregate metrics improve while every segment gets worse (or vice versa). Always slice by acquisition channel, plan tier, geo, and device class before declaring a baseline.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy / consent boundaries.</description>
        <reason>PII or behavioral data may be unusable for product analytics under GDPR/CCPA without a lawful basis. Requirements built on data you cannot legally use will fail at the legal review gate.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Causal vs. correlational confusion.</description>
        <reason>"Users who use feature X retain 2x" almost never means "shipping feature X for everyone doubles retention". Self-selection swallows the effect. Frame requirements around hypotheses to be tested, not foregone conclusions.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>AI ROI fiction.</description>
        <reason>95% of enterprise AI projects fail without a data strategy. The framework asks for the four impact areas — most teams fill three with guesses; mark unknowns as "to be measured" not as point estimates.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools-and-platforms">
      <p>Recommended tools for data-driven requirements:</p>
      <list>
        <item>dbt — Version-controlled SQL transformations; agents reference dbt models as the canonical KPI definitions.</item>
        <item>bq — BigQuery CLI; agents pull baselines as JSON, stamp as_of from query timestamp.</item>
        <item>snowsql — Snowflake CLI equivalent for warehouse queries.</item>
        <item>posthog (REST) — Self-hosted/SaaS product analytics with first-class API; pull funnels and cohort retention as evidence.</item>
        <item>mixpanel (REST/JQL) — Event analytics queryable from agents; cohort + funnel endpoints.</item>
        <item>metabase-cli / Metabase API — Open-source BI; agents render baseline charts and embed in the requirement doc.</item>
        <item>pwr (R) / statsmodels (Python) — A/B power calculation; computes required N from baseline + MDE.</item>
        <item>numpy + pandas + scipy.stats — Cohort segmentation, Simpson's-paradox checks, CI computation on baselines.</item>
        <item>pandas-profiling / ydata-profiling — One-shot data quality report agents can attach to evidence section.</item>
        <item>gh + jq — Pull product issue counts / churn signal from support repos as supplementary evidence.</item>
        <item>claude CLI — Run the question / requirement / review passes against the JSON schema.</item>
      </list>

      <p>SaaS platforms supporting data-driven requirements:</p>
      <list>
        <item>PostHog — OSS/SaaS, self-hostable; agents can run trends, funnels, cohort retention queries; ideal default for OSS-leaning teams.</item>
        <item>Mixpanel — SaaS, strong for event-based KPI baselines; rate limits on free tier.</item>
        <item>Amplitude — SaaS, cohort + retention + impact analysis exposed as API.</item>
        <item>GA4 — SaaS (free), web-traffic baseline; agents fetch via google-analytics-data SDK.</item>
        <item>Segment / Rudderstack — SaaS/OSS, source of truth for event schema; agents validate that proposed metrics are actually emitted.</item>
        <item>Looker / Mode / Hex — SaaS, BI; agents reference saved Looks / models as canonical KPI definitions.</item>
        <item>Metabase — OSS, cheap default BI for small teams; agents read Q&amp;A endpoints.</item>
        <item>Statsig / GrowthBook / Eppo / Optimizely — SaaS/OSS, A/B platforms; agents pre-register experiments with hypothesis, MDE, primary metric.</item>
        <item>Hightouch / Census — SaaS, reverse-ETL; agents trigger sync of measured outcomes back into product DB once experiment ends.</item>
        <item>Atlan / DataHub / OpenMetadata — SaaS/OSS, data catalogs; agents look up metric ownership, freshness SLA, lineage before citing a number.</item>
        <item>Great Expectations / dbt tests — OSS, data-quality checks the agent can run before trusting a baseline.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Diverge on hypotheses before locking the question. Use brainstorm agents to generate multiple candidate hypotheses and KPI choices before committing to the analysis direction.</item>
        <item>Gate-check requirements for rigor. Have sdd-executor-agent re-read every requirement: baseline cited, target numeric, measurement method named, validation plan present. Reject requirements with "TBD" in success metrics.</item>
        <item>Use power calculation before running the test. Do not design A/B tests without pre-calculating MDE and required N; underpowered tests produce false negatives.</item>
        <item>Timestamp every baseline. "Churn was 12%" is useless without "as of 2026-04-15 computed via SQL in dashboard Q.34". Require ISO dates and source URLs.</item>
        <item>Triangulate with multiple data sources. One data source can be stale, biased, or wrong; use four independent signal types (usage + performance + business + feedback) to validate assumptions.</item>
        <item>Redact PII before sharing baselines. Run Presidio on any sample row, any query result that contains email, ID, free text before pasting into Slack, Confluence, or an LLM prompt.</item>
        <item>Measure quarterly calibration. After features ship, compare predicted target vs. measured outcome; log calibration error per author and per domain (e.g., "we systematically over-promise on conversion in payments").</item>
        <item>Lock success criteria upfront. Define metric definitions and baseline queries in the requirement document before development; do not re-measure after you know the result.</item>
        <item>Avoid vanity metrics. Tie every requirement to a downstream metric (revenue, retention, CSAT) rather than a top-of-funnel proxy (page views, DAU).</item>
        <item>Require hypothesis framing. Every requirement must state what hypothesis is being tested and what outcome would constitute success vs. failure; avoid "improve the experience" without a specific, testable claim.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/data-driven-req.md" purpose="Requirement template with business context, data sources table, analysis summary, success metrics, and A/B validation plan."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://dbt.getdbt.com"/>
      <link href="https://posthog.com"/>
      <link href="https://mixpanel.com"/>
      <link href="https://amplitude.com"/>
      <link href="https://www.metabase.com"/>
      <link href="https://docs.greatexpectations.io"/>
      <ref slug="data-analysis"/>
      <ref slug="acceptance-criteria"/>
      <ref slug="requirements-validation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
