<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="schedule-development Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for schedule-development. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use FS dependencies by default; use SS/FF/SF only when truly required and document the justification in the activity list.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Most "we can parallelize" claims fail at integration; FS is conservative and explicit about ordering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track near-critical paths (float less than 2 days) explicitly alongside the critical path; report them at every status review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A near-critical path one day shorter than the critical path becomes critical after one slip and is invisible without slack analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the schedule baseline after kickoff; re-baseline only on approved change requests, never on standup updates.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Constant re-baselining hides slip from stakeholders; tracking variance against the original baseline reveals true schedule health.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Effort hours are not duration days; model resource availability explicitly (a 40-hour task for a 50%-available resource takes 10 days, not 5).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Effort-vs-duration confusion is the most common single source of schedule slip in agent-generated schedules.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject any schedule where activities have no explicit predecessors defined in the source data; agents must not infer dependencies from prose.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hallucinated dependencies produce incorrect critical paths and conceal missing information that the PM must resolve.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use business-calendar libraries for all date arithmetic; never compute working days with raw date math.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Raw date math silently skips weekends, public holidays, and half-days, producing schedule dates that do not match calendar reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
