<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Schedule Development Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the schedule-development methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="fs-by-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use FS dependencies by default; SS/FF/SF only when truly required and document the justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scheduling literature">Most 'we can parallelize' claims fail at integration; FS is conservative and explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="track-near-critical-paths" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track near-critical paths (float &lt; 2 days) alongside the critical path; report them at every status review.</statement>
      <rationale source="CPM practice">A near-critical path one day shorter becomes critical after one slip and is invisible without slack analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="lock-baseline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the schedule baseline after kickoff; re-baseline only on approved change requests, never on standup updates.</statement>
      <rationale source="EVM / baseline-discipline practice">Constant re-baselining hides slip from stakeholders.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="effort-not-duration" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Effort hours are not duration days; model resource availability explicitly (40 effort-hours at 50% availability = 10 days).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — agent-schedule audits">Effort-vs-duration confusion is the most common single source of schedule slip in agent-generated schedules.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="explicit-predecessors" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reject any schedule where activities have no explicit predecessors defined in the source data; agents must not infer dependencies from prose.</statement>
      <rationale source="Schedule-quality practice">Hallucinated dependencies produce incorrect critical paths and conceal missing information.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="business-calendar" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use business-calendar libraries for all date arithmetic; never compute working days with raw date math.</statement>
      <rationale source="Date-arithmetic practice">Raw date math silently skips weekends, public holidays, and half-days.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Pure agile teams with fixed-cadence sprints — velocity and roadmap replace CPM</item>
      <item>Highly creative / R&amp;D work where activity duration is unknowable</item>
      <item>Tasks under 2 weeks with a single owner — a checklist suffices</item>
      <item>Fixed-deadline projects where you back-plan from end date — use reverse-pass</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
