<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-cpm-process" title="Critical Path Method Process">
  <summary>Five-step process from WBS work packages to a baselined schedule with critical path and buffers.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Activities">
    <p>Convert each WBS work package into 3-7 specific activities with a clear deliverable. Fewer activities hide risk; more create false-precision overhead. Name activities as verb+noun ("Design auth flow", not "Auth").</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Sequence Activities">
    <p>Assign predecessor relationships with dependency types:</p>
    <list>
      <item>FS (Finish-to-Start) — predecessor must finish before successor starts; default type, use unless explicitly justified otherwise</item>
      <item>FF (Finish-to-Finish) — both activities finish together (documentation with development)</item>
      <item>SS (Start-to-Start) — both start together (testing starts when development starts)</item>
      <item>SF (Start-to-Finish) — rare; use only when required and document why</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: PERT Three-Point Estimation">
    <p>For each activity collect Optimistic (O), Most Likely (M), and Pessimistic (P) durations. Compute expected duration and standard deviation:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Expected duration = (O + 4M + P) / 6</item>
      <item>Standard deviation = (P - O) / 6</item>
      <item>Example: O=3d, M=5d, P=10d → Expected = (3 + 20 + 10)/6 = 5.5d</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Forward and Backward Pass">
    <p>Forward pass: traverse activities in topological order, propagating Early Start (ES) and Early Finish (EF). ES of first activity = 0; ES of successor = max(EF of all predecessors + lag). EF = ES + duration.</p>
    <p>Backward pass: traverse in reverse topological order. LF of last activity = EF of last activity. LF of predecessor = min(LS of all successors - lag). LS = LF - duration. Total float = LF - EF = LS - ES. Critical path: all activities with float = 0.</p>
    <reference path="scripts/critical-path.py">CPM forward/backward pass script (networkx)</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Buffers">
    <p>Critical Chain buffering: place one project buffer at the project end (typically 50% of critical path standard deviation sum). Place feeding buffers where non-critical paths join the critical path. Do not pad individual activities — hidden per-task slack always gets consumed (Parkinson's Law).</p>
    <reference path="templates/activity-list.md">Activity list template with dependencies</reference>
  </section>
</text>
