<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="scope-management">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>Scope management defines, documents, and controls what a project will and will not deliver with a written scope statement, signed baseline, and formal change-control gate.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>scope</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>change-control</tag>
      <tag>scope-creep</tag>
      <tag>acceptance-criteria</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Scope Management</title>

    <summary>Scope management defines, documents, and controls what a project will and will not deliver. It requires a written scope statement with explicit exclusions, a signed scope baseline, and a formal change-control gate — so every addition is evaluated for cost and schedule impact before it enters the project.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Scope creep is the leading cause of budget and schedule overrun. Without a locked baseline and a process to evaluate changes, teams absorb "small" additions until the project is unrecognizable. A written exclusions list closes the gap that vague deliverable language opens. Requirements traceability from source to test ensures nothing is forgotten and nothing unauthorized is built.</p>
      <p>Scope statements written once and never refreshed become museum pieces; teams plan against the actual backlog while the statement contradicts reality. "Out of scope" lists protect against named exclusions but miss adjacent unspoken expectations (NFRs, interoperability, accessibility, data migration). Acceptance criteria written in business language fail at handoff to engineering; they need testable assertions or they breed disputes. LLMs given vague scope statements happily produce confident WBS hallucinations; garbage in, confidently elaborated garbage out. Scope baseline locked too early traps the project in obsolete decisions; balance with disciplined change control. Gold plating is hard to detect from documentation alone — it shows up as features in the PR that nobody asked for. Scope creep blame culture replaces scope control discipline; the fix is process, not finger pointing. Requirements traceability matrices (RTMs) require continuous maintenance; abandoned RTMs are worse than no RTM.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Fixed-price or fixed-scope contracts where scope creep damages margin.</item>
        <item>Regulated programs (medical, finance, government) where scope is part of compliance evidence.</item>
        <item>Multi-vendor programs where contracted scope per vendor must compose into one deliverable.</item>
        <item>Strategic transformations (ERP, CRM, cloud migration) needing formal scope statement + WBS + validated deliverables.</item>
        <item>Projects showing scope creep symptoms: repeated re-baselining, "while you're in there" requests, confused acceptance criteria.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF startups iterating on hypotheses — strict scope control kills learning.</item>
        <item>Internal R&amp;D or discovery sprints — locking scope before learning is anti-pattern.</item>
        <item>Pure agile teams with continuous discovery — backlog refinement replaces scope statements.</item>
        <item>One-person side projects — scope statement is overhead.</item>
        <item>When the root problem is unclear requirements or absent stakeholders; fix those first.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="scope-types">
      <p>Distinguish product scope (features and functions) from project scope (work required to deliver them); confusion between the two creates phantom deliverables. A team that conflates the two may build the right product but omit required project work (testing, migration, training), or track project tasks as if they were product requirements.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Distinguish product scope (features and functions) from project scope (work required to deliver them); confusion between the two creates phantom deliverables.</statement>
        <rationale>A team that conflates the two may build the right product but omit required project work (testing, migration, training), or track project tasks as if they were product requirements.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Core terms every PM must apply consistently:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Product Scope — features and functions of the product being delivered.</item>
        <item>Project Scope — all work required to deliver the product scope, including PM, testing, documentation, migration.</item>
        <item>Scope Baseline — the approved scope statement + WBS + WBS dictionary; the reference against which all changes are measured.</item>
        <item>Scope Creep — uncontrolled expansion of scope without formal change-control approval; the primary cause of budget and schedule overrun.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="requirement-types">
      <p>Classify every requirement at collection time to ensure completeness:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Business requirements — why the project exists (e.g., increase revenue 20%).</item>
        <item>Stakeholder requirements — what stakeholders need (e.g., executive dashboard).</item>
        <item>Solution / functional requirements — capabilities the system must have.</item>
        <item>Transition requirements — what is needed to move from current to future state (data migration, training).</item>
        <item>Non-functional requirements — performance, security, usability constraints.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Collect all five requirement types before closing the scope statement; missing transition requirements are the most common hidden scope.</statement>
        <rationale>Transition work (data migration, staff training, parallel-run periods) is often scoped out by accident, then absorbed mid-project as "of course that was included."</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="moscow-prioritization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply MoSCoW (Must/Should/Could/Won't) to all requirements at elicitation; rejecting nothing is committing to everything.</statement>
        <rationale>Unlabeled requirements are implicitly "Must", which makes every requirement equally non-negotiable and prevents meaningful trade-off conversations when scope pressure arrives.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Must — required for the release to be viable; failure to deliver = project failure.</item>
        <item>Should — high value but workable without; defer to next iteration if needed.</item>
        <item>Could — nice to have; include only if time and budget allow.</item>
        <item>Won't — explicitly excluded from this release; documented to prevent re-entry.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="step-1-collect-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use at least two elicitation techniques per stakeholder group; interviews alone miss tacit knowledge that workshops and observation surface.</statement>
        <rationale>Each technique reaches different requirement types: interviews uncover explicit needs, observation reveals unstated workflows, prototyping exposes gaps in stated requirements.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Interviews — one-on-one to surface individual needs and constraints.</item>
        <item>Workshops — cross-functional groups resolve conflicts and surface interdependencies.</item>
        <item>Observation — watching users perform tasks reveals requirements they cannot articulate.</item>
        <item>Questionnaires — scale across many stakeholders; good for quantitative priorities.</item>
        <item>Prototyping — trigger concrete feedback on gaps and misunderstandings.</item>
        <item>Document analysis — extract requirements from existing systems, contracts, regulations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-define-scope">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every scope statement must include an explicit "Out of Scope" section; if it is not listed as excluded, stakeholders will assume it is included.</statement>
        <rationale>Disputes at project end almost always involve something absent from the scope statement but also absent from the exclusions list — ambiguity defaults to "included" in client interpretation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>A complete scope statement contains: objectives (measurable), product scope description, deliverables with acceptance criteria, explicit exclusions, constraints, and assumptions.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-validate-scope">
      <rule>
        <statement>Obtain formal written acceptance for each deliverable against pre-agreed acceptance criteria before moving to the next phase; verbal acceptance is not acceptance.</statement>
        <rationale>Verbal sign-off degrades with time — stakeholders forget what they approved and scope disputes become "he said / she said" with no documentary evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Deliverable formally accepted: written acceptance form with criteria checked, reviewer name, date, signature. Stored in project document repository.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>PM emails "looks good to me" after a demo. No criteria checked, no named reviewer. Client later denies acceptance.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="step-4-control-scope">
      <rule>
        <statement>Route every scope change through the formal change-control process before any work begins; informal "small" changes are how projects absorb 30% of unplanned work.</statement>
        <rationale>Six small changes each consuming two days equals 12 unplanned days — equivalent to a major change that would have required CCB approval. The aggregation is invisible without the register.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Monitor scope baseline weekly against actual deliverables and WBS.</item>
        <item>Evaluate every change request for scope, schedule, cost, and risk impact.</item>
        <item>Update scope documents only after formal approval.</item>
        <item>Communicate all approved changes to the full team before implementation.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="requirements-traceability">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every requirement must trace to design, build, test, and acceptance evidence; 100% RTM coverage is a release gate, not a nice-to-have.</statement>
        <rationale>RTM coverage is the only mechanism that prevents requirements from being dropped silently during delivery — coverage gaps are acceptance risk made visible before go-live.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Maintaining the RTM only at project start and never updating it during delivery.</description>
        <reason>An abandoned RTM creates a false sense of coverage; gaps accumulate invisibly and surface as acceptance failures or post-launch defects.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="scope-creep-prevention">
      <rule>
        <statement>Pair every approved scope change with a cost and schedule re-estimate in the same change request; reject standalone scope deltas that arrive without impact analysis.</statement>
        <rationale>Scope without impact analysis is a blank check; teams accept scope and absorb the cost silently, which destroys schedule and budget discipline.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a scope creep retro monthly: review accepted "small" changes, count cumulative days added, present the aggregate to the sponsor.</statement>
        <rationale>Small changes are invisible individually; aggregating them monthly makes the drift visible and creates a natural escalation trigger before it becomes a crisis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>When declining a scope request, offer an alternative (next phase, separate project) and document the decision; "no" with no alternative breeds work-arounds.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholders who are rejected without alternatives find informal channels to get their request implemented anyway, bypassing scope control entirely.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="acceptance-criteria-quality">
      <rule>
        <statement>Write acceptance criteria as testable assertions in Given/When/Then form, or as explicit numeric thresholds; reject criteria that are not independently verifiable.</statement>
        <rationale>Narrative criteria ("the system should be fast") produce acceptance disputes; Gherkin or numeric criteria produce pass/fail verdicts that both parties can measure independently.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Acceptance criterion: "The search should return relevant results quickly." — Not testable; "relevant" and "quickly" are undefined.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Acceptance criterion: "Given a catalog of 10,000 products, when a user submits a search query, then results appear within 2 seconds and the top result matches the query keyword." — Independently verifiable.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-scope-guard">
      <rule>
        <statement>Scope baseline lives in version-controlled YAML (scope/baseline.yaml); CODEOWNERS restricts direct edits to the sponsor; every baseline change requires an approved change-request ID in the commit message.</statement>
        <rationale>Wiki-hosted scope documents have no diff history and no access control; git-tracked YAML makes changes auditable, and CODEOWNERS makes unauthorized edits impossible.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>A scope-guard agent reviews PRs and new tickets against the WBS baseline and emits a verdict (in_scope / out_of_scope / ambiguous / gold_plating); humans merge — the agent never auto-approves.</statement>
        <rationale>Agent verdicts remove routine triage labor; the human-in-loop on merge ensures political and contextual judgment is applied before scope boundaries are crossed.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Locking scope baseline too early without adequate stakeholder validation, then defending it against legitimate clarifications.</description>
        <reason>Premature baseline lock traps the project in obsolete decisions; balance with disciplined change control that distinguishes clarifications (no cost/schedule impact) from scope additions (require approval).</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Gold plating — developers adding unrequested features to "improve" the product.</description>
        <reason>Gold plating consumes contingency, delays tested deliverables, and introduces unreviewed scope that may fail acceptance or create downstream support burden.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Scope is encoded as a typed scope/baseline.yaml (objectives, deliverables with acceptance criteria, in_scope, out_of_scope, constraints, assumptions, risks) plus scope/wbs.yaml and scope/rtm.yaml (requirements traceability). Subagents enforce the baseline: a scope-guard agent reviews PRs / stories against the WBS, flagging work-not-in-WBS or WBS-items-without-implementation. A change-impact agent activates whenever a scope-affecting issue is filed, producing impact analysis for the change-control board. Acceptance criteria are stored as machine-readable Gherkin or rule lists wherever possible.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-sdd-executor-agent (drives scope work as SDD tasks: TASK_baseline_scope, TASK_wbs_v1, TASK_rtm_baseline, TASK_validate_deliverable_NN). Custom scope-guard-agent (sonnet) — given a PR / new ticket, validates against WBS and scope baseline; flags out-of-scope, ambiguous-scope, or unmapped-to-WBS work. Custom acceptance-author-agent (sonnet) — converts narrative deliverables to testable Gherkin acceptance criteria with explicit boundary conditions. Custom rtm-updater-agent (sonnet) — for each requirement, traces to design / build / test / acceptance evidence; outputs RTM coverage report (% covered, % verified, % gaps). Custom creep-detector-agent (sonnet) — scans recent commits, tickets, and Slack threads for emerging scope creep signals (recurring "small" additions, "while you're in there" requests). Custom validation-prep-agent (haiku) — given an upcoming sign-off, prepares evidence packet matching deliverable acceptance criteria.</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern: You are scope-guard. Inputs: PR diff / new ticket, scope-baseline.yaml, wbs.yaml. Emit STRICT JSON: { "verdict": "in_scope|out_of_scope|ambiguous|gold_plating", "wbs_match": "&lt;wbs_id&gt;|none", "deliverable_match": "&lt;id&gt;|none", "rationale": "&lt;= 2 sentences", "evidence_quotes": ["from baseline or PR"], "next_step": "merge|change_request|reject|clarify_with_&lt;role&gt;" }. Rules: do not infer scope from intent; require explicit baseline match. gold_plating verdict requires an unrequested-feature line in the diff.</p>
      <p>Acceptance criteria authoring prompt: Convert deliverable description to Gherkin scenarios with Given/When/Then and explicit Examples table where parameterizable. Reject any criterion that is not testable.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: git + git tag baseline-vN (version-control scope baseline; tag locks), yq / jq (patch baseline.yaml, wbs.yaml, rtm.yaml), mermaid-cli / mmdc (render WBS tree, RTM matrix), pandoc (render scope statement to PDF/DOCX for sign-off), behave / cucumber / pytest-bdd (run executable acceptance criteria), pre-commit (block scope edits without change-request reference / sponsor approval), gh / glab (mirror change requests as PRs against scope/baseline.yaml), csvkit (slice large RTM exports), markdownlint (enforce structure on scope/baseline.md).</p>
      <p>Services &amp; apps: Jira / Linear / Azure DevOps (SaaS, REST + JQL/GraphQL, backlog of in-scope work; epic ↔ WBS mapping). Polarion / Jama / DOORS (SaaS / on-prem, REST/OSLC, enterprise requirements + RTM for regulated domains). Notion / Confluence / SharePoint (SaaS, REST, scope statement host; weak typing — validate on commit). ProductBoard / Aha! (SaaS, REST, product roadmap + scope intent; agents read, do not write). ReqSuite / Modern Requirements (SaaS, REST, lighter alternative to Polarion). Smartsheet (SaaS, REST, scope + WBS in single sheet for SMB). GitHub Projects / GitLab Epics (SaaS, REST/GraphQL, lightweight scope tracking for engineering-led programs). Cucumber Studio / Xray BDD (SaaS, REST, hosted Gherkin acceptance criteria + execution linkage). TestRail / Zephyr (SaaS, REST, validation evidence).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Scope baseline lives in git, not a wiki; tag baseline locks (baseline-v1); CODEOWNERS = sponsor on scope/. Always include explicit out-of-scope list — "if it's not listed, it might be in" loses every dispute. Acceptance criteria are testable assertions, not narrative; convert to Gherkin or executable rules wherever possible. RTM coverage is a release gate: 100% of requirements must trace to design + test + acceptance evidence before sign-off. Constraints and assumptions are first-class — surfacing them prevents the disputes that scope statements were supposed to resolve. Distinguish product scope (features) from project scope (work) — confusion between the two creates phantom deliverables. Pair every scope change with cost + schedule re-estimate in the same change request; reject standalone scope deltas. Use MoSCoW prioritization on requirements (Must/Should/Could/Won't); rejecting nothing means committing to everything. Run a scope creep retro monthly — review accepted "small" changes and quantify cumulative drift. "Saying no" is a process, not an attitude; offer alternatives (next phase, separate project) and document the decision.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLMs hallucinate scope based on plausibility; require baseline matches and reject "scope inferred from intent". Agents writing acceptance criteria default to vague pass/fail; force Gherkin Given/When/Then with explicit Examples tables. RTM updaters silently re-link evidence to wrong requirement when IDs are similar; always require unique stable IDs and exact-match linking. Gold plating detection is fragile via diff alone; pair with feature-flag review and product-owner sign-off. Auto-merging in-scope verdicts removes critical human judgment; agent emits verdict, human merges. Scope baselines edited mid-CR break audits; protect with branch protection and require approved CR ID in commit message. Stakeholder-specific scope ("just for the CFO dashboard") creates hidden scope; force enumeration in baseline. Agents reading legacy requirements docs accept ambiguity rather than flagging it; force the agent to emit an ambiguity_log. Long context: large RTMs (&gt;500 reqs) blow the prompt; partition by feature area and operate on slices. Human-in-the-loop checkpoints (mandatory): baseline lock, baseline change, gold-plating verdicts, deliverable validation/sign-off, RTM gap closure decisions.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/requirements-doc.md" purpose="Requirements documentation template (business, stakeholder, functional, non-functional)."/>
      <template path="templates/scope-statement.md" purpose="Project scope statement template with approval block."/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/rtm_coverage.py" purpose="Audit RTM YAML for design/build/test/accept coverage; exit non-zero on gaps."/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/foundational/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/iiba-babok-guide/"/>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow_method"/>
      <ref slug="work-breakdown-structure"/>
      <ref slug="wbs-creation"/>
      <ref slug="change-control"/>
      <ref slug="requirements-documentation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
