<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="EV for Fixed-Bid Outsource Core Rules">
  <summary>The two-ledger discipline that lets a fixed-bid PM track margin without losing the client-facing scope-completion view.</summary>
  <section title="Two-ledger model">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Run two parallel ledgers per engagement: ledger-A "client scope" records PV-S (planned scope value), EV-S (scoped value earned), no AC because the client price is fixed; ledger-B "vendor margin" records PV-C (planned internal cost), EV-C (cost-budget earned proportional to EV-S), AC-C (actual internal labour cost). SPI is computed once (EV-S/PV-S); CPI is computed only on ledger B (EV-C/AC-C).</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing scope and margin into one ledger hides the failure mode the variant exists to catch: scope can be 100% complete on time while margin is destroyed. Two ledgers separate "did we deliver" from "did we earn".</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Work packages are sized at 1-5% of the total scope value each. Larger packages hide partial-completion noise; smaller packages create overhead without earning fidelity. Engagements with too-large WBS rebalance before ledger-B rollout.</statement>
      <rationale>Earned-value at sub-percent granularity becomes accounting; at ≥10% it becomes binary (done/not-done). The 1-5% band is where the curves remain informative without drowning the PM in updates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Change requests are recorded as ledger-A scope deltas at the client-approved price (PV-S adjusts, the locked total adjusts) AND ledger-B cost-budget deltas at the internally-estimated cost (PV-C adjusts). The two deltas must be approved together; one-side-only updates are forbidden and rejected by the tracker.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-side change updates are the most common cause of mid-engagement margin surprise — scope grows on the client side, cost-budget never grows on the vendor side, AC eventually catches up and the margin disappears silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Three early-warning metrics are computed weekly and trigger documented actions: (1) CPI-C &lt; 0.85 → margin-recovery plan within 7 days; (2) SPI-S &lt; 0.85 → scope or schedule re-plan within 7 days; (3) cumulative AC-C &gt; 60% with EV-C &lt; 50% at midpoint → executive escalation. Each metric has a named owner.</statement>
      <rationale>Without thresholds and named owners the metrics decay into a dashboard nobody acts on. Documented thresholds plus owners convert numbers into routed work.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>At engagement close the two ledgers reconcile in a single closure record: ledger-A reports scope completion (% of contracted value delivered); ledger-B reports realised margin (contracted revenue − final AC-C); the variance between PV-C at signature and AC-C at close is decomposed by attributed cause (estimation error, scope creep accepted without CR, productivity, rework). Closure without reconciliation is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale>Without attributed variance the team cannot improve estimates on the next bid; the same margin hole reopens. Forced attribution at close is the only mechanism that feeds the next bid model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Engagement: P4-2026-acme-migration  (fixed bid $180k)
Ledger A (client scope): PV-S=$180k, EV-S=$108k (60% complete), SPI=1.02
Ledger B (vendor margin): PV-C=$135k (budgeted internal cost), EV-C=$81k, AC-C=$93k → CPI-C=0.87
Action: CPI-C < 0.90 → margin-recovery plan: cut 0.5 FTE rework on module X, re-baseline WBS 7-9.
CR-014 approved 2026-05-12: scope +$12k (PV-S → $192k), cost +$8k (PV-C → $143k), both sides recorded same day.
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
SPI: 1.02 ✅
Earned value: $108k of $180k.
(margin status: not tracked)
]]></code>
      <note>One ledger, no margin view, no thresholds — close-out review will discover the margin hole when nothing can be done about it.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
