<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gce-autoscaling Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gce-autoscaling. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The autoscaler's initialization_period (cooldown_period in Terraform) MUST be set greater than the VM startup time plus application warmup time. For applications with initialization &gt; 2 minutes, predictive autoscaling MUST be enabled with OPTIMIZE_AVAILABILITY mode.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">If the cooldown period is shorter than VM startup, the autoscaler observes high CPU on starting VMs and interprets it as demand, triggering additional scale-out when the existing scale-out has not yet registered. This results in over-provisioning proportional to the ratio of startup time to cooldown period.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every autoscaler MUST configure scale_in_control with a time_window_sec of at least 600 seconds (10 minutes) and a max_scaled_in_replicas fixed count or percentage that prevents more than 20% of instances from being removed in that window.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without scale-in controls, a traffic dip lasting 60+ seconds triggers aggressive scale-in. When traffic returns, the reduced fleet is undersized and latency rises while the autoscaler re-scales out. The 10-minute window smooths short traffic dips and prevents the flapping pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production autoscalers MUST set min_replicas to at least 1 for single-zone MIGs and at least 3 for regional MIGs. max_replicas MUST be set with cost awareness: calculate the maximum expected load at 60% CPU utilization to derive max_replicas, then add a 20% safety margin.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">min_replicas = 0 causes a cold-start gap on every scale-to-zero event. max_replicas without a ceiling risks runaway scaling from a metric misconfiguration or DDoS event; the ceiling limits financial blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
