<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="gce-autoscaling Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for gce-autoscaling as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Setting the autoscaler cooldown period shorter than the VM startup time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Starting VMs consume high CPU during initialization. A short cooldown causes the autoscaler to observe high CPU across the fleet and issue additional scale-out before the in-progress scale-out has had time to reduce the average CPU. This produces over-provisioning proportional to (startup_time / cooldown_period).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using only CPU utilization as the autoscaling signal for an HTTP(S) frontend behind a load balancer.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CPU does not accurately reflect request rate for I/O-bound or network-bound services. A service can be CPU-idle while being request-saturated. Use load_balancing_utilization or a custom RPS metric as the primary signal for HTTP frontends.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Setting target CPU utilization above 80% for production autoscaling.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>At 80-90% utilization there is no headroom for traffic spikes. By the time the autoscaler decides to scale out (after observing sustained high CPU), latency has already spiked. Target 60% to preserve 40% spike headroom; this is the documented GCP recommendation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
