<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="design-docs-big-tech">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd</domain>
    <summary>Design-document practices from Google, Amazon, Uber, Spotify, Stripe, Meta, Microsoft. When to write, trigger rules, LLM assistance limits, common mistakes.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>design-docs</tag>
      <tag>rfc</tag>
      <tag>architecture</tag>
      <tag>big-tech</tag>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Design Docs at Big Tech Companies</title>

    <summary>Reference survey of design-document practices at Google, Amazon, Uber, Spotify, Stripe, Netflix, Microsoft, Airbnb, Shopify, and Atlassian. Covers document names (RFC, ERD, 6-Pager, ADR), review formats, and the trigger rules for when a doc is required vs. optional. The core rule: write before coding; match document weight to change scope; always include "do nothing" as an alternative.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Design docs serve four purposes: early issue identification (cheap to fix on paper), consensus building, knowledge sharing, and onboarding. Without them, architecture decisions are re-litigated repeatedly and new engineers cannot reconstruct intent. LLMs excel at generating doc outlines and alternatives sections but cannot supply organizational history or system-specific context — those require human authorship.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Choosing a design doc format before starting a cross-team feature or architecture change</item>
        <item>Adapting an RFC/ERD process to your team's async culture and scale</item>
        <item>Using an LLM to draft initial structure from requirements (outlines and alternatives)</item>
        <item>Onboarding new engineers via existing design docs as primary reference material</item>
        <item>Deciding whether a change needs a 1-pager, full RFC, or no doc at all</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bug fixes and features under 2 days — skip the doc, write code</item>
        <item>Purely internal team decisions with no cross-team impact</item>
        <item>When organizational context, team politics, or proprietary system details are critical — LLMs cannot supply these</item>
        <item>Post-implementation documentation — design docs must precede coding to be useful</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="company-overview">
      <p>Design documents serve four universal purposes: early issue identification (cheap to fix on paper), consensus building, knowledge sharing, and onboarding. Each company developed its own format based on culture and scale.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Google: informal Google Doc, inline comments, emphasis on "why" and trade-offs, always include "do nothing" alternative</item>
        <item>Amazon: 6-Pager (narrative prose, no bullets, max 6 pages) + PR-FAQ (press release first, then FAQ); silent 20-25 min read at meeting start; "working backwards" from customer</item>
        <item>Uber: RFC evolved to tiered ERD — Lightweight (team), Standard (cross-team), Heavyweight (org-wide); mailing list circulation with named approvers</item>
        <item>Spotify: two-stage — RFC for consensus (1-3 weeks open), ADR for recording the decision; break large RFCs into big-picture + focused sub-RFCs</item>
        <item>Stripe: strong written culture; RFCs for any decision needing cross-team alignment; high-bar async review; mentorship integrated</item>
        <item>Meta/Facebook: notably less formal — no company-wide RFC process; 1-pagers optional; compensates with high talent bar and long tenures. Not recommended for most teams.</item>
        <item>Microsoft: FDD (functional) + TDD (technical) integrated with Security Development Lifecycle (SDL); security is first-class, not afterthought</item>
        <item>Shopify: GitHub PR-based RFC with explicit review deadline; deadline-driven consensus works well with agent-drafted PRs</item>
        <item>Atlassian: Confluence-based, triad model (eng/PM/design), validated against architecture principles</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="google-design-docs">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always include "do nothing" as Alternative 1 in the alternatives section.</statement>
        <rationale>Sometimes the best decision is not to build. Forcing this option ensures the author justifies why building is worth the cost and risk.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Process: author writes → shares with close collaborators → wider review → optional formal meeting → doc becomes historical artifact. No strict format, but common structure has emerged: Context and Scope, Goals and Non-Goals, Overview, Detailed Design, Alternatives Considered, Cross-cutting Concerns.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="amazon-6-pager-and-pr-faq">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Write in narrative prose, no bullet points, maximum 6 pages; supporting data goes in an unlimited appendix.</statement>
        <rationale>Dense prose forces the author to synthesize; bullets permit loose thinking. Every word must carry information.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>PR-FAQ starts with a hypothetical press release announcing the finished product, then a FAQ document adding detail. This forces customer-centric thinking from day one. Meeting process: printed copies distributed, 20-25 minutes silent reading, discussion, printouts with handwritten notes returned to author.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="uber-tiered-erd">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use the lightest template that fits the change scope; do not over-engineer the process.</statement>
        <rationale>Uber evolved from simple RFCs to tiered ERDs precisely because heavyweight process for lightweight changes slows teams without adding value.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Lightweight: team-only changes, mini RFC, team lead approver</item>
        <item>Standard: cross-team impact, full RFC, multiple team approvers</item>
        <item>Heavyweight: org/company-wide, detailed ERD, principal engineers</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="spotify-rfc-and-adr-two-stage">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Separate the RFC (consensus-reaching) from the ADR (decision-recording); do not conflate the two jobs in one document.</statement>
        <rationale>An RFC trying to reach consensus and record the decision simultaneously produces a document that does neither well. The RFC is collaborative and iterative; the ADR is the immutable record.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="when-to-write">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Match document weight to change scope; write before coding, never after.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-implementation documentation defeats the purpose — design docs exist to catch issues when changes are still cheap.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Bug fix: no doc needed</item>
        <item>Small feature (1-2 days): optional 1-pager, team only</item>
        <item>Medium feature (1-2 weeks): standard design doc, team + stakeholders</item>
        <item>Large feature (1+ month): detailed RFC, cross-team review</item>
        <item>Architecture change: RFC + ADR, company-wide</item>
        <item>New service or system: full design doc, architecture review</item>
        <item>API changes affecting consumers: yes</item>
        <item>Database schema changes: yes</item>
        <item>Security-sensitive changes: yes</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-assistance-effectiveness">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use LLMs for initial structure, alternative brainstorming, and prose refinement; require human validation for every technical accuracy claim.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs generate plausible but technically inaccurate design docs when system-specific context is absent. Technical accuracy is the one dimension where LLM effectiveness is Low-Medium.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>High LLM effectiveness: initial structure from requirements, prose refinement, alternative brainstorming</item>
        <item>Medium-High: risk identification, surface edge cases</item>
        <item>Low-Medium: technical accuracy (requires expert validation)</item>
        <item>Not applicable: organizational context, team history, stakeholder preferences, proprietary technology</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Limit LLM-generated alternatives to 2-3 concrete options; agents over-generate when not constrained.</statement>
        <rationale>5+ alternatives overwhelm reviewers and dilute focus. The value is in comparing 2-3 realistic options, not exhaustively listing all possibilities.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using the design doc as a spec — conflating "why/how" with "what".</description>
        <reason>Design doc answers HOW; spec answers WHAT. Mixing them produces a document that does neither well and forces readers to untangle intent from implementation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No alternatives section — only the chosen solution is documented.</description>
        <reason>Reviewers question judgment when they cannot see what was rejected. Future engineers re-litigate the decision because the reasoning is invisible.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Writing the design doc after implementation begins.</description>
        <reason>Defeats the primary purpose. Architectural issues caught post-implementation cost orders of magnitude more to fix than issues caught at the design stage.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Too many approvers — more than 10 participants.</description>
        <reason>Consensus gridlock; the review process takes longer than the implementation. Google and Amazon both observe this threshold empirically.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No "do nothing" option in alternatives.</description>
        <reason>Without the baseline, reviewers always ask "why not just leave it as is?" Include it to pre-empt the question and force the author to justify the build decision.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/prompt-design-doc.txt" purpose="LLM prompts for generating design doc skeleton, architecture decisions, design review, and code generation"/>
    </templates>

  </content>
</methodology>
