<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Executive Stakeholder Demo Narrative Frame Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Executive Stakeholder Demo Narrative Frame must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Message has: audience, primary call-to-action, falsifier, and timestamp. Messages without an audience field are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Comms-design practice (Andy Crouch, Strong &amp; Weak, 2016)">broadcast-to-everyone is broadcast-to-no-one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drafts go through one review pass before send. Sent messages are archived with their version and the audience that received them.</statement>
      <rationale source="Press-release / comms QA practice from comms-management literature">Press-release / comms QA practice from comms-management literature.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Templates are filled, never invented from scratch each time. Template drift (variant-per-sender) is the silent death of comms ops.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brand-voice practice from style-guide discipline">A bespoke deck per demo doubles prep time AND lets the narrative drift between calls. Filling the canonical demo narrative template preserves brand voice and keeps the story arc consistent across stakeholders.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-30min-timebox" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Executive demos MUST be timeboxed to 30 minutes and rehearsed end-to-end at least once within 48 hours of the live run. Demos lacking a rehearsal record are flagged in the pre-flight checklist; demos that overrun the timebox are marked as drift in the post-demo log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Executive comms practice">VP/SVP attention is the scarcest resource; running past the timebox is read as "the speaker does not respect my time" and forfeits the meeting's primary commitment. Rehearsal catches the demo's biggest defect — implicit assumptions only the operator understood — before the live audience does.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-pre-demo-signed-brief" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every demo MUST ship with a one-page pre-demo brief signed (digitally or otherwise) by the sponsoring stakeholder ≥24 hours before the live run. The brief names: audience seniority, the single business outcome the demo seeks, the one decision being asked for, and the post-demo handoff. Demos without a signed brief are blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Executive comms practice / B2B demo research">A live demo without a signed brief routinely surprises the sponsor mid-run ("I didn't know we were asking for budget today"); the signed brief converts the demo from theatre into a forecastable decision moment with an explicit ask and explicit hand-off.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the Applies-If preconditions fail OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or to no methodology at all).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application of a methodology produces worse artefacts than no methodology at all because downstream consumers trust the schema and act on bad data. The skip-record makes the non-application traceable so future audits can detect drift.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored application">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Trigger: Client demo prep + run
Artefact: structured output meeting the contract in content/02-output-contract.xml
Evidence: ≥1 named source per rule (URL, ticket, transcript_id)
Decision: downstream consumer can act without re-deriving reasoning
]]></code>
      <note>Demonstrates the closed loop the methodology creates — trigger → artefact → decision — with auditability at each step.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored application">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Trigger: 'we should do this thing'
Artefact: prose paragraph, no schema
Evidence: 'industry best practice'
Decision: ambiguous — every reader interprets differently
]]></code>
      <note>Each ambiguity above is a failure mode catalogued in content/03-failure-modes.xml. The methodology exists to prevent exactly this shape.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
