<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PH Launch Day Runbook Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules every PH Launch Day Runbook application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-ph-launches-reset" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>PH launches reset at 00:01 PT — anchor every step in the runbook to PT and convert to local; missing the PT reset by even 30 minutes shifts you out of the morning hunter wave and is a launch-killer.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-pre-stage-two" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pre-stage two artifacts the night before: a maker's comment (≤280 chars, includes "I'll be here all day answering questions") and a 30-second product video pinned to the listing — listings without both fall ≥30% in attention on average.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-triage-incoming-comments" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Triage incoming comments into 4 classes within 10 minutes of receipt: (a) ASK = product/use-case question → reply with concrete answer + CTA, (b) PRAISE = thank + add a use-case nudge, (c) CRITIQUE = thank + acknowledge + name your next iteration, (d) SPAM = ignore; comments older than 10 minutes drop in algo weight.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-reply-with-a" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reply with a unique sentence on every comment — never copy/paste; PH downranks visibly templated replies, and the comment thread is your sales surface for 14 hours.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-drive-every-comment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Drive every comment toward one ask: signup, demo booking, or DM; threads without a CTA convert ≤1%, threads with a single clear CTA convert 6-12% per typical indie launch.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-schedule-three-energy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Schedule three energy refuels at +6h, +10h, +14h: 20-minute breaks with food, water, and no screens; founders who skip these crash at hour 12 and miss the EU evening wave.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-log-every-signup" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Log every signup, demo, and meaningful conversation in a launch-day sheet with timestamp and source comment; this is the input for the post-launch drip and the launch retrospective — without the log, the launch is unmeasurable.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Carries forward from v1 source; preserve until revised in next pass.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
