<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules">
  <rule testable="true">PH launches reset at 00:01 PT — anchor every step in the runbook to PT and convert to local; missing the PT reset by even 30 minutes shifts you out of the morning hunter wave and is a launch-killer.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Pre-stage two artifacts the night before: a maker's comment (≤280 chars, includes "I'll be here all day answering questions") and a 30-second product video pinned to the listing — listings without both fall ≥30% in attention on average.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Triage incoming comments into 4 classes within 10 minutes of receipt: (a) ASK = product/use-case question → reply with concrete answer + CTA, (b) PRAISE = thank + add a use-case nudge, (c) CRITIQUE = thank + acknowledge + name your next iteration, (d) SPAM = ignore; comments older than 10 minutes drop in algo weight.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Reply with a unique sentence on every comment — never copy/paste; PH downranks visibly templated replies, and the comment thread is your sales surface for 14 hours.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Drive every comment toward one ask: signup, demo booking, or DM; threads without a CTA convert ≤1%, threads with a single clear CTA convert 6-12% per typical indie launch.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Schedule three energy refuels at +6h, +10h, +14h: 20-minute breaks with food, water, and no screens; founders who skip these crash at hour 12 and miss the EU evening wave.</rule>
  <rule testable="true">Log every signup, demo, and meaningful conversation in a launch-day sheet with timestamp and source comment; this is the input for the post-launch drip and the launch retrospective — without the log, the launch is unmeasurable.</rule>
  <example>Indie SaaS launches "Stripely". 00:01 PT submit + maker's comment pre-staged. 00:05 PT first hunter upvote. 00:30 PT comment from @user1 asking about Stripe Tax — ASK class, reply at 00:32 with concrete answer + signup link, logged in sheet as signup-source-comment-3. 06:00 PT: first refuel break, 20 min. By 14:00 PT: 312 upvotes, 41 comments handled (avg reply 4 minutes), 84 signups logged with comment-source attribution, #2 of day at midnight. Post-launch drip seeded from the 41 commenters.</example>
</text>
