<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-advanced-sections" title="Design Doc Advanced Sections Rules">
  <summary>Rules and structure for each advanced section in a design document: component hierarchy, dependencies, security, performance, testing, and migration.</summary>

  <section title="Component Hierarchy (Frontend Only)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document component hierarchy as a tree (no ASCII art diagrams). Include a TypeScript interface definition for each component's props.</statement>
      <rationale>Props interfaces become the source of truth — implementation copies from design, not the reverse. Missing interfaces lead to inconsistent prop shapes across components.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Skip this section entirely for pure backend features.</statement>
      <rationale>Component hierarchy adds no value when there is no UI to design.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>AuthLayout → RegisterForm (props: onSuccess, onError?) → EmailInput, PasswordInput, PasswordStrengthMeter, SubmitButton. Each component has a TypeScript interface in the design doc before implementation begins.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>ASCII art component tree with box-drawing characters.</description>
      <reason>Violates the "no ASCII art" documentation convention and is not parseable by agents.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Dependency Table">
    <rule>
      <statement>List every new package and external service with: name, version (pinned range), purpose, license, and whether a fallback exists for local development.</statement>
      <rationale>Undocumented dependencies are discovered at build time or in production. License tracking is a legal requirement for enterprise deployments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Package: bcrypt ^5.1.0 | Purpose: password hashing | License: MIT | Local fallback: N/A (required). External service: SendGrid | Purpose: email delivery | Required: Yes | Local fallback: log to console in dev.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Mitigations Table">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include a security table with columns: Concern | Mitigation | AD Reference. Every mitigation must reference a specific AD-X architectural decision. Cover at minimum: password storage, XSS, CSRF, SQL injection, and rate limiting.</statement>
      <rationale>Security mitigations without AD references are not traceable — code reviewers cannot verify that the mitigation was actually implemented as designed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use only NFR-X security values from spec.md for targets (e.g., "bcrypt cost 12"). Never invent security parameters.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents default to generic "use bcrypt" without cost factor. The cost factor is a tunable performance/security tradeoff that must be specified in the spec.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Security section that says "use best practices for authentication".</description>
      <reason>Not traceable, not implementable, not reviewable. Every mitigation needs a specific technique and an AD reference.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Performance Considerations Table">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each performance concern: specify the concern, strategy, target (taken directly from NFR-X in spec.md), and AD reference. Never invent target numbers — if NFR is absent, write "TBD — NFR required".</statement>
      <rationale>Agents invent latency targets when spec NFRs are absent. Invented targets create false confidence and cannot be used as acceptance criteria.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Login latency | connection pooling | &lt; 500ms p95 (from NFR-001) | AD-004. Token validation | JWT stateless | &lt; 10ms (from NFR-002) | AD-002.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Test Pyramid">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define three test layers: unit (coverage % target), integration (list all API endpoints to test with happy path and error path), E2E (list critical user flows, not just happy paths). Coverage targets must be project constants from constitution.md.</statement>
      <rationale>E2E suites that cover only happy paths miss the highest-impact failure modes. Integration tests with only happy paths leave error handling unverified.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>List specific test file paths for at least the unit layer. Agents cannot generate tests without knowing where they go.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague "write tests" instructions produce tests in arbitrary locations that break CI path configuration.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Migration Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include a migration section only when design.md lists schema changes (new tables, altered columns, index changes). If no schema changes exist, explicitly state "No migration required".</statement>
      <rationale>Agents frequently generate boilerplate migration sections even when no schema changes exist. Explicit "not applicable" prevents confusion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Migration strategy must include: rollout plan (staged percentages or feature flag), rollback procedure (step-by-step), and backward compatibility statement.</statement>
      <rationale>Rollout without rollback is a deployment risk. Backward compatibility statement prevents breaking changes from going unreviewed.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
