<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Design Doc Advanced Patterns Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Design Doc Advanced Patterns. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-trigger-block-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a trigger fires (cross-system, hot-path, security, migration) the matching block is mandatory — not optional.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — design-doc review audits">Optional advanced blocks get skipped under deadline pressure; trigger-driven mandates prevent that.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-sequence-diagram-named-actors" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sequence diagrams name every actor; anonymous boxes (&apos;service A&apos;, &apos;frontend&apos;) are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="PlantUML / Mermaid convention">Anonymous boxes prevent the reviewer from tracing the change against the real architecture.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-capacity-numbers-sourced" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capacity claims cite a source (load test, p95 metric, vendor SLO); &apos;should be fast&apos; is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="SRE Workbook capacity planning">Unsourced capacity claims are guesses; CI cannot regression-check them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-failure-table-mttr-column" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Failure-mode table carries an MTTR column; rows without MTTR are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="FMEA practice">MTTR is the metric that ranks failure modes by recovery cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-migration-rollback-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Migration playbook specifies a rollback budget in minutes that fits the ops SLO.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — ops on-call">Without a budget, mid-migration rollback decisions become panic-driven.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-base-doc-link" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every advanced block links back to the matching section in the base design doc.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience — doc navigation">Free-floating advanced blocks become orphaned references during reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md &quot;Applies If&quot; do not all hold, OR any &quot;Skip If&quot; disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-design-doc-advanced-patterns.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
