<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-checklist" title="Design Doc Advanced Patterns Checklist">
  <summary>Phase-by-phase checklist and quality gates for each advanced design section.</summary>

  <section title="Prerequisites">
    <list>
      <item>spec.md with FR-X and NFR-X items is approved (human sign-off exists)</item>
      <item>base design.md with AD-X architectural decisions is present</item>
      <item>constitution.md is accessible for test coverage targets and tech standards</item>
      <item>features/done/ reviewed for similar security or performance patterns to reuse</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Component Hierarchy (skip if no UI)">
    <list>
      <item>Tree structure uses plain indentation — no ASCII art box-drawing characters</item>
      <item>Each component has a TypeScript interface definition (props, optional props marked with ?)</item>
      <item>State management approach is documented (local state, context, store)</item>
      <item>Component behavior documented: validation triggers, loading states, event handlers</item>
      <item>All component file paths specified (e.g., src/components/auth/RegisterForm.tsx)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Dependency Table">
    <list>
      <item>Every new npm/pip/gem package listed with pinned version range</item>
      <item>License noted for each package</item>
      <item>External services listed with Required/Optional and local dev fallback</item>
      <item>No packages added that duplicate existing dependencies (check constitution.md)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Mitigations">
    <list>
      <item>Table columns present: Concern | Mitigation | AD Reference</item>
      <item>Mandatory concerns covered: password storage, XSS, CSRF, SQL injection, rate limiting, input validation</item>
      <item>Every mitigation references a specific AD-X decision</item>
      <item>All security parameters (bcrypt cost, rate limit thresholds) sourced from spec.md NFR-X — none invented</item>
      <item>Domain-specific threats considered (business logic abuse, multi-tenant isolation if applicable)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Performance Considerations">
    <list>
      <item>Table columns present: Concern | Strategy | Target | AD Reference</item>
      <item>Every target value traced to a specific NFR-X from spec.md</item>
      <item>No invented numbers — absent NFR means "TBD — NFR required"</item>
      <item>Strategy column is concrete (e.g., "connection pooling, max 20 connections") not generic (e.g., "use caching")</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Test Pyramid">
    <list>
      <item>Unit layer: coverage target % (from constitution.md), specific test file paths listed</item>
      <item>Integration layer: all API endpoints listed with happy path and at least one error path</item>
      <item>E2E layer: critical flows listed including error flows and edge cases (not only happy paths)</item>
      <item>Mocking strategy documented (which external services are mocked in tests)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Migration Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>If design.md includes no schema changes, write "No migration required" and skip this section. Do not generate boilerplate migration content for greenfield features.</statement>
      <rationale>Boilerplate migration sections confuse implementers and create unnecessary review overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Data migration steps (if applicable): numbered, reversible where possible</item>
      <item>Backward compatibility: explicitly stated as maintained or broken (with migration path)</item>
      <item>Rollout plan: stages with percentages or feature flag names</item>
      <item>Rollback procedure: numbered steps to undo the deployment</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Review Gate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Design review (human) must occur before impl-plan is written. The advanced sections are the primary review surface. No impl-plan authoring until design has human sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale>Advanced sections (security, migrations) contain the highest-risk design decisions. Reviewing them before implementation prevents costly rework.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
