<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-workspace-setup" title="ClickUp Workspace Setup Rules">
  <summary>Rules for ClickUp hierarchy design, ClickApps configuration, custom statuses, and custom fields.</summary>

  <section title="Workspace Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit hierarchy depth to 4 levels: Workspace (organization) → Space (department/team) → Folder (project/initiative) → List (phase/workflow stage). Never create Folders inside Folders — it creates navigation complexity that cannot be displayed in most views.</statement>
      <rationale>Every hierarchy level adds a navigation click. Deeper hierarchies increase onboarding friction and create permission management complexity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Spaces to separate teams with different workflows and permission requirements. Spaces have independent status sets and ClickApp configurations — never share a Space between teams with incompatible workflows.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing teams in one Space forces a single status workflow on all of them. Separate Spaces allow Engineering to use Sprints while Marketing uses a content calendar without conflict.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="ClickApps Configuration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable these ClickApps at workspace level: Custom Fields, Priorities (Urgent/High/Normal/Low), Multiple Assignees. Enable Sprints and Time Tracking at Space level where applicable. Enabling Sprints workspace-wide forces sprint discipline on spaces that do not practice it (e.g., Support).</statement>
      <rationale>Workspace-level ClickApps apply to all Spaces. Space-level ClickApps are opt-in — enabling sprint management only where needed reduces noise elsewhere.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create custom fields at the highest applicable level: Workspace if used everywhere, Space if team-specific, Folder if project-specific. Never create the same field twice at different levels — use the inherited version.</statement>
      <rationale>Duplicate fields at multiple hierarchy levels create data inconsistency when filters aggregate across levels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use dropdown type for Sprint and Component fields — not free text. This prevents typos, enables filtering, and allows automation rules to trigger on specific values.</statement>
      <rationale>Free-text sprint names like "Sprint1", "sprint 1", "Sprint 01" break filters and automation. Dropdowns enforce consistent values.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the total number of visible custom fields per view to 8 or fewer. Archive custom fields that are not actively used.</statement>
      <rationale>Too many fields create cognitive load and slow down task entry. Fields not used in automation or reporting have no value in the main view.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Status Workflow">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the status workflow at Space level, not List level. A consistent status set across all Lists in a Space enables cross-list filtering and automation. Typical development workflow: Backlog → Ready for Dev → In Development → Code Review → QA Testing → Complete / Won't Do.</statement>
      <rationale>Per-List status sets make cross-list "show all In Development tasks" queries impossible. Space-level statuses are queryable across all Folders and Lists.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
