<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-automation-views" title="ClickUp Automation and Views Rules">
  <summary>Rules for automation rule patterns, view configuration, and integration setup in ClickUp.</summary>

  <section title="Automation Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with 3-5 automation rules and add more only as specific manual friction points are identified. Document every automation rule in a team handbook — undocumented automations confuse new team members who observe unexpected behavior.</statement>
      <rationale>Automation bloat creates circular triggers and unexpected state changes. Each rule should solve a confirmed pain point, not a hypothetical one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Test every automation rule on a test task before enabling it in production. Automation loops (rule A triggers rule B which triggers rule A) cause infinite task state changes. Check for circular dependencies before enabling.</statement>
      <rationale>ClickUp automation loops are not automatically detected. They cause task status thrashing and notification spam that is difficult to diagnose after the fact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Automation 1: when status changes to "In Development" → assign from custom field "Developer". Automation 2: when task created in List "Features" → apply task template "Feature Template". Automation 3: when due date arrives AND status not in ["Complete", "Won't Do"] → send email to assignee. These three cover the most common manual steps without creating circular dependencies.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Automation: when status changes to "In Development" → set status to "In Progress". Then: when status changes to "In Progress" → set status to "In Development".</description>
      <reason>Circular automation loop. Task will switch states indefinitely until manually stopped.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Views">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create purpose-specific views rather than general-purpose catch-all views: List view for detailed task management (all fields visible), Board for kanban execution (grouped by status), Gantt for timeline planning (with dependencies), Workload for capacity planning, Dashboard for sprint metrics. Each view should answer a specific question.</statement>
      <rationale>General-purpose views become cluttered. Purpose-specific views load faster (fewer fields) and train team members on which view to use for each workflow step.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Add Workload view whenever Sprint ClickApp is enabled. Workload requires Time Estimates on tasks to show capacity — set time estimates as a required field when Sprints are active.</statement>
      <rationale>Capacity planning without time estimates is guesswork. Workload view is only useful when estimates are populated consistently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Integrations">
    <rule>
      <statement>For GitHub integration: enable branch naming convention "clickup-{task_id}-{task_name}" to create automatic task-to-PR links. Set auto status to "Complete" on PR merge. Store the integration webhook URL in .aidocs/memory/ — it changes when re-authenticated.</statement>
      <rationale>Branch name conventions enable ClickUp to detect linked PRs automatically without manual linking by developers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>For Slack integration: notify on status changes and comment additions, not on every field change. Over-notification causes recipients to mute the channel within days.</statement>
      <rationale>Signal-to-noise ratio is the primary failure mode of PM tool Slack integrations. Scope notifications to meaningful state changes only.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
