<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-outcome-decomposition" title="Outcome Decomposition">
  <summary>Rules for decomposing a business goal into product outcomes, leading indicators, and experiments — the core PM skill that connects roadmap items to measurable business impact.</summary>

  <section title="Decomposition Chain">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decompose business goals in this chain: Business Goal → Product Outcome → Leading Indicator → Experiment. Each layer must be causally plausible, not just correlated.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping layers produces roadmaps where features connect loosely to goals. The chain forces the team to articulate the mechanism: "If we improve onboarding (product outcome), TTV drops (leading indicator), which should reduce churn (business goal)."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define success criteria for each experiment before running it. Statistical significance required for experiments with 1000+ users; practical significance threshold required for smaller samples.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc success criteria are subject to confirmation bias. Pre-defined criteria make the experiment falsifiable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Example Decomposition">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Business goal "increase revenue 20%" decomposed into two product outcomes, each with leading indicators and experiments.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Business Goal: Increase revenue 20%

  Product Outcome 1: Reduce churn from 8% to 5%
    Leading Indicator: NPS improvement (proxy for retention intent)
    Experiments:
      - Onboarding redesign (hypothesis: reduces activation time by 40%)
      - Re-engagement email sequence (hypothesis: 15% win-back rate)
    Success Criteria: defined upfront, statistical significance at p<0.05

  Product Outcome 2: Increase activation rate from 25% to 40%
    Leading Indicator: Time-to-value (TTV) reduction
    Experiments:
      - Guided tour for new users
      - Personalized feature suggestions based on role
    Success Criteria: TTV from 3 days to 1 day, measured on cohorts
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="The PM Role Shift">
    <rule>
      <statement>Present yourself as "architect of impact," not "owner of the roadmap." The roadmap is the artifact; the outcome is the job.</statement>
      <rationale>PMs who identify as roadmap owners defend features. PMs who identify as outcome architects drop features that are not moving the metric and replace them — which is the right behavior.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/outcome-decomposition.md">Outcome decomposition tree template</reference>
</text>
