<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-audience-segmentation" title="Roadmap Audience Segmentation">
  <summary>Stakeholder communication matrix showing what each audience needs from a roadmap artifact and why the same document cannot serve all audiences.</summary>

  <section title="Communication Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Create separate roadmap artifacts for each audience from one source. Never share the same document with all stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale>Engineering needs sprint-level detail and dependencies. Customers need capability descriptions without implementation specifics. The board needs outcome metrics with quarterly targets. Sales needs problem-solution framing with a confidence signal. One document that serves all serves none.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Audience-Specific Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>External / customer-facing roadmaps: use theme-based abstractions, no specific dates — use "H1 2026" or "Coming Soon" horizon labels instead.</statement>
      <rationale>Specific dates become contractual commitments in customers' minds. Abstracted horizons communicate direction without creating support escalations when dates slip.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Board / executive roadmaps: lead with outcome metrics and quarterly targets. Include confidence levels. Do not include feature lists — executives need to know if the product will hit the business goal, not which features ship in Q2.</statement>
      <rationale>Boards are accountable for business outcomes. A feature list answer to a business goal question signals misalignment between product and strategy.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Engineering roadmaps: include outcome targets, confidence levels, sprint-level detail for Now, and options (not THE solution) for Next. Dependencies and blockers must be explicit.</statement>
      <rationale>Engineers who understand the outcome can propose better solutions. Options framing ("we have three approaches to this outcome") produces better technical decisions than feature mandates.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sales roadmaps: lead with the problem being solved, then the solution. Include a confidence signal ("confident", "exploring"). Only include items you can commit to when deals close within 90 days.</statement>
      <rationale>Sales uses roadmaps to close deals. Uncommitted items that end up on sales decks create product commitments the team cannot honor.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
