<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-managing-pressure" title="Managing Roadmap Pressure">
  <summary>Four techniques for responding to stakeholder pressure for specific features or dates while maintaining an outcome-based orientation.</summary>

  <section title="Confidence Levels Instead of Commitments">
    <rule>
      <statement>Replace date commitments with confidence levels (High / Medium / Low / Exploring). When pressed for dates, provide a confidence level plus the conditions that would promote it to "high."</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders accept uncertainty more readily when it is named and bounded. "High confidence for Q2 if discovery completes by end of March" is more credible than a date that will slip silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Options Framing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Present options, not THE solution: "We have three approaches to achieving this outcome. Here are the trade-offs." Then ask the stakeholder to choose based on priorities.</statement>
      <rationale>Options framing positions the PM as a strategic partner, not a feature factory. Stakeholders who choose an option own the trade-off — they are less likely to escalate when the deprioritized option is not built.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Lead with Data">
    <rule>
      <statement>When presenting a priority order, lead with the data and outcome before the "what." "Churn is our top metric risk this quarter; here is why we are prioritizing retention over new features."</statement>
      <rationale>Feature arguments are subjective; metric arguments are objective. Data-led framing shifts the conversation from "I want X" to "will X move the metric?"</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Show the Why Before the What">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure every roadmap presentation: outcome we are targeting → evidence it matters → options we considered → what we chose and why → confidence level. Never start with the feature list.</statement>
      <rationale>Starting with the feature list invites feature negotiation. Starting with the outcome invites metric discussion. The latter produces better decisions faster.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
