<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="schedule-development">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-traditional</domain>
    <summary>A process for converting WBS work packages into a sequenced, resourced, and buffered schedule with an identified critical path using PERT, dependency types, and CCPM-style buffers.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
      <tag>scheduling</tag>
      <tag>critical-path</tag>
      <tag>cpm</tag>
      <tag>pert</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Schedule Development</title>

    <summary>A process for converting WBS work packages into a sequenced, resourced, and buffered schedule with an identified critical path. Use three-point estimation (PERT) for any activity over 5 days, explicit dependency types (FS/SS/FF/SF), and CCPM-style project and feeding buffers. Buffers must be visible and named — never hidden inside individual task estimates.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without critical-path analysis, teams apply equal focus to all tasks and are surprised when non-critical delays cascade. Hidden padding inside task estimates makes buffer management impossible. Three-point estimation forces honest pessimistic scenarios and catches the "optimistic by 30%" bias that causes late projects.</p>
      <p>"Single-point" estimates create false precision; without three-point or Monte Carlo, dates lie. Critical path drifts as work progresses; schedules not refreshed weekly stop reflecting reality. Resource conflicts hide when the plan ignores per-resource capacity (parallel tasks, same person). Padding hidden inside individual estimates → invisible buffers no one can manage. "Optimistic by 30%" base rate — humans systematically underestimate; agents inherit this if seeded with human estimates only.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Programs with hard external deadlines (regulatory, market, contractual) requiring critical-path defense.</item>
        <item>Multi-team or multi-vendor work with cross-team dependencies needing FS/SS/FF links.</item>
        <item>Fixed-bid proposals where the schedule baseline drives the price.</item>
        <item>Resource-constrained programs needing leveling and conflict detection.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure-Scrum cadence with empowered PO — sprint plan replaces schedule.</item>
        <item>Continuous-flow or Kanban product teams.</item>
        <item>Projects shorter than 2 weeks — a checklist beats a Gantt.</item>
        <item>Discovery or R&amp;D where activity duration is fundamentally unknowable.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="step-1-define-activities">
      <p>Convert each WBS work package into one or more specific activities.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Convert each WBS work package into one or more specific activities. Activities are verb-led (unlike WBS packages which are noun-led) and describe the work, not the deliverable.</statement>
        <rationale>WBS packages answer "what"; activities answer "how and by whom". Keeping the two separate preserves the scope baseline while enabling scheduling flexibility.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-2-sequence-activities">
      <p>Activities must be sequenced using explicit dependency types to capture both hard (technical, contractual) and soft (resource preference) dependencies.</p>
      <list>
        <item>FS (Finish-to-Start): Activity B cannot start until A finishes. Most common.</item>
        <item>FF (Finish-to-Finish): B finishes at the same time as A (e.g., documentation finishes with development).</item>
        <item>SS (Start-to-Start): B starts when A starts (e.g., testing starts when dev starts on first unit).</item>
        <item>SF (Start-to-Finish): Rare — B cannot finish until A starts (e.g., night shift covers until day shift begins).</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Distinguish hard dependencies (technical, contractual) from soft dependencies (resource preference); soft dependencies can be broken if the schedule demands it.</statement>
        <rationale>Treating soft dependencies as hard creates false critical paths and hides schedule optimization opportunities.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="step-3-estimate-durations">
      <p>Durations must be estimated using three-point estimation (PERT) for any activity over 5 days to surface pessimistic scenarios and catch optimistic bias.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use three-point estimation (PERT) for any activity over 5 days: Duration = (O + 4M + P) / 6. Never use single-point estimates for complex or novel work.</statement>
        <rationale>Single-point estimates inherit the "optimistic by 30%" human bias. Three-point forcing requires a pessimistic scenario, which surfaces schedule risk early rather than at delivery.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>O = 3 days, M = 5 days, P = 10 days → PERT = (3 + 20 + 10) / 6 = 5.5 days. The pessimistic estimate forces the team to articulate the "what if it goes wrong" scenario.</note>
      </example>
      <p>Analogous estimation: use similar past tasks as reference. Parametric estimation: use metrics (e.g., 1 API endpoint = 4 hours, 10 endpoints = 40 hours).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step-4-identify-critical-path">
      <p>Run CPM (Critical Path Method) with forward and backward passes to find activities with zero float. Any delay on a critical activity delays the project by the same amount and is where management attention must focus.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run CPM (forward and backward pass) to find activities with zero float; any delay on a critical activity delays the project by the same amount. Focus management attention here.</statement>
        <rationale>Without critical path analysis, teams give equal attention to all tasks. Delays on non-critical tasks are invisible until they cascade onto the critical path — by then, recovery costs multiply.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Flag activities with float less than 2 days as "near-critical"; these become the next critical path when the primary critical activity slips.</statement>
        <rationale>Critical path analysis is a point-in-time snapshot. Near-critical activities are the most likely successors to become critical when any small variance occurs.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Use the CPM script to compute forward/backward pass, float, and critical path from YAML activity list.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="step-5-add-explicit-buffers">
      <p>Buffers must be explicit, named, and managed separately from individual task estimates using CCPM (Critical Chain Project Management) style.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Add a named project buffer at the end of the critical path (typically 15–25% of CP duration) and feeding buffers where non-critical paths join the critical path. Never embed buffers inside individual task estimates.</statement>
        <rationale>Hidden individual buffers are invisible to the PM and cannot be managed. Named CCPM buffers make schedule risk explicit and allow the PM to release buffer intentionally rather than discover it was consumed silently.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="examples-and-antipatterns">
      <p>Worked examples and the five most common scheduling antipatterns.</p>
      <example type="good" title="MVP Schedule (9 weeks)">
        <note>Discovery 2w (no buffer), Design 2w + 2d feeding buffer, Sprint 1 2w, Sprint 2 2w, Testing 1w + 3d feeding buffer, Launch 3d + 2d project buffer. Named buffers are separate line items; they total 1 week and are managed as a pool, not as per-task slack.</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Solopreneur Schedule Allocation">
        <note>Morning (3h) = deep work on critical-path tasks. Afternoon (2h) = non-critical support tasks. Evening (1h) = admin held as personal buffer. Mon-Wed = Project A (critical). Thu-Fri = Project B (secondary). The critical path receives focused, uninterrupted time; non-critical runs on interruption-safe afternoon slots.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No dependencies defined — every task appears to run in parallel on the plan.</description>
        <reason>Parallel-looking schedules hide sequential constraints. When a dependency causes a delay, the team learns about it at the dependency boundary, not during planning when it could have been mitigated.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Optimistic single-point estimates — every task is the best-case duration.</description>
        <reason>Projects almost never run at best-case. A schedule built on optimistic estimates has no slack for real-world variance, so the first delay propagates immediately to the end date.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring the critical path — treating all tasks as equally important.</description>
        <reason>Equal management attention on all tasks means critical tasks get insufficient focus. The project finishes late on the path that received the least attention.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No buffers — the schedule shows tasks back-to-back with zero slack.</description>
        <reason>A single delay anywhere on the critical path breaks the end date with no recovery option. The PM must re-negotiate scope or dates under pressure, in public, in crisis mode.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Resource conflicts — the same person is scheduled on parallel tasks simultaneously.</description>
        <reason>Theoretical parallel execution that ignores per-resource capacity produces a plan that is physically impossible. Resource leveling must be applied before baseline commitment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>A subagent is well-suited to: convert a WBS into an activity list, propose dependencies (FS/SS/FF/SF) by analyzing leaf descriptions, generate three-point estimates against analogous projects, identify the critical path, recommend feeding/project buffers (CCPM-style), and run weekly schedule-vs-actual variance reports. Humans own duration commitments, resource assignments, and stakeholder-facing date communications. Pair the agent with EVM (separate methodology) for performance tracking once execution starts.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: faion-pm-agent (owns schedule baseline, runs CPM, drafts variance reports), faion-business-analyst (strong for activity-vs-deliverable mapping and dependency identification), /faion (gate that PRs reference activity IDs, helping schedule actuals stay accurate).</p>
      <p>Prompt pattern: Given this WBS (YAML), produce an activity list with id, wbs_ref, name, predecessors:[{id, type:FS|SS|FF|SF, lag}], est_o, est_m, est_p, pert_mean, resource. Constraints: every leaf maps to >=1 activity; PERT = (O+4M+P)/6. Flag activities lacking analogous estimation source as needs_calibration.</p>
      <p>Compute the critical path. Output: forward pass: [{id, ES, EF}], backward pass: [{id, LS, LF, total_float}], critical_path: [id,...], project_duration: &lt;days&gt;, recommended_buffers: project_buffer (15-25% of CP), feeding_buffers per non-critical merge.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools: mpxj (Java/CLI for MS Project .mpp/.xml files), python-mpxj / pyp6xer (Python access to Project / Primavera XER), gantt (npm gantt-task-react CLI for JSON → Gantt SVG), mermaid-cli (render gantt blocks to SVG/PNG), frappe-gantt (lightweight HTML Gantt from JSON), taskjuggler (full open-source CPM/CCPM scheduler), plan (Python plan CLI for YAML schedules with dependency math).</p>
      <p>Services &amp; apps: MS Project / Project for the Web (SaaS, Graph API, industry default full CPM/leveling), Primavera P6 Oracle (Enterprise, XER/REST, construction/megaproject standard), Smartsheet (SaaS, REST API, hierarchical Gantt with predecessors), OpenProject (OSS/SaaS, REST API, free CPM + Gantt + baselines), TaskJuggler (OSS, text DSL, programmable agent-friendly), LiquidPlanner (SaaS, REST API, probabilistic three-point baked in), Asana / Monday timeline (SaaS, REST/GraphQL, lightweight no true CPM).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Use three-point estimates (PERT) for any activity &gt; 5 days; single-point only for trivial work. Make buffers explicit (CCPM-style project + feeding buffers); never hide them in task estimates. Re-baseline when accumulated changes exceed 10% of duration; otherwise actuals lose meaning. Keep per-resource capacity inputs; without them parallel tasks are fiction. Flag any activity with float &lt; 2 days as "near-critical" — these become the next critical path. Track milestone slip rate (count of milestones slipped / total) as a leading indicator. For agile-hybrid: schedule at the epic/release level, run sprint cadence inside; do not Gantt every story.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLMs default to optimistic estimates (M ≈ O); explicitly request a P that is 1.5-2× M. Auto-detected dependencies miss soft / resource dependencies; require human review of the dependency graph. Critical path computed by an LLM in prose is error-prone — use a deterministic CPM script and pass the JSON to the LLM only for narrative. Schedules > 100 activities exceed comfortable context; chunk by phase or summary task and pass detail on demand. Don't let the agent commit to dates with stakeholders; dates require sponsor signoff. Human-in-loop checkpoints: (1) baseline approval, (2) any critical-path change, (3) re-baseline events, (4) milestone-slip communications.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/activity-list.md" purpose="Activity list table with ID, duration, dependencies, and resources."/>
      <template path="templates/cpm.py" purpose="Minimal CPM script: forward/backward pass, float, critical path output from YAML."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_path_method"/>
      <link href="https://www.mpxj.org"/>
      <link href="https://taskjuggler.org"/>
      <ref slug="work-breakdown-structure"/>
      <ref slug="cost-estimation"/>
      <ref slug="earned-value-management"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
