<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Engagement Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the stakeholder-engagement methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="default-cadence-by-quadrant" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply the default cadence by quadrant: Manage Closely=weekly 1:1, Keep Satisfied=biweekly summary, Keep Informed=monthly digest, Monitor=release notes only.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — engagement-fatigue audits">Default cadence is empirically calibrated; deviating without rationale causes fatigue (over-engagement) or surprises (under-engagement).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="evidence-required-for-attitude" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Require an evidence field on every attitude assertion — no evidence means attitude='unknown', not 'supportive'.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — register-quality audits">LLMs over-classify everyone as supportive (politeness bias); forcing evidence eliminates false positives.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="triangulate-with-behaviour" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioural signal: meeting attendance, response time, escalations, or sentiment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Field experience">People say 'supportive' in workshops and undermine in private; behaviour is less gameable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="hidden-stakeholder-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include a hidden stakeholder pass: legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream API consumers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — late-blocker postmortems">Systematically missed stakeholders are the top source of late-stage blockers; they never appear in org-chart exports.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="register-in-git" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Store the register in git (YAML), not a wiki — diffs become the engagement history; CODEOWNERS gate sponsor sign-off on attitude changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Configuration management practice">Wiki pages have no diff, no per-field access control, no CI integration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-auto-send-execs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Engagement communications to executives, regulators, customers, board are drafted by the agent and sent by the human.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — auto-send incident postmortems">Auto-send is forbidden — tone and timing decisions are governance acts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skip this methodology when">
    <list>
      <item>Solo founders or very small teams (under 5 stakeholders)</item>
      <item>One-off internal hotfixes or refactors with no business stakeholder change</item>
      <item>Anonymous open-source community projects</item>
      <item>Crisis or incident response — incident command structure replaces engagement plan during P0</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
