<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Stakeholder Engagement — Framework and Process">
  <summary>Five-step engagement process, Power/Interest grid, quadrant strategies, and the communication matrix pattern.</summary>

  <section title="Five-Step Process">
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Identify all stakeholders — sponsor, users, customers, team, regulators, suppliers, influencers. Seed from org chart, charter, RFP, and contract.</item>
      <item>Step 2: Analyze Power/Interest — map each stakeholder on the 2x2 grid; apply Mitchell-Agle-Wood (power × legitimacy × urgency) for political risk.</item>
      <item>Step 3: Plan engagement strategies — one strategy per quadrant; override only with explicit rationale.</item>
      <item>Step 4: Execute communication plan — cadence, channel, owner, content per stakeholder.</item>
      <item>Step 5: Monitor and adapt — refresh quarterly minimum; triangulate self-reported attitude with behavioural signals.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Quadrant Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply the default cadence by quadrant: Manage Closely = weekly 1:1, Keep Satisfied = biweekly summary, Keep Informed = monthly digest, Monitor = release notes only.</statement>
      <rationale>Default cadence is empirically calibrated to stakeholder tolerance; deviating without rationale causes either fatigue (over-engagement) or surprises (under-engagement).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>High Power + High Interest (Manage Closely): weekly meetings, direct updates, real-time dashboard access, early warning on delays.</item>
      <item>High Power + Low Interest (Keep Satisfied): monthly briefings, escalation path, fast response to queries, no unnecessary meetings.</item>
      <item>Low Power + High Interest (Keep Informed): newsletters, status reports, sprint demos where relevant.</item>
      <item>Low Power + Low Interest (Monitor): general announcements, release notes.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Attitude Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require an evidence field on every attitude assertion — no evidence means attitude = "unknown", not "supportive".</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs over-classify everyone as "supportive" by default (politeness bias). Forcing evidence eliminates false positives that lead to missed resistors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioural signal: meeting attendance, response time, escalations, or Slack sentiment.</statement>
      <rationale>People say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private; behavioural signals are less gameable than self-report.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating all Manage Closely stakeholders with the same tone and cadence.</description>
      <reason>A CFO and a regulator demand opposite communication styles even though both fall in the same quadrant — context-specific strategy is required.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Hidden Stakeholder Review">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a hidden stakeholder pass: legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream API consumers.</statement>
      <rationale>Systematically missed stakeholders are the top source of late-stage blockers in enterprise programs; they never appear in org-chart exports.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/register.yaml">Stakeholder register schema with all required fields</reference>
  <reference path="templates/engagement-due.py">Script to flag stakeholders past their engagement cadence</reference>
</text>
