<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="stakeholder-engagement Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for stakeholder-engagement as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating all Manage Closely stakeholders with the same tone and cadence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A CFO and a regulator demand opposite communication styles even though both fall in the same quadrant — context-specific strategy is required.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent invents stakeholder names not found in org-chart or charter inputs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs hallucinate plausible-sounding personas; always seed with real org-chart export and reject any name not in the source list unless flagged suggested_to_verify.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent sends engagement communications directly to executives without human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Auto-send is forbidden to executives, regulators, customers, board. Agent drafts; sponsor or PM approves and sends.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Bulk reclassification of stakeholder quadrants in a single agent run.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cap agent edits to 5 stakeholders per run and require human review on the diff — bulk changes destroy the evidence trail and can reverse carefully built relationships.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
