<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-tools-and-references" title="Stakeholder Engagement — Tools, Services, and References">
  <summary>CLI tools, SaaS integrations, best practices, and key references for stakeholder register management.</summary>

  <section title="CLI Tools">
    <list>
      <item>yq — read/patch register YAML in pipelines (apt install yq / brew install yq)</item>
      <item>jq — aggregate JSON exports from CRM/HR systems</item>
      <item>graphviz (dot) — render influence/impact graph and relationship network (apt install graphviz)</item>
      <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — generate 2x2 quadrant chart from YAML as PNG/SVG (npm i -g @mermaid-js/mermaid-cli)</item>
      <item>pandoc — convert register and engagement plan to PDF/DOCX for sponsor review (https://pandoc.org)</item>
      <item>pre-commit — block commits to attitude/quadrant changes without evidence: field</item>
      <item>gh / glab — mirror engagement actions as issues; CODEOWNERS gate sponsor sign-off</item>
      <item>op (1Password CLI) — pull sensitive contact info without committing it to git</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Services">
    <list>
      <item>Microsoft Graph (Entra ID) — source of truth for internal org chart; required to seed register without inventing.</item>
      <item>Workday HCM / BambooHR — authoritative for level, span of control, manager; used for influence inference.</item>
      <item>Salesforce — authoritative for external (customer) stakeholders; REST + Bulk API.</item>
      <item>Slack / MS Teams — source for behavioural signal; use with explicit consent only.</item>
      <item>SurveyMonkey / Typeform / Qualtrics — periodic stakeholder pulse surveys feeding attitude triangulation.</item>
      <item>Mural / Miro / FigJam — workshop canvas for matrix exercises; agents can post sticky notes via API.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>One canonical register in git; if Workday or Salesforce holds source data, mirror nightly — do not maintain two truths.</statement>
      <rationale>Two register sources diverge within weeks; the one not updated during a crisis is the one consulted, producing wrong engagement actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the register as confidential — private repo, not a wiki page; run password-scrubber-agent before any commit.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholder attitude data leaking to the wrong stakeholder terminates relationships; candid commentary is common in these files.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Calendar audits prevent burnout — if any stakeholder appears in more than 3 weekly meetings, consolidate.</statement>
      <rationale>Well-meant high-touch engagement burns goodwill faster than under-engagement when it exceeds the recipient's tolerance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="References">
    <list>
      <item>PMI PMBOK 7e — Stakeholder Performance Domain.</item>
      <item>Mendelow, A. (1991) — Power-Interest grid (the matrix this methodology uses).</item>
      <item>Mitchell, Agle &amp; Wood (1997) "Toward a Theory of Stakeholder Identification and Salience" — AMR.</item>
      <item>Freeman, R. E. "Strategic Management: A Stakeholder Approach."</item>
      <item>Bourne, L. "Stakeholder Relationship Management" — includes Stakeholder Circle methodology.</item>
      <item>ISO 21500 / 21502 — project management stakeholder engagement guidance.</item>
      <item>Sibling methodologies: communications-management/, stakeholder-register/, stakeholder-engagement-advanced/, change-control/</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
