<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="feedback">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>communicator</domain>
    <summary>Structured models for delivering and receiving feedback that is specific, behavior-focused, and actionable using SBI, SBII, and Radical Candor frameworks.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>feedback</tag>
      <tag>communication</tag>
      <tag>behavior-change</tag>
      <tag>coaching</tag>
      <tag>difficult-conversations</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Giving and Receiving Feedback</title>
    <summary>A set of structured models for delivering and receiving feedback that is specific, behavior-focused, and actionable. The primary framework is SBI (Situation-Behavior-Impact), extended with SBII (add Intent inquiry) and Radical Candor (care personally + challenge directly). For receiving feedback, the LEARN framework prevents defensive reactions. Core rule: describe observable behavior and concrete impact, never personality or judgment.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Vague feedback ("good job", "this is wrong") does not change behavior because it provides no actionable signal. Feedback that attacks personality triggers defensiveness and shuts down learning. SBI decouples observation from judgment — the recipient can act on it without feeling attacked. Radical Candor research shows that most feedback failures are in the "ruinous empathy" quadrant (too nice, says nothing) rather than being too harsh.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Code reviews where you need behavior change, not just code fixes.</item>
        <item>Performance discussions and 1-on-1 coaching.</item>
        <item>Post-incident retrospectives where root cause involves a person's action.</item>
        <item>Any situation where someone's behavior had a clear impact on the team or project.</item>
        <item>Requesting feedback from others on a specific area.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Real-time public forums — critical feedback must always be private.</item>
        <item>When you are emotionally activated — draft, wait, review before delivering.</item>
        <item>When the issue is a skill gap rather than a behavior — switch to coaching mode.</item>
        <item>For praise that genuinely needs no specifics — spontaneous positive reactions are fine.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="sbi-model">
      <p>Deliver feedback using the SBI structure: Situation (specific context), Behavior (observable action), Impact (concrete effect on team, project, or person).</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Deliver feedback using the SBI structure: Situation (specific context), Behavior (observable action), Impact (concrete effect on team, project, or person).</statement>
        <rationale>SBI decouples observation from judgment. The recipient can act on "you interrupted the client twice" (behavior); they cannot act on "you were rude" (character). Specificity eliminates the "when?" ambiguity that makes feedback forgettable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Client meeting feedback using SBI">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Situation:  "In yesterday's client meeting..."
Behavior:   "When you interrupted the client twice..."
Impact:     "The client seemed frustrated and we lost momentum."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Character-based feedback — not actionable">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"You're impatient and you don't listen to clients."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="sbii-extension">
      <p>The SBII extension adds an Intent inquiry step to SBI, converting one-directional feedback into dialogue.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Add an Intent inquiry ("Help me understand what you were trying to do?") after the Impact step when the behavior could have a legitimate reason you don't know.</statement>
        <rationale>SBII prevents the fundamental attribution error — assuming the person acted from a negative motive when there may be a good reason. It converts feedback delivery into dialogue.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Code review SBII example">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"In the code review (S), when you approved without comments (B),
I was surprised because that PR had several issues (I).
Can you help me understand your thinking? (Intent)"
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="radical-candor-quadrant">
      <p>Radical Candor combines caring personally with challenging directly. Most feedback failures are in the "ruinous empathy" quadrant — feedback so softened it communicates nothing actionable.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Deliver feedback that is simultaneously caring (you want the person to succeed) and direct (you challenge the behavior clearly). Avoid both ruinous empathy and obnoxious aggression.</statement>
        <rationale>Kim Scott's research shows most feedback failures are in the "ruinous empathy" quadrant — feedback so softened it communicates nothing actionable. The recipient feels good but does not change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Radical Candor (goal): "I care about your growth, and this needs to change"</item>
        <item>Ruinous Empathy (avoid): "It's fine..." when it is not</item>
        <item>Obnoxious Aggression (avoid): "This is garbage, what were you thinking?"</item>
        <item>Manipulative Insincerity (avoid): talking behind back, passive-aggressive</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply Radical Candor in sequence: ask first ("Can I give you some feedback?"), be specific with SBI, be immediate (within 48 hours), be private.</statement>
        <rationale>Asking permission engages the recipient as a participant rather than a subject, reducing defensiveness before the content is delivered.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="learn-framework-for-receiving">
      <p>LEARN is a framework for receiving feedback without defensiveness: Listen without defending, Explore with specific examples, Acknowledge the effort, Reflect privately before judging, then act with Next steps or explain why not.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Receive feedback using LEARN: Listen without defending, Explore with specific examples, Acknowledge the effort, Reflect privately before judging, then act with Next steps or explain why not.</statement>
        <rationale>Defensiveness in the moment prevents accurate processing of the feedback signal. The Reflect step creates a gap between receiving and evaluating — this gap is where behavioral change is possible.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Scripts for common receiving situations">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Unclear feedback: "Can you give me a specific example?"
Disagreeing:      "I see it differently. Can we discuss?"
Feeling attacked: "I need a moment to process this."
Agreeing:         "You're right, I'll work on that."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="bad" title="Defensive responses to avoid">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Yes, but..."
"You don't understand..."
"Everyone else does it this way..."
"That's not fair..."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="eec-model-for-positive-feedback">
      <p>EEC is the structure for effective positive feedback: Example (specific situation), Effect (concrete impact), Continue (explicit encouragement to repeat). It makes positive feedback as actionable as constructive feedback.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Give positive feedback using EEC: Example (specific situation), Effect (concrete impact), Continue (explicit encouragement to repeat).</statement>
        <rationale>Vague praise ("great job") does not signal what behavior to repeat. EEC makes positive feedback as actionable as constructive feedback.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="EEC positive feedback example">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Example:  "When you led the demo yesterday..."
Effect:   "The client was impressed and asked for a proposal..."
Continue: "Keep doing this — it's exactly what we need."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="timing-rules">
      <p>Feedback is most effective when delivered close to the behavior, in private for critical feedback, and with clear context.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Give feedback within 48 hours of the behavior. Apply the 2-minute rule: if feedback takes less than 2 minutes to give, give it now.</statement>
        <rationale>Delayed feedback loses specificity — memory of the behavior degrades, context shifts, and the recipient cannot connect the feedback to the actual event.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always give critical feedback in private. Give praise publicly when the recipient is comfortable with public recognition.</statement>
        <rationale>Public criticism activates social threat response, making the recipient defensive and unwilling to process the content. Private delivery removes the audience variable.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Feedback sandwich: positive → negative → positive.</description>
        <reason>Recipients learn to ignore the positive frames and wait for the real feedback, while the positive content becomes meaningless through association. Use direct, respectful SBI instead.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using "you're [adjective]" constructions: "you're unreliable", "you're careless".</description>
        <reason>Adjectives describe personality, not behavior. The recipient cannot change who they are; they can change what they do.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="agent-integration-guidelines">
      <p>Agents can assist with feedback drafting when given specific situation, behavior, and impact context. They excel at SBI and EEC formatting, but human judgment remains essential for relationship context and timing decisions.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>When using agents to draft feedback: provide the situation, observable behavior, and measurable impact explicitly. Require human review before sending any drafted feedback to a real person.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents can format SBI correctly but lack the relationship history and nuance to assess whether the feedback tone is appropriate or the facts are accurate in context.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Agentic SBI drafting workflow">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Agent receives:
- Situation: Code review of PR #142 (auth refactor)
- Behavior: Token validation logic duplicated across 3 handlers
- Impact: Code reviewer spent 15 minutes tracing authority; inconsistency creates security risk if one copy diverges

Agent produces:
"In this PR (#142), when the token validation logic was duplicated across 3 handlers, I spent 15 minutes tracing which version was authoritative. The inconsistency creates a security risk if one copy gets patched and others don't. Going forward: extract to a single validate_token() utility and import it."
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <list>
        <item>Agents default toward Ruinous Empathy (too soft) unless explicitly prompted to "be direct." Remove hedging language ("you might consider," "perhaps") in review.</item>
        <item>Agents frequently produce feedback sandwiches because it is the most common pattern in training data. Explicitly prohibit it in the prompt.</item>
        <item>SBII Intent Inquiry is powerful but agents can only draft the opening question; they cannot conduct the real two-way follow-up conversation.</item>
        <item>Agents sometimes reverse SBI into IBS (lead with impact). Enforce order explicitly in the prompt format.</item>
        <item>Run a personality adjective check on every drafted SBI statement. Any word describing character must be removed and replaced with observable behavior.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/positive-feedback.txt" purpose="EEC-based positive feedback message template"/>
      <template path="templates/constructive-feedback.txt" purpose="SBI-based constructive feedback message template"/>
      <template path="templates/asking-for-feedback.txt" purpose="Template for requesting targeted feedback on a specific area"/>
    </templates>
  </content>
</methodology>
