<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Tailwind Design Tokens Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Tailwind Design Tokens. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-config-from-tokens" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>tailwind.config.js (or v4 CSS config) is GENERATED from tokens.json; manually edited Tailwind theme keys are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Single-source-of-truth convention">Manual Tailwind edits create a second source; CI must rebuild the config from tokens on every change.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-theme-mirrors-semantic" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tailwind theme.colors / theme.spacing / theme.fontSize keys mirror the SEMANTIC tier of tokens (e.g. theme.colors.feedback.error), not the global tier.</statement>
      <rationale source="Token-tier convention">Mirroring global produces value-named utilities (bg-red-500) instead of intent-named (bg-error-500); semantic mirror keeps utilities tied to design intent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-no-arbitrary-values" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Arbitrary value syntax (bg-[#FF6633], p-[12px]) is CI-blocked in production code; arbitrary syntax is allowed only in marked prototype files.</statement>
      <rationale source="Token-discipline convention">Arbitrary values are escape hatches that erode the token layer; the CI block makes drift visible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-purge-unused-after-rename" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On semantic token rename, Tailwind safelist + purge config are updated to avoid orphan classes shipping to production.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tailwind purge mechanics">Without purge update, renamed tokens leave dead classes shipping bytes to users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-dark-mode-via-class-strategy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Dark mode uses class strategy (darkMode: &apos;class&apos;) with semantic tokens that swap values; media-query strategy is rejected for token-driven projects.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tailwind dark-mode docs">Class strategy lets users override system preference; media-query strategy ties theming to the OS without override.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do NOT run this methodology — emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition and route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above for flat methodologies), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-tailwind-design-tokens.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
