<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-integration-rules" title="Tailwind + Design Tokens Integration Rules">
  <summary>Rules for mapping design tokens to Tailwind CSS configuration using CSS custom properties, with correct RGB channel handling for opacity modifier compatibility.</summary>

  <section title="RGB Channel Pattern for Colors">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define color tokens as RGB channel values (not hex) in CSS custom properties to preserve Tailwind opacity modifier functionality (bg-primary/50).</statement>
      <rationale>Tailwind opacity modifiers generate classes like bg-primary/50 by injecting an alpha channel. This only works when the color is expressed as separate RGB channels that can be combined with a transparency value. Raw hex breaks the modifier syntax entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="css"><![CDATA[:root {
  --color-primary-rgb: 59 130 246;
  --color-primary: #3B82F6;
}]]></code>
      <note>RGB channel variable enables opacity modifiers; hex variable available for non-Tailwind consumers.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="javascript"><![CDATA[// tailwind.config.js
module.exports = {
  theme: {
    extend: {
      colors: {
        primary: {
          default: 'rgb(var(--color-primary-rgb) / <alpha-value>)',
        }
      }
    }
  }
}]]></code>
      <note>alpha-value placeholder is Tailwind v3+ syntax for opacity modifier injection.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Color token defined as hex in Tailwind config: primary: 'var(--color-primary)'</description>
      <reason>bg-primary/50 silently renders as fully opaque because the opacity modifier cannot decompose a hex CSS variable into RGB channels.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Theme Extension vs Replacement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always extend the Tailwind default theme (theme.extend) rather than replacing it — replacement removes useful defaults like font-sans, leading-*, and the full default spacing scale.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents frequently generate config at the theme level instead of theme.extend, silently wiping defaults that downstream components depend on.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Extend Tailwind's spacing scale with semantic token names (spacing.md = 16px) rather than overriding the numeric scale (spacing.4 = 16px) — both can coexist.</statement>
      <rationale>Numeric and semantic scale coexistence allows gradual migration without breaking existing components that use the default numeric scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="CSS Variable Declaration">
    <rule>
      <statement>Declare all token-mapped CSS custom properties in a @layer base { :root { } } block — never in a component CSS file.</statement>
      <rationale>@layer base ensures custom properties are available to all Tailwind utilities without specificity conflicts and survive PurgeCSS/JIT correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Safelist token-generated classes that are constructed dynamically (e.g., bg-${color}) to prevent JIT purge from removing them.</statement>
      <rationale>Tailwind JIT only keeps classes it finds as literal strings in source files; dynamic class construction is invisible to the scanner and the class is silently dropped.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Pipeline Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the Style Dictionary build step in the CI pipeline before tailwind build runs; never hand-edit the generated tailwind-theme.js.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual edits to generated files are overwritten on next token sync; the generated file must be treated as a build artifact, not source of truth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enforce no-arbitrary-value via eslint-plugin-tailwindcss to prevent new hardcoded values entering the codebase after token integration.</statement>
      <rationale>Token migration is reversible without enforcement; developers under deadline will reach for arbitrary values and the token layer degrades over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/tailwind.config.js">Tailwind config with CSS variable token references and RGB channel pattern</reference>
  <reference path="templates/build-tailwind-tokens.mjs">Node.js script generating tailwind-theme.js and tokens.css from tokens.json</reference>
</text>
