<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-narrative-structure" title="Feature Narrative Structure">
  <summary>The canonical feature-narrative.json schema: required fields, authoring discipline, and the limit-before-benefit rule that prevents mis-selling.</summary>

  <section title="Required Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every feature narrative must contain: purpose (one sentence, no marketing adjectives, names the user job), behavior_change (before/after observable in product), measurable_outcome (metric + baseline + current + isolation_method), limit (what it intentionally does NOT do), and affected_personas[] (name + job + value_received per persona).</statement>
      <rationale>Missing any of these fields produces renders that either over-promise (no limit), cannot be verified (no outcome), or address no specific user (no persona). Each field is required, not optional.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>State the limit before the benefit in every render. Sales cannot accidentally over-sell if the limit is upstream of the pitch.</statement>
      <rationale>Limits edited out of sales materials lead to over-promising. By ordering limit before benefit in the canonical source, every render inherits the limit-first structure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>measurable_outcome.isolation_method must be one of: a/b, holdout, pre/post, or unverified. Never report a metric move without specifying how causation was isolated.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders learn to distrust PM data when correlation is passed off as causation. The isolation_method field forces honesty and prevents outcome-washing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Refuse to invent outcomes. If a metric is unverified, write "unverified" — never optimistic-extrapolate. If a persona is not in the persona registry, reject it.</statement>
      <rationale>Hallucinated outcomes compound across renders. Each audience-specific render amplifies inaccuracies in the source; a wrong number in the executive memo becomes a board-level commitment.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Authoring Discipline">
    <rule>
      <statement>Co-author the narrative with engineering during the design phase, not after shipping. Engineering reviews behavior_change for accuracy before the narrative is used for any render.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc narratives drift from what was actually built. Engineering review during design catches scope drift early and prevents the post-ship discovery that the story does not match the product.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Co-locate feature-narrative.json with the SDD feature folder: .aidocs/.../in-progress/FEATURE/feature-narrative.json. Refresh on every status flip (internal → GA, GA → deprecated, scope change).</statement>
      <rationale>Narratives stored separately from specs become orphaned artifacts. Co-location with the SDD lifecycle ensures the narrative travels with the feature and is refreshed when scope changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Ban the following tokens from all narrative fields and renders: "best", "leading", "revolutionary", "seamless", "powerful", "next-gen", "delight". Lint output; regenerate on any hit.</statement>
      <rationale>Marketing tone makes AI assistants interpret product descriptions as promotional content and reduces the precision of pre-sales answers. Literal, specific language produces more accurate AI-mediated representations.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <note>Purpose field: "Lets a CSM resolve a billing dispute without leaving Zendesk." Names the persona, the job, and the constraint — no adjectives.</note>
  </example>
  <example type="bad">
    <note>Purpose field: "Powerful new integration that seamlessly boosts productivity for customer-facing teams." No persona, no job, no constraint, banned tokens.</note>
  </example>
</text>
