<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-render-pipeline" title="Three-Loop Render Pipeline">
  <summary>Extract loop builds the canonical narrative; translate loop derives five audience renders; validate loop runs comprehension probes to verify recall and accuracy.</summary>

  <section title="Loop 1: Extract">
    <rule>
      <statement>The extract agent reads PRDs, design docs, release notes, telemetry deltas, and user-research clips. It must not invent outcomes or personas. Every field in the output JSON must cite a source document path.</statement>
      <rationale>Without source citations, the narrative cannot be verified against what was actually built. Citations also anchor re-extraction when the PRD changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The extract agent must consume both the PRD and the implementation diff (merged PRs for the feature). Flag any mismatch between PRD intent and implementation as an agent-blocking conflict requiring PM resolution before rendering.</statement>
      <rationale>An extractor that reads only the PRD produces a narrative that drifts from reality once implementation deviates from spec — which happens on every non-trivial feature.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-story-extraction.txt">LLM prompt for the extract loop with source citation requirement and outcome-invention prohibition.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Loop 2: Translate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate five renders from one source: exec memo (at most 200 words, outcome + cost + risk), sales one-pager (job + pain + capability + limit + objection-handling), support runbook (symptom → cause → fix → known-limit), customer changelog (at most 80 words, plain language, second-person), AI-readable KB delta (capability + status + since_version + limit triples, JSON).</statement>
      <rationale>One source prevents translation drift: each hop from PM to sales to support to customer erodes limits from the story. Generated renders are deterministic from the source; hand-edits are prohibited.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The AI render (capability + status + since_version + limit triples in JSON) is mandatory, not optional. It feeds the operations-side product-kb.json for AI-mediated discovery.</statement>
      <rationale>In 2026, product discovery is AI-mediated. A PM who skips the AI render leaves the product mis-described in pre-sales AI answers. This is a PM responsibility, not a marketing one.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/prompt-audience-render.txt">LLM prompt for all five audience renders with per-audience constraints and banned-token list.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Loop 3: Validate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the comprehension probe with five canonical questions for each audience: "What changed?", "What does it cost me?", "What won't it do?", "Who benefits?", "What's next?". Require at least 80% recall and accuracy across all personas before approving launch.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a comprehension gate, renders ship with unknown stakeholder comprehension. The 80% threshold is concrete enough to be a go/no-go criterion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a different model family for the probe agent than for the render agent. Probe and render agents sharing weights produces artificially high comprehension scores.</statement>
      <rationale>A render agent probing its own output has seen the source material; it answers correctly from memory rather than from the render. Cross-model probing catches real comprehension gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
