<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="Product Explainability Antipatterns">
  <summary>Common failure modes in PM narrative work: structural traps, render drift, and agentic gotchas.</summary>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Feature-list trap: PM lists what shipped instead of explaining what changed for the user. Stakeholders nod, retain nothing, and mis-sell.</description>
    <reason>Feature lists describe implementation, not value. "Added bulk-export API endpoint" tells a CSM nothing about what changes for their customer.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Translation collapse: PM speaks PM-ese; sales translates to sales-ese; CS translates again to customer-ese. Each hop drops a limit or invents a capability.</description>
    <reason>Eliminate hops with generated renders from one canonical source. Hand-editing any render is forbidden; diffs from the canonical source are the only allowed change.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Outcome-washing: "NPS went from 42 to 44" presented as the result of the feature without an isolation method.</description>
    <reason>Correlation presented as causation teaches stakeholders to distrust PM data. isolation_method is a required field; unverified is the honest answer when you don't know.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Stale story: narrative written at launch and never updated; six months later capabilities have changed but the deck has not.</description>
    <reason>Refresh on every status flip. feature-narrative.json has a content hash checked against the current PRD and telemetry; stale narratives fail the gate before re-rendering.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>AI-readability blindness: PM writes only for humans; the same LLM that answers a customer's pre-sales question now misrepresents the product.</description>
    <reason>In 2026, the AI render is a PM deliverable, not a marketing afterthought. Skipping it leaves the product misrepresented in the AI-mediated buying journey.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Limit erosion across renders: the translate loop summarizes; summarization drops limits; the customer-facing render omits what the feature does NOT do.</description>
    <reason>Limits are passed as a separate verbatim, never-summarized field. Each render is linted to confirm the limit string is present before publish.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Outcome inflation: render agents round 2.1% to "double-digit improvement" or extrapolate one cohort to "all users".</description>
    <reason>Hard rule: render agent must echo measurable_outcome.metric + baseline + current verbatim; rephrasing numbers is prohibited.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
