<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-explainability Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-explainability as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Feature-list trap: PMs default to listing what shipped instead of explaining what changed for the user; stakeholders nod, retain nothing, mis-sell.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feature lists describe implementation, not value. "Added bulk-export API endpoint" tells a CSM nothing about what changes for their customer.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Translation collapse: PM speaks PM-ese; sales translates to sales-ese; CS translates again to customer-ese. Each translation drops a limit or invents a capability.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Eliminate hops with generated renders from one canonical source. Hand-editing any render is forbidden; diffs from the canonical source are the only allowed change.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcome-washing: "We shipped X, NPS went from 42 to 44" — correlation passed off as causation, no isolation, no instrumentation. Stakeholders learn to distrust PM data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Correlation presented as causation teaches stakeholders to distrust PM data. isolation_method is a required field; unverified is the honest answer when you do not know.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Hero-narrative bias: PM owns the story so the PM looks good in it; engineering and design contributions disappear, internal trust erodes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force credit lines: "Designed by [name], engineered by [team]"; remove first-person voice from exec memo.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale story: The story is written at launch and never updated; six months later capabilities have changed but the deck has not, sales is selling vapor.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Refresh on every status flip. feature-narrative.json has a content hash checked against the current PRD and telemetry; stale narratives fail the gate before re-rendering.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Audience collapse: One artifact tries to serve exec, sales, support, customer, regulator at once; ends up serving none well.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Generate five renders from one source: exec memo, sales one-pager, support runbook, customer changelog, AI-KB delta. Each render is audience-optimized.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Limit-omission: Limits are perceived as "negative" and edited out before they reach sales; sales over-promises; CS absorbs the gap.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Limits are passed as a separate verbatim, never-summarized field. Each render is linted to confirm the limit string is present before publish.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>AI-readability blindness: PMs write for humans only; the same LLM that just answered a customer's pre-sales question now misrepresents the product. PM owns this and most PMs do not realize it yet (2026 reality).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>In 2026, the AI render is a PM deliverable, not a marketing afterthought. Skipping it leaves the product misrepresented in the AI-mediated buying journey.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Storytelling vs. specification confusion: PMs hide ambiguity behind narrative ("delights users", "boosts productivity"); engineers re-derive specs from the story and ship the wrong thing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Author with engineering, not after. PM drafts narrative during design phase; engineering reviews for accuracy of behavior_change. Catches scope drift early and prevents post-hoc invention.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcome inflation: Render agents will round 2.1% to "double-digit improvement" or extrapolate one cohort to "all users".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hard rule: render agent must echo measurable_outcome.metric + baseline + current verbatim; no rephrasing of numbers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Limit erosion across renders: Translate-loop summarizes, summarization drops limits. Pass limits as a separate, verbatim, never-summarized field; lint each render to confirm the limit string is present.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Each render is linted to confirm the limit string is present before publish.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Persona invention: Extractor agents will invent personas to fill affected_personas[] when input is sparse.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Anchor allowed personas to a registry (personas.json) and reject others.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Marketing-tone leakage: Even with banned-tokens lists, LLMs route around (top-tier, category-defining).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Maintain an evolving banned-token list; periodically have a second LLM lint for marketing tone.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Hero narrative bias: Generator favors PM-as-protagonist framing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force credit lines: "Designed by [name], engineered by [team]"; remove first-person voice from exec memo.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-15" severity="medium">
      <description>Stale narrative re-publish: Cron-driven render re-runs without an extract refresh produce confidently-wrong artifacts after capability changes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always re-extract before re-rendering; never cache the narrative without a content hash check against PRD + telemetry.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-16" severity="medium">
      <description>Comprehension-probe gaming: Probe agent and render agent share weights → probe scores artificially high.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use a different model family for probe vs. render (e.g. render with Claude, probe with GPT-4 or Gemini).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-17" severity="medium">
      <description>Confidentiality leak: Narratives often expose unlaunched features, customer names, internal infra.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run password-scrubber-agent before any render leaves engineering's repo.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-18" severity="medium">
      <description>AI-readability skipped: PM treats AI render as a marketing concern.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Wrong: the AI render feeds the operations-side KB and the next pre-sales conversation. Make the AI render mandatory, not optional.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-19" severity="medium">
      <description>Cross-locale drift: Translation agents helpfully soften limits ("does not support" → "is best for").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Localize structurally with per-locale render passes; never machine-translate limits.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-20" severity="medium">
      <description>Silent disagreement between extractor and engineering: If extractor reads PRD only and never reads the implementation diff, narrative drifts from reality.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Extractor must consume both PRD and recent commits; flag mismatches as agent-blocking.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-21" severity="medium">
      <description>Stakeholder feedback never closes the loop: Renders ship one-way; comprehension failures do not update the narrative.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feed sales objections, support tickets, and AI-mis-answers back into the extractor as ground-truth signals; otherwise quality plateaus.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
