<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Cardinality and Cost Guardrails Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `Cardinality and Cost Guardrails` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="label-allow-list" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each metric MUST publish an explicit allow-list of labels. Any label not on the list MUST be dropped at ingest.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cortex/Mimir ops guide">Implicit label additions cause cardinality explosions that are invisible until the bill arrives.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="recording-rules-roll-up" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-user / per-request metrics MUST be rolled up via recording rules before retention; raw high-cardinality series MUST be capped at ≤ 7 days.</statement>
      <rationale source="Prometheus performance audit">Long retention on raw cardinality is the most expensive pattern available.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="log-volume-budget" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each service MUST publish a daily log-volume budget; ingestion exceeding the budget for &gt; 1 hour triggers automatic sampling.</statement>
      <rationale source="Datadog log billing analysis">Unbounded logs from a single misbehaving service can blow a monthly budget in an afternoon.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="drop-rule-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every label drop / log sampling rule MUST list a named owner; anonymous drop rules are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="internal — drop-rule rot audit">Anonymous drop rules silently delete signal months later when no-one knows why.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="audit-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cardinality + log-volume guardrails MUST be audited monthly against actual ingest costs.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps Foundation guidance">Drift between policy and bill is the canary for hidden cardinality.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>