<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="regulatory-compliance-2026 Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for regulatory-compliance-2026. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>US government entities must comply with ADA Title II at WCAG 2.1 AA by April 24, 2026 (large entities, 50K+ population) or April 24, 2027 (smaller entities).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DOJ final rule published March 2024. Non-compliance exposes state/local agencies to DOJ investigation, private lawsuits, and loss of federal funding.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>EAA requires WCAG 2.1 AA (via EN 301 549) for new e-commerce, banking, transport, and e-book products from June 28, 2025; existing products have until June 28, 2030.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">EU member states set their own enforcement; fines up to 4% of annual revenue. Web Accessibility Directive already applies to all public-sector websites.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every public-facing product must publish an accessibility statement that includes conformance level, known limitations, contact information, and the date of the last review.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Required by ADA Title II (DOJ rule), EU Web Accessibility Directive, and EAA. The statement is the primary compliance evidence regulators and plaintiffs request first.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce a Voluntary Product Accessibility Template (VPAT) — also called an Accessibility Conformance Report (ACR) — for every product used in government or enterprise procurement; update annually or after major changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">US Section 508 and ADA Title II procurement standards require VPAT evidence. EU public sector procurement increasingly requires EN 301 549 ACRs. Without one, vendors are excluded from bids.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Organizations must maintain an internal accessibility policy documenting organizational commitment, responsible parties, testing cadence, training requirements, and procurement standards.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">DOJ consent decrees and EU member state enforcement demand evidence of systemic process, not one-off fixes. Policy is the paper trail that proves ongoing effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Exemptions are narrow, must be individually documented, and always require an accessible alternative to be provided.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Regulators and courts reject blanket exemptions. Each exemption needs a written justification, scope limitation, and alternative access path.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
