<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-documentation-requirements" title="Compliance Documentation Requirements">
  <summary>Required documents for accessibility compliance: accessibility statement, VPAT/ACR, and accessibility policy — with mandatory fields and update triggers.</summary>

  <section title="Accessibility Statement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every public-facing product must publish an accessibility statement that includes conformance level, known limitations, contact information, and the date of the last review.</statement>
      <rationale>Required by ADA Title II (DOJ rule), EU Web Accessibility Directive, and EAA. The statement is the primary compliance evidence regulators and plaintiffs request first.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/accessibility-statement.txt">Accessibility statement template with all mandatory fields</reference>
    <list>
      <item>Conformance level stated (e.g., "Partially conformant with WCAG 2.1 Level AA").</item>
      <item>Known limitations listed — vague "ongoing effort" language is not sufficient.</item>
      <item>Contact mechanism for accessibility issues (email, phone, or form).</item>
      <item>Date of last statement update.</item>
      <item>Feedback/complaint process described.</item>
      <item>Alternative access methods noted if applicable.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="VPAT / ACR">
    <rule>
      <statement>Produce a Voluntary Product Accessibility Template (VPAT) — also called an Accessibility Conformance Report (ACR) — for every product used in government or enterprise procurement; update annually or after major changes.</statement>
      <rationale>US Section 508 and ADA Title II procurement standards require VPAT evidence. EU public sector procurement increasingly requires EN 301 549 ACRs. Without one, vendors are excluded from bids.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>All WCAG criteria addressed (pass / partial / not supported / not applicable).</item>
      <item>Evidence of conformance cited per criterion.</item>
      <item>Known issues documented with remediation timeline.</item>
      <item>Updated annually or on major version changes.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Policy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Organizations must maintain an internal accessibility policy documenting organizational commitment, responsible parties, testing cadence, training requirements, and procurement standards.</statement>
      <rationale>DOJ consent decrees and EU member state enforcement demand evidence of systemic process, not one-off fixes. Policy is the paper trail that proves ongoing effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Responsible parties identified (owner, team).</item>
      <item>Testing cadence: automated CI, quarterly manual audits, annual comprehensive audit.</item>
      <item>Training requirements per role (dev, designer, content, procurement).</item>
      <item>Procurement standards — VPAT required from all software/service vendors.</item>
      <item>Complaint and escalation process.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
