<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-enforcement-and-exemptions" title="Enforcement Penalties and Exemptions">
  <summary>Enforcement consequences by jurisdiction and valid exemptions — with documentation requirements for each exemption claim.</summary>

  <section title="Enforcement by Jurisdiction">
    <section title="United States (ADA)">
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Consequence                      | Typical Range
Private lawsuit settlement       | $5,000 - $75,000+
Legal fees (plaintiff)           | $50,000 - $200,000+
Consent decree + monitoring      | Multi-year compliance program
DOJ investigation                | Reputational + remediation cost
Loss of federal funding          | For government entities
        ]]></code>
        <note>Thousands of ADA web lawsuits filed annually. Serial plaintiffs target e-commerce, banking, and healthcare.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section title="European Union (EAA)">
      <example type="bad">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Consequence                          | Notes
Fine up to 4% of annual revenue      | Per member state enforcement
Product withdrawal from market       | If non-conformant after deadline
Prohibition of services              | Regulator order
Compensation to affected individuals | Civil action
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section title="Other Jurisdictions">
      <list>
        <item>Canada: Complaints to CRTC or provincial accessibility commissioners.</item>
        <item>UK: Unlawful discrimination claims under Equality Act 2010.</item>
        <item>Australia: Complaints to Australian Human Rights Commission.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Valid Exemptions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Exemptions are narrow, must be individually documented, and always require an accessible alternative to be provided.</statement>
      <rationale>Regulators and courts reject blanket exemptions. Each exemption needs a written justification, scope limitation, and alternative access path.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Pre-existing content — content published before the compliance deadline and not subsequently altered.</item>
      <item>Archived content — clearly marked as archived, not updated, not relied on for active services.</item>
      <item>Third-party content not under organizational control — must still provide an accessible alternative.</item>
      <item>Undue burden — must document why compliance is an undue financial or administrative burden AND provide an alternative.</item>
      <item>Fundamental alteration — compliance would change the fundamental nature of the service; must be documented and alternative provided.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Claiming "undue burden" without a documented cost analysis and alternative access plan.</description>
      <reason>Courts and regulators reject undocumented exemptions; the burden of proof is on the organization claiming the exemption.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
