<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="Stakeholder Register Structure">
  <summary>Required fields for each register entry, the Power/Interest grid for prioritization, and the hidden-stakeholder checklist that prevents systematic omissions.</summary>

  <section title="Register Fields">
    <p>Each entry in the register must carry:</p>
    <list>
      <item>id — unique stable identifier (S-01, S-02, ...); never reuse after deprecation.</item>
      <item>name — full name, validated against an authoritative directory (Entra ID, Workday, CRM); agents must not invent names.</item>
      <item>role — position or function; source from directory, not assumption.</item>
      <item>organization — department or external org.</item>
      <item>category — one of: Sponsor, User, Customer, Team, Regulator, Supplier, Influencer.</item>
      <item>power — H/M/L; documented with source evidence.</item>
      <item>interest — H/M/L.</item>
      <item>impact — H/M/L; how strongly the project affects them.</item>
      <item>attitude — +/0/-/unknown; defaults to "unknown" without behavioral or quoted evidence.</item>
      <item>quadrant — derived from power/interest: Manage Closely / Keep Satisfied / Keep Informed / Monitor.</item>
      <item>cadence — communication frequency; required for all High-power stakeholders.</item>
      <item>owner — PM or team member responsible for this relationship.</item>
      <item>evidence — list of quotes, transcript references, or log entries supporting attitude and power assertions.</item>
      <item>last_engaged — date of most recent substantive interaction.</item>
      <item>hidden_flag — true if discovered via the hidden-stakeholder checklist, not initial analysis.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Store contact information via a secrets manager (e.g., 1Password op:// URL), never inline in the register; registers contain PII and are shared more broadly than contact credentials should be.</statement>
      <rationale>Inline contact data in a shared repo becomes a PII leak vector; referencing by key allows the register to be shared while keeping personal details protected.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Power/Interest Grid">
    <p>Plot each stakeholder on the Mendelow 2x2 grid to determine engagement intensity:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Manage Closely (High power, High interest) — actively engage, involve in decisions, weekly contact minimum.</item>
      <item>Keep Satisfied (High power, Low interest) — regular updates with no surprises; engage before decisions that affect them.</item>
      <item>Keep Informed (Low power, High interest) — regular communication, solicit feedback; these are your champions-in-waiting.</item>
      <item>Monitor (Low power, Low interest) — minimal effort; watch for changes in attitude or power.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>For programs with regulatory or political risk, overlay Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience (power x legitimacy x urgency); the 2x2 alone flattens political complexity that drives high-stakes blockers.</statement>
      <rationale>Influence is not the same as seniority; gatekeepers (EAs, infosec PMs, procurement leads) often hold de facto veto power that the 2x2 maps to Low-power because they lack formal title.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Hidden Stakeholder Checklist">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the hidden-stakeholder checklist at project initiation and at each phase gate; systematic omissions are more common than random ones.</statement>
      <rationale>The same categories are missed on most projects: legal, infosec, procurement, FinOps, accessibility, works council/union, downstream API consumers, regulators. A checklist converts "we forgot" into "we confirmed absent."</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Legal / Compliance — data processing agreements, IP, contracts.</item>
      <item>Information Security — access, encryption, audit trail.</item>
      <item>Procurement / FinOps — vendor contracts, cloud spend approval.</item>
      <item>Accessibility — a11y requirements for regulated or public-facing products.</item>
      <item>Works Council / Union — organizational change requiring co-determination.</item>
      <item>Downstream API / Data Consumers — systems or teams that depend on outputs.</item>
      <item>Regulators / Standards Bodies — external bodies with compliance authority.</item>
      <item>Customer Success / Support — teams absorbing the operational change.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
