<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Stakeholder Register Rules and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Rules for maintaining register accuracy, evidence-backed attitudes, PII handling, and safe agentic curation; anti-patterns that make the register misleading or a liability.</summary>

  <section title="Freshness and Evidence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Refresh the register at minimum quarterly; monthly during high-volatility periods (post-merger, leadership change, regulator activity); an unrefreshed register is wrong, not just old.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholder power and attitude change with organizational events; a stale register leads the PM to engage the wrong people at the wrong intensity, wasting effort and missing real risks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every attitude assertion (+/-) must reference at least one behavioral signal (attendance pattern, response time, escalation, direct quote); attitude defaults to "unknown" without evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-reported or assumed attitude is unreliable; observed behavior is more predictive. Requiring evidence also forces the PM to have real conversations rather than guessing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Triangulate attitude from at least two independent signals before updating from "unknown"; a single data point is noise.</statement>
      <rationale>Cross-cultural communication differences, tone misread in email, and politeness norms all produce false signals; corroboration reduces misclassification.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="PII and Security">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the register as confidential: store in a private repo, run a PII scrubber pre-commit to block candid commentary and salary data, encrypt at rest if shared beyond the immediate team.</statement>
      <rationale>Registers contain candid assessments of individuals' attitudes and influence; leaked registers damage relationships and may constitute GDPR Article 9 violations if attitude implies political opinion or health status.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including candid negative commentary about a stakeholder in a machine-readable field that is passed to third-party LLMs or shared in team channels.</description>
      <reason>Machine-readable candid data is one copy-paste or API call away from the subject; it damages trust, creates legal liability, and inhibits honest assessment in future registers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Curation">
    <rule>
      <statement>The register-curator agent must validate every name against an authoritative directory before proposing an add or update; reject names absent from the source.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs hallucinate plausible names from titles; a register populated with invented people is worse than no register — it creates false confidence in coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap agent edit batches at 10 patches per run; require human review on the diff before merge; never allow the agent to deprecate stakeholders autonomously.</statement>
      <rationale>Bulk automated reclassification destroys historical signal and may remove stakeholders who are still active but temporarily quiet; human review preserves context the agent cannot infer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/register_audit.py">Register completeness and evidence audit script</reference>
    <reference path="templates/register-entry.yaml">YAML template for a single stakeholder entry</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Size and Partitioning">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Maintaining a single register with more than 50-100 entries without partitioning by category or org unit.</description>
      <reason>Registers above 50 entries become unusable for active engagement planning; the PM dilutes attention across too many relationships. Partition by category (Sponsor, Regulator, User, Vendor) and operate on slices.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
