<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Personas: Types, Elements, and Creation Process">
  <summary>Defines persona types, required elements, and the five-step creation and validation process.</summary>

  <section title="Persona Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose persona type based on research maturity: research-based when data exists, proto-personas before data collection, provisional when assumptions must be made explicit.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing types without labeling them leads teams to treat assumptions as validated findings. Each type has a different confidence level and different update trigger.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Type comparison: research-based (data from interviews, surveys, analytics — most reliable); provisional (assumptions to validate — explicit uncertainty); proto-personas (team's current understanding — quick alignment before research).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Required Elements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every persona must include: name, demographics (context), goals (what they want to achieve), frustrations (pain points), behaviors (how they act), a representative quote sourced from real data, and usage context (when/where/devices).</statement>
      <rationale>Demographics-only personas are useless for design decisions. Goals and behaviors are the decision-making levers; demographics are context only.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Limit primary personas to 3-5. Each must represent a distinct combination of goals, behaviors, and context — not a demographic variant of an existing persona.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams cannot remember more than 5 personas. Too many personas dilutes focus; team members fall back to designing for whoever they imagined first.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Creation Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Conduct research first (interviews primary; surveys, analytics, support tickets, sales input as supplements), then identify behavioral clusters, then create personas, then validate with stakeholders.</statement>
      <rationale>Personas created without research reinforce team assumptions. The research-to-clustering-to-artifact sequence ensures claims trace back to evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Step 1: gather data from multiple sources. Step 2: look for clusters sharing similar goals, behaviors, pain points, and context. Step 3: draft personas with evidence citations. Step 4: validate with stakeholders and team members. Step 5: share across the organization and reference in design decisions.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every Goal, Frustration, and Behavior field must cite at least one evidence ID from source data. Mark inferences explicitly as [INFERENCE]. Do not invent quotes — use verbatim quotes from identified participants (anonymized IDs).</statement>
      <rationale>Evidence-free inferences are indistinguishable from opinions. Evidence IDs allow audits and rebuild trust when stakeholders challenge findings.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation and Lifecycle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap evidence-free inferences at 20% per persona. Refresh research-based personas after every product pivot or new market entry; refresh proto-personas after the first 5 user interviews close.</statement>
      <rationale>Personas decay as products and markets evolve. A stale persona actively misleads: teams make confident decisions based on a user type that no longer exists.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/persona-template.md">Full research-based persona document structure</reference>
    <reference path="templates/proto-persona-template.md">Lightweight proto-persona with explicit assumption fields</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/persona_evidence_check.py">Automated evidence-coverage check</reference>
  </section>
</text>
