<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-usage-patterns" title="Using Personas in Design Decisions">
  <summary>How to reference personas effectively in design reviews, user stories, prioritization, and JTBD pairing.</summary>

  <section title="Design Reviews">
    <rule>
      <statement>In every design review, frame feature questions against specific primary personas by name: "Would Sarah understand this view?" and "How does this help Sarah's goal of quick insights?"</statement>
      <rationale>Abstract user references ("the user") invite everyone to project their own model. Named persona references force the conversation onto documented, shared evidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="User Stories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write user stories using the persona name as the subject: "As Sarah, I want to see a performance summary so that I can quickly prepare for meetings."</statement>
      <rationale>Persona-sourced stories are auditable: if the story cannot be traced to a goal or frustration in the persona, it may be a hidden assumption masquerading as a user need.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Prioritization">
    <rule>
      <statement>When prioritizing features, state which persona is served and at what tier: "This feature helps Sarah (primary) but not Tom (secondary). Prioritize for Sarah."</statement>
      <rationale>Without explicit persona mapping, prioritization debates have no resolution mechanism beyond seniority or volume.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a "non-persona" alongside each primary persona set — an explicit statement of who the product is NOT for. Use it to reject features in reviews.</statement>
      <rationale>Saying no in design reviews requires negative space. A non-persona makes the rejection grounded and depersonalized.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="JTBD Connection">
    <p>Personas and Jobs-to-be-Done are complementary, not competing: persona answers WHO is using the product; JTBD answers WHAT job they are hiring it for. Example: Sarah (persona) hires the dashboard (product) to make her look informed in leadership meetings (job). Pairing them enables both empathy and precise value-proposition scoping.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Persistence Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep personas as living Markdown in a research repository (not PDFs). Diff history shows when assumptions change. Reference the same persona in user stories, A/B test hypotheses, and onboarding flows.</statement>
      <rationale>PDF personas become posters. Posters do not affect decisions. Version-controlled files allow the team to audit drift and trace which research wave updated which field.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
