<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="personas Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for personas as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Nobody uses the personas after creation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Personas built without a plan for integration into design reviews, user stories, and prioritization are posters. Usage only follows if the team commits to referencing them in rituals.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Personas consist only of demographic data (age, role, location) with no goals, behaviors, or frustrations.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Demographics tell you nothing about what to build. Goals and behaviors are the design levers; demographic data is context at best.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>More than 5-6 primary personas exist for a single product.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Teams cannot hold more than ~5 personas in working memory. Excess personas cause designers to default to their own mental model because the persona set is too large to use.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Personas were created once and never updated despite product pivots or new markets.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Stale personas mislead. A persona describing a 2021 user in a product that has since expanded to a new geography is worse than no persona — it is confident misinformation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Personas created from team assumptions without any user research.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Assumption-based personas reinforce existing biases rather than revealing user reality. They feel validated because they look like real personas.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Quote fields contain synthesized, "voicey" paraphrases invented by the author rather than verbatim participant quotes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Synthetic quotes tank credibility at first audit and are indistinguishable from hallucination. Use verbatim quotes with anonymous participant IDs only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM generates plausible quotes and demographics without grounding them in source transcripts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs hallucinate fluent, contextually appropriate-sounding quotes. Locking the drafter to evidence-only mode and rejecting outputs with quotes not in the source corpus prevents this.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Persona names and photos encode demographic stereotypes (always-female-marketer, always-male-CTO).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Stereotype-encoded personas bias design decisions and are embarrassing in stakeholder reviews. Audit the persona set for diversity and rotate names and photos per update cycle.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent merges research data from different markets or locales into a single persona without explicit instruction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cultural assumptions embedded in one-market data (US tech-comfortable manager) do not transfer across markets. Segment by locale first, create personas second.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
