<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-index" title="Product Manager Methodologies Index">
  <summary>Complete index of all 33 methodologies in the product-manager skill, organized by domain, with a quick selection guide mapping PM tasks to methodology slugs.</summary>

  <section title="Core 18 Methodologies">
    <section title="MVP and MLP">
      <list>
        <item>mvp-scoping: Teams build too much before validation. Output: core problem, minimum features, 4-week constraint.</item>
        <item>mlp-planning: MVP works but users do not love it. Output: WOW moments, delight features, MLP phases.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Feature Prioritization">
      <list>
        <item>feature-prioritization-rice: Too many features, limited resources. Formula: RICE = (Reach x Impact x Confidence) / Effort.</item>
        <item>feature-prioritization-moscow: Stakeholders disagree on priorities. Buckets: Must/Should/Could/Won't (60%/20%/10%/0%).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Planning and Roadmaps">
      <list>
        <item>roadmap-design: No clear development direction. Output: Now-Next-Later with milestones and 20% buffer.</item>
        <item>user-story-mapping: Features lack user context. Structure: Activities to Tasks to Releases.</item>
        <item>release-planning: Unclear work for upcoming sprint. Output: Sprint goal, capacity, velocity.</item>
        <item>product-launch: No clear release timeline. Output: Release goal, effort, sprints plus 20% buffer.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Goals and Metrics">
      <list>
        <item>okr-setting: Goals are vague or unmeasurable. Framework: Objective plus 3-5 Key Results plus Initiatives.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Discovery and Validation">
      <list>
        <item>problem-validation: Building solutions for non-problems. Output: 5+ interviews, competitor analysis, search volume.</item>
        <item>product-discovery: Root cause not understood. Method: Five Whys (5 levels deep).</item>
        <item>jobs-to-be-done: Features do not match user needs. Format: When [situation], I want [motivation], So I can [outcome].</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Business Models">
      <list>
        <item>business-model-research: Business model not structured. Framework: Lean Canvas (9 blocks).</item>
        <item>value-proposition-design: Product-market fit unclear. Framework: Customer segment plus Value map.</item>
        <item>niche-evaluation: Too many opportunities. Output: Weighted scoring (market size, competition, fit, monetization).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Operations">
      <list>
        <item>backlog-management: Backlog items unclear or oversized. Principles: DEEP, Definition of Ready.</item>
        <item>stakeholder-management: Features disconnected from goals. Chain: Goal to Actor to Impact to Deliverable.</item>
        <item>risk-assessment: Unknown risks in product decisions. Method: Impact x Uncertainty matrix, test high-risk first.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Extended 15 Methodologies">
    <section title="Discovery and Research">
      <list>
        <item>continuous-discovery-habits: Building weekly customer touchpoint habits.</item>
        <item>feedback-management: Collecting, triaging, and acting on user feedback.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Product Development">
      <list>
        <item>minimum-product-frameworks: Choosing among MVP, MLP, MMP, MAC, RAT, MDP, MVA, MFP, SLC.</item>
        <item>mlp-planning: Evolving from MVP to Minimum Lovable Product via 4-layer audit.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Roadmaps and Strategy">
      <list>
        <item>competitive-positioning: Market positioning against competitors.</item>
        <item>portfolio-strategy: Multi-product portfolio management.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Growth and Scale">
      <list>
        <item>product-led-growth: PLG strategy and implementation.</item>
        <item>experimentation-at-scale: Scaling experiments to 100+ per year with statistical rigor.</item>
        <item>learning-speed-competitive-moat: Organizational learning velocity as competitive advantage.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section title="Operations and Lifecycle">
      <list>
        <item>product-lifecycle: Introduction, Growth, Maturity, Decline stage management.</item>
        <item>product-analytics: Analytics and measurement frameworks.</item>
        <item>technical-debt-management: Technical debt registration, scoring, and paydown strategy.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Quick Selection Guide">
    <list>
      <item>Define MVP: mvp-scoping.</item>
      <item>Add delight to MVP: mlp-planning.</item>
      <item>Choose right minimum product framework: minimum-product-frameworks.</item>
      <item>Choose next feature: feature-prioritization-rice OR feature-prioritization-moscow.</item>
      <item>Create roadmap: roadmap-design.</item>
      <item>Set team goals: okr-setting.</item>
      <item>Validate idea: problem-validation, jobs-to-be-done.</item>
      <item>Launch product: product-launch.</item>
      <item>Manage backlog: backlog-management.</item>
      <item>Build discovery habit: continuous-discovery-habits.</item>
      <item>Scale experiments: experimentation-at-scale.</item>
      <item>Act on user feedback: feedback-management.</item>
      <item>Assess product stage: product-lifecycle.</item>
      <item>Address technical debt: technical-debt-management.</item>
      <item>Build learning velocity moat: learning-speed-competitive-moat.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
