<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SOC2 Control-to-Repo Artifact Map Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of soc2-control-to-repo-artifact-map enforces. Each rule has a statement, a rationale anchored to industry practice, and a source citation.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every SOC2 control listed in the audit scope is mapped to at least one live repo artifact (config, runbook, IaC file) — not just policy documents.</statement>
      <rationale source="AICPA SOC2 Trust Services Criteria">Policies without operating evidence fail SOC2 Type II.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The map is committed in the repo (YAML/Markdown) — not exclusively in a GRC tool.</statement>
      <rationale source="Drata / Vanta SOC2 implementation guides 2026">Repo is the source-of-truth engineers actually maintain; GRC tools drift behind reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each control entry names: artifact path, owning team, evidence retention SLA, last-verified date.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE — Audit + Compliance practices">Without these, the map is unusable at audit time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audit log evidence is retained per the strictest applicable SLA (typically ≥12 months for Type II).</statement>
      <rationale source="AICPA SOC2 Type II evidence requirements">Short-retention logs invalidate the year-long audit window.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every control is re-verified at most quarterly; stale verification triggers a remediation work item.</statement>
      <rationale source="Drata / Vanta SOC2 implementation guides 2026">Audit periods are 6-12 months; quarterly verification keeps drift bounded.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, skip this methodology and route to the adjacent one referenced in Related.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 skill-authoring conventions">A skip rule keeps the decision tree closed: every branch ends at a real rule id.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>