<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Flexibility and Efficiency of Use Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Flexibility and Efficiency of Use. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-default-path-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default path is fully usable without shortcuts; accelerators only layer on top.</statement>
      <rationale source="Nielsen Heuristic #7">Forcing shortcuts on novices creates onboarding friction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-shortcuts-discoverable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shortcuts are discoverable via menus, tooltips, or a help layer; hidden shortcuts cannot accelerate users who do not find them.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Undiscovered shortcuts deliver zero value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-power-user-personalisation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Power users can personalise the workspace — saved views, custom layouts, keyboard maps — within bounded limits.</statement>
      <rationale source="Power-user research">Bounded personalisation respects both flexibility and consistency.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-batch-and-template" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Repetitive flows expose batch operations and templates; per-item repetition is a smell.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Repetitive flows without batch waste expert time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-conventions-honoured" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shortcuts honour OS conventions (cmd-s save, esc cancel); novel shortcuts require a written rationale.</statement>
      <rationale source="Apple HIG and Material guidelines">Custom shortcuts that fight muscle memory cause errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-flexibility-efficiency.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
