<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Card Sorting Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding Card Sorting. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-open-then-closed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run open sort first to discover natural groupings, then closed sort to validate; running only closed sort biases toward team-drafted categories.</statement>
      <rationale source="Optimal Workshop — Card-sorting guide">Closed-only sort cannot surface the categories the team missed.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-cards-with-context" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each card carries a short scope sentence; bare titles cause participants to invent context.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Without context, participants sort by surface label only.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-min-15-participants" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Minimum 15 representative participants per segment for statistical reliability of clusters.</statement>
      <rationale source="Optimal Workshop benchmarks">Below 15 the cluster dendrogram is noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-no-team-sorters" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Internal team members do not participate; they bias toward the existing taxonomy.</statement>
      <rationale source="UX-research practice">Team sorters reproduce the team's prior mental model.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-synthesis-by-rank" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Synthesis uses agreement-score and similarity-matrix tools; intuitive grouping by the researcher is not enough.</statement>
      <rationale source="Practitioner experience">Eyeball synthesis loses the signal in noisy sorts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-card-sorting.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
