<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Card Sorting Process">
  <summary>Six-step process for planning and running card sort studies to inform information architecture decisions.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1 — Define Goals">
    <rule>
      <statement>State specific research questions before selecting card sort type or preparing cards.</statement>
      <rationale>Goals determine whether to run open (discover categories), closed (validate structure), or hybrid (refine existing IA) sort. Mixing goals in one study produces inconclusive data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Research questions: How do users group our content? What labels make sense to users? Does our navigation match user mental models?</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2 — Prepare Cards">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use 30-60 cards with real content labels written in user language, not internal terminology.</statement>
      <rationale>Over 60 cards causes cognitive fatigue. Jargon on cards tests familiarity with internal terminology rather than mental models. Under 10 items does not justify the study overhead.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3 — Choose Format">
    <list>
      <item>Open sort: users create their own categories — use for early exploration and discovery</item>
      <item>Closed sort: users sort into predefined categories — use to validate a proposed structure</item>
      <item>Hybrid: predefined + user can add — use to refine an existing IA</item>
      <item>In-person: richer discussion, follow-up questions possible, limited scale</item>
      <item>Remote/digital: scalable, convenient, less engagement per participant</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4 — Recruit Participants">
    <rule>
      <statement>Recruit 15-20 participants for open sort; 30+ for closed sort statistical validity.</statement>
      <rationale>Below 15 participants, co-occurrence clusters are statistically unstable. Closed sort requires more participants because placement percentages need sufficient N to be meaningful.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5 — Conduct Sessions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Give participants clear, neutral instructions that do not prime any grouping scheme.</statement>
      <rationale>Priming instructions contaminate results. Instructions must state the task without suggesting categories or grouping logic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Open sort: "Please organize these cards into groups that make sense to you. You can create as many groups as you need. When done, give each group a name."</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6 — Analyze Results">
    <rule>
      <statement>Compute co-occurrence rates for all card pairs; apply thresholds: above 70% — group together; 40-70% — borderline; below 40% — keep separate.</statement>
      <rationale>Co-occurrence data reveals which groupings are statistically robust vs. which reflect individual preferences. Outlier cards (below 40% with any partner) indicate content needing redesign, not just recategorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/cooccurrence.py">Python script for computing co-occurrence matrix from open sort export</reference>
  </section>
</text>
