<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-analysis" title="Card Sort Analysis Methods">
  <summary>Co-occurrence matrix construction, similarity thresholds, standardization metric, and outlier interpretation rules.</summary>

  <section title="Co-occurrence Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each pair of cards, compute the percentage of participants who grouped them together; this is the co-occurrence rate.</statement>
      <rationale>Co-occurrence data reveals statistically robust groupings independent of the category labels participants used, which vary widely between individuals in open sorts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/cooccurrence.py">Python script for co-occurrence matrix computation from open sort export</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Similarity Thresholds">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply three-tier thresholds: above 70% co-occurrence — group together in IA; 40-70% — consider grouping, investigate further; below 40% — keep separate or investigate content problem.</statement>
      <rationale>These thresholds are empirically calibrated for 15-20 participant studies. Below 15 participants, all thresholds are statistically meaningless — report sample size prominently when under threshold.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cards with no co-occurrence above 40% with any partner are outliers — these indicate content that needs redesign (renaming, splitting, or merging), not just recategorization.</statement>
      <rationale>Outlier cards signal that users cannot form a mental model for the content itself, not that the categorization is wrong. Forcing outlier cards into categories produces navigation that feels arbitrary.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Standardization Metric">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure standardization (how consistently participants created similar categories) as an overall study quality indicator.</statement>
      <rationale>Low standardization across participants may indicate cards are ambiguous, participants are too heterogeneous, or the content domain has no shared mental model — all of which affect how much weight to give the results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>High standardization: most users created similar categories — results are reliable, proceed to tree testing</item>
      <item>Low standardization: each user had a unique approach — investigate card label clarity before building IA from this data</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Mandatory Follow-up">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always run tree testing on the IA structure proposed from card sort results before building; card sorting shows grouping preferences, not findability.</statement>
      <rationale>Card sorting tells you how users group content; it does not tell you whether users can find content in a hierarchical navigation built from those groupings. Tree testing is the validation step.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
