<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Card Sorting Examples and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Open sort and closed sort examples with real data, common mistakes, and agentic co-occurrence analysis workflow.</summary>

  <section title="Open Sort Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>E-commerce product categories open sort, 20 participants. Results: 15/20 grouped "Laptops" and "Desktops" together. Participants named this group "Computers" (not "Computing Devices" which was the internal term). "Tablets" split: 8 users with computers, 7 with phones. Insight: Create "Computers" category using user vocabulary; run tree test with Tablets in both locations to determine final placement.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Closed Sort Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Categories: Electronics, Home, Clothing. Smart Watch: 85% Electronics, 5% Home, 10% Clothing — clear placement. Heated Blanket: 40% Electronics, 55% Home, 5% Clothing — ambiguous, needs further investigation. Fitness Tracker: 70% Electronics, 10% Home, 20% Clothing — acceptable placement with minor ambiguity toward Clothing.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using 80+ cards in a single session.</description>
      <reason>Cognitive fatigue sets in above 60 cards. Participants start grouping quickly without careful consideration, producing lower-quality data. Split into two separate focused studies.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using internal terminology (jargon) on cards.</description>
      <reason>Jargon tests vocabulary familiarity, not mental models. Cards must use user language. If your sitemap says "Resource Hub", the card must say "Guides and Templates".</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running closed sort without running open sort first.</description>
      <reason>Closed sort can only validate categories you already have. Open sort discovers the categories users actually expect. Running closed sort first bakes in untested assumptions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agent receives content inventory (list of page/item names) and generates a card list with jargon replaced by user-friendly language. After study runs, agent receives exported participant groupings as JSON/CSV, computes co-occurrence matrix, identifies strong clusters (above 70%), borderline items (40-70%), and outliers (below 40%). Proposes candidate IA structure. Generates tree test spec as mandatory follow-up.</p>
    <reference path="templates/cooccurrence.py">Python script for co-occurrence matrix computation</reference>
    <reference path="templates/card-sort-plan.md">Study plan template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/results-report.md">Results report template with recommendation structure</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent produces confident IA recommendations from fewer than 15 participants.</description>
      <reason>Below 15 participants, co-occurrence clusters are statistically unstable. Flag sample size prominently in output and label recommendations as hypotheses requiring validation.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent treats card sort results as final without mandating tree testing.</description>
      <reason>Card sorting shows how users group content; it does not validate that users can find content in a hierarchy built from those groupings. Tree testing is always required before building.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
