<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="card-sorting Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for card-sorting as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using 80+ cards in a single session.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cognitive fatigue sets in above 60 cards. Participants start grouping quickly without careful consideration, producing lower-quality data. Split into two separate focused studies.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Using internal terminology (jargon) on cards.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Jargon tests vocabulary familiarity, not mental models. Cards must use user language. If your sitemap says "Resource Hub", the card must say "Guides and Templates".</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Running closed sort without running open sort first.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Closed sort can only validate categories you already have. Open sort discovers the categories users actually expect. Running closed sort first bakes in untested assumptions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent produces confident IA recommendations from fewer than 15 participants.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Below 15 participants, co-occurrence clusters are statistically unstable. Flag sample size prominently in output and label recommendations as hypotheses requiring validation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent treats card sort results as final without mandating tree testing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Card sorting shows how users group content; it does not validate that users can find content in a hierarchy built from those groupings. Tree testing is always required before building.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents generating card lists from sitemaps will include admin/internal pages that should not be tested.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always filter to user-facing content only. Internal pages bias the study toward internal structure rather than user mental models.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Co-occurrence clustering is sensitive to card label wording — agents rephrase cards between the study design and analysis phases.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents must not rephrase cards between study design and analysis. Wording changes alter how cards cluster, invalidating the study data.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Publishing an IA recommendation from sort data alone without human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Business, legal, and technical constraints are invisible to the agent. Human review is required before publishing recommendations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
