<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="FinOps Framework — INFORM / OPTIMIZE / OPERATE Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="phased-progression" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>FinOps work MUST progress through INFORM → OPTIMIZE → OPERATE in order; skipping phases produces noisy decisions and unsustainable savings.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps Foundation Framework">Optimizing without visibility leads to wrong decisions; operating without optimization preserves waste.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="named-practitioner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A named FinOps practitioner / lead MUST own the program with explicit RACI for each cost decision class.</statement>
      <rationale source="Accountability">Anonymous programs fade; named ownership creates feedback loops with stakeholders.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cross-functional-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>FinOps council MUST meet on a fixed cadence (≥monthly) with Eng, Finance, Business representation. Async-only fails for cross-functional coordination.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps Foundation">Cloud cost decisions cross functional boundaries; sync forums force alignment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kpi-evidence-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each phase MUST publish phase-specific KPIs with baselines and deltas. INFORM: coverage, dashboard adoption. OPTIMIZE: waste rate, RI/SP coverage. OPERATE: budget variance, automation coverage.</statement>
      <rationale source="Evidence-based program management">Without phase-specific KPIs the program drifts into theatre; KPIs anchor what 'progress' means.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="phase-exit-gates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each phase MUST define an exit gate (e.g. INFORM exits when tag coverage ≥80% and dashboards exist). Programs MAY iterate on phases but MUST not jump gates.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sequencing discipline">Phase gates prevent the program from claiming OPERATE-level maturity while INFORM artefacts are absent.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when (a) cloud spend &lt;$100k/yr, OR (b) no cross-functional sponsorship, OR (c) program is in pure cost-cutting mode (single-shot, no sustainability requirement).</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">FinOps framework overhead requires scale + sponsorship + sustainability; without them, lighter tools win.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
