<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-coverage-gaps" title="Coverage Gap Analysis and Alignment Matrix Rules">
  <summary>Priority areas for the +18% Business Environment shift, alignment-matrix management rules, and agent failure modes in certification content generation.</summary>

  <section title="Business Environment Priority Areas">
    <rule>
      <statement>For the +18% Business Environment shift, prioritize these methodology areas first before re-doing People or Process content: benefits-realization, value-stream-management, change-control, pm-framework-focus-areas. Add sustainability framing (ISO 14001, GRI) to each.</statement>
      <rationale>The Business Environment domain grew from 8% to 26%; existing methodology libraries built on PMBOK 6/7 are structurally deficient here. Filling this gap delivers the highest exam-score improvement per study hour.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Alignment Matrix Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store the alignment matrix in git as CSV with columns: domain, task_id, enablers, themes, covered_by (methodology slugs), evidence_anchor. Empty covered_by = gap. Never claim coverage without an evidence_anchor.</statement>
      <rationale>A git-tracked matrix creates a diff history as the ECO changes; treating it as the system-of-record (and generating the wiki from it, not the reverse) prevents drift between documentation and actual coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-run the alignment mapping after each annual ECO refresh and after any PMBOK edition release. Wire coverage_gaps.py to CI; failures open an issue assigned to the curriculum owner.</statement>
      <rationale>ECO changes are typically announced 6 months before effective date; a CI-triggered gap report provides automated early warning rather than a manual audit cycle.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="scripts/coverage_gaps.py">Reads alignment-matrix.csv; reports uncovered ECO tasks by domain</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Failure Modes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent recommends allocating 33% of study time to People domain because it is 33% of the exam weight.</description>
      <reason>Domain-weight allocation ignores individual candidate gaps; the correct allocation is weight multiplied by gap (1 - current coverage), not weight alone.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent-generated practice questions include verbatim ECO wording or known exam questions.</description>
      <reason>PMI prohibits posting verbatim exam content; questions must be rephrased with scenario context added. Auto-generated questions must pass an SME review before any distribution.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent generates dates for a study plan ("Week 5: Mar 12") without computing from the candidate's actual exam date.</description>
      <reason>Hard-coded dates misalign with every candidate's actual timeline; compute dates via Python from the exam date input, never inline in the LLM output.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
