<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="voice-ui Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for voice-ui. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define all six VUI components before writing any dialogue or NLU config.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Shared vocabulary prevents intent/slot confusion during team handoff and NLU training.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose voice only for tasks in the left column; route all right-column tasks to visual UI.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">ASR accuracy, privacy, and discovery constraints make voice unsuitable for complex or sensitive tasks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Identify tasks where hands-free or eyes-free operation provides measurable value before touching dialogue design.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Designing voice for unsuitable tasks wastes NLU budget and produces frustrated users.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write natural-language happy-path and error dialogues before defining intents, slots, or NLU configs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dialogue-first design catches unnatural phrasing and missing recovery paths before any code is written.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each intent must have at least 5 sample utterances covering natural phrasing variations.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">NLU models underfit without phrasing diversity; users say the same thing dozens of different ways.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write initial prompts as single questions; keep error prompts to one sentence plus one example.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Long prompts force users to remember too much audio; concision reduces cognitive load and re-prompting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every intent must have a three-tier error strategy: rephrase → examples → fallback (agent or visual).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Single-tier error handling ("Please try again") is the primary cause of user abandonment in voice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run Wizard-of-Oz testing (human plays the system) before any NLU training begins.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">WoZ reveals what users actually say — which is often different from every utterance the team wrote.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use implicit confirmation for low-risk actions; use explicit confirmation for irreversible or high-cost actions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Explicit confirmation for every action creates confirmation fatigue; skipping it for irreversible actions causes errors users cannot undo.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every prompt must contain exactly one question or one instruction, never both.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dual-purpose prompts force users to choose which part to answer, causing intent mismatch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r11" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Reprompts must be shorter than the original prompt and progress in specificity: shorter → with examples → with fallback offer.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Identical reprompts produce the same ASR error; each tier must change the information available to the user.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
