<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Six-Step Voice UI Design Process">
  <summary>The ordered design process from use-case selection to user testing, with concrete outputs at each step.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Voice-Appropriate Use Cases">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify tasks where hands-free or eyes-free operation provides measurable value before touching dialogue design.</statement>
      <rationale>Designing voice for unsuitable tasks wastes NLU budget and produces frustrated users.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Write Sample Dialogues First">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write natural-language happy-path and error dialogues before defining intents, slots, or NLU configs.</statement>
      <rationale>Dialogue-first design catches unnatural phrasing and missing recovery paths before any code is written.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[User: "Set a timer for 15 minutes"
System: "Timer set for 15 minutes, starting now."

User: "Add milk to my shopping list"
System: "I've added milk to your shopping list."]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Define Intents and Slots">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each intent must have at least 5 sample utterances covering natural phrasing variations.</statement>
      <rationale>NLU models underfit without phrasing diversity; users say the same thing dozens of different ways.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Intent: ControlLight
Slots:
  - room (required): "living room", "kitchen"
  - action (required): "on", "off", "dim"

Sample utterances:
- "Turn off the living room lights"
- "Lights off in the living room"
- "Living room lights off"
- "Switch off the living room lights"
- "Kill the lights in the living room"]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Author Prompts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write initial prompts as single questions; keep error prompts to one sentence plus one example.</statement>
      <rationale>Long prompts force users to remember too much audio; concision reduces cognitive load and re-prompting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Initial: "What would you like to order?"
Error:   "I didn't catch that. Try saying a size like 'medium' or 'large'."
Confirm: "That's a large pepperoni for pickup at noon. Should I place the order?"]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA["Hello! Welcome to Pizza Palace, the best pizza in town!
We have so many great options! What can I get for you today?"]]></code>
      <note>Verbose initial prompts increase time-to-first-response and are perceived as robotic.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Design a Three-Tier Error Ladder">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every intent must have a three-tier error strategy: rephrase → examples → fallback (agent or visual).</statement>
      <rationale>Single-tier error handling ("Please try again") is the primary cause of user abandonment in voice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>1st error: rephrase the original prompt more concisely.</item>
      <item>2nd error: rephrase with concrete examples of valid input.</item>
      <item>3rd error: offer a human agent transfer or visual alternative.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Test with Users">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run Wizard-of-Oz testing (human plays the system) before any NLU training begins.</statement>
      <rationale>WoZ reveals what users actually say — which is often different from every utterance the team wrote.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
