<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-rules" title="VUI Rules, Confirmation Strategy, and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Concrete testable rules for prompt quality, confirmation strategy, and known failure modes when agents design VUI.</summary>

  <section title="Confirmation Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use implicit confirmation for low-risk actions; use explicit confirmation for irreversible or high-cost actions.</statement>
      <rationale>Explicit confirmation for every action creates confirmation fatigue; skipping it for irreversible actions causes errors users cannot undo.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Low-risk reversible (add to list, set reminder) → implicit: "Adding milk to your list."</item>
      <item>High-risk or costly (place order, delete account) → explicit: "That's $18.50. Should I place the order?"</item>
      <item>Irreversible and high-value → explicit + repeat details before confirmation.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Prompt Quality Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every prompt must contain exactly one question or one instruction, never both.</statement>
      <rationale>Dual-purpose prompts force users to choose which part to answer, causing intent mismatch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reprompts must be shorter than the original prompt and progress in specificity: shorter → with examples → with fallback offer.</statement>
      <rationale>Identical reprompts produce the same ASR error; each tier must change the information available to the user.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="ASR and LLM Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM-based VUI confirms an action ("Done!") without verifying the back-end succeeded.</description>
      <reason>Latency and API errors mean the action may have failed; hallucinated confirmations erode trust irreparably.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Total round-trip latency over 1.5 seconds without streaming audio.</description>
      <reason>Users interpret gaps beyond 1.5 s as system failure and start speaking again, causing overlapping ASR input.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Utterance logs retained without a privacy/PII policy defined in the design phase.</description>
      <reason>Voice utterances contain sensitive context; retention policy must be a design constraint, not an afterthought.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No "endpointing" visual cue — the user cannot see if the system is listening.</description>
      <reason>Without a visible or auditory listening indicator, users do not know when to speak, causing silence timeouts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Task completion rate — did the user accomplish their goal without fallback?</item>
      <item>Turns to complete — how many exchanges were needed? (target: 1-2 for simple commands)</item>
      <item>Error rate — % of turns that triggered a reprompt.</item>
      <item>Fallback rate — % of sessions that hit the 3rd-tier error fallback.</item>
      <item>CSAT — post-interaction satisfaction score.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/voice-flow.md"/>
    <link path="templates/prompt-spec.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
