<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Search Intent To Brief Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules every Search Intent To Brief application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-intent-class-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every brief MUST declare exactly one primary intent class from {Informational, Comparative, Transactional, Navigational}. Multi-intent briefs (e.g. "informational + comparative") MUST be split into two briefs.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Mixed intent forces the drafter to write two articles in one; both halves underperform. Splitting is cheaper than hedging.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-must-cover-entities" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brief MUST list ≥5 must-cover entities extracted from the union of top-10 SERP titles and headings. Each entity is tagged with `mention_count` (how many top-10 results name it). Drafter MUST cover every entity with `mention_count ≥ 4`.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Entity coverage is the strongest correlate of topical relevance scoring. Missing high-frequency entities is the single biggest reason AI drafts under-rank.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-jtbd-frame" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brief MUST contain a Jobs-to-be-Done line: "When I &lt;situation&gt;, I want to &lt;motivation&gt;, so I can &lt;outcome&gt;." All three slots filled with concrete strings; no placeholders.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Without JTBD, the draft addresses the query string, not the reader's underlying problem. JTBD is what converts traffic into engagement.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-serp-features-inventory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brief MUST list every SERP feature observed on the live SERP at brief time: {featured_snippet, people_also_ask, image_pack, video_carousel, knowledge_panel, local_pack, top_stories, sitelinks, none}. For each present feature, the brief MUST declare whether the article will TARGET or IGNORE it.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">SERP features are the highest-CTR real estate. Briefs that ignore them ship articles that rank but get zero clicks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-contract-not-suggestion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The brief MUST be written as a contract — required H2s, required word-count range, required internal links, required outbound citations — not as suggestions. A drafter (human or AI) deviating from the contract triggers a rejection at review, not a "looks fine" sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="gap-analysis 2026-05-17">Suggestions are ignored under deadline pressure. Contracts force the brief author to do the thinking once and downstream drafters to comply, which is why AI drafting unanchored from a contract produces slop.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
