<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Financial Basics — Tracking Framework">
  <summary>Four-stage financial tracking framework: Track, Analyze, Monitor, Review — with revenue categories, expense targets, and P&amp;L structure.</summary>

  <section title="Core tracking requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Separate personal and business banking from day one. Never mix accounts. Open a dedicated business checking account and a dedicated tax-reserve savings account before accepting the first payment.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixed accounts invalidate expense categorization automation, create tax deduction defensibility problems on audit, and make cash-flow analysis impossible. This is the single highest-leverage setup action.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Reconcile the books monthly within the first 5 days of the following month. Later than 5 days and the signal degrades — memory fades, receipts disappear, context is lost.</statement>
      <rationale>Monthly reconciliation catches categorization errors while the founder still remembers the context of each transaction. Quarterly or annual reconciliation produces a noisy ledger that is hard to rely on for decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Revenue tracking">
    <list>
      <item>Subscriptions: track MRR from Stripe dashboard or billing system — not from bank deposits (timing differs)</item>
      <item>One-time sales: from payment processor exports</item>
      <item>Services / consulting: from invoice system (track sent and paid separately)</item>
      <item>Affiliate / ads: from platform reporting</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Expense categories and target percentages">
    <rule>
      <statement>Alert when any expense category exceeds its target percentage for two consecutive months. The alert is a flag for human review, not an automatic cut.</statement>
      <rationale>Expense percentage drift is the earliest signal of profit margin erosion. Catching it in month two instead of year-end preserves the option to course-correct.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Infrastructure (hosting, tools, domains): target 5-15% of revenue</item>
      <item>Marketing (ads, content, design tools): target 10-30% of revenue</item>
      <item>Operations (software, services): target 5-10% of revenue</item>
      <item>Contractors (design, dev, support): target 10-30% of revenue</item>
      <item>Administrative (legal, accounting): target 2-5% of revenue</item>
      <item>Owner pay: the remainder after expenses and tax reserve</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Financial ratios">
    <list>
      <item>Gross margin: (Revenue - COGS) / Revenue — target above 70% for SaaS</item>
      <item>Operating margin: Operating profit / Revenue — target above 20%</item>
      <item>Net margin: Net profit / Revenue — target above 10%</item>
      <item>LTV:CAC ratio — target above 3:1</item>
      <item>Rule of 40: Revenue growth % + Profit margin % — target above 40 for growth-stage SaaS</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="templates/unit-economics.py"/>
    <link path="templates/monthly-pnl.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
