<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-unit-economics" title="Financial Basics — Unit Economics">
  <summary>LTV, CAC, payback, and gross margin formulas with healthy ranges, worked example, and application conditions.</summary>

  <section title="Core formulas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use LTV = ARPU / monthly churn rate only for products with linear retention (roughly constant monthly churn). For products older than 6 months, use cohort-based LTV to account for non-linear retention curves.</statement>
      <rationale>The simple formula assumes every month has equal churn probability. Real retention curves front-load churn (new users churn fastest). Cohort analysis is more accurate but requires longer data history.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>ARPU = $50/month, churn = 5%/month. LTV = $50 / 0.05 = $1,000. Ad spend = $5,000, new customers = 50. CAC = $100. LTV:CAC = 10:1 (excellent). Payback = $100 / ($50 x 0.75 gross margin) = 2.7 months.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Healthy ranges and flags">
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag any of these conditions for human review: LTV:CAC below 3:1 (acquisition engine broken), payback period above 12 months (cash-flow risk), gross margin below 70% for SaaS (structural COGS problem), Rule of 40 below 40 for growth-stage SaaS.</statement>
      <rationale>These thresholds are industry heuristics validated across thousands of SaaS companies (Bessemer, OpenView benchmarks). Crossing them does not mean failure, but requires conscious explanation rather than silent acceptance.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Suppress unit-economics dashboards when paid customer count is below 100. Below this threshold, LTV and CAC calculations have high noise. Show absolute revenue and raw churn count instead.</statement>
      <rationale>With 20 customers, a single churned customer shifts monthly churn rate by 5%. Dashboards showing "churn 5%" with N=20 create false precision that misleads decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="CAC calculation scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>CAC = total marketing spend / new customers acquired. This treats all marketing spend as acquisition cost. Separately track brand and retention spend if significant; blended CAC misleads when channels have very different performance.</statement>
      <rationale>A company spending 60% on brand awareness and 40% on performance marketing will have an inflated blended CAC that misrepresents true acquisition efficiency. Segment when channel mix diverges.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Rule of 40 applied to bootstrapped lifestyle businesses or pre-product-market-fit startups.</description>
    <reason>Rule of 40 is a growth-stage SaaS heuristic. At pre-PMF, optimizing for this metric redirects focus from finding what customers want. At lifestyle scale, profit may intentionally be low due to owner withdrawals.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <reference path="templates/unit-economics.py">Unit-economics snapshot: LTV, CAC, LTV:CAC, payback, health flags</reference>
</text>
