<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ops-financial-basics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ops-financial-basics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Calculating LTV and CAC but ignoring gross margin. A company with ARPU $100, churn 5%, and CAC $50 appears to have LTV:CAC equals 2x, but if gross margin is only 40%, the true margin per customer is $40, not $100.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Gross margin is essential because it represents the cash available to cover the acquisition cost and future expenses. A high ARPU with low margin is fragile; a lower ARPU with high margin is more resilient.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Including non-cash expenses (depreciation, stock options, accrued vacation) in the P and L without tracking cash burn separately.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A founder can be "profitable on paper" while burning cash. Track cash-basis P and L (cash in / cash out) separately from accrual-basis for decision-making.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Acquiring customers aggressively while gross margin is 55 percent, assuming "we'll optimize later."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Later" does not come. Every new customer at 55 percent margin accelerates cash burn. Investors and co-founders will pressure for profitability, not for optimization. Fix margin before scaling.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Offering unlimited free customer support or custom integrations for every customer, disguising labor costs in "customer success" instead of COGS.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hidden labor costs erode margin in invisible ways. If 20 customers require 5 hours of custom integration each (100 hours), at $100/hour contractor cost, that is $10k/month in hidden COGS. Recognize it, price for it, or eliminate the service.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Enabling every team member to subscribe to any tool they request, resulting in $500 plus monthly in duplicate or unused subscriptions.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tool sprawl is insidious because each subscription feels small until they aggregate. A CEO using Slack, HubSpot, Notion, Zapier, Intercom, and Calendly may have 6 subscriptions times $100-500 each equals $2k plus monthly with no visibility. Require procurement approval for tools greater than $50/month.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
