<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="continuous-discovery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-planning</domain>
    <summary>Weekly discovery cadence of interviews and feedback to keep roadmap grounded in user evidence. Allocate 15–20% capacity, maintain controlled vocabulary, tie changes to opportunities.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>discovery</tag>
      <tag>continuous</tag>
      <tag>user-research</tag>
      <tag>cadence</tag>
      <tag>roadmap</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Continuous Discovery</title>
    <summary>Continuous discovery is a weekly cadence of user interviews, feedback synthesis, and opportunity-to-roadmap diffing that keeps product decisions connected to fresh user evidence. Allocate 15–20% of capacity to it, maintain a controlled vocabulary of themes (new themes need approval), and tie every roadmap change to at least one cited opportunity from the discovery repository.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Discovery treated as a one-time project-start activity produces a roadmap frozen to the assumptions of launch day. Teresa Torres' research shows teams that run weekly touchpoints with users make fundamentally different prioritization decisions than those that rely on launch-time research — because the problem space shifts and user behavior reveals what interviews cannot predict. A continuous loop closes the feedback cycle between user evidence and product direction, ensuring that hypotheses are tested and roadmaps evolve with user needs.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Post-MVP product where weekly insight is needed to keep the roadmap honest and grounded in evidence.</item>
        <item>Team has at least one customer-touching channel (interviews, support, in-app, analytics) feeding raw signal into the discovery process.</item>
        <item>Pairing with roadmap-design so Now/Next/Later buckets keep evolving in response to emerging user evidence.</item>
        <item>Solo PM or founder who needs an automated cadence to replace a research team and synthesize signals into themes.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF / 0-to-1 products — use product-discovery (deep-dive phase) until you have customers and a steady signal source.</item>
        <item>Products with fewer than 50 active users — discovery becomes anecdote-driven and too noisy to inform strategic roadmap decisions.</item>
        <item>Heavily regulated environments where every customer touch needs legal review (loop is too slow to be useful).</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="cadence">
      <p>Four-frequency discovery cadence — daily, weekly, biweekly, quarterly — with concrete activities, a capacity allocation rule, and automation requirements. The cadence interlocks activities at different time scales: daily signal ingestion (passive behavioral data), weekly sense-making (active interviews), biweekly roadmap response (closing the loop), and quarterly structural review (vocabulary and sample audits). Without structure, discovery becomes "do user research sometime" and loses signal to competing work.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Allocate 15–20% of team capacity to discovery. Schedule it as recurring calendar blocks; discovery never wins against feature pressure if it is optional.</statement>
        <rationale>Unscheduled discovery tasks are the first thing dropped under sprint pressure. A fixed calendar slot makes the cost visible and prevents the loop from collapsing.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Daily: review the support ticket triage digest and scan analytics for anomalies (&gt;2 sigma from baseline).</statement>
        <rationale>Support and analytics are passive behavioral signals that surface pain without requiring user scheduling. Anomaly detection at 2 sigma catches real problems before they accumulate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Weekly: run 1–3 user interviews, synthesize the prior 7 days of feedback into themes against the controlled vocabulary, review competitor changelogs, and draft interview questions for next week.</statement>
        <rationale>Weekly interviews compound into 50+ sessions per year — a research corpus no one-time study can match. Weekly competitor review catches market changes before they become strategic surprises.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Biweekly: diff current opportunities against the roadmap, propose adds/removes/re-prioritizations, and have a human decide and record the rationale.</statement>
        <rationale>Discovery without a roadmap feedback loop is theater. The biweekly diff is where evidence becomes decisions. Every roadmap change must cite at least one opportunity from the discovery repo.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Quarterly: re-baseline the theme vocabulary and audit interview sample for segment bias (who have you not talked to in 90 days?).</statement>
        <rationale>Theme vocabulary drift across weeks destroys longitudinal trends. Sample bias audits prevent a discovery process that only hears from engaged power users while passive and at-risk segments go unrepresented.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Schedule daily/weekly tasks via cron, n8n, or a scheduled trigger. Missed weeks erode the loop — automate or it dies.</statement>
        <rationale>Human-remembered cadences slip to "when there's time." The discovery loop requires the same infrastructure discipline as any other automated pipeline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="synthesis">
      <p>Rules for clustering feedback into stable opportunity themes, maintaining a controlled vocabulary, storing verbatim evidence, and linking themes to roadmap initiatives. Synthesis is the translation layer between raw signal and actionable opportunity. This section covers the governance structures that prevent common failure modes: theme drift, hallucination from low-signal periods, loss of evidence trail, and disconnection from roadmap response. Verbatim storage ensures the synthesis process is auditable and ground truth is preserved.</p>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Maintain a versioned controlled vocabulary of theme IDs (e.g., T-onboarding-friction). New themes require explicit human approval before being used in synthesis output.</statement>
        <rationale>Theme renaming across weeks destroys longitudinal trends. A new theme named "onboarding issues" this week and "activation friction" next week looks like two problems when it is one. Treat vocabulary changes as schema migrations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Require evidence_count &gt;= 3 before promoting a signal to a named theme. Themes with fewer than 3 signals are noise, not pattern.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs hallucinate themes from single data points. The minimum evidence threshold prevents one angry user from becoming a roadmap priority.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Always store verbatim quotes alongside synthesized themes. The summary is a navigation aid; the verbatim is the audit trail.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM-summarized interviews lose tone, sarcasm, and nuance. When a roadmap decision is challenged, the verbatim — not the summary — is what grounds the argument.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Redact PII before passing interview transcripts or support tickets to any LLM. Use a pre-pass regex or scrubber agent.</statement>
        <rationale>Customer names, emails, and identifiers in LLM input create compliance risk and degrade the generalizability of synthesis output.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every roadmap change must cite at least one opportunity ID from the discovery repository. Changes without citation are opinion-driven, not evidence-driven.</statement>
        <rationale>The citation requirement creates accountability and makes the reasoning auditable when priorities shift in the next cycle.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Triangulate: use at least two signal types — behavioral (analytics), attitudinal (interviews), and market (competitor monitoring). One source alone misleads.</statement>
        <rationale>Analytics shows what users do but not why. Interviews show why but are subject to social desirability bias. Competitor monitoring shows what the market is converging on. None is sufficient alone.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="antipatterns">
      <p>Five failure modes that turn continuous discovery into theater or produce misleading signals, with diagnosis and recovery paths for each pattern.</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Discovery runs every week but roadmap decisions never change in response to findings.</description>
        <reason>Discovery without a feedback loop into the roadmap is ceremony. If the biweekly diff never produces a proposed change, either the discovery is not surfacing real signals or the roadmap is being protected from evidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Weekly interviews recruit only engaged, active users.</description>
        <reason>Active users are not representative of the full user base. Passive users and at-risk churners have different problems. Run a quarterly sample-bias audit and rotate recruitment criteria to include users with low recent activity.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Theme vocabulary grows without governance — new theme names appear each week for the same underlying problem.</description>
        <reason>Renaming destroys longitudinal analysis. You cannot track whether "activation friction" is improving if it was called "onboarding issues" last month. Lock the vocabulary and require approval for changes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM synthesis is the only artifact — raw transcripts and verbatim quotes are discarded.</description>
        <reason>Summaries lose tone, nuance, and edge cases. When a decision is challenged, "the LLM said users want X" is not defensible. The verbatim is the source of truth; the summary is a navigation aid.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Discovery cadence is calendar-optional and skips when a sprint is busy.</description>
        <reason>Discovery always loses to feature pressure if it is optional. Schedule it as non-negotiable recurring blocks and automate the data ingestion steps so the weekly review cannot be skipped without explicit team decision.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/weekly-synthesis.json" purpose="JSON schema for weekly synthesis agent output with themes, verbatims, and roadmap links"/>
      <template path="templates/discovery-cadence.py" purpose="Script that emits this week's discovery checklist as JSON (daily/weekly/biweekly/quarterly tasks)"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/"/>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/continuous-discovery-habits-book/"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com/"/>
      <ref slug="product-discovery"/>
      <ref slug="roadmap-design"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
