<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Vector DB Security — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules: no anonymous access, TLS everywhere, private network only, audit every admin call, PII handling procedure.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-no-anonymous" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Production DB MUST require authentication (API key OR OIDC). Anonymous access endpoint disabled.</statement>
      <rationale source="vendor security guides; OWASP">Default-open vector DBs are scanned + exploited within hours of public exposure. Auth is the first wall.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-tls-everywhere" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All listeners MUST use TLS ≥1.2. Plain HTTP listeners are forbidden in production.</statement>
      <rationale source="industry security baseline">Embedded queries can contain sensitive payloads (PII, business secrets). Plain-text transport leaks both queries and results.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-private-network-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>DB listener MUST bind to a private subnet OR be reachable only via a VPC-internal LB. Public-internet exposure is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="cloud security posture">Even with auth, exposed listener invites enumeration + DDoS. Network isolation is defence in depth.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-audit-every-admin-call" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every admin operation (collection create / drop / config change, key rotate, schema change) MUST emit an audit log entry with timestamp + actor + action + outcome.</statement>
      <rationale source="SOC2 / ISO27001">Forensic ability post-incident requires reconstruction of admin actions. Silent admin changes block forensics.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-pii-handling-procedure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If corpus may contain PII, security-config MUST declare: detection method (Presidio / regex), redaction or pseudonymisation, GDPR right-to-erasure response time, retention period.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art 17; HIPAA Security Rule">PII without process is a compliance violation. Vector DBs are especially tricky: erasure requires removing the vector AND the original.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
