<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="interface-analysis">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>business-analyst</domain>
    <summary>Identify and document system boundaries: data elements, protocols, frequency, volume, security. At scale: portfolio landscape register with criticality tiers, data sensitivity, ownership.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>interface-analysis</tag>
      <tag>system-integration</tag>
      <tag>data-flows</tag>
      <tag>enterprise-architecture</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>integration</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Interface Analysis</title>

    <summary>Identifies and documents all boundaries and connections between a solution and external systems, users, hardware, and communication channels, then specifies data elements, protocols, frequency, volume, security, and error handling for each. At enterprise scale, a portfolio-level integration landscape register (one row per source-target pair, with criticality tier, sensitivity classification, and owner) precedes per-interface specification and feeds SOC2/ISO 27001/GDPR Art. 30 compliance evidence. Systems built in isolation fail at integration time; interface requirements discovered during development are the most expensive to fix.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Systems built in isolation fail at integration time. Interface requirements discovered during development are the most expensive to fix (late-change cost). At enterprise scale, undocumented "shadow integrations" — Zapier recipes, manual SFTP scripts, Excel macros — are the single most common source of audit findings and security incidents. An active-traffic reality check (90 days no traffic → retirement candidate; traffic without a register entry → governance violation) keeps the register honest.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-discovery for an enterprise-wide programme (ERP migration, M&amp;A, core-system replacement) requiring a portfolio-level interface inventory.</item>
        <item>Drafting an integration target operating model: which team owns which interface, approval process, single source of truth.</item>
        <item>Building a cross-system traceability matrix (capability → process → system → interface) to scope SOWs and impact analyses.</item>
        <item>API contract governance: naming, versioning, deprecation, SLA, security baseline standards for all internal/external interfaces.</item>
        <item>Vendor/partner onboarding with 20+ interfaces requiring a criticality-rated register with renewal dates.</item>
        <item>Producing IT general controls evidence (SOC2, ISO 27001, GDPR Art. 30) listing every system-to-system data flow with PII classification.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single feature with one external API call — use the per-interface spec in ba-modeling/interface-analysis.</item>
        <item>Greenfield startup with fewer than five systems — a one-page integration diagram is enough.</item>
        <item>Pure technical refactor (bumping protobuf version) where business capability mapping adds no decision value.</item>
        <item>Organisation lacks a system-of-record for applications (no APM/CMDB) — build that first.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="interface-types">
      <p>Classify every identified connection point into one of four types before specifying it.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Classify every identified connection point into one of four types before specifying it; mixed-type specifications produce documents with missing fields and incomplete error handling.</statement>
        <rationale>Each type has a distinct attribute set (protocol for system interfaces, device specifics for hardware interfaces, flow/trigger for communication interfaces); misclassification causes incomplete specifications discovered during integration testing.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>User interface — human interaction points: screens, reports, forms, dashboards.</item>
        <item>System interface — system-to-system connections: REST/SOAP APIs, file transfers, database connections, message queues.</item>
        <item>Hardware interface — physical device connections: scanners, printers, sensors, POS terminals.</item>
        <item>Communication interface — data exchange protocols: HTTP, SFTP, EDI X12, HL7, SWIFT, EDIFACT, fixed-width files.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="five-step-analysis-procedure">
      <p>Systematically identify, document, specify, and validate every interface.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Complete the interface questions checklist for every interface: who/what is on each end, what data is exchanged, what format, how triggered, frequency, volume, failure modes, error handling, security, and ownership.</statement>
        <rationale>Interface specifications with missing error handling, missing volume estimates, or missing security requirements are the most common cause of integration failures discovered during performance testing or production incidents.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Step 1 — Identify: list all connection points by asking what systems connect, what data flows in/out, who are the users, what devices are involved, what external parties interact.</item>
        <item>Step 2 — Document: capture all attributes per interface (name, type, direction, source/target, data, format, protocol, frequency, volume, security, error handling).</item>
        <item>Step 3 — Define data elements: specify each field (element name, type, required flag, validation rules, description).</item>
        <item>Step 4 — Specify behaviors: normal flow, error scenarios, retry logic, timeout handling, idempotency requirements.</item>
        <item>Step 5 — Validate with stakeholders: technical teams of connected systems, users for UI interfaces, operations for monitoring, security for access control.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Specifying only the happy-path flow without error scenarios.</description>
        <reason>Real integrations fail; undocumented error handling produces ad-hoc implementation decisions at development time that are inconsistent across interfaces and invisible to operations teams.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Omitting volume and frequency estimates from the interface specification.</description>
        <reason>Systems cannot handle unexpected load; volume underestimates are the leading cause of production performance failures at integration points.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Specifying authentication and security as "TBD" or "standard security".</description>
        <reason>Security requirements left unspecified default to the developer's judgment, producing inconsistent auth mechanisms, missing encryption, and audit failures.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Interface versioning not specified at initial design time.</description>
        <reason>Unversioned interfaces break downstream consumers on every change with no migration path; versioning strategy must be decided before the interface is published.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="enterprise-landscape">
      <p>At scale, interface analysis becomes a portfolio governance problem. Run discovery as a four-pass process, with human sign-off at three critical gates.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>**Pass 1 — Discovery subagent** ingests CMDB exports, API gateway access logs, iPaaS (Workato/Boomi/MuleSoft) catalogues, and produces a raw inventory. Do NOT invent interfaces not present in inputs.</statement>
        <rationale>The discovery pass must be conservative; inventing interfaces creates phantom entries the BA must later explain and removes.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>**Pass 2 — BA subagent** classifies each interface by business capability, criticality (1–4), data sensitivity (public/internal/confidential/restricted), and ownership; emits the integration landscape register. Capabilities must come from a closed list (the org's capability map).</statement>
        <rationale>Capability mapping is a business judgment, not a technical metric; constraining to an approved capability list prevents hallucinated capabilities.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>**Pass 3 — Governance subagent** diffs the register against the enterprise contract standard (naming, versioning, auth, SLA fields) and opens findings. Cite the standard line number for every finding.</statement>
        <rationale>Structured governance rules (encoded as Spectral rules or similar) are more enforceable than written PDFs alone.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>**Pass 4 — Human-in-the-loop review** with architecture and security before publication. Mandatory sign-offs: (1) capability-to-system mapping by Architecture, (2) sensitivity classification by Data Office, (3) tier-1 criticality by business owner, (4) deprecation decisions before retirement.</statement>
        <rationale>These judgments involve business stakeholders and cannot be automated; mandatory sign-off creates accountability.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>**Quarterly audit pass**: re-pull CMDB + iPaaS feeds, diff against committed register, open SDD tasks for new/retired interfaces. Any interface in the register without traffic in the gateway for 90 days → candidate for retirement; any traffic without a register entry → governance violation.</statement>
        <rationale>Active-traffic reality checks keep the register honest and surface shadow IT.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="landscape-register-schema">
      <p>The portfolio-level integration landscape register is a table with stable IF-IDs that other documents can reference.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Each row in the landscape register represents one logical interface (source-target pair) with a stable IF-ID. Single source of truth per interface: the OpenAPI/AsyncAPI/Protobuf file in the owning team's repo. The register only references it (link + commit hash), never copies field-level details.</statement>
        <rationale>Duplicating interface specs across the register and per-interface documents creates drift; one source of truth is enforceable via CI checks.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Capability-first IDs: tie every interface to a business capability code (`CAP-FIN-AR-01`) so retirement decisions are made at capability level, not by team.</statement>
        <rationale>When a business capability retires (e.g., manual expense reports → automated), all its interfaces are retirement candidates; capability-first IDs make this traceability explicit.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Criticality tiers drive policy: tier-1 interfaces require contract tests, breaking-change review, and 24/7 monitoring; tier-4 needs only the register row.</statement>
        <rationale>Criticality is a business judgment about impact; different tiers justify different governance overhead.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Data sensitivity inherited from data catalogue: do not re-classify at interface level; pull from Purview/Collibra/Atlan. If unknown, emit `unknown` and surface for human review.</statement>
        <rationale>Field-level truth lives in the data catalogue; interface-level classification is a lossy aggregate.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Deprecation calendar: every interface has a `valid-until` date or "evergreen"; agents scan quarterly and warn on stale ones.</statement>
        <rationale>Interfaces without planned retirement are governance debt; date-stamping them surfaces the decision for renewal or retirement.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="governance-and-standards">
      <p>Encode interface standards as code (Spectral rules) rather than written PDFs; humans approve exceptions only.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Standards as code: encode the API contract standard as Spectral rules and run them in every team's CI; written PDFs alone are ignored.</statement>
        <rationale>CI gates enforce compliance on every change; governance boards review exceptions only. This scales to polyglot portfolios.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Two views, one register: capability view for executives (heatmap), technical view for engineers (sequence + auth); generate both from the same register.</statement>
        <rationale>Single register, multiple views prevents stakeholder groups from seeing inconsistent state.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Federated governance over central: a small standards team curates rules; product teams own their interfaces; quarterly review board handles exceptions only.</statement>
        <rationale>Centralized governance becomes a bottleneck; federated with clear escalation paths scales to large portfolios.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Plain-text artefacts: register in Markdown/CSV in Git, not in a proprietary EA tool only — agents need to read and diff.</statement>
        <rationale>Plain text in Git enables CI checks, diff reviews, and automated governance; proprietary tools are agent-unfriendly.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="common-failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inventory rot: an interface register collected by spreadsheet ages within one quarter; without an automated feed (CMDB + API gateway logs + iPaaS catalogue) the doc becomes a liability.</description>
        <reason>Automate the discovery pass quarterly; diff against the committed register to surface drift. Make the audit part of the SDD cycle.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Shadow integrations (Zapier, Make, manual SFTP scripts on someone's laptop, Excel macros pulling from SharePoint) never make it onto the BA's diagram and cause every audit finding.</description>
        <reason>Explicitly task a separate discovery pass against email/Slack/Workato/Power Automate logs to surface candidates. Make shadow IT discovery a sub-task.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Capability-to-system mapping disagrees across Architecture, Finance, and IT — the BA inherits the political fight, not just the modelling task.</description>
        <reason>Get architecture sign-off on the capability-to-system map before launching the landscape discovery. Store the mapping as a separate approved artifact.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Governance theatre: contract review boards approve in hours what teams need to ship in minutes; ungoverned channels appear (slack DMs, untracked dev keys).</description>
        <reason>Encode governance rules in CI (Spectral, oasdiff) so teams get instant feedback; escalate only genuine exceptions to a review board.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>PII/data-classification is best-guessed at landscape level; field-level truth lives in the per-interface spec, so the landscape view is structurally lossy.</description>
        <reason>Pull sensitivity classification from the data catalogue (Purview/Collibra/Atlan), not from interface specs. Mark unknowns explicitly.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM agents over-collapse heterogeneous flows ("all integrations are REST") — async/file/EDI/SWIFT/HL7 v2/EDIFACT channels are routinely misclassified.</description>
        <reason>Require the agent to cite a payload sample or gateway log line per row. Preserve the protocol family in a separate column for diversity.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents conflate "interface" with "endpoint" — one interface can have many endpoints; force the prompt to use IF-ID = logical contract, not URL path.</description>
        <reason>Define interface explicitly in the prompt: "one logical contract between source and target; one row per source-target pair; multiple endpoints under one interface are subsumed."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Direction perspective drift: across a portfolio, "inbound" depends on which system you sit at. Anchor each row to source→target, never relative terms.</description>
        <reason>Enforce source→target direction in every row. Use consistent naming (Source, Target, not Upstream/Downstream).</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Channel misclassification (REST vs RPC vs Webhook vs Event) — require the agent to cite a payload sample or gateway log line per row.</description>
        <reason>Require evidence: each row has a `payload_sample_link` or `gateway_log_ref`. Reject rows without evidence.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Capability mapping invented from system names: agents hallucinate capability codes; require a closed list (the org's capability map) as input.</description>
        <reason>Pass the capability map to the agent as a closed vocabulary. Reject any capability code not in the list.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Sensitivity classification: agents default to "internal" when unsure — instead instruct them to emit `unknown` and surface for human review.</description>
        <reason>Forbid the agent from guessing; mandate `unknown` for any row without explicit classification in the source system.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Owner fields auto-filled from system name pattern guesses; only accept owners present in CMDB output.</description>
        <reason>Validate every owner against the CMDB extract. Reject agents' guesses; flag as `tbd` and escalate to human.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Criticality is a business judgement, not a technical metric — never let the agent set tier-1 without explicit human sign-off.</description>
        <reason>Forbid the agent from setting criticality > 2 without explicit approval. Tier-1 requires business owner sign-off.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Long-tail integrations (EDI X12, SWIFT, HL7 v2, EDIFACT, fixed-width files) get squashed into "file transfer" — preserve the protocol family in a separate column.</description>
        <reason>Keep protocol, channel, and format as separate columns. Preserve heterogeneity.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Shadow IT: agents will not find what is not in their inputs. Explicitly task a separate pass against email/Slack/Workato/Power Automate to surface candidates.</description>
        <reason>Shadow IT discovery is a separate pass with human spot-checking. Do not expect agents to find what is hidden.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Single source of truth per interface: the OpenAPI/AsyncAPI/Protobuf file in the owning team's repo. The register only references it.</item>
        <item>Capability-first IDs: tie every interface to a business capability code so retirement decisions are made at capability level.</item>
        <item>Criticality tiers drive policy: tier-1 requires contract tests and 24/7 monitoring; tier-4 needs only the register row.</item>
        <item>Standards as code: encode the API contract standard as Spectral rules and run them in every team's CI.</item>
        <item>Deprecation calendar: every interface has a `valid-until` date or "evergreen".</item>
        <item>Data sensitivity inherited from data catalogue: pull from Purview/Collibra/Atlan, not from interface specs.</item>
        <item>Two views, one register: capability view for executives (heatmap), technical view for engineers (sequence + auth).</item>
        <item>Active-traffic reality check: 90 days no traffic → retirement candidate; traffic without a register entry → governance violation.</item>
        <item>Federated governance over central: small standards team curates rules; product teams own interfaces; board handles exceptions only.</item>
        <item>Plain-text artefacts: register in Markdown/CSV in Git for CI checks and automated governance.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/interface-specification.md" purpose="Per-interface spec: overview, connected systems, data spec, technical spec, operational spec, error handling, security."/>
      <template path="templates/interface-catalog.md" purpose="Interface catalog summary table with diagram placeholder and links to per-interface specs."/>
      <template path="templates/landscape-register.md" purpose="Portfolio landscape register table (IF-ID, Source, Target, Channel, Criticality, Sensitivity, Owner, SLA, Standard?)."/>
      <template path="templates/landscape-merge.sh" purpose="Script: merge CMDB export + gateway dump → starter register.csv for BA enrichment."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://pubs.opengroup.org/togaf92/"/>
      <link href="https://pubs.openapis.org/"/>
      <link href="https://backstage.io/docs/features/software-catalog/"/>
      <link href="https://docs.stoplight.io/docs/spectral/"/>
      <ref slug="ba-modeling"/>
      <ref slug="api-governance"/>
      <ref slug="requirements-lifecycle"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
