<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="employer-branding">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>comms</group>
    <domain>hr-recruiter</domain>
    <summary>Build and maintain employer brand across Glassdoor, LinkedIn, careers pages, and testimonials with structured audit, content strategy, and human-approval gates. Requires a completed EVP.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>employer-branding</tag>
      <tag>recruitment</tag>
      <tag>brand</tag>
      <tag>content-strategy</tag>
      <tag>recruiting</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <requires>
      <ref slug="employee-value-proposition"/>
    </requires>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Employer Branding</title>

    <summary>Strategy and execution methodology for building and maintaining an employer brand across Glassdoor, LinkedIn, careers page, employee testimonials, and content calendars. Requires a completed EVP as input. The testable rule: every external-facing brand asset must trace back to a named EVP pillar, and no asset containing DEI claims, compensation data, or employee quotes may be published without human approval.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Employer brand drives application quality and quantity independent of job-board spend. Review monitoring within 48 hours improves rating trend; mechanical calendars without novelty injection decay in 4-6 weeks. AI-generated testimonials that read synthetic and Glassdoor responses that sound defensive are documented reputation risks. Human approval before any external publish is the non-negotiable gate.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Annual or quarterly employer-brand audit: scrape reviews, benchmark vs. competitors, identify perception-reality gaps.</item>
        <item>Producing a 4-12 week content calendar across LinkedIn, Instagram, careers blog.</item>
        <item>Drafting and rotating employee testimonials from employee-supplied raw material.</item>
        <item>Monitoring and responding to Glassdoor/Indeed/Comparably reviews within 48h SLA.</item>
        <item>Building and nurturing a talent community (rejected-but-strong candidates).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>No EVP or culture document exists — do `employee-value-proposition` methodology first.</item>
        <item>Crisis comms (layoffs, PR incident) — switch to crisis-communication workflow; brand agents produce tone-deaf copy during crises.</item>
        <item>Highly regulated industries where every external post requires compliance review before agents can draft but not publish.</item>
        <item>Sub-30-employee companies — the founder's voice is the brand; structured calendars are overkill.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="brand-audit-framework">
      <p>Perception-vs-reality audit process using Glassdoor, LinkedIn, candidate surveys, and exit interviews.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Run brand audits annually at minimum. A gap greater than 1.0 on a 5-point scale between internal perception (employee surveys) and external perception (Glassdoor/Comparably) signals repositioning is needed.</statement>
        <rationale>A large perception gap means either the EVP over-promises (candidates arrive disappointed) or the brand under-communicates genuine strengths (missed talent).</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Compare each EVP pillar against 3-5 direct talent competitors. Identify where you lead, where you are table-stakes, and where you trail — and never claim leadership where you trail.</statement>
        <rationale>Candidates research employers on Glassdoor and LinkedIn before applying. Positioning claims that contradict visible competitor data undermine recruiter credibility in screening calls.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Respond to every Glassdoor review within 48 hours, including positive ones. Cap responses at 80 words. Never use "We are committed to..." Never dispute employee experience; only describe actions taken or planned.</statement>
        <rationale>Over-defensive responses go viral and amplify negative reviews. Responses that dispute employee perception demonstrate the exact culture problems reviewers described.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Audit inputs to collect:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Glassdoor: overall rating, review themes (pros/cons frequency), response rate trend.</item>
        <item>LinkedIn: follower growth rate, organic post engagement, career page conversion rate.</item>
        <item>Candidate surveys: post-interview NPS, "why declined" categories, source attribution.</item>
        <item>Employee surveys: eNPS, top-ranked EVP pillars vs. bottom-ranked, open-text themes.</item>
        <item>Exit interviews: top 3 stated reasons for leaving, manager-specific patterns.</item>
      </list>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-publishing Glassdoor responses without human approval.</description>
        <reason>Agent-generated responses that contradict employee experience or sound legalistic create PR incidents that are harder to recover from than the original review.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <reference path="templates/glassdoor-response.txt">Response structure for Glassdoor reviews: acknowledge, describe action, 80-word cap.</reference>

      <p>Tools and services for brand auditing include Glassdoor for Employers (reviews API for enterprise tiers), Indeed Employer and Comparably (limited APIs, mostly UI-driven), LinkedIn Talent Solutions (career pages and analytics via API), and reputation monitoring platforms like Reputation.com and ReviewTrackers.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="content-strategy">
      <p>Content calendar structure, channel-specific voice rules, and employee testimonial intake pipeline.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Rotate four content types in a 4-week repeating cycle: employee spotlight, behind-the-scenes, culture moment, job opening promo. Every slot must trace back to a named EVP pillar.</statement>
        <rationale>Mechanical calendars without novelty injection decay after 4-6 weeks of engagement. The 4-type rotation balances brand-building with hiring intent and gives the algorithm enough variety to avoid suppression.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Content rotation schedule:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Week 1: Employee spotlight (LinkedIn) — personal story tied to Growth or Purpose pillar.</item>
        <item>Week 2: Behind-the-scenes (Instagram/video) — ≤90s, culture moment in action.</item>
        <item>Week 3: Culture moment (LinkedIn long-form) — ≤300 words, specific event or milestone.</item>
        <item>Week 4: Open role promo (LinkedIn + Indeed) — paired with "what we're building" context post.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Never use the same post copy across channels. LinkedIn requires professional framing; Instagram requires visual-first brevity; careers blog allows long-form authenticity.</statement>
        <rationale>Channel voice mismatch produces flat copy that is suppressed by algorithms and dismissed by audiences. The same text on LinkedIn and TikTok will underperform on both.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Cap LinkedIn hashtags at 3-5 per post. Never stuff more than 5.</statement>
        <rationale>LinkedIn best practice is 3-5 hashtags; more signals low-quality content and suppresses organic reach.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every employee testimonial must have a signed consent form and image release before publication. Use DRAFT-only status with [NAME] [TITLE] tokens until consent is captured and confirmed.</statement>
        <rationale>Publishing testimonials without consent exposes employees and the company to legal liability. Agents must never auto-publish; always require explicit human confirmation that consent is on file.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Require employee-supplied raw quotes before drafting testimonials. Never synthesize quotes from job-offer letters, LinkedIn profiles, or performance reviews.</statement>
        <rationale>AI-generated testimonials that were not said by real employees are ethically indefensible and legally risky if used in candidate-facing materials.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Repurposing one testimonial format across all channels without adaptation.</description>
        <reason>A 300-word LinkedIn testimonial becomes unreadable on Instagram; a 30-second video quote loses context in a blog post. Repurpose with channel-specific editing, not copy-paste.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <reference path="templates/content-calendar.md">4-week brand content plan with per-slot hook, body, CTA, asset brief.</reference>
      <reference path="templates/testimonial-brief.md">Employee testimonial intake: raw quote fields, consent checklist, approval flow.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="rules-and-gates">
      <p>Human-approval gates, ToS constraints, and antipatterns for employer branding agent workflows.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Any external publication — LinkedIn post, Glassdoor response, Instagram content, blog post — requires human approval before publish. Agents draft; humans approve and post.</statement>
        <rationale>Brand voice drift, DEI misrepresentation, and legally risky compensation claims are impossible to fully prevent at generation time. The approval gate is the only reliable safeguard.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>DEI claims (diversity percentages, ERG names, inclusion programs) must be sourced from HRIS data, not synthesized. Every DEI claim in a draft must have a data citation or be marked UNVERIFIED.</statement>
        <rationale>Invented diversity statistics are a serious legal and reputational risk. Candidates and journalists verify claims; inaccurate statistics cause brand damage that exceeds the original benefit.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Do not scrape Glassdoor or Indeed without their official API (Glassdoor for Employers tier). Automated scraping without API access violates ToS and can result in employer account suspension.</statement>
        <rationale>A suspended employer account on Glassdoor removes all company review responses and brand profile, causing permanent brand damage that exceeds the value of scraped data.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Use UTM-tagged careers page links per channel for source attribution; agents must add UTMs by default. Diversity content should lead with employee voices, never with leadership claims; metrics only when published quarterly internally. Pair every "we're hiring" post with a "what we're building" post — applications follow trust, not job listings. Repurpose content efficiently: one long-form testimonial → 5 LinkedIn quotes → 1 video → 1 newsletter feature.</p>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Cliché injection in every brand draft: "passionate team," "world-class culture," "amazing people."</description>
        <reason>These phrases appear on 90%+ of employer brand pages and provide zero differentiation. They train candidates to ignore the content.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Generating fake employee names or composite quotes when raw material is missing.</description>
        <reason>Fabricated employee voices are unethical and constitute false advertising in candidate-facing materials. Always require real employee input before drafting.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Brand voice drift across 50+ content generations without re-anchoring.</description>
        <reason>Agents drift from the established voice even when the brand guide is in context. Include 3 approved sample posts in every content generation prompt to re-anchor tone.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Hashtag stuffing: LLMs add 15+ hashtags per post.</description>
        <reason>LinkedIn best practice is 3–5 per post; overstuffing signals low-quality content and suppresses reach.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Image rights violations: agents pull stock images that may be unlicensed.</description>
        <reason>Use whitelisted libraries only (Unsplash, company DAM) to avoid legal exposure.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Localization mishap: a US-positive phrase ("crushing it") translates poorly across markets.</description>
        <reason>Agents must localize per market, not direct-translate; market-specific language is the agent's responsibility before submission.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <p>Best practices summary: audit perception (external) vs. reality (internal surveys) annually; gap > 1.0 on 5-pt scale = repositioning needed. Respond to every Glassdoor review within 48h, including positive ones; pattern-match, don't templatize. Get written employee consent + image release before testimonial publication; store in HRIS. Never auto-publish any external brand asset; always human approval on external content, DEI claims, compensation claims, and employee quotes.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/content-calendar.md" purpose="4-week brand content plan with channel, hook, body, CTA, asset brief per slot."/>
      <template path="templates/glassdoor-response.txt" purpose="Response structure for negative/mixed reviews: acknowledge, describe action, cap 80 words."/>
      <template path="templates/testimonial-brief.md" purpose="Employee testimonial intake: raw quote fields, consent checklist, publication approval flow."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="employee-value-proposition"/>
      <link href="https://business.linkedin.com/talent-solutions/employer-brand"/>
      <link href="https://www.glassdoor.com/employers/employer-branding/"/>
      <link href="https://www.indeed.com/hire/c/info/employer-branding"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
