<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Stakeholder Sentiment Tracker — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for an opt-in, weekly, three-class sentiment trend with an alarm trigger and a mandatory action-plan attachment.</summary>

  <section title="Rules">

    <rule id="r1-consent-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Ingestion of any source artefact for sentiment tracking MUST be preceded by documented consent: either an organisation-level policy citation OR a per-stakeholder opt-in record stored with the consent date and the artefact scope. The PM MUST be able to produce the consent record on demand.</statement>
      <rationale source="GDPR Art.6 lawful-basis patterns; corporate sentiment-monitoring case law">Sentiment tracking on private communications without consent is a legal and trust-destroying risk. Storing the consent record as a precondition makes the entire pipeline defensible if it is ever questioned.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-three-class-rubric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The classification rubric MUST use exactly three classes — `supportive`, `cautious`, `hostile` — with at least 5 explicit linguistic markers per class checked into the rubric file. Free-form sentiment scores (-1 to 1, 0-100) are not accepted because they hide the markers behind a number.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reichheld NPS critique; closed-vocab sentiment classifier literature">Three-class output is what PMs can act on; numeric scores are noise that invites cherry-picking the threshold. Pinned linguistic markers also make the classifier auditable when a stakeholder disputes a "hostile" label.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-weekly-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The pipeline MUST run on a fixed weekly cadence, at the same weekday/time, and MUST produce a per-stakeholder entry even when no new artefacts arrived (with an explicit "no signal" class). Skipping a week silently is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Continuous-monitoring patterns (Allspaw); silence-as-signal in customer-success ops">A "no signal" week is itself a data point — a stakeholder who has gone quiet is a known precursor to going hostile. Letting the pipeline skip silently loses that signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-two-week-alarm" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An alarm MUST fire when EITHER (a) a stakeholder's classification declines for 2 consecutive weeks (supportive→cautious or cautious→hostile), OR (b) any single week's classification is `hostile`. The alarm MUST be delivered to the PM channel within 24 hours of the run completing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Distressed-project rescue patterns; sponsor-attrition retrospectives">Two-week decline catches the silent drift pattern; single-week hostile catches the acute event. Together they cover both failure modes without flooding the PM with noise on normal weeks.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-action-plan-attached" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An alarm MUST be paired with a written PM action plan within 72 hours, containing: (a) hypothesised cause, (b) named intervention (call / meeting / written response), (c) deadline. Alarms left without an action plan past 72 hours block the next sentiment run.</statement>
      <rationale source="OKR retro discipline; PDCA loop closure">An alarm without an action is a notification, not a tool. Blocking the next run is the only enforcement that survives a busy PM week; otherwise alarms accumulate and the system decays into noise.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Sentiment run — 2026-05-20

## Stakeholder: Maria Lopes (VP Ops, sponsor)
- Sources: 14 emails, 3 meeting transcripts (consent: 2026-01-10)
- Markers hit: "concerned", "let's reconsider", "timeline slipping"
- Class: cautious (down from supportive last week — 2-week decline trend)
- Trend (last 6 weeks): supportive, supportive, supportive, supportive, cautious, cautious

## ALARM
- Stakeholder: Maria Lopes
- Reason: 2-week decline (supportive → cautious → cautious)
- Action plan (filed 2026-05-22):
  - Hypothesis: April milestone slip eroded confidence.
  - Intervention: 30-min 1:1 with Maria, walk through revised plan + slip RCA.
  - Deadline: 2026-05-24
      ]]></code>
      <note>Consent recorded. Three-class output. Trend visible. Alarm fired and paired with an action plan within 72h.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
# Sentiment dashboard

| Stakeholder | Score |
|-------------|-------|
| Maria Lopes | 4/10  |
| Tomás Silva | 7/10  |

(No prior weeks shown; no consent record; no alarm threshold defined.)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Free-form score, no trend, no consent trail, no alarm policy, no action plan. Functionally a feeling expressed in numbers.</note>
    </example>

  </section>
</text>
