<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="gcp-storage Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for gcp-storage. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Bucket storage class MUST be selected based on data access frequency: Standard for hot data (accessed &gt;1x/month), Nearline for warm data (accessed &lt;1x/month), Coldline for cold data (accessed &lt;1x/quarter), and Archive for compliance archives (accessed &lt;1x/year or policy-driven only). Buckets MUST NOT default to Standard for all tiers; misaligned storage class multiplies monthly storage costs 10-20x.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Storage cost per GB/month: Standard $0.020, Nearline $0.010, Coldline $0.004, Archive $0.0012. Retrieval fee per GB: Standard $0, Nearline $0.01, Coldline $0.02, Archive $0.05. For data accessed &lt;1x/month, Nearline cost = $0.01/GB stored + $0.01/GB retrieved = $0.02 total; Standard = $0.20 + $0 retrieval = $0.20 total (10x more). Archive for quarterly-accessed data pays $0.005 storage + $0.05 retrieval but quarterly cost = $0.005*90 + $0.05 = $0.50; yearly cost = $0.005*365 + $0.05*4 = $0.203 (4x cheaper than Coldline).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buckets MUST define lifecycle rules that transition objects from Standard → Nearline (30d) → Coldline (90d) → Archive (365d) matching observed access patterns, unless data has a specific compliance retention period. Lifecycle rules MUST be tested on a sample dataset first and MUST NOT be applied retroactively to billions of objects without billing impact analysis. Rules for noncurrent versions MUST be configured separately from LIVE version transitions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Lifecycle transitions are non-reversible; once data moves to Archive, retrieval fee ($0.05/GB) applies immediately. Testing on sample data with lifecycle dry-run (gcloud storage buckets update --dry-run) prevents unexpected cost surprises. Noncurrent versions (enabled by versioning) accumulate storage cost; cleaning them up on a 90-day schedule reduces cost 5-10x for high-write scenarios.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All buckets MUST enable uniform bucket-level access (UBA) to replace legacy ACL-based access. Buckets MUST NOT grant allUsers or allAuthenticatedUsers roles except for explicitly public CDN/website buckets with separate Security policy. Service accounts MUST be granted least-privilege roles: storage.objectCreator (write-only), storage.objectViewer (read-only), storage.objectAdmin (read-write-delete) based on application needs. Cross-project access MUST use Service Account credentials with Workload Identity Federation for external callers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Legacy ACLs (per-object, per-user) create matrix of access rules that are unmaintainable and audit-opaque. UBA simplifies to single policy per bucket, enabling centralized IAM review. Least-privilege prevents credential over-provisioning: an application writing logs needs objectCreator, not objectAdmin. Workload Identity Federation eliminates need to export and rotate service account keys, reducing key exposure surface to near-zero.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buckets storing PII, financial data, or compliance-sensitive data MUST use CMEK encryption with Cloud KMS keys rotated at least annually. KMS keyring MUST be in the same location as the bucket to avoid cross-region key retrieval latency. KMS CryptoKey MUST grant storage.serviceAgent the cloudkms.cryptoKeyEncrypterDecrypter role automatically (or manually for fine-grained control). CSEK MUST NOT be used; it requires per-request key management and is operationally burdensome.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">GMEK (default) encrypts data but uses Google-managed keys; customers cannot audit or rotate keys. CMEK enables key rotation policies (preventing unauthorized decryption if key is compromised), audit logging (Cloud Audit Logs records all encrypt/decrypt operations), and compliance evidence (demonstrate customer control over data encryption). CSEK requires managing per-object keys in application code, increasing operational risk. Cloud KMS in same location as bucket avoids 10-50ms cross-region latency on every encrypt/decrypt.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buckets accessed from a single Compute Engine region MUST be regional in that same region to minimize latency and eliminate inter-region egress charges. Buckets requiring high availability and disaster recovery MUST be dual-region (two specific regions selected by Google for geographic separation) to survive single-region outages. Buckets serving global traffic MUST be multi-regional (continent-scoped: US, EU, ASIA) for lowest latency to all users. Regional buckets MUST NOT be changed to dual/multi-region post-creation (bucket location is immutable); plan location before creating. Compliance requirements (data residency) MUST be verified before location selection; some regulations require data to stay in specific country/region.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Same-region access: zero egress cost, 10-20ms latency. Cross-region egress: $0.12/GB. Regional bucket accessed from different region = expensive and slow. Dual-region enables RTO/RPO compliance (disaster recovery; data survives region failure). Multi-regional provides global distribution but at higher cost (3 copies, one per continent). Bucket location is immutable; changing requires copying to new bucket (time, cost, downtime).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Public static content MUST be served through Cloud CDN with cache mode CACHE_ALL_STATIC for assets (CSS, JS, images) and CACHE_BASED_ON_HEADERS for dynamic content. Cache TTLs MUST be set per content type: 1-year for versioned assets, 1-week for images, &lt;5 seconds for API responses. Origin bucket MUST be in a separate IAM space from private data buckets; public CDN bucket MUST grant allUsers storage.objectViewer role only, never storage.objectAdmin.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">CACHE_ALL_STATIC caches immutable content (versioned file names with hash: app.abc123.js) indefinitely; prevents "stale" served content by design. Dynamic content uses Cache-Control header from origin to determine TTL. Cache hit ratios of 95%+ reduce origin load 20x and latency 5x. Separate buckets prevent accidentally granting CDN public access to private data. Cloud Armor (bot protection, geo-blocking, rate limiting) applied at load balancer prevents DDoS and abuse.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buckets accessed from Compute Engine or Kubernetes Engine MUST be co-located in the same region to minimize latency and eliminate egress charges. Buckets with latency-critical workloads (&lt;10ms p99) MUST use Rapid Storage (available in specific zones: us-central1-a, us-central1-b, us-central1-c, and growing). Parallel uploads/downloads MUST use gsutil -m (multiprocessing) or client library parallel composite uploads for files &gt;150MB to maximize throughput.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Cross-region egress costs $0.12/GB (intra-region is free). Latency: intra-region read = 10-20ms, cross-region = 100-200ms, cold start in Rapid Storage = 0.5-1ms. Rapid Storage trades cost ($0.035/GB/month vs $0.020 Standard) for 20x latency reduction. Parallel operations enable throughput: 4 parallel uploads of 40MB each = 160MB/s; sequential uploads = 40MB/s.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Versioning MUST be enabled for buckets storing critical or compliance-sensitive data (backups, legal documents, financial records). Versioning SHOULD NOT be enabled for high-volume logs or temporary data to avoid storage cost explosion. Noncurrent version retention policy MUST be configured: delete noncurrent versions after X days (typically 30-90 days) to bound storage cost. Retention policies (legal hold, indefinite retention) MUST be applied only when compliance requires it; they prevent deletion and should be documented with retention justification. Versioning queries (list-versions, get version history) SHOULD be done via BigQuery audit logs, not gcloud directly, for large version counts.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Versioning prevents data loss from accidental overwrites or deletes: rollback to previous version instantly. Cost: each version consumes storage (versioned bucket = 2x cost if every object is rewritten). Noncurrent version cleanup (e.g., keep 3 versions, delete older) prevents unbounded growth. Retention policies lock data for compliance (SOC2, HIPAA, PCI-DSS); they cannot be removed until retention period expires. Large version histories (millions of versions) slow gcloud operations; BigQuery is more efficient for analytics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Signed URLs MUST be used for temporary access (hours, not days). Signed URL duration MUST match use case: 1 hour for form uploads, 15 minutes for API responses, 1 day for file downloads. Signed URLs MUST be generated by authorized principals (service account with signing permissions) not users; users receive the signed URL. HTTPS MUST be used when transmitting signed URLs to prevent interception (HTTPS is enforced for gcloud operations but document this for custom implementations). Signed URLs MUST NOT be embedded in logs or monitoring (they are bearer tokens); if leaked, anyone can access the object until expiration. Signed policies (for HTML forms) MUST be preferred over embedded signed URLs in web pages.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Signed URLs avoid granting permanent IAM access: generate URL on-demand, expires after time period. HTTPS ensures URL is not sniffed. Short duration (1h) limits damage if URL is leaked. Signed policies enable browser-based uploads without backend intermediary (form POST with policy + signature). Documentation of duration prevents accidental long-term access (30-day signed URLs are bearer tokens; 30-day is too long for security).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r10" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buckets MUST enable Data Access audit logging (roles: storage.GetIamPolicy, storage.ListBucket, storage.GetObject, storage.PutObject, storage.DeleteObject) for compliance/security audits. Data Access logs MUST be exported to BigQuery for long-term retention and alerting. Storage Insights MUST be enabled for buckets &gt;100GB to identify unused data and optimize storage class allocation. Cost anomaly alerts MUST be configured in Cloud Monitoring to notify on unexpected egress or early deletion charges.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Admin Activity logs (on by default) record bucket creation/deletion but not object reads. Data Access logs (opt-in, billable ~$5-10 per 100GB after free tier) record every operation for audit trails. Exporting to BigQuery enables retention beyond 90 days and SQL queries to identify patterns (e.g., which users access which objects, hourly access distribution). Storage Insights costs $0.10 per GB/month analyzed; ROI is high for large buckets (identify 10TB unused data = $200/month savings).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
