<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="gcp-storage Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for gcp-storage as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using Archive for data with unpredictable or bursty access patterns without understanding early deletion penalties.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Archive has 365-day minimum duration. If data is deleted after 200 days, you pay for the full 365 days ($0.0012 * 365 / 30 = $0.0146/GB month) but only used 200 days. Use Coldline (90-day) for unpredictable access instead.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating lifecycle rules that transition data based on assumptions about future access patterns without analyzing actual access logs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Use Storage Insights or BigQuery export of storage logs to validate assumptions. Data accessed only in specific months (e.g., tax data accessed in Q1) benefits from time-based transitions; data accessed randomly needs Autoclass instead. Assumptions lead to premature transitions and high retrieval costs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Sharing long-lived service account keys with applications instead of using Workload Identity or Workload Identity Federation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Shared keys rotate infrequently and are exposed if code is open-sourced or logs are leaked. Workload Identity (in-GCP) and WIF (cross-cloud) bind Kubernetes service accounts or external identities (AWS STS, GitHub OIDC) to Google service accounts without keys. Rotate identities by changing role bindings; no key rotation needed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Using CSEK (customer-supplied keys) to comply with bring-your-own-key requirements.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CSEK requires managing keys in application code (HTTP header X-Goog-Encryption-Key on every request). If key is lost, data is irrecoverable. Use CMEK + Cloud KMS instead: manage keys in KMS (Google-operated HSM), audit via Cloud Audit Logs, rotate via policy, no per-request key management.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating multi-region buckets for all data to "maximize availability" when single-region or dual-region is sufficient.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multi-region (continent-scoped) stores 3 copies and costs more. For most applications, regional + backup (cross-region replication) is better. Only use multi-region if you have users across continents and need sub-100ms latency everywhere.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Setting very high TTLs (e.g., max-ttl=31536000 / 1 year) on all content without versioning strategy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>If you serve app.js with 1-year TTL and then deploy a bug fix, cached clients won't download new version for 365 days. Always version mutable content (app.v2.js, app.v3.js) and serve versioned URLs with aggressive TTL. Unversioned content (index.html) should have short TTL (&lt;1 hour) to enable rapid deploy-to-live cycles.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Using random object name prefixes (UUIDs) to avoid "hot object" throttling, then later discovering aggregate throughput is still bottlenecked.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Request rate limiting applies per bucket, not per object. Randomizing prefixes reduces per-object request rate throttling (rare edge case) but doesn't increase overall bucket throughput. Root cause of slowness is usually co-location, parallelism, or network path; fix those first. Only use prefix randomization if explicitly hitting per-object rate limits and confirmed by gcloud monitoring.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Using versioning as a backup mechanism instead of geographic replication or cross-bucket replication.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Versioning protects against logical errors (accidental delete, overwrite) but not against bucket deletion or regional disaster. For true backup, use cross-region replication (dual-region bucket) or replicate to a different bucket in a different region. Versioning + replication = defense in depth.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Generating long-duration signed URLs (days/months) to avoid regenerating them frequently.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Long-duration signed URLs are bearer tokens; if leaked, attacker has access for entire duration. Generate URLs on-demand with short duration. Backend generates URL per request (seconds of overhead), not hours of convenience.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Enabling Data Access logging for all operations without sampling, generating massive BigQuery tables and high egress/write costs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Data Access logs are billable. A bucket with 1M daily operations = 30M rows/month in BigQuery. Use --log-filter to exclude routine operations (e.g., exclude storage.GetObject operations from monitoring app reads) and --sampling to log only 1% of high-volume operations. Balance audit trail completeness with cost.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
