<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="writing-specifications">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd</domain>
    <summary>A specification answers WHAT to build and WHY, functioning as the anti-hallucination anchor for LLM execution agents with structured functional requirements and acceptance criteria.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>specification</tag>
      <tag>requirements</tag>
      <tag>acceptance-criteria</tag>
      <tag>llm-execution</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Writing Specifications</title>
    <summary>A specification answers WHAT to build and WHY. It functions as the anti-hallucination anchor for LLM execution agents: every FR-X must be a SHALL statement meeting SMART criteria, and every acceptance criterion must use concrete values in Given-When-Then format. The spec is not considered complete until a second, fresh-context agent outputs "SPEC APPROVED" after running the AC coverage checklist (happy path, error handling, boundary conditions, security, performance, accessibility).</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Traditional specs were alignment artifacts for humans. LLM agents require specs that act as programming interfaces: structured requirements with measurable thresholds replace narrative context and implied constraints. Without an explicit "Out of Scope" section, agents implement out-of-scope features. The "curse of instructions" — model adherence drops with more than 200 FRs — forces ruthless prioritization and phase splitting.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Before any LLM-assisted implementation: the spec is the primary context document</item>
        <item>When requirements come as vague requests — transform them into structured FR-X + AC-X artifacts</item>
        <item>Writing CLAUDE.md or project rules using the three-tier boundary system (Always / Ask First / Never)</item>
        <item>Any feature affecting multiple files, teams, or external APIs</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Bug fix with a known root cause and clear fix — write the fix, not a spec</item>
        <item>Configuration-only change — no functional requirements to specify</item>
        <item>One-off script or throwaway prototype — overhead exceeds value</item>
        <item>When requirements are so volatile they will change before implementation starts</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="what-a-spec-is">
      <rule>
        <statement>A specification answers WHAT to build and WHY; it must not answer HOW.</statement>
        <rationale>Conflating WHAT with HOW produces a document that confuses intent with implementation, prevents clean design alternatives, and creates traceability problems when designs change.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Specification: WHAT and WHY → requirements, user stories, acceptance criteria</item>
        <item>Design doc: HOW → architecture, API contracts, data models</item>
        <item>Implementation plan: IN WHAT ORDER → tasks, dependencies, token estimates</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>The specification is the anti-hallucination anchor: every LLM execution agent loads it as its primary context document.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a spec, agents infer intent from code patterns and produce implementations that diverge from stakeholder intent. The spec is the source of truth for what gets built.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="six-core-areas-for-llm-execution">
      <p>Research across 2,500+ agent configurations identified six areas that must be explicit in a spec for reliable LLM execution:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Commands: executable commands with flags (e.g., "npm test", "pytest -v")</item>
        <item>Testing: framework, location, and coverage target</item>
        <item>Project structure: directory layout with exact paths</item>
        <item>Code style: real code snippets showing the actual pattern, not prose descriptions</item>
        <item>Git workflow: branch naming and commit format</item>
        <item>Boundaries: what agents must never touch</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="three-tier-boundary-system">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every spec must include an explicit Boundaries section with Always, Ask First, and Never tiers.</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit boundaries, agents default to maximum autonomy. The "Out of Scope" section and "Never" tier are the most important boundary setters — without them, agents implement excluded features.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Always (Safe Actions): run tests before committing, follow existing patterns, add type annotations</item>
        <item>Ask First (High Impact): database schema changes, API contract modifications, dependency upgrades</item>
        <item>Never (Hard Stops): commit secrets, delete production data, bypass security checks</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="avoiding-ambiguity">
      <rule>
        <statement>Replace every vague qualifier with a concrete, measurable value.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents interpret vague terms differently from humans and from each other. "Fast" produces implementations targeting anywhere from 50ms to 5s; "&lt;500ms p95" is unambiguous.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>"Should be fast" → "Response time &lt;500ms p95"</item>
        <item>"Handle errors gracefully" → "Display error message, log to Sentry, no stack traces to user"</item>
        <item>"Support many users" → "10,000 concurrent connections"</item>
        <item>"Good user experience" → "&lt;3 clicks to complete task"</item>
        <item>"Secure authentication" → "bcrypt with 12 rounds, JWT with 15min expiry"</item>
        <item>"Mobile friendly" → "Responsive breakpoints: 320px, 768px, 1024px"</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="context-window-management">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep total FR count below 200; divide large specs into phases when FR count exceeds that threshold.</statement>
        <rationale>The "curse of instructions" — model adherence drops as the total number of instructions increases. Ruthless prioritization and phase splitting maintain agent reliability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Use table format for dense information instead of prose</item>
        <item>Reference external files instead of inlining full content</item>
        <item>Include only relevant code snippets, not entire files</item>
        <item>Divide large specs into backend/frontend/migration phases with explicit boundaries</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="smart-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every FR must satisfy SMART: Specific, Measurable, Achievable, Relevant, Time-bound (priority-assigned).</statement>
        <rationale>Non-SMART requirements are unverifiable. An agent cannot determine whether "users need auth" is implemented; it can verify "unregistered users cannot create accounts."</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Specific: exactly who and what (bad: "Users need auth" → good: "Unregistered users cannot create accounts")</item>
        <item>Measurable: how to measure success (bad: "Should be fast" → good: "Login &lt;500ms p95")</item>
        <item>Achievable: technically feasible (bad: "AI reads minds" → good: "OAuth 2.0 with Google")</item>
        <item>Relevant: tied to business goal (bad: "Nice to have" → good: "Blocks monetization")</item>
        <item>Time-bound: priority assigned (bad: "Eventually" → good: "Must have for MVP")</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="requirement-format">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use "System SHALL" for must-have requirements; use "System SHOULD" for should-have; never use passive voice or conditional language.</statement>
        <rationale>SHALL is unambiguous obligation. Conditional language ("should", "could", "may") allows agents to skip requirements under their own interpretation of priority.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### FR-001: Email Registration

**Requirement:** System SHALL allow users to register with email and password.
**Rationale:** Enables user identification for premium features.
**Traces to:** US-001
**Priority:** Must
**Validation Rules:**
- Email: RFC 5322 format, unique in system
- Password: min 8 chars, 1 uppercase, 1 digit
        ]]></code>
        <note>Traces to a user story. Priority is explicit. Validation rules are concrete, not prose.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="moscow-prioritization">
      <list>
        <item>Must: MVP requirement, cannot launch without</item>
        <item>Should: important feature, include if possible</item>
        <item>Could: nice to have, only if time allows</item>
        <item>Won't: explicit exclusion, not in this release</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="given-when-then-acceptance-criteria">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every FR must have at least one AC in Given-When-Then format with concrete, specific values — no vague terms.</statement>
        <rationale>ACs produced by agents are often too happy-path. Error handling, boundary conditions, and security scenarios require explicit prompting. A spec without these ACs produces implementations that handle only the success case.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
### AC-001: Successful Registration

Given: User is on registration page
And: Email "test@example.com" does not exist in system
When: User enters email "test@example.com" and password "SecurePass1"
And: User clicks "Register" button
Then: Account is created in database
And: User receives verification email within 30 seconds
And: User is redirected to dashboard
And: Success message "Check your email" is displayed
        ]]></code>
        <note>Concrete values throughout: specific email, specific password, specific timeout (30 seconds), specific redirect destination, specific message text.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="ac-coverage-checklist">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every feature must have ACs covering: happy path, error handling, boundary conditions, security scenarios, performance scenarios (if NFRs exist), and accessibility.</statement>
        <rationale>Without explicit coverage requirements, agents write only happy-path ACs. Security scenarios (auth bypass, injection attempts) are almost never included without explicit instruction.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Happy path: main success scenario with expected outputs</item>
        <item>Error handling: validation failures, service unavailability, timeout</item>
        <item>Boundary conditions: min/max values, empty states, null inputs</item>
        <item>Security scenarios: auth bypass attempt, injection attempt</item>
        <item>Performance scenarios: load handling, response time under concurrency</item>
        <item>Accessibility: screen reader, keyboard navigation</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/spec-full.md" purpose="Full feature spec with user personas, FRs, NFRs, ACs, boundaries"/>
      <template path="templates/spec-mvs.md" purpose="Minimal viable spec for simple single-task features"/>
      <template path="templates/spec-api.md" purpose="REST/GraphQL API endpoint spec with request/response/error shapes"/>
      <template path="templates/spec-component.md" purpose="UI component spec with props, variants, states, accessibility"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-spec.txt" purpose="Prompts for writing and reviewing specs for LLM executability"/>
      <template path="templates/check-spec.sh" purpose="Shell script validating FR-X, AC-X, Given/When/Then presence and flagging vague terms"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="quality-gates-confidence"/>
      <ref slug="reflexion-learning"/>
      <ref slug="sdd-workflow-overview"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
