<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-community-building Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-community-building. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Progress through stages in order — do not open invitations until the SEED stage has 5-10 planted conversations and 50 hand-picked members confirmed.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Launching empty is the single most common community failure. Visitors who arrive and see no activity leave immediately and never return. The first impression cannot be undone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pick exactly one platform and build depth there before considering others — multi-platform splits both member attention and your management capacity.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each platform requires a different engagement style and moderation approach. Running two platforms at 50% capacity produces two ghost towns instead of one thriving community.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define the community's value proposition across all three pillars (Access, Connection, Content) before writing the first invitation — members join for one pillar and stay for another.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Communities that offer only one pillar churn when the founding hook loses novelty. The Access pillar (founder availability) is highest at launch but cannot scale; Connection and Content pillars must be established before Access fades.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Hand-pick the first 50 members from existing engaged contacts — email subscribers, early users, engaged commenters — not the general public.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Quality of the founding cohort determines the culture and conversation norms for the entire community. Strangers with no prior engagement produce transactional interactions; engaged contacts produce genuine dialogue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Establish at least one daily ritual, one weekly ritual, and one monthly ritual — vary wording each week even if the structure repeats to prevent ritual fatigue.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Rituals create the habit of checking the community. A member who skips two rituals in a row is unlikely to return; daily rituals make the community part of the daily workflow before the habit window closes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Make rituals low-friction: a "what are you working on today?" standup beats a weekly essay prompt for participation rate by 5-10x.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">High-friction rituals punish busy members and create participation guilt. Low-friction rituals include everyone, including lurkers who would otherwise disengage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Trigger a personal welcome within 48 hours of every new member joining — the first 48 hours are the highest-churn window.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">New members who receive no personal contact in the first 48 hours have a 60-70% probability of never posting. A personal welcome converts lurkers into participants at the moment of highest receptivity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r8" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not open new channels or spaces until existing ones are consistently active — empty spaces signal low community health to every new visitor.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">New members calibrate community quality by scanning visible activity. Five active channels look healthier than fifteen half-empty ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r9" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track DAU/MAU (target 20%, great 40%+) and post rate (target 10% of members posting monthly, great 25%+) as the primary health signals — total member count is a vanity metric.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A community of 500 with 40% DAU/MAU is healthier and more monetizable than a community of 5,000 with 5% DAU/MAU. Growth strategy should optimize for ratio, not absolute count.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
