<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework-and-seeding" title="SEED-NURTURE-SCALE-MONETIZE Framework and First-Member Seeding">
  <summary>The four-stage community lifecycle, platform selection criteria, the three community value pillars, and the hand-picking process for seeding the first 50 members.</summary>

  <section title="Four-Stage Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Progress through stages in order — do not open invitations until the SEED stage has 5-10 planted conversations and 50 hand-picked members confirmed.</statement>
      <rationale>Launching empty is the single most common community failure. Visitors who arrive and see no activity leave immediately and never return. The first impression cannot be undone.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>SEED: invite 50 hand-picked members, plant 5-10 conversations before anyone else arrives</item>
      <item>NURTURE: establish daily, weekly, and monthly rituals; personal welcome within 48 hours of each new join</item>
      <item>SCALE: enable member-to-member connections via pairing, breakout groups, collaboration board</item>
      <item>MONETIZE: community access becomes a product feature or paid tier</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pick exactly one platform and build depth there before considering others — multi-platform splits both member attention and your management capacity.</statement>
      <rationale>Each platform requires a different engagement style and moderation approach. Running two platforms at 50% capacity produces two ghost towns instead of one thriving community.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Discord: real-time, rich features; best for tech, gaming, crypto; noisy, hard to search</item>
      <item>Slack: familiar, searchable; best for B2B professional communities; expensive at scale</item>
      <item>Circle: structured, monetizable; best for courses and memberships; less sticky</item>
      <item>Reddit: SEO and organic growth; less control over experience</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Community Value Pillars">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define the community's value proposition across all three pillars (Access, Connection, Content) before writing the first invitation — members join for one pillar and stay for another.</statement>
      <rationale>Communities that offer only one pillar churn when the founding hook loses novelty. The Access pillar (founder availability) is highest at launch but cannot scale; Connection and Content pillars must be established before Access fades.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Access: to you, experts, or exclusive information not available elsewhere</item>
      <item>Connection: to peers with similar goals, industry, or stage</item>
      <item>Content: educational, entertaining, or actionable material on a consistent schedule</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Seeding First Members">
    <rule>
      <statement>Hand-pick the first 50 members from existing engaged contacts — email subscribers, early users, engaged commenters — not the general public.</statement>
      <rationale>Quality of the founding cohort determines the culture and conversation norms for the entire community. Strangers with no prior engagement produce transactional interactions; engaged contacts produce genuine dialogue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Invitation script for the founding cohort.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Hey [Name],

I'm building a small community of [description].

I loved your [recent post/project/comment] about [topic].

Would you like early access? We're keeping it small
(~50 people) to maintain quality conversations.

[Link]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <reference path="templates/launch-checklist.md">Pre-launch / Launch Week / First Month checklist</reference>
  </section>
</text>
