<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rituals-and-health-metrics" title="Rituals, Member Connections, Health Metrics, and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Daily, weekly, and monthly ritual cadence for habit formation, mechanisms for enabling member-to-member connections, health metrics with target thresholds, and community antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Ritual Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Establish at least one daily ritual, one weekly ritual, and one monthly ritual — vary wording each week even if the structure repeats to prevent ritual fatigue.</statement>
      <rationale>Rituals create the habit of checking the community. A member who skips two rituals in a row is unlikely to return; daily rituals make the community part of the daily workflow before the habit window closes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Make rituals low-friction: a "what are you working on today?" standup beats a weekly essay prompt for participation rate by 5-10x.</statement>
      <rationale>High-friction rituals punish busy members and create participation guilt. Low-friction rituals include everyone, including lurkers who would otherwise disengage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Daily: morning standup thread (what are you working on?), win/loss sharing</item>
      <item>Weekly: office hours with you, member spotlight, weekly roundup newsletter</item>
      <item>Monthly: guest AMA, challenge or hackathon, retrospective thread</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/community-guidelines.md">Community guidelines template with purpose, values, and moderation policy</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Member Connection Mechanisms">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trigger a personal welcome within 48 hours of every new member joining — the first 48 hours are the highest-churn window.</statement>
      <rationale>New members who receive no personal contact in the first 48 hours have a 60-70% probability of never posting. A personal welcome converts lurkers into participants at the moment of highest receptivity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Intro threads: new members introduce themselves with a structured prompt</item>
      <item>Pairing: match members with similar goals for 1:1 conversations</item>
      <item>Breakout groups: cohorts of 5-10 people around shared interests or stages</item>
      <item>Collaboration board: members post help-wanted and help-offered items</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not open new channels or spaces until existing ones are consistently active — empty spaces signal low community health to every new visitor.</statement>
      <rationale>New members calibrate community quality by scanning visible activity. Five active channels look healthier than fifteen half-empty ones.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Health Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track DAU/MAU (target 20%, great 40%+) and post rate (target 10% of members posting monthly, great 25%+) as the primary health signals — total member count is a vanity metric.</statement>
      <rationale>A community of 500 with 40% DAU/MAU is healthier and more monetizable than a community of 5,000 with 5% DAU/MAU. Growth strategy should optimize for ratio, not absolute count.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>DAU/MAU: good 20%, great 40%+</item>
      <item>Post rate: good 10% of members, great 25%+</item>
      <item>Average response time to posts: good &lt;4 hours, great &lt;1 hour</item>
      <item>30-day retention: good 70%, great 85%+</item>
      <item>NPS: good 30, great 50+</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/health-scorer.py">Python health scorer from Discord/Circle activity exports</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Over-moderating: removing posts aggressively or requiring approval before posts are visible.</description>
    <reason>Heavy moderation kills spontaneity and signals distrust. Members self-censor when they feel monitored. Light touch moderation with clear guidelines produces better outcomes.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Only the founder posting — treating the community as a broadcast channel.</description>
    <reason>If members can only receive content rather than contribute it, the community is a newsletter. Communities require member-generated content to produce the connection value that justifies membership.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Growing headcount faster than community health metrics support.</description>
    <reason>Rapid growth in a community with low DAU/MAU dilutes conversation quality and makes new members feel like they joined after the good times. Quality of engagement must precede scale of membership.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
