<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="PMBoK 8 Focus Areas Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="950" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding PMBoK 8 Focus Areas. Each pairs a binary check and a sourced rationale.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="five-focus-areas-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Rubric MUST cover all five PMBoK 8 focus areas (Initiating, Planning, Executing, Monitoring and Controlling, Closing). Skipping any focus area is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 8 — Focus Areas chapter">Skipping focus areas creates lifecycle blind spots; the rubric's value is comparable end-to-end coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="seven-domains-mapped" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each focus area MUST map to applicable performance domains; the focus area × domain matrix MUST be populated.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBoK 8 — Focus Areas distribution chapter">Unmapped cells indicate artefact gaps; mapping forces explicit completeness.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="artefact-references-cited" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each rubric cell MUST cite ≥1 project artefact (template, plan, register) demonstrating coverage. Empty cells forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Faion content discipline">Empty cells make the rubric purely aspirational; artefact references prove the framework is real.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="audit-trail-version" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each rubric run MUST carry a PMBoK 8 version reference and refresh date. Untracked versions forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 21500 audit standards">Untracked versions cause confusion when PMBoK revisions ship; audit trail makes comparison possible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="non-applicable-justified" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cells marked NA (focus area × domain pair that doesn't apply) MUST carry a justification. Silent NA forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — rubric audit 2026">Silent NA hides missing coverage; justification forces honest assessment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for PMBoK 8 Focus Areas fail (see Skip-If list in AGENTS.md), the operator MUST skip this methodology and document the fallback reason instead of fabricating an output.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — faion methodology guardrails">Applying PMBoK 8 Focus Areas outside its envelope produces false-precision artefacts. Explicit skip preserves epistemic discipline.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
