<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="growth-gtm-strategy Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for growth-gtm-strategy. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define exactly ONE ICP for the first 6 months; define the anti-ICP explicitly alongside it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Splitting GTM effort across multiple segments dilutes messaging, channel focus, and product priorities. "SMB and Enterprise" means building two different products and running two different sales motions simultaneously — both suffer. The anti-ICP prevents sales from chasing bad-fit deals that look like revenue but destroy retention and referenceability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Write the value proposition using the For/Who/Is/Unlike/We formula; mark every unverified claim as ASSUMPTION.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The formula forces specificity at each step: who the customer is, what problem they have, what category the product belongs to, who the competitors are, and what is genuinely different. "ASSUMPTION" tagging prevents treating an unvalidated value prop as a foundation for channel spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Select 2-3 channels maximum; master them before adding a third; assign each channel a funnel role (awareness / consideration / conversion), not just a name.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Seven channels listed by an LLM ("SEO, content, Product Hunt, LinkedIn, cold email, paid, community") means seven partial efforts that none receive enough focus to compound. Two channels mastered produce more results than seven channels half-tried. Each channel must be assigned a role: awareness-only channels should not be held accountable for CPA.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Choose sales motion based on ACV and CAC payback; validate with unit economics before committing to motion.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Self-serve works when ACV is too low to justify a human sales touch (under $5K/year). Enterprise requires human sales when ACV justifies multi-month sales cycles. Choosing enterprise motion for a $99/month product burns sales resources; choosing self-serve for a $50K deal loses the contract to a competitor with a dedicated rep.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not start paid acquisition until the product achieves a measurable retention threshold in private or public beta.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Paid acquisition into a leaky product accelerates churn, not growth. Spending on acquisition before retention is validated means the budget is funding users who will leave before the CAC is recovered. Establish a retention baseline (e.g., 40% D7 for consumer) before opening paid channels.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review GTM performance monthly (not weekly, not quarterly); each review writes a delta entry to the GTM doc — not a rewrite.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Weekly reviews are too noisy for strategy signals; quarterly reviews discover off-track KPIs too late to course-correct. Delta entries (not rewrites) preserve the decision history — you need to know why you made previous choices to evaluate whether current results are a strategy failure or an execution failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
