<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-gtm-framework" title="GTM Framework: ICP, Value Proposition, Channels, Sales Motion">
  <summary>Five-question GTM framework: define one ICP with anti-ICP, craft a positioning statement, select 2-3 channels, and choose a sales motion matched to ACV and CAC payback.</summary>

  <section title="Ideal Customer Profile">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define exactly ONE ICP for the first 6 months; define the anti-ICP explicitly alongside it.</statement>
      <rationale>Splitting GTM effort across multiple segments dilutes messaging, channel focus, and product priorities. "SMB and Enterprise" means building two different products and running two different sales motions simultaneously — both suffer. The anti-ICP prevents sales from chasing bad-fit deals that look like revenue but destroy retention and referenceability.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>ICP components for B2B: Industry, Company size, Revenue range, Tech stack signals, Specific pain point, Buyer role and decision power. ICP components for B2C: Age range, Goals and frustrations, Budget and decision timeline, Information sources (where they learn).</p>
    <antipattern>
      <description>ICP defined as "SMBs, startups, and enterprises across all industries".</description>
      <reason>This is not an ICP — it is a market. An ICP must be specific enough that you can name 50 companies or people who fit it. If you cannot name them, the ICP is too broad to guide channel or messaging decisions.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Value Proposition">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write the value proposition using the For/Who/Is/Unlike/We formula; mark every unverified claim as ASSUMPTION.</statement>
      <rationale>The formula forces specificity at each step: who the customer is, what problem they have, what category the product belongs to, who the competitors are, and what is genuinely different. "ASSUMPTION" tagging prevents treating an unvalidated value prop as a foundation for channel spend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Value proposition using the formula with explicit framing of ICP and differentiator.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
For: solopreneurs building digital products
Who: struggle with scattered tools and no methodology
Our: Faion Network
Is: an AI-powered development framework
That: provides 282 proven methodologies and AI agents
Unlike: generic courses or just-tools platforms
We: combine education with working software

[ASSUMPTION: "282 proven" requires validation against user outcomes data]
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Channel Selection">
    <rule>
      <statement>Select 2-3 channels maximum; master them before adding a third; assign each channel a funnel role (awareness / consideration / conversion), not just a name.</statement>
      <rationale>Seven channels listed by an LLM ("SEO, content, Product Hunt, LinkedIn, cold email, paid, community") means seven partial efforts that none receive enough focus to compound. Two channels mastered produce more results than seven channels half-tried. Each channel must be assigned a role: awareness-only channels should not be held accountable for CPA.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Organic: SEO, content, social, community — long-term, low CAC, slow to start.</item>
      <item>Paid: Google Ads, Meta Ads, LinkedIn Ads — fast start, scalable, requires conversion data to optimize.</item>
      <item>Outbound: email, events, cold calls — high-value B2B where human relationship matters.</item>
      <item>Partnerships: affiliates, integrations — leverage existing audiences, slow to build.</item>
      <item>Product-led: freemium, viral loops, self-serve — requires product that demonstrates value immediately.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Sales Motion">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose sales motion based on ACV and CAC payback; validate with unit economics before committing to motion.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-serve works when ACV is too low to justify a human sales touch (under $5K/year). Enterprise requires human sales when ACV justifies multi-month sales cycles. Choosing enterprise motion for a $99/month product burns sales resources; choosing self-serve for a $50K deal loses the contract to a competitor with a dedicated rep.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/gtm-feasibility.py">Unit-economics check: LTV, CAC payback, motion eligibility by ACV range</reference>
    <list>
      <item>Self-serve: ACV $60-$5K/year, max payback 6 months. Product must be self-explanatory.</item>
      <item>Sales-assisted: ACV $1.2K-$30K/year, max payback 12 months. Inside sales + demos.</item>
      <item>Enterprise: ACV $25K+/year, max payback 18 months. Field sales, legal, procurement.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-launch-and-review.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/gtm-one-pager.md"/>
    <link path="templates/competitive-map.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
