<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-launch-and-review" title="GTM Launch Plan, Review Cadence, and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Phased launch structure, monthly review cadence for living GTM documents, competitive positioning, and agent-specific failure modes to prevent.</summary>

  <section title="Phased Launch">
    <p>Three-phase launch reduces risk and generates learning before full investment: Private Beta (50-100 hand-picked users, high-touch feedback, critical bug fixes), Public Beta (open waitlist, early-access pricing, gather testimonials), General Availability (full launch, PR push, paid acquisition starts).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not start paid acquisition until the product achieves a measurable retention threshold in private or public beta.</statement>
      <rationale>Paid acquisition into a leaky product accelerates churn, not growth. Spending on acquisition before retention is validated means the budget is funding users who will leave before the CAC is recovered. Establish a retention baseline (e.g., 40% D7 for consumer) before opening paid channels.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Monthly Review Cadence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Review GTM performance monthly (not weekly, not quarterly); each review writes a delta entry to the GTM doc — not a rewrite.</statement>
      <rationale>Weekly reviews are too noisy for strategy signals; quarterly reviews discover off-track KPIs too late to course-correct. Delta entries (not rewrites) preserve the decision history — you need to know why you made previous choices to evaluate whether current results are a strategy failure or an execution failure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Monthly review agenda: actual vs. target 90-day metrics, channel CAC/LTV by segment, ICP validation (are we actually acquiring the ICP?), anti-ICP drift (are sales chasing bad-fit deals?), top 3 risks and kill-switches.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Competitive Positioning">
    <p>Build a 2x2 competitive map with two dimensions that matter to your ICP. Position yourself in an open quadrant. Key competitors: list 3-5 with their strengths, weaknesses, and where you win. Update when a new competitor emerges or a significant feature launches.</p>
    <reference path="templates/competitive-map.md">Competitive landscape table and positioning statement template</reference>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Competitive analysis that sources all claims from a single review platform (G2 or Capterra).</description>
      <reason>G2 reviews are gamed; companies encourage positive reviews and dispute negative ones. SimilarWeb traffic is noisy at under 100K MAU. Triangulate across at least 3 independent sources: review platforms, Crunchbase/LinkedIn funding data, and direct user interviews.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Constraints">
    <list>
      <item>Every GTM doc produced by an agent must have explicit ASSUMPTION tags on unverified claims. Reject docs without them.</item>
      <item>Channels listed must each have an assigned funnel role and explicit reasoning tied to ICP behavior data, not generic recommendations.</item>
      <item>Pricing experiments require legal sign-off (price discrimination rules, regional pricing law). Agent surfaces this gate; does not implement pricing changes unilaterally.</item>
      <item>ICP derived from won-deal data only has survivorship bias. Agent must also analyze lost deals and never-tried segments.</item>
      <item>Strategy and tactics are distinct. A GTM strategy is category-level decisions (which channel, which motion, which ICP). A task list ("write 10 blog posts") is execution. Reject strategy outputs that are actually task lists.</item>
      <item>A "vision" sentence written by an LLM regresses to the mean — it will be forgettable. Humans write the vision; agents draft options for humans to choose from.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/01-gtm-framework.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/gtm-one-pager.md"/>
    <link path="templates/gtm-feasibility.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
