<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="Requirements Traceability — Core Concepts">
  <summary>Traceability directions, coverage and gap analysis, link role vocabulary, and metrics with targets.</summary>

  <section title="What Traceability Answers">
    <p>Traceability links requirements to their origins and downstream artifacts. It answers four questions:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Where did this requirement come from? (upstream trace)</item>
      <item>What does this requirement affect? (downstream trace)</item>
      <item>Is every business need covered? (forward coverage)</item>
      <item>Is every component justified? (backward coverage)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Traceability Directions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain bidirectional traceability: forward from need to implementation (coverage) and backward from implementation to need (justification). Both directions are required for regulated audits.</statement>
      <rationale>Forward coverage without backward traceability produces unjustified tests and code; backward traceability without forward coverage produces unverified requirements.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Forward — from business need to stakeholder req to solution req to design to code to test. Purpose: verify coverage.</item>
      <item>Backward — from test to code to design to solution req to stakeholder req to business need. Purpose: justify every artifact.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Link Role Vocabulary">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use exactly five link roles across the program: satisfies, derives, implements, verifies, conflicts. Reject any other role at lint time.</statement>
      <rationale>A consistent role vocabulary enables automated coverage analysis; ad-hoc roles produce a matrix that no tool can query reliably.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>satisfies — need → requirement (stakeholder need satisfies business need).</item>
      <item>derives — requirement → requirement (solution req derived from stakeholder req).</item>
      <item>implements — requirement → code or design artifact.</item>
      <item>verifies — test → requirement.</item>
      <item>conflicts — requirement to requirement (bidirectional conflict requiring resolution).</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Traceability Strategy Levels">
    <p>Choose the traceability depth appropriate to the project context:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Minimum — business req to functional req only. Appropriate for low-risk internal tools.</item>
      <item>Standard — adds design to test links. Appropriate for most enterprise projects.</item>
      <item>Full — adds code to user story to epic links. Required for regulated industries.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Coverage and Gap Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin coverage thresholds in CI: forward coverage at least 95%, backward coverage 100%, orphan count 0. Failure blocks the merge.</statement>
      <rationale>Thresholds without enforcement are decoration; unchecked RTMs go stale within 2-3 sprints and give false assurance to auditors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Coverage analysis questions:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Are all business requirements traced to solution requirements? Gap = business requirement without solution requirement.</item>
      <item>Are all solution requirements traced to tests? Gap = testing gap.</item>
      <item>Are there orphan requirements with no parent? These require linking or deletion.</item>
      <item>Are there tests without requirements? These are possible gold-plating or undocumented NFRs.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Traceability Metrics">
    <list>
      <item>Forward coverage — (linked requirements / total requirements) x 100. Target: more than 95%.</item>
      <item>Backward coverage — (justified items / total items) x 100. Target: 100%.</item>
      <item>Test coverage — (requirements with tests / total requirements) x 100. Target: more than 90%.</item>
      <item>Orphan count — items with no links. Target: 0.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
