<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Requirements Traceability — Process and Maintenance">
  <summary>Four-step traceability process: define strategy, create matrix, maintain on change, analyze coverage. Includes the generated-not-maintained rule.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Traceability Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Decide traceability depth (minimum/standard/full) and the complete link role vocabulary before creating any artifact. Encode both in a YAML config file committed to the repo root.</statement>
      <rationale>Strategy decisions made after artifacts exist produce inconsistent coverage; changing the strategy mid-project requires retroactive linking that agents and humans both do poorly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Create Traceability Matrix — Generated, Not Maintained">
    <rule>
      <statement>The RTM is a generated artifact, not a hand-edited file. Each source artifact carries typed links in its frontmatter (traces: [BR-05, SR-12]); a builder script aggregates them into the matrix and computes coverage. Agents emit patches to source artifact frontmatter; the generator owns the canonical matrix state.</statement>
      <rationale>Spreadsheet RTMs go stale within 2-3 sprints because no single person owns the maintenance burden. Generated matrices stay current as long as source artifacts are edited and the generator runs in CI.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rtm.py">Python script generating RTM from frontmatter traces across a docs tree</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Maintain Traceability on Change">
    <rule>
      <statement>When a requirement is added, link it to its parent before committing. When a requirement changes, walk downstream links and flag affected artifacts. When a requirement is deleted, remove all links and update the matrix.</statement>
      <rationale>Unlinked new requirements become orphans that fail coverage checks; unchanged downstream links after a requirement change produce misleading impact assessments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Conventional Commits with REQ scope (feat(REQ-045): ...) and Refs: footers for multi-requirement commits to get a free code-to-req trace via git log.</statement>
      <rationale>Structured commit messages feed backward traceability from code to requirement without any additional tooling beyond the git log.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Analyze Coverage and Report">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag a traceability baseline at every release. PRs must show the coverage diff so a regression is visible in review.</statement>
      <rationale>Baseline diffs make coverage regression visible before merge; without them, regressions accumulate silently until audit time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agents write the RTM directly instead of patching source artifact frontmatter.</description>
      <reason>Direct RTM edits bypass the generator and produce inconsistencies between source artifacts and the matrix; the generator must own the canonical state.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs hallucinate links by associating artifacts that share a keyword but have no actual dependency.</description>
      <reason>Hallucinated links poison the matrix and pass coverage thresholds while hiding real gaps. Every proposed link must cite a quoted span from each artifact as evidence; links below 0.9 confidence require human review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Too granular tracing — linking every UI label and log message.</description>
      <reason>Over-tracing buries signal in noise; trace only at the lowest level where a defect would be material to the business or auditor.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
