<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Requirements Traceability — Examples">
  <summary>E-commerce checkout traceability tree, impact analysis table, tools, and antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Example: E-Commerce Checkout Traceability">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Business Requirement BR-05: Enable customers to complete purchases online.</note>
      <note>SR-12: Customer can checkout cart (satisfies BR-05).</note>
      <note>FR-30: Display cart summary (derives SR-12) → D-15: Cart component design (implements FR-30) → TC-45: Verify cart displays correctly (verifies FR-30).</note>
      <note>FR-31: Accept payment information (derives SR-12) → D-16: Payment form design (implements FR-31) → TC-46: Verify payment entry (verifies FR-31).</note>
      <note>FR-32: Confirm order (derives SR-12) → D-17: Confirmation page design (implements FR-32) → TC-47: Verify order confirmation (verifies FR-32).</note>
      <note>Coverage: BR-05 is fully covered (forward) and every test cites its FR (backward). Orphan count: 0.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Impact Analysis Using Traceability">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Scenario: Business requirement BR-03 is changing. Use the link graph to identify all affected artifacts within 2 hops.</note>
      <note>Stakeholder Requirements: SR-05, SR-06 — needs review.</note>
      <note>Solution Requirements: FR-10, FR-11, FR-12 — may need update.</note>
      <note>Design Documents: D-08, D-09 — needs revision.</note>
      <note>Test Cases: TC-20, TC-21, TC-22 — needs update.</note>
      <note>Human-in-the-loop gate: impact sign-off required before any artifact is modified.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Tools for Traceability">
    <list>
      <item>Requirements Management — Jira, Azure DevOps, Jama Connect: best for KA-3 traceability matrices via issue links.</item>
      <item>Specialized RM — IBM DOORS Next, Polarion ALM, StrictDoc: required for regulated industries (ISO 13485, IEC 62304, DO-178C).</item>
      <item>Git-native RM — Doorstop: Markdown + YAML with built-in link and publish commands.</item>
      <item>Spreadsheets — Excel, Google Sheets: acceptable for small projects only; go stale without a generator.</item>
      <item>Generator script — rtm.py: aggregates frontmatter traces across a docs tree into a coverage report.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/rtm.py">RTM generator from frontmatter traces</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hand-editing the RTM instead of patching source artifact frontmatter.</description>
      <reason>Manual RTM edits bypass the generator and produce inconsistencies; the matrix must be a build product, not a hand-maintained document.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-time traceability exercise — not updating on changes.</description>
      <reason>An outdated RTM is worse than none because it gives false assurance to auditors and misleads impact analysis.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Coverage metrics gaming — linking one tautological test per requirement to achieve 100% forward coverage.</description>
      <reason>Tautological links pass coverage thresholds while hiding real gaps; pair coverage metrics with mutation testing or acceptance-criteria density to detect gaming.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
