<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="requirements-traceability Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for requirements-traceability as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents write the RTM directly instead of patching source artifact frontmatter.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Direct RTM edits bypass the generator and produce inconsistencies between source artifacts and the matrix; the generator must own the canonical state.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs hallucinate links by associating artifacts that share a keyword but have no actual dependency.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hallucinated links poison the matrix and pass coverage thresholds while hiding real gaps. Every proposed link must cite a quoted span from each artifact as evidence; links below 0.9 confidence require human review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Too granular tracing — linking every UI label and log message.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Over-tracing buries signal in noise; trace only at the lowest level where a defect would be material to the business or auditor.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Hand-editing the RTM instead of patching source artifact frontmatter.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Manual RTM edits bypass the generator and produce inconsistencies; the matrix must be a build product, not a hand-maintained document.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>One-time traceability exercise — not updating on changes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An outdated RTM is worse than none because it gives false assurance to auditors and misleads impact analysis.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Coverage metrics gaming — linking one tautological test per requirement to achieve 100% forward coverage.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Tautological links pass coverage thresholds while hiding real gaps; pair coverage metrics with mutation testing or acceptance-criteria density to detect gaming.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
