<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-study-design" title="Diary Study Design and Planning">
  <summary>Study type selection, design decisions, entry format rules, recruitment targets, and planning checklist for longitudinal diary studies.</summary>

  <section title="Study Types">
    <p>Three diary study types, selected by the nature of the behavior under study:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Interval-contingent: participants record at fixed times (daily, weekly). Best for: routine behaviors, habit formation, onboarding progression.</item>
      <item>Event-contingent: participants record when a specific event occurs (used the product, experienced a problem). Best for: specific interactions, trigger mapping.</item>
      <item>Signal-contingent: participants record when prompted at random intervals. Best for: capturing natural moments, reducing recall bias. Requires careful timezone handling per participant.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Design Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap entry completion time at 5 minutes. Any entry that takes longer causes attrition spikes after day 4.</statement>
      <rationale>Diary fatigue in interval-contingent studies begins around day 7 and accelerates if entry burden is high. The 5-minute cap is the single most important mechanical control for data quality across the study period.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Vary the prompt text daily. Repeated identical prompts degrade response quality after day 4 as participants learn to minimize effort.</statement>
      <rationale>Participants answer what they expect the prompt to ask, not what it actually asks. Prompt variation forces genuine recall each entry.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Recruit 30% over target to absorb 20–40% dropout over 4 weeks. Pay incentives in tranches (signup, mid-study, exit interview).</statement>
      <rationale>Flat one-shot incentive payment increases dropout once the payment is received. Tranche structure maintains engagement through the full study duration.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Run a 3-day pilot with 2 participants before launching the full study.</statement>
      <rationale>Every logistic bug (broken reminder links, confusing entry fields, wrong timezone, missing consent flow) surfaces in a pilot. Fixing post-launch costs 10x the pilot effort.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Entry Format">
    <p>Each entry should collect: timestamp (auto), location/context (structured options), what happened (open text), outcome rating (1–5 scale), problems or frustrations (open text), optional photo or voice note. Limit to 5 required questions maximum.</p>

    <p>Weekly micro-interviews (15 min per participant) clarify ambiguous entries while context is fresh. Do not accumulate 4 weeks of entries before starting analysis — code incrementally.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Planning Checklist">
    <p>Before launch: research questions defined, study type and duration decided, entry frequency and format designed, capture platform selected, entry template tested by 2 pilots, incentive structure finalized, ethics review completed (can stall weeks — start early), screening criteria defined, consent flow built.</p>

    <p>Recruitment: participants recruited and screened, consent obtained, onboarding session completed, reminder cadence configured, attrition escalation path defined.</p>
  </section>
</text>
