<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns-and-workflow" title="Diary Study Antipatterns and Agentic Workflow">
  <summary>Common failure modes, self-report bias controls, agentic workflow guidance, and entry-coding schema for diary studies.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running analysis only after all entries are collected (batch analysis at study end).</description>
      <reason>Losing context by waiting too long: late-study entries are analyzed without the pattern visibility that incremental coding provides. Themes from early entries often reframe late-entry meaning.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Signal-contingent prompts sent at fixed UTC times without per-participant timezone localization.</description>
      <reason>Prompts arriving at 2 AM local time get skipped or dashed off. LLMs default to UTC and disrespect local norms — pin to verified participant timezone table.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Uploading photo entries to a cloud LLM before PII redaction.</description>
      <reason>Photo entries often contain inadvertent PII: faces, addresses, documents visible in frame. Redact before any cloud upload. EXIF metadata also contains GPS coordinates.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Auto-translating multi-language entries during analysis.</description>
      <reason>Quote in source language, translate at reporting time only. Auto-translation during analysis changes nuance and destroys the verbatim evidence needed for credibility.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Self-Report Bias Controls">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat participant self-report as directional signal, not metric. Never aggregate sentiment scores from diary entries into a single KPI without human coding validation.</statement>
      <rationale>Self-report bias suppresses negative and embarrassing moments. Participants under-report breakdowns in contexts where they feel observed. Sentiment scoring of self-report is noisy; LLM synthesis can generate patterns absent in sparse longitudinal data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agentic Workflow">
    <p>Agents are strong for: scaffolding (study plan, screener, entry templates, reminder cadence), automating follow-up scheduling, clustering and theme extraction from the entry corpus, attrition tracking. Agents are weak for: generating synthetic insights before human-coded baseline (LLMs over-fit to their own clustering), speaker attribution in audio entries, PII detection in images.</p>

    <p>Schedule reminder dispatch via cron or queue, not conversational chat. Diary studies live or die on logistics consistency — an agent that misses a reminder cohort destroys that day's data window.</p>

    <p>Entry coding schema for LLM-assisted analysis:</p>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="json"><![CDATA[{
  "timestamp": "ISO8601",
  "location_context": "home|work|commute|other",
  "trigger": "string or null",
  "outcome": "string or null",
  "sentiment": -2,
  "feature_used": ["string"],
  "breakdown_reported": false,
  "quote": "verbatim or null"
}]]></code>
      <note>Mark uncertain fields as null. Never invent quote text. Output as JSONL, one entry per line.</note>
    </example>

    <reference path="templates/diary-reminders.py">Script: emit per-participant reminder schedule with early-study weighting</reference>
  </section>
</text>
