<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="diary-studies Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for diary-studies as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Running analysis only after all entries are collected (batch analysis at study end).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Losing context by waiting too long: late-study entries are analyzed without the pattern visibility that incremental coding provides. Themes from early entries often reframe late-entry meaning.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Signal-contingent prompts sent at fixed UTC times without per-participant timezone localization.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Prompts arriving at 2 AM local time get skipped or dashed off. LLMs default to UTC and disrespect local norms — pin to verified participant timezone table.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Uploading photo entries to a cloud LLM before PII redaction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Photo entries often contain inadvertent PII: faces, addresses, documents visible in frame. Redact before any cloud upload. EXIF metadata also contains GPS coordinates.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-translating multi-language entries during analysis.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Quote in source language, translate at reporting time only. Auto-translation during analysis changes nuance and destroys the verbatim evidence needed for credibility.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
