<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Distribution Channel Research Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Distribution Channel Research methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="nineteen-channels-considered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consider all 19 Traction channels (plus AI-era variants) before shortlisting; explicit rejection log for the 16 not picked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Weinberg &amp; Mares, Traction (2014)">Founders default to whatever channel they already use; the explicit consideration log surfaces blind spots.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="shortlist-three-channels" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Shortlist exactly 3 channels for paid test; do not test more than 3 in parallel.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — channel-test budget audit">Spreading &lt;=$5k across 5+ channels yields no statistical signal anywhere.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="test-budget-cap-500" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each channel test must have an explicit &lt;=$500 stop-loss; abort the test the moment spend crosses the cap.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Q3 2025 budget post-mortem">Unbounded tests turn into 'we already spent it, let it run' sunk-cost spirals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="score-four-axes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score every test on 4 axes: CAC, reach, time-to-signal (days), retention-of-channel-customers (D30).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — channel retention audit">Lowest-CAC channel often has worst retention; multi-axis scoring prevents single-metric optimization.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="name-tripwires" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When locking the top 1-2 channels, name explicit tripwires (CAC &gt; X, reach &lt; Y) that trigger a retest.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — channel-fatigue Q1 2026">Channels degrade; without tripwires the team rides a dead channel.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
