<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="distribution-channel-research Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for distribution-channel-research. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Keep a "20% experiments" budget non-negotiable even when the primary channel is working — channel concentration risk is the #1 GTM failure mode at $100K+ MRR.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Channels saturate. Apple ATT, Google cookie deprecation, and algorithm changes have each eliminated primary channels for SaaS companies with no backup. The 20% budget maintains optionality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Focus on exactly 1 channel from 0 to $10K MRR, expand to 2-3 channels from $10K to $50K MRR, then diversify. 80% effort on 1-2 proven channels, 20% on experiments.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Trying all channels at once means mastering none. Channel mastery requires iterating 10+ experiments per channel — spreading across 5 channels produces 2 iterations each, which is insufficient for learning the economics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use a free-text "How did you hear about us?" field, not a dropdown — dropdowns force respondents into the wrong bucket and corrupt the discovery map.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Dropdowns create selection bias toward the channels you already know. Free text surfaces channels you did not consider and catches "dark social" attribution (podcast, friend DM, Slack community).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score each channel on six factors (audience presence 25%, competitors using 15%, cost to test 20%, time to results 15%, scalability 15%, team capability 10%) and require a cited source or interview reference for audience presence and competitors-using scores.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Uncited scores are preferences disguised as analysis. Forcing citations for the two highest-weight factors prevents agents from recommending SEO by default because training data is saturated with SEO examples.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat LTV:CAC &gt; 3:1 as a Phase-2 gate, not a Phase-1 gate — Phase-1 micro-tests are buying signal, not unit economics validation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LTV is uncertain for early-stage products. Killing a channel after a $300 test because LTV:CAC is 2:1 is premature — the sample size is too small for economic conclusions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Predefine a kill criterion (e.g., "if CAC &gt; $X after $500 spend, kill") before money is spent — prevents sunk-cost continuation.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Post-hoc evaluation always finds reasons to continue. A pre-registered kill criterion removes the sunk-cost bias and makes test results actionable regardless of the outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the agent has zero customer interviews, flag this explicitly in the output header so the reader knows the input quality — fall back to competitor inference with a clear "UNVERIFIED" label on every inferred channel.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Channel research output reads plausible but un-actionable when built entirely from competitor inference without customer source data. The quality flag prevents the output from being acted on at the same confidence level as interview-grounded research.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
