<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-research-process" title="Channel Research Five-Step Process">
  <summary>Customer discovery mapping, channel fit matrix scoring, economics modeling, micro-test framework, and pre-registered kill criteria.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Map Customer Discovery">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a free-text "How did you hear about us?" field, not a dropdown — dropdowns force respondents into the wrong bucket and corrupt the discovery map.</statement>
      <rationale>Dropdowns create selection bias toward the channels you already know. Free text surfaces channels you did not consider and catches "dark social" attribution (podcast, friend DM, Slack community).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Customer interviews: "How did you find [competitor]?" and "Where do you usually discover new tools?"</item>
      <item>Analytics: UTM source breakdown, referrer analysis (multi-touch, not last-click)</item>
      <item>Competitor analysis: SimilarWeb traffic mix, Meta Ad Library, LinkedIn Ad Library</item>
      <item>Audience research: SparkToro for "where does this audience hang out?" — sites, podcasts, social handles</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Channel Fit Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score each channel on six factors (audience presence 25%, competitors using 15%, cost to test 20%, time to results 15%, scalability 15%, team capability 10%) and require a cited source or interview reference for audience presence and competitors-using scores.</statement>
      <rationale>Uncited scores are preferences disguised as analysis. Forcing citations for the two highest-weight factors prevents agents from recommending SEO by default because training data is saturated with SEO examples.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Viable channels: those scoring above 3.5/5 weighted total AND with LTV:CAC &gt; 3:1 in Phase-2 testing.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Channel Economics">
    <list>
      <item>Cost per impression → CTR → CPC → conversion rate → CAC</item>
      <item>LTV:CAC ratio target: &gt; 3:1 for Phase-2 scaling, &gt; 1:1 minimum for Phase-1 micro-tests</item>
      <item>Time to ROI: organic channels typically 6-12 months; paid channels immediate but front-loaded cost</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat LTV:CAC &gt; 3:1 as a Phase-2 gate, not a Phase-1 gate — Phase-1 micro-tests are buying signal, not unit economics validation.</statement>
      <rationale>LTV is uncertain for early-stage products. Killing a channel after a $300 test because LTV:CAC is 2:1 is premature — the sample size is too small for economic conclusions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Test Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Predefine a kill criterion (e.g., "if CAC &gt; $X after $500 spend, kill") before money is spent — prevents sunk-cost continuation.</statement>
      <rationale>Post-hoc evaluation always finds reasons to continue. A pre-registered kill criterion removes the sunk-cost bias and makes test results actionable regardless of the outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Phase 1 micro-test: $100-500 budget, 1-2 weeks, answer "does this channel generate signal?"</item>
      <item>Phase 2 scale test: $1-5K budget, 1 month, answer "what are the economics?"</item>
      <item>Phase 3 optimize: tune targeting/creative before increasing budget</item>
      <item>Separate "channel" from "creative": 3 distinct creative concepts before killing a channel</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/channel-fit-scorer.py">Weighted matrix scorer from YAML channel definitions.</reference>
  <reference path="templates/channel-report.md">Full channel research report template.</reference>
</text>
