<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="distribution-channel-research Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for distribution-channel-research as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs hallucinating CPC, CPM, and conversion benchmarks without citing source and date.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require the agent to cite source + date for every economic number. Reject answers that fail the citation requirement. CPC/CPM numbers shift 2x+ within 12-24 months.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents over-recommending SEO and content marketing because training data is saturated with those examples.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Explicitly prompt for non-obvious channels (integrations, niche marketplaces, communities, podcasts) and require a justification for why standard channels were or were not selected.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Last-click attribution baked into agent reasoning under-crediting dark social, podcast, and community channels.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Feed self-reported attribution data alongside analytics. Last-click alone produces wrong recommendations for top-of-funnel channels that have long conversion cycles.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent committing to a Phase 1/Phase 2/Phase 3 calendar with specific dates or week counts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Per workspace rules, no time estimates — phases are gated by milestones (e.g., "after 100 paying customers"), not weeks. Phase gates on outcomes prevent premature scaling.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
