<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Persona Building Process">
  <summary>Five-step process for creating research-backed buyer personas: gather real data, cluster patterns, define segments, build persona with cited traits, validate with customers.</summary>

  <section title="Data Sources">
    <rule>
      <statement>Conduct a minimum of 10 customer interviews before creating any persona. Do not build personas from imagination or market assumptions.</statement>
      <rationale>Personas without interview data produce "demographic theatre" — plausible-looking characters that never change a real decision. Ten interviews is the minimum for identifying patterns that recur across multiple people.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Data sources ranked by signal strength: interviews (goals, frustrations, workflow), surveys (demographics, tool usage), analytics (behavior, engagement), support tickets (problems, exact language used), social media (interests, how they talk), sales calls (objections, motivations).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Pattern Clustering">
    <p>Cluster interview findings on five dimensions: role/title, goals, frustrations, behaviors, buying triggers. Record both frequency (how many people said this) and intensity (how strongly they expressed it).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every trait in the final persona must have a transcript citation in the format [transcript-id:line]. Traits with fewer than 3 supporting citations across transcripts are marked [WEAK] and excluded from the primary persona.</statement>
      <rationale>Uncited traits are hypotheses, not findings. Marking weak traits prevents them from driving product decisions while keeping them visible for future validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Segment Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start with ONE primary persona. Add secondary personas only after the product has traction. Define a negative persona (who NOT to target) from the start.</statement>
      <rationale>Multiple personas at seed stage split focus and produce muddled positioning. The negative persona is more decision-shaping than the primary — "who do we say no to?" is the harder and more valuable question.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Segment types: Primary (main buyer, most revenue — focus all design here), Secondary (important but smaller — support their needs), Negative (explicitly not for them — do not market to, politely decline in sales).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Persona Elements">
    <p>Essential elements (required): name (memorable, role-based), role (job title/situation), demographics (only if 5+ transcripts agree), goals (what success looks like), frustrations (what blocks them), behaviors (how they work and buy), quote (verbatim from interview).</p>
    <p>Advanced elements (add only when handing off to marketing or design): day in the life, tools used, information sources, objections, buying trigger.</p>
    <reference path="templates/persona-full.md">Full persona template with all fields</reference>
    <reference path="templates/persona-lean.md">Lean 6-field template for working use</reference>
    <reference path="templates/persona-negative.md">Negative persona template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Validation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show the persona to 3 real customers and ask "does this sound like you?" before committing the document to the repository. If 2 of 3 say "no", rebuild.</statement>
      <rationale>Personas validated only internally often reflect team assumptions rather than customer reality. External validation catches the most common failure mode: the team's mental model of the customer diverges from the actual customer.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Update frequency: major update quarterly, minor tweaks as you learn, full rebuild after pivot or entry into a new market.</p>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-gotchas.xml"/>
    <link path="templates/cluster-personas.py"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
