<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Persona Examples and Common Mistakes">
  <summary>Two worked personas (Newsletter Nate for SaaS, Agency Amy for project management) and a common-mistakes table with fixes.</summary>

  <section title="Example: Newsletter Nate">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Primary persona for a SaaS tool targeting freelance writers. All traits sourced from interviews.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Newsletter Nate

**Who:** 34-year-old freelance writer, runs paid newsletter with 2,000 subscribers, makes $4K/month from writing.

**Goal:** Grow subscriber base to 10,000 and reduce time on operations.

**Frustration:** Email platform is expensive at scale; no easy way to sell digital products; analytics are confusing.

**Quote:** "I'm a writer, not a tech person. I just want it to work." [T03:L87]

**Buys when:** Current tool fails or becomes too expensive on price jump.

**Based on:** 12 interviews (all freelance writers with paid newsletters)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example: Agency Amy">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Primary persona for a project management tool targeting 5-person design agencies.</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Agency Amy

**Who:** 38-year-old agency owner, 5-person design agency, $500K annual revenue.

**Goals:** Stop projects going over budget; improve client communication; scale without overhead.

**Frustrations:** Team uses 6 different tools; clients don't understand project status; time tracking is inconsistent.

**Quote:** "I need my team aligned without micromanaging." [T07:L42]

**Buys when:** A project goes over budget for the third time in a quarter.

**Based on:** 15 interviews (agency owners, 3-15 employees)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating personas with no interview data, using demographics or market reports as the source.</description>
      <reason>Fabricated personas produce wrong product decisions. A persona without transcript citations is a hypothesis dressed as a finding.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Creating 4+ personas at seed stage and trying to design for all of them simultaneously.</description>
      <reason>Multiple personas split focus and produce muddled messaging. One primary persona until the product has traction and ARR to justify more.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Including stock-photo demographics (age, city, salary) that no one on the team ever references in a product decision.</description>
      <reason>Demographic fields that never change a decision are dead weight. Include a demographic field only if it drives a specific product or messaging choice.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Publishing a persona document and never updating it.</description>
      <reason>By month 6 the actual ICP has often shifted. A stale persona still drives copy. Quarterly review or kill the artifact.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping the negative persona definition.</description>
      <reason>"Who do we say no to?" shapes sales qualification and product scope more concretely than the primary persona. Define it early and link it to the sales-disqualification SOP.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
