<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="persona-building Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for persona-building as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating personas with no interview data, using demographics or market reports as the source.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Fabricated personas produce wrong product decisions. A persona without transcript citations is a hypothesis dressed as a finding.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Creating 4+ personas at seed stage and trying to design for all of them simultaneously.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multiple personas split focus and produce muddled messaging. One primary persona until the product has traction and ARR to justify more.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Including stock-photo demographics (age, city, salary) that no one on the team ever references in a product decision.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Demographic fields that never change a decision are dead weight. Include a demographic field only if it drives a specific product or messaging choice.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Publishing a persona document and never updating it.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>By month 6 the actual ICP has often shifted. A stale persona still drives copy. Quarterly review or kill the artifact.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping the negative persona definition.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>"Who do we say no to?" shapes sales qualification and product scope more concretely than the primary persona. Define it early and link it to the sales-disqualification SOP.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Asking an LLM to "write a persona for indie SaaS founders" without supplying transcript data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs will produce plausible-sounding frustrations, quotes, and demographics from training data priors rather than your actual customers. Every persona trait must be grounded in a transcript citation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Running synthesis at temperature above 0.3 for clustering and trait extraction.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Higher temperature fabricates variation that looks like diverse customer segments. Use temperature 0 for clustering; reserve creative phrasing only for the optional characteristic quote field.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Feeding 30+ interview transcripts into one synthesis call.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Long-context dumps cause the model to collapse to averages and lose outliers. Use map-reduce: cluster per transcript, merge cluster summaries, synthesise the merged summaries.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Including demographic fields (age, city, income) without 5+ transcript agreements.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs encode demographic stereotypes from training data. "32-year-old freelance designer in Brooklyn" will appear plausibly even when none of your interviews confirm it. Strip demographics from the synthesis prompt unless the data supports them.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Always feeding transcripts in the same order to the synthesis agent.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs exhibit recency and primacy bias; the first and last transcripts in a batch disproportionately shape the output. Shuffle transcript order between runs; if the persona changes drastically, the data is too thin for a stable finding.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
