<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="MVP Scoping Framework">
  <summary>MVP definition, the MVP-vs-MLP distinction, and the MoSCoW prioritisation model with scope percentage targets.</summary>

  <section title="What MVP Is">
    <p>Minimum Viable Product is the smallest version that solves the core problem, delivers value to early adopters, and allows you to learn and iterate. Key insight: MVP is about learning, not launching a polished product.</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Start with MVP to validate the core hypothesis, then evolve to MLP for retention. Do not skip validation to go straight to polish.</statement>
      <rationale>Polishing a product before validating demand is expensive. MVP first confirms the problem-solution fit exists; MLP then makes the solution worth keeping.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="MoSCoW Prioritisation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Categorise every feature as Must Have, Should Have, Could Have, or Won't Have. Must-Have count must not exceed 5. Total effort for Must+Should must fit within the target timebox.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a hard cap on Must-Haves, scope creep makes MVPs into 6-month projects. The cap forces real trade-off decisions rather than deferring them to "later".</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Must Have (60% of scope): non-negotiable; product fails to deliver core value without these.</item>
      <item>Should Have (20% of scope): important but has workarounds; include if time allows.</item>
      <item>Could Have (15% of scope): nice-to-have; cut first under time pressure.</item>
      <item>Won't Have: explicitly excluded from this version; documented to prevent scope creep.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Kill Signal Requirement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every MVP scope document must include a kill signal: the specific evidence that would prove the hypothesis wrong and stop the project. Example: "If fewer than 10% of users complete the core flow within 2 weeks, shut down."</statement>
      <rationale>Without a kill signal, an MVP becomes an unfalsifiable experiment. Teams will ship regardless of what they learn, because there is no pre-agreed failure criterion to act on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
