<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="MVP Scoping Process">
  <summary>Six-step process from problem definition through definition of done, with validation checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define the Core Problem">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write the problem statement using this template: "For [target user] who [has this problem], our MVP will prove that [hypothesis] by delivering [core outcome] in [timeframe] with [constraints]."</statement>
      <rationale>The template forces explicit hypothesis statement before scoping begins. Scope without a hypothesis produces features without a learning goal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Identify the Core Value">
    <rule>
      <statement>Answer: "What is the ONE thing this product must do well?" Apply the value test: if you remove this feature, is the product useless? If yes, it is core value. If no, it is not.</statement>
      <rationale>Every scope decision derives from the core value. Features that do not support or enable the core value are candidates for Won't Have regardless of how good they are on their own.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: List All Features">
    <rule>
      <statement>Brain-dump all features first, then categorise each as Core (product doesn't work without it), Important (users would miss it), Nice-to-have (users can wait), or Out of scope.</statement>
      <rationale>Categorising before applying MoSCoW prevents anchoring on the first few ideas. The full dump also creates the Won't Have list, which is as important as the Must Have list.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Apply MoSCoW">
    <rule>
      <statement>Assign each feature a MoSCoW priority. Verify: Must-Haves do not exceed 5, total Must+Should effort fits the timebox. If either check fails, cut Must-Haves before extending the timeline.</statement>
      <rationale>Extending the timeline to accommodate scope is the default failure mode. The constraint forces real prioritisation instead of deferring trade-offs to engineering.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/lint-scope.py">Automated validator for must-have count, learning goal, kill signal, and effort budget</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Validate Scope">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run five checks before locking scope: solves core problem end-to-end, first user can complete core job without future features, value delivered is testable, buildable in target timeframe, has a testable hypothesis.</statement>
      <rationale>Scope that fails any check will fail in production. End-to-end validation is the most commonly skipped check — partial flows deliver no value even when they function correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Define Done">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write explicit completion criteria: feature list with acceptance criteria, definition of "good enough" quality, what to measure or learn, and the next decision after MVP results arrive (validate → build, invalidate → pivot).</statement>
      <rationale>MVP without a definition of done runs indefinitely. The next-decision field closes the loop: teams must decide in advance what they will do with the results.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/mvp-scope-doc.md">Full MVP scope document template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/mvp-quick-check.md">Five-question quick validator</reference>
  </section>
</text>
