<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="MVP Scoping Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Time-tracking app and course platform worked examples with MoSCoW scope decisions and learning goals, plus antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Time Tracking App">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: freelancers forget to track time and lose billable hours. Starting feature dump: 40+ features including mobile app, team features, integrations, advanced reports, budgets, etc.</note>
      <note>MVP scope (4 weeks): Must Have — start/stop timer (core functionality), project selection (assign time), basic report (see tracked time), simple invoice (get paid). Won't Have: mobile app (responsive web suffices), team features (solo focus), integrations (manual for now), advanced reports (spreadsheet export).</note>
      <note>Learning goal: will users actually track time daily? Kill signal: if fewer than 40% of registered users log time on 3+ days in the first 2 weeks, validate a different approach.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Course Platform">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Problem: course creators struggle with tech setup. MVP scope (6 weeks): Must Have — upload video/text lessons (core content), paywall/payment (must monetize), student access control (protect content), basic progress tracking (show value).</note>
      <note>Won't Have: quizzes (manual feedback), certificates (v2), community features (use external Discord), mobile app (responsive web), advanced analytics (basic counts only).</note>
      <note>Learning goal: will creators pay $29/month for simplicity over full-featured competitors? Kill signal: if 0 of 20 early-access invitees pay after trial, pivot pricing or positioning.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>More than 5 Must-Have features.</description>
      <reason>Every item added to Must-Have extends the timeline and narrows the learning. With 10 Must-Haves, the MVP is a 3-month project. Cap at 5 and demote the rest.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>No Won't-Have list.</description>
      <reason>Without explicit exclusions, scope creep enters through "just one more thing" requests. The Won't-Have list is a public commitment that prevents renegotiation of every cut feature.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>No learning goal or kill signal.</description>
      <reason>An MVP without a hypothesis is just a small product launch. Without a pre-agreed failure criterion, teams ship regardless of results and call it validated.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>MVP takes 6 months to build.</description>
      <reason>If it takes 6 months, it is not minimum. Revisit scope, cut Must-Haves further, or use micro-MVPs to validate assumptions before building.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Building MVP without weekly user feedback.</description>
      <reason>Assumptions invalidated at week 2 can redirect the remaining build. Waiting until launch to discover the hypothesis is wrong wastes all remaining build time.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
