<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="pain-point-research Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for pain-point-research. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define audience, context, and domain before searching; never begin mining without a written scope statement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Vague scope produces unactionable findings. "Founders" is too broad; "solo founders, US, post-launch B2B SaaS, under $10k MRR" produces searchable, comparable pain points.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Mine at least 3 source tiers per research session; never rely on a single source type.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Reddit alone is biased toward complainers. Mixing Tier 1 complaints with Tier 2 questions and Tier 4 gigs triangulates the real pain landscape.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Capture the verbatim quote and URL for every pain point; never substitute an agent's paraphrase.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Paraphrases lose signal and cannot be re-validated. Every quote must link to an actual URL or it is worthless for downstream validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Score every pain point using: Score = (Frequency × 0.30) + (Severity × 0.25) + (Reach × 0.20) + (Spend × 0.15) + (Alternatives × 0.10). Scale each factor 1-5.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The weighted formula prevents single-factor inflation. Frequency dominates because a pain that affects users daily is a stronger product anchor than a catastrophic but rare pain.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Priority thresholds: score above 4 = critical (high priority), 3-4 = significant (worth solving), 2-3 = moderate (could be a feature), below 2 = minor (deprioritize).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Clear numeric thresholds prevent subjective override of the scoring. A score of 3.8 is not "basically a 4"; it is significant but not critical.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run 5-Whys analysis for the top 3 scored pain points; the first-order pain is rarely the right thing to build.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Building for first-order symptoms produces features, not products. Root causes reveal structural opportunities that competitors also miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
