<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-discovery-framework" title="Pain Point Discovery Framework">
  <summary>How to define research scope, mine pain points from 4 source tiers, and extract root causes using 5-Whys analysis.</summary>

  <section title="Scope Definition">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define audience, context, and domain before searching; never begin mining without a written scope statement.</statement>
      <rationale>Vague scope produces unactionable findings. "Founders" is too broad; "solo founders, US, post-launch B2B SaaS, under $10k MRR" produces searchable, comparable pain points.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Audience: Freelance web developers
Context: Client project management
Domain: Remote services
Goal: Find 20 pain points in 4 hours
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Source Tiers">
    <p>Tier 1 (highest signal): direct complaints — Reddit sorted by top/controversial, Twitter/X rants, Product Hunt negative reviews, G2/Capterra 1-3 star reviews, App Store 1-2 star reviews.</p>
    <p>Tier 2 (problem indicators): questions — Quora "how to" queries, Stack Overflow duplicates, subreddit FAQ sections, Google "People Also Ask" results.</p>
    <p>Tier 3 (communities): Slack groups, Discord servers, Facebook groups, Indie Hackers discussions.</p>
    <p>Tier 4 (jobs and gigs): Upwork job posts, Fiverr popular gigs, LinkedIn job listings for "looking for someone to...".</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Mine at least 3 source tiers per research session; never rely on a single source type.</statement>
      <rationale>Reddit alone is biased toward complainers. Mixing Tier 1 complaints with Tier 2 questions and Tier 4 gigs triangulates the real pain landscape.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture the verbatim quote and URL for every pain point; never substitute an agent's paraphrase.</statement>
      <rationale>Paraphrases lose signal and cannot be re-validated. Every quote must link to an actual URL or it is worthless for downstream validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Root Cause Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run 5-Whys analysis for the top 3 scored pain points; the first-order pain is rarely the right thing to build.</statement>
      <rationale>Building for first-order symptoms produces features, not products. Root causes reveal structural opportunities that competitors also miss.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Pain: "I spend 3 hours/week on expense reports"
Why 1: Reports are manual
Why 2: System does not auto-import receipts
Why 3: No OCR integration
Why 4: IT will not approve new tools
Why 5: Tool approval process takes 6 months
Root cause: Organizational friction in tool adoption
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/pain-point-log.md">Research log template with scope, per-pain entries, and summary table</reference>
  <reference path="templates/reddit-mining.md">Reddit-specific extraction template</reference>
</text>
