<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-scoring-and-categorization" title="Pain Point Scoring and Categorization">
  <summary>Eight pain categories, the 5-factor weighted scoring matrix, priority thresholds, and antipatterns in pain scoring.</summary>

  <section title="Pain Categories">
    <list>
      <item>Time Waste — takes too long to do X (example: "spend 2 hours updating reports").</item>
      <item>Money Loss — costs more than it should (example: "paying $200/mo for features I don't use").</item>
      <item>Complexity — too hard to understand or configure.</item>
      <item>Integration — tools don't work together; copy-paste between apps.</item>
      <item>Reliability — doesn't work consistently; crashes regularly.</item>
      <item>Support — can't get help; no response from support.</item>
      <item>Process — workflow is broken; too many approvals for simple changes.</item>
      <item>Learning — hard to get started; long setup time.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Matrix">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score every pain point using: Score = (Frequency x 0.30) + (Severity x 0.25) + (Reach x 0.20) + (Spend x 0.15) + (Alternatives x 0.10). Scale each factor 1-5.</statement>
      <rationale>The weighted formula prevents single-factor inflation. Frequency dominates because a pain that affects users daily is a stronger product anchor than a catastrophic but rare pain.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Frequency (30%): 1 = rarely, 3 = weekly, 5 = daily.</item>
      <item>Severity (25%): 1 = annoying, 3 = painful, 5 = blocking.</item>
      <item>Reach (20%): 1 = few people, 3 = many, 5 = everyone in defined audience.</item>
      <item>Spend (15%): 1 = $0 spent solving it, 3 = some spend, 5 = significant spend.</item>
      <item>Alternatives (10%): 1 = many alternatives exist, 3 = few, 5 = none.</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Priority thresholds: score above 4 = critical (high priority), 3-4 = significant (worth solving), 2-3 = moderate (could be a feature), below 2 = minor (deprioritize).</statement>
      <rationale>Clear numeric thresholds prevent subjective override of the scoring. A score of 3.8 is not "basically a 4"; it is significant but not critical.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Inflating Reach to 5 ("everyone has this") without three distinct sources mentioning it.</description>
      <reason>Complaints are loud and unrepresentative. Cap Reach at 4 unless multiple independent sources confirm broad prevalence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Splitting scoring across multiple agent calls, each with a fresh context window.</description>
      <reason>The scoring rubric drifts between calls; item 40 gets a different standard than item 1. Score the full batch in one agent call with the rubric in the system prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Mining only one source type (e.g., only Reddit) and treating results as representative.</description>
      <reason>Reddit skews toward complainers and outliers. The "fine but mediocre" majority — where most opportunity lives — doesn't post there.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/batch-scorer.py">Python script that reads JSON list of pains, computes weighted scores, outputs CSV</reference>
</text>
