<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="opportunity-solution-trees">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>researcher</domain>
    <summary>Visual discovery framework connecting outcomes to opportunities to solutions to assumption tests. Stores as YAML/JSON in git; render targets only are visual tools.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>discovery</tag>
      <tag>ost</tag>
      <tag>framework</tag>
      <tag>research</tag>
      <tag>torres</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Opportunity Solution Trees</title>
    <summary>A visual discovery framework (Teresa Torres) that connects a single business Outcome to Opportunities (customer needs, grounded in evidence), Solutions (3+ per opportunity for compare-and-contrast), and Assumption Tests (one falsifiable experiment per solution). Stored as YAML/JSON in git; visual tools (Vistaly, Miro) are render targets only.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Without an OST, teams jump to solutions before understanding the problem space, or maintain flat idea backlogs that cannot be prioritized by evidence. The tree structure enforces opportunity-first thinking, requires evidence citations per node, and separates "compare and contrast" from "commit" — reducing the risk of building the wrong thing confidently.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Translating a single business outcome (KPI, OKR) into a discovery backlog of customer-rooted opportunities.</item>
        <item>Synthesising raw user-research artefacts (interview notes, JTBD, support tickets, NPS verbatims) into a navigable structure.</item>
        <item>Aligning PM/design/engineering on which sub-problems are in scope before any solution is committed.</item>
        <item>Deciding between competing solution ideas under a fixed opportunity ("compare and contrast" via experiments).</item>
        <item>Maintaining a living artefact during continuous discovery cycles (weekly interviews, ongoing experiments).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pure delivery / sprint planning — use a roadmap, Now/Next/Later, or Jira board instead.</item>
        <item>Compliance, regulatory, or contract-driven work where the "opportunity" is fixed and only execution remains.</item>
        <item>Single-developer side projects where outcome ↔ solution distance is trivial (the tree adds ceremony, not insight).</item>
        <item>Crisis / incident response where speed beats discovery rigour.</item>
        <item>When you have zero customer evidence — building an OST from "what we think users want" produces a confident-looking lie.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Where It Fails / Limitations">
      <list>
        <item>Garbage-in/garbage-out: opportunities not grounded in actual interview transcripts become solutions in disguise (most common failure mode).</item>
        <item>Tree explosion: teams brainstorm 50+ opportunities, lose focus, and never run experiments. Width must be pruned.</item>
        <item>Outcome-as-solution: outcome phrased as "ship feature X" short-circuits the entire framework before it starts.</item>
        <item>Single-solution branches: skipping "compare and contrast" yields no real choice; always generate 3+ solutions per opportunity.</item>
        <item>Stale trees: an OST not updated weekly becomes a project-plan-with-extra-shapes.</item>
        <item>LLM hallucination of opportunities: pattern-matched from training data, not from your customers — sounds plausible, traces to nothing.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="OST Node Types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Enforce layer separation: Outcome (what we want to achieve, metric-based), Opportunity (unmet customer need in customer language), Solution (proposed approach — 3+ per opportunity), Assumption Test (one falsifiable experiment per solution).</statement>
        <rationale>Solutions phrased as opportunities short-circuit the discovery process. Assumptions without falsifiable tests cannot inform build/no-build decisions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Outcome: one per tree root — phrased as a measurable metric ("Activation rate W1: 30% to 45% by Q3")</item>
        <item>Opportunity: unmet customer need in the customer's own language — verb + need + context ("New users can't tell what to do first after signup")</item>
        <item>Solution: proposed approach — structural diversity required (one tech, one process, one content solution)</item>
        <item>Assumption Test: one pre-registered falsifiable test per solution with a failure threshold</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Evidence Requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every opportunity node must cite at least 2 evidence IDs (interview transcript line, support ticket, survey row) — no evidence means no node.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs pattern-match opportunities from training data that sound plausible but trace to nothing. Evidence IDs force grounding in actual user data and enable the critic to verify the claim.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Store the OST as YAML/JSON in git — Miro/Vistaly/FigJam are render targets only, not the source of truth.</statement>
        <rationale>Visual tools are write-mostly for agents. Round-tripping a hand-edited Miro board back into structured form is brittle. Git-tracked YAML enables diffing and idempotent agent passes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use stable IDs (O-1, OP-3, S-7) for all nodes — agents diff and reference by ID, not statement text which changes across passes.</statement>
        <rationale>Statement text drifts on every rewrite. Stable IDs enable the critic agent to reference prior versions and detect when a solution is being disguised as an opportunity.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Compare-and-Contrast Requirement">
      <rule>
        <statement>Generate at least 3 solution candidates per opportunity before any selection — "compare and contrast" is the core value of the OST; single-solution branches defeat the framework.</statement>
        <rationale>A single solution under an opportunity is a waterfall roadmap with extra shapes. Three structural alternatives (e.g., interactive tour, templated starter, contextual tooltips) enable genuine trade-off analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Opportunity OP-1: "New users can't tell what to do first after signup" → S-1: Interactive 3-step product tour (desirability + usability risk), S-2: Templated starter project on first login (desirability + feasibility), S-3: Contextual tooltip overlay (usability + technical risk).</note>
      </example>
      <example type="bad">
        <note>Single solution under OP-1: "Add an onboarding checklist" — no compare-and-contrast possible; the team commits without evaluating alternatives.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Tree Depth and Width">
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the tree shallow and iterable: 1 outcome, 5-7 opportunities, 3 solutions per opportunity, 1 experiment per solution. Prune monthly.</statement>
        <rationale>Brainstorming 50+ opportunities and never running experiments is width without depth — theater, not discovery. Monthly pruning archives stale branches and prevents OST collapse under its own weight.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Best run as a multi-pass pipeline: a researcher subagent ingests raw evidence (transcripts, tickets, surveys) and emits clustered opportunities with citations; a PM/synthesis subagent shapes the tree (outcome → opportunities → solutions); an experiment-designer subagent attaches assumption tests per solution; a critic subagent challenges each node ("is this really an opportunity or a solution?", "what evidence supports this?"). Persist the tree as structured JSON/YAML so each pass is idempotent and diffable, then render to Mermaid/Markdown for humans and push to Vistaly/Miro for the team.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Recommended Subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-research-agent (existing, see researcher/CLAUDE.md) — runs pains and validate modes to produce the evidence base.</item>
        <item>ost-synthesizer — clusters pains into opportunities, enforces customer-language phrasing, requires evidence citations.</item>
        <item>ost-solution-generator — produces ≥3 solution candidates per opportunity, tags each with assumption types (desirability/viability/feasibility/usability/ethicality).</item>
        <item>ost-experiment-designer — attaches one falsifiable assumption test per solution (Mom-Test interview, fake-door, prototype, data dive).</item>
        <item>ost-critic — adversarial review: flags solutions-disguised-as-opportunities, missing evidence, unfalsifiable experiments, single-solution branches.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Pipeline Architecture">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run OST generation as multi-pass: ingest → cluster → critique → expand → diff. Never attempt a one-shot OST — token-budgeted single-call produces shallow, lossy trees.</statement>
        <rationale>One-shot conflates all layers: outcomes phrased as features, opportunities phrased as solutions. Each pass has a single responsibility and can be verified before the next begins.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Patterns">
      <example type="good">
        <note>ost-synthesizer prompt — strict JSON output with evidence_ids required:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are ost-synthesizer. Input: array of interview snippets with stable IDs.
Cluster into opportunities. Rules:
- Phrase each opportunity in the customer's own language (verb + need + context).
- Each opportunity must cite >=2 snippet IDs as evidence.
- Reject any node that names a solution, technology, or feature.
- Output JSON: {"opportunities":[{"id","statement","evidence_ids[]","parent_id|null"}]}.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
      <example type="good">
        <note>ost-critic prompt — verdict per node with three required checks:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
You are ost-critic. For each node, answer:
1. Is this an opportunity or a solution wearing a disguise? (cite signal)
2. Evidence count and quality (1-5).
3. Compare-and-contrast: how many sibling solutions exist?
4. Falsifiable experiment attached? Y/N.
Output: {"node_id", "verdict": "keep|rephrase|drop", "reason"}.
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Assumption Test Requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every assumption test must have a pre-registered failure threshold before it runs — "we'll measure usage after launch" is delivery, not discovery.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-hoc interpretation of results always finds success. A pre-registered threshold ("&lt;40% completion = drop the solution") makes the test genuinely falsifiable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Allowed test types: smoke test, fake door, prototype test, Wizard of Oz, concierge, Mom Test interview, data dive</item>
        <item>Forbidden: "ship and measure" — that is delivery, not an assumption test</item>
        <item>Required fields: riskiest_assumption, success_metric, falsifier threshold</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools">
      <list>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc): Render OST JSON → SVG/PNG diagrams — npm i -g @mermaid-js/mermaid-cli</item>
        <item>mdtree / markmap-cli: Markdown indented list → interactive mind-map — npm i -g markmap-cli</item>
        <item>jq: Validate / transform OST JSON between passes — apt/brew</item>
        <item>yq: YAML variant for human-edited trees — apt/brew</item>
        <item>Vistaly REST API: Programmatic CRUD on outcomes/opportunities/solutions/assumption-tests — docs.vistaly.com</item>
        <item>Miro REST API: Push generated tree to a board (sticky-per-node) — developers.miro.com</item>
        <item>Figma/FigJam Plugin API: Custom OST widget (zhouk/ost-figjam-widget reference) — figma.com/developers</item>
        <item>Linear / Jira / GitHub APIs: Link Solution nodes → delivery issues — native REST</item>
        <item>claude-cli headless: Run subagents in batch (-p mode) for tree passes — npm i -g @anthropic-ai/claude-code</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Services and Apps">
      <list>
        <item>Vistaly: OST-native SaaS — Purpose-built for Torres OST; native Jira/Linear/GitHub sync; REST + Zapier</item>
        <item>Miro: Whiteboard SaaS — Yes (REST API, OAuth) — Official OST template; sticky-note OST is brittle for diffs</item>
        <item>FigJam: Whiteboard SaaS — Partial (Plugin API) — OST widget exists; no full REST CRUD</item>
        <item>Whimsical: Diagram SaaS — Limited — Embed/share API only, no node-level write</item>
        <item>Productboard: Product mgmt SaaS — Yes (REST API) — Can host opportunities (Insights → Features); not a true tree UI</item>
        <item>Mural: Whiteboard SaaS — Yes (REST API) — Generic, OST template available</item>
        <item>CraftUp OST Builder: Free web tool — No API — Manual; exports MD/CSV/JSON — useful as schema reference</item>
        <item>Jira Product Discovery: Idea mgmt — Partial — Atlassian community has open OST request; workaround via custom fields</item>
        <item>Lucidchart: Diagram SaaS — Yes (REST API) — Generic tree shapes, no OST semantics</item>
        <item>Mermaid Live / GitHub: Diagram-as-code — Native — Best fit for git-tracked, agent-edited OST</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Anchor every opportunity to ≥2 evidence IDs (transcript line, ticket, survey row). No evidence → no node.</statement>
        <rationale>Each reference must be traceable to actual user data.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Enforce customer language at the opportunity layer; reject feature/tech vocabulary via a regex/critic pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Feature language masks the underlying customer need.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Generate ≥3 solutions per opportunity before any selection — "compare and contrast" is the whole point.</statement>
        <rationale>Multiple alternatives enable genuine trade-off analysis.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Pick one target opportunity per discovery cycle; the rest stay parked. Width without depth is theatre.</statement>
        <rationale>Focused depth produces real learning; scattered width is theater.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Store the OST as code (YAML/JSON in git); Miro/Vistaly is a render target, not the source of truth.</statement>
        <rationale>Git enables diffing, auditing, and idempotent agent passes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-run the critic agent after every human edit; trees decay fast.</statement>
        <rationale>Human rewrites drift opportunities into solutions without maintaining evidence.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Tag each solution with assumption type (desirability/viability/feasibility/usability/ethicality) so experiment design is targeted.</statement>
        <rationale>Assumption typing directs tests to the specific risk category that would kill the solution.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep the tree shallow but iteratable: 1 outcome × 5–7 opportunities × 3 solutions × 1 experiment beats a 200-node monster.</statement>
        <rationale>Shallow trees complete; deep sprawling trees stall.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use stable IDs (O-1, OP-3, S-7) — agents diff and reference by ID, not statement text.</statement>
        <rationale>Text changes on every rewrite; IDs are stable across passes.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs love to invent opportunities that pattern-match the domain ("users want better UX") with no transcript trace — always require evidence_ids and verify they exist.</item>
        <item>One-shot generation conflates layers: outcomes phrased as features, opportunities phrased as solutions. Run a dedicated layer-validator pass.</item>
        <item>"Generate 3 solutions" prompts return three rephrasings of the same idea unless you force structural diversity (e.g., one tech, one process, one content solution).</item>
        <item>Token-budgeted single-call OST → shallow, lossy. Use multi-pass: ingest → cluster → critique → expand → diff.</item>
        <item>Subagents drift on terminology between calls; pin a glossary (Outcome / Opportunity / Solution / Assumption Test) in every system prompt.</item>
        <item>Don't let the agent "finish" the tree. OST is never done; the agent should output next_interview_questions and next_riskiest_assumption, not a closing summary.</item>
        <item>Visual tools (Miro, FigJam) are write-mostly for agents — round-tripping a hand-edited Miro board back into structured form is brittle. Prefer git-tracked YAML as the canonical form, sync one-way to the visual tool.</item>
        <item>Be wary of "AI OST builders" that produce a tree from a one-line prompt; they hallucinate confidence. Useful only as a starter scaffold to be torn down by evidence.</item>
        <item>Experiments often degrade into "we'll measure usage after launch" — that is not falsifiable. Force a pre-registered failure threshold (e.g., &lt;40% completion = drop).</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="YAML Schema Reference">
      <p>Canonical agent-friendly form for multi-pass pipelines:</p>
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
# ost.yaml — agent-friendly canonical form
outcome:
  id: O-1
  metric: "Activation rate W1"
  target: "30% → 45% by Q3"
opportunities:
  - id: OP-1
    parent: O-1
    statement: "New users can't tell what to do first after signup"
    evidence: [INT-04, INT-09, TKT-211]   # interview/ticket IDs
    sizing: { reach: high, impact: high, confidence: med }
solutions:
  - id: S-1
    parent: OP-1
    statement: "Interactive 3-step product tour"
    assumption_types: [desirability, usability]
  - id: S-2
    parent: OP-1
    statement: "Templated starter project on first login"
    assumption_types: [desirability, feasibility]
experiments:
  - id: E-1
    parent: S-1
    type: prototype-test
    riskiest_assumption: "users will complete a 3-step tour"
    success_metric: "≥60% complete tour"
    falsifier: "<40% complete"
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="Rendering to Mermaid">
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# render OST yaml → mermaid → svg
yq -o=json ost.yaml | jq -r '
  "graph TD",
  (.outcome | "O[\(.id): \(.metric)]"),
  (.opportunities[] | "O --> \(.id)[\(.statement)]"),
  (.solutions[] | "\(.parent) --> \(.id)((\(.statement)))"),
  (.experiments[] | "\(.parent) --> \(.id)>\(.type)]")
' > ost.mmd
mmdc -i ost.mmd -o ost.svg
      ]]></code>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ost.yaml" purpose="Canonical OST schema with all four node types and stable IDs"/>
      <template path="templates/ost-render.sh" purpose="Converts ost.yaml to Mermaid SVG via mmdc"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/opportunity-solution-trees/"/>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/2023/09/tools-of-the-trade-opportunity-solution-tree/"/>
      <link href="https://www.vistaly.com/product/opportunity-solution-tree"/>
      <link href="https://docs.vistaly.com/documentation/integrations/jira"/>
      <link href="https://miro.com/templates/opportunity-solution-tree/"/>
      <link href="https://www.figma.com/templates/opportunity-solution-tree/"/>
      <link href="https://github.com/zhouk/ost-figjam-widget"/>
      <link href="https://blog.vistaly.com/posts/ost_patterns"/>
      <link href="https://www.producttalk.org/ai-opportunity-solution-trees/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
