<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Naming and Domains Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Naming and Domains application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="pronounceable-in-locales" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Names MUST be pronounceable in each target locale (test by reading to one native speaker per locale). Unpronounceable candidates are dropped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Brand-recall research">Unpronounceable names lose recall and word-of-mouth referrals.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="trademark-checked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Top-3 finalists are checked against the USPTO TESS, EUIPO, and a generic Google search. Any near-hit drops the candidate.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trademark-conflict avoidance">Late-stage trademark collisions force rebrands and cost more than the upfront check.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="apex-domain-available" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apex .com (or, fallback, .ai / .net) MUST be available or acquirable at &lt;USD 1k. ccTLD-only fallback is allowed only if the brand is locale-bound.</statement>
      <rationale source="Domain-availability discipline">Subdomain or hyphenated alternates hurt SEO and trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="handles-checked" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Top-3 names are checked on X, GitHub, LinkedIn, and Bluesky. Unavailable handles drop the candidate unless the operator commits to a documented suffix (-app / -hq).</statement>
      <rationale source="Brand-cohesion discipline">Disjoint social handles fragment the brand at launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ranked-rationale" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Final report ranks top 3 with explicit rationale per criterion (recall / trademark / domain / handles). Single-name reports are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-record discipline">Single-name reports hide the trade-offs and force later relitigation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
