<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-naming-strategies" title="Product Naming Strategies and Generation Process">
  <summary>Seven strategies for generating product names, criteria for evaluating candidates, and a step-by-step generation process.</summary>

  <section title="Naming Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply all 7 strategies to keywords and generate at least 20 candidates before evaluating any.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-strategy generation produces names that cluster; diversity requires parallel exploration across strategy types.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Descriptive — states what the product does (Dropbox, YouTube)</item>
      <item>Invented — made-up word with no prior meaning (Spotify, Kodak)</item>
      <item>Compound — two meaningful words combined (Facebook, Snapchat)</item>
      <item>Metaphor — symbolic meaning borrowed from another domain (Amazon, Apple)</item>
      <item>Portmanteau — syllables from two words blended (Pinterest = pin + interest, Instagram = instant + telegram)</item>
      <item>Alliteration — repeated initial sound aids memory (PayPal, Coca-Cola)</item>
      <item>Acronym — initialism for the product's full name (IBM, NASA)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Good Name Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Reject any candidate that fails more than one of these six tests: easy to spell, easy to pronounce, memorable, .com domain available, no trademark conflicts, works internationally.</statement>
      <rationale>A name that fails on domain or trademark is unusable regardless of how memorable it is; a name with pronunciation ambiguity fails at word-of-mouth.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Target 5-10 characters. Avoid hyphens, numbers, and ambiguous letters (l/I/1, O/0).</statement>
      <rationale>Short names attract premium pricing; very long names are unmemorable; ambiguous characters kill voice spelling.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Generation Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define brand attributes (3-5 adjectives) and keyword buckets (product, benefit, emotion) before generating any names.</statement>
      <rationale>Names generated without a brief converge on generic register. Brief anchors diversity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Step 1: Define brand attributes (3-5 adjectives)</item>
      <item>Step 2: List keywords by bucket — product, benefit, emotion</item>
      <item>Step 3: Apply each strategy to each keyword bucket</item>
      <item>Step 4: Generate 20+ candidates</item>
      <item>Step 5: Filter by availability (domain + trademark)</item>
      <item>Step 6: Test pronunciation with 5 people from target market</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/naming-brief.md">Structured brief template for capturing attributes, keywords, candidates, and top 3.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Prompting an LLM without explicit forbidden-words list produces names ending in -ly, -ify, -hub, or starting with Smart-, AI-.</description>
      <reason>LLMs are mode-collapsed on startup naming patterns. Same prompt yields Lify, Spark, Loop, Flux, Atlas, Nova, Pulse repeatedly. Diversity requires an anti-pattern list in the prompt.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Accepting a name without native-speaker pronunciation test.</description>
      <reason>Agent-generated names like "Krapp", "Pschitt", or "Sega" (Italian: saw/handjob) have culturally negative meanings agents miss. Requires L1 speaker review.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <note>Task Management Tool — complete generation run</note>
    <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Attributes: Simple, fast, powerful
Keywords: tasks, workflow, automation
Anti-patterns: NO [-ly, -ify, -hub, AI-, smart-, Spark, Atlas, Nova]

Generated: TaskFlow (compound), Tasko (invented), QuickTask (descriptive), Flowdo (portmanteau), Taskr (invented)
Filtered: TaskFlow (.com available, 8 chars, 2 syllables)
Winner: TaskFlow
]]></code>
  </example>
</text>
