<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-domain-availability" title="Domain and Handle Availability Checking">
  <summary>Priority order for domain and handle checks, actions by availability status, alternative strategies when primary is taken, and agent-specific gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Check Priority">
    <rule>
      <statement>Check .com first. If .com is taken by an active product, move to the next name candidate rather than accepting an alternative TLD for a serious brand.</statement>
      <rationale>.com is still the default for credibility in B2B. .io is acceptable for devtools. .ai only if ML product and budget tolerates premium. Skip .xyz/.tech for serious brands.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Priority 1 — .com domain (essential for credibility)</item>
      <item>Priority 2 — GitHub org (essential for open-source)</item>
      <item>Priority 3 — .io domain (acceptable for tech products)</item>
      <item>Priority 4 — Twitter/X handle (important for marketing)</item>
      <item>Priority 5 — .co domain (alternative TLD)</item>
      <item>Priority 6 — LinkedIn company URL slug (nice to have)</item>
      <item>Also check: npm package, PyPI package if applicable</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Availability Actions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Register handles on all platforms in the same hour as registering the domain — even if unused — to prevent squatting.</statement>
      <rationale>GitHub org, npm/PyPI, Twitter, LinkedIn — squatters monitor new domain registrations and claim matching handles within hours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Available → Register immediately</item>
      <item>Premium (priced) → Consider if under $5K for revenue-generating product</item>
      <item>Taken (parked &gt;5 years, price &gt;$5K) → Walk away for non-revenue projects</item>
      <item>Taken (active product) → Move to next name candidate</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Alternative Domain Strategies">
    <p>When primary .com is taken, try in order before accepting an alternative TLD:</p>
    <list>
      <item>Add "get" prefix: gettaskflow.com</item>
      <item>Add "app" or "hq" suffix: taskflowhq.com</item>
      <item>Different TLD: taskflow.io</item>
      <item>Creative spelling (only if still unambiguous): taskflw.com</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/domain-check-report.md">Domain/handle availability matrix template with trademark check and fallback alternatives.</reference>
    <reference path="scripts/check-names.sh">Bulk availability runner: reads names.txt, outputs CSV matrix across .com/.io/.co, GitHub, npm, PyPI, Twitter.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Trademark Check">
    <rule>
      <statement>Trademark check must end at a human attorney. Agent USPTO TESS output is an informational risk band, not legal clearance.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents miss similar marks (phonetic, design). A free .com that infringes is worse than a paid premium that is clear.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Treating agent trademark pre-filter as legal clearance.</description>
      <reason>USPTO TESS HTML changes yearly, scrapes break, and phonetic similarity is not caught by string matching. Agent output is risk-band only.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>WHOIS responses vary by registry — "no match" / "not found" / "no entries" / "AVAILABLE" are all different strings; agent regex misses some.</description>
      <reason>Some TLDs deny WHOIS to non-authenticated clients (.de needs DENIC TCP); agents falsely report "available". Always confirm at registrar API, not just WHOIS.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Price scraping stale domains without re-fetching within 48h of registration decision.</description>
      <reason>Premium domain pricing fluctuates; scraped prices can be weeks old and the listed price may have changed or the domain may have been claimed.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <example type="good">
    <note>TaskFlow availability: primary taken, fallback found</note>
    <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
taskflow.com     → Taken (active SaaS product)
gettaskflow.com  → Available → Register
taskflow.io      → Available → Register as backup
@taskflow        → Taken
@gettaskflow     → Available → Register

Recommendation: gettaskflow.com + @gettaskflow
]]></code>
  </example>
</text>
