<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="naming-and-domains Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for naming-and-domains as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Prompting an LLM without explicit forbidden-words list produces names ending in -ly, -ify, -hub, or starting with Smart-, AI-.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLMs are mode-collapsed on startup naming patterns. Same prompt yields Lify, Spark, Loop, Flux, Atlas, Nova, Pulse repeatedly. Diversity requires an anti-pattern list in the prompt.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Accepting a name without native-speaker pronunciation test.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agent-generated names like "Krapp", "Pschitt", or "Sega" (Italian: saw/handjob) have culturally negative meanings agents miss. Requires L1 speaker review.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating agent trademark pre-filter as legal clearance.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>USPTO TESS HTML changes yearly, scrapes break, and phonetic similarity is not caught by string matching. Agent output is risk-band only.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>WHOIS responses vary by registry — "no match" / "not found" / "no entries" / "AVAILABLE" are all different strings; agent regex misses some.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Some TLDs deny WHOIS to non-authenticated clients (.de needs DENIC TCP); agents falsely report "available". Always confirm at registrar API, not just WHOIS.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Price scraping stale domains without re-fetching within 48h of registration decision.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Premium domain pricing fluctuates; scraped prices can be weeks old and the listed price may have changed or the domain may have been claimed.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
