<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="product-lifecycle">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Four-stage framework (Introduction → Growth → Maturity → Decline) for diagnosing product lifecycle stage and applying the matching investment strategy.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>product-lifecycle</tag>
      <tag>portfolio-management</tag>
      <tag>stage-strategy</tag>
      <tag>investment-allocation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Product Lifecycle Management</title>
    <summary>A four-stage framework (Introduction → Growth → Maturity → Decline) for diagnosing which lifecycle stage a product is in and applying the matching investment strategy. Each stage has distinct focus areas, key metrics, and transition triggers. The process runs in four steps: assess stage from metrics, validate with multi-quarter trends, apply stage-appropriate strategy, and plan the next-stage transition.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Products managed with the same tactics regardless of maturity stage waste investment. Growth acquisition tactics applied to a Maturity product over-spend on CAC; optimization investments applied to an Introduction product starve PMF discovery. Stage-aware allocation is the lever: right strategy, right metrics, right expectations per stage.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Quarterly portfolio review — decide investment level for each shipped product and stop applying growth budget to maturity or decline assets.</item>
        <item>A product hits a metrics inflection (growth slows from 30% to 8%, churn jumps) — need a structured stage reassessment, not a gut call.</item>
        <item>Pre-roadmap step: tag every product with its stage before sequencing the year.</item>
        <item>End-of-life decision: product declining for 3+ quarters, need a sunset plan with migration timeline.</item>
        <item>Investor or board update: defending why a Maturity product gets retention budget instead of new features.</item>
        <item>Stage transition checkpoint: Introduction product hits PMF and must shift from "learn fast" to "scale" tooling.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF startup with one product still hunting for fit — there is no lifecycle yet, only a discovery loop.</item>
        <item>Sub-feature decisions inside one product (which feature to build next) — RICE / MoSCoW are sharper at that grain.</item>
        <item>Pure B2B services / agency revenue with no productized asset — lifecycle math is undefined.</item>
        <item>Internal tools / platforms with no external customers — they have a usefulness curve, not a revenue curve.</item>
        <item>Crisis weeks (P0 outage, security incident) — survival first, restore lifecycle planning after.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="introduction-stage">
      <p>Low revenue, negative profit, early adopters only, high uncertainty, frequent pivots.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>In Introduction, maximize learning and product-market fit validation over revenue extraction. Invest 70%+ in iteration and PMF, 0% in sunset activities.</statement>
        <rationale>Pre-PMF, every dollar on acquisition before fit is wasted CAC. The stage ends only when activation and early retention signal demand.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Key metrics: activation rate, early retention (Day 7), NPS from early users.</item>
        <item>Stage signal: MRR &lt; $10k OR growth &gt; 50% YoY AND profitability negative AND &lt;12 months since launch.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="growth-stage">
      <p>Rapidly increasing revenue, market acceptance, competition increasing, scaling challenges.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>In Growth, invest 60%+ in customer acquisition and feature expansion to capture market share before competition intensifies. Build team and infrastructure in parallel.</statement>
        <rationale>Growth windows close fast; under-investing in acquisition during Growth produces a smaller Maturity base from which to defend.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Key metrics: growth rate, CAC, LTV, market share, revenue.</item>
        <item>Stage signal: growth &gt;= 20% YoY for 2+ quarters AND profitability improving AND competition increasing.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="maturity-stage">
      <p>Stable or slowing revenue, market saturation, intense competition, optimization focus.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>In Maturity, shift 50%+ of investment to retention and optimization; cap new acquisition at &lt;30%. Measure profitability and efficiency ratios, not growth rate.</statement>
        <rationale>New customer acquisition becomes expensive in saturated markets; retaining existing customers and extracting margin is the highest-ROI lever.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Key metrics: profitability, churn rate, NPS, cost efficiency ratios.</item>
        <item>Stage signal: growth &lt; 15% YoY AND profitability at peak AND saturated market signals.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="decline-stage">
      <p>Decreasing revenue, technology shift, customer migration, resource reallocation.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>In Decline, invest 60%+ in optimization and sunset activities; stop new acquisition investment. Focus on cash harvesting, migration support, and sunset timeline.</statement>
        <rationale>Continued acquisition spend in Decline produces negative-ROI customers who still need support through the sunset window.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Key metrics: cash flow, migration rate, support cost, timeline to sunset.</item>
        <item>Stage signal: growth &lt; 0 for 2+ quarters AND customer migration evidence.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="stage-appropriate-strategies">
      <rule>
        <statement>Anchor every stage label to at least two evidence sources (e.g., MRR series + cohort retention). Single-metric staging is the #1 cause of misclassification.</statement>
        <rationale>Single metrics are gamed or misread; two independent sources provide triangulation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Re-classify quarterly. SaaS stage transitions can happen in two quarters; annual reviews apply the wrong strategy for 9-12 months.</statement>
        <rationale>Stage transitions are not annual events; quarterly cadence matches the speed at which market conditions shift.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Applying growth acquisition tactics to a Decline-stage product.</description>
        <reason>Acquisition spend compounds losses — acquired customers still generate support cost during the sunset window with no long-term LTV payback.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Refusing to declare Decline because the label is politically costly — lobbying for "late Maturity" indefinitely.</description>
        <reason>Delayed Decline classification extends over-investment; pre-commit numeric kill thresholds (e.g., "MRR YoY &lt; 0 for 3 quarters = automatic Decline review") to remove the political judgment call.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="assessment-process">
      <section name="step-1-assess-current-stage">
        <rule>
          <statement>Collect at least 4-8 quarters of MRR, growth rate, churn, gross margin, and market share data before classifying. With fewer than 4 quarters of history, default to Intro with low confidence.</statement>
          <rationale>Stage transitions can happen in 2 quarters; short histories produce high-variance classifications that reverse on the next data point.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <list>
          <item>Intro signal: MRR &lt; $10k OR growth &gt; 50% YoY AND negative profitability AND &lt;12mo since launch.</item>
          <item>Growth signal: growth &gt;= 20% YoY for 2+ quarters AND improving profitability AND increasing competition.</item>
          <item>Maturity signal: growth &lt; 15% YoY AND peak profitability AND saturated market signals.</item>
          <item>Decline signal: growth &lt; 0 for 2+ quarters AND customer migration evidence.</item>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section name="step-2-validate-stage">
        <rule>
          <statement>Review metrics trends over 3+ quarters, compare to market benchmarks, consider external factors (category shift, new technology), and get cross-functional team alignment before finalizing the stage label.</statement>
          <rationale>Single-person classification is subject to optimism bias; team alignment surfaces conflicting signals that a solo reviewer misses.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <antipattern>
          <description>Using revenue YoY growth as the sole classification signal for network-effect or bundling products.</description>
          <reason>Network-effect products can show low revenue but high engagement (still Growth); bundling products can show stable revenue while the real value is migrating to a different SKU.</reason>
        </antipattern>
      </section>

      <section name="step-3-apply-stage-strategy">
        <rule>
          <statement>Explicitly map current investments (% engineering cost on acquisition / retention / optimization / sunset) against the stage-appropriate allocation rubric. Flag and resolve any misalignment before next quarter planning.</statement>
          <rationale>Investment misalignment — growth tactics in Decline, optimization tactics in Intro — is the primary source of wasted product budget at the portfolio level.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>

      <section name="step-4-plan-transitions">
        <rule>
          <statement>Pre-commit numeric transition triggers when entering Maturity, not when entering Decline: e.g., "if MRR YoY &lt; 0 for 3 consecutive quarters, automatic Decline review." Document in portfolio decisions log.</statement>
          <rationale>By the time Decline is obvious, the org has already over-invested for 2-4 quarters. Pre-committed thresholds remove the political delay.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Treat stage transitions as bidirectional. A Maturity product can re-enter Growth via a new segment, pricing tier, or 10x feature unlock. Always evaluate revival vs. sunset before committing to harvest mode.</statement>
          <rationale>Default-to-sunset is expensive when the underlying user need still exists. Re-platforming can recover Maturity-equivalent performance for 20% of new-product cost.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="examples">
      <example type="good" title="SaaS Product in Growth">
        <note>Assessment: 40% YoY growth, just reached profitability, 3 new competitors entered the market in the last two quarters.</note>
        <note>Stage: Growth (confirmed by 2 independent signals: YoY growth &gt; 20% + improving profitability).</note>
        <note>Strategy: Accelerate customer acquisition, expand feature set for enterprise segment, build sales team, invest in infrastructure to support scale.</note>
        <note>Transition trigger: Growth slows to &lt; 15% YoY for two consecutive quarters — begin Maturity strategy shift (reduce acquisition %, increase retention %).</note>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Legacy Product in Decline">
        <note>Assessment: -10% YoY revenue, customers actively migrating to a newer platform, core technology becoming outdated.</note>
        <note>Stage: Decline (confirmed by 2 independent signals: negative YoY growth + customer migration evidence).</note>
        <note>Strategy: Maintain core functionality only, help customers migrate, reduce support costs, plan explicit sunset timeline of 18 months.</note>
        <note>End goal: Complete migration of all active users within 18 months; communicate sunset date 6 months in advance; wind down support contracts at sunset.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Same metrics tracked regardless of lifecycle stage.</description>
        <reason>Growth rate is the primary metric in Introduction and Growth but meaningless in Maturity (where profitability and churn matter more) and actively misleading in Decline.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Emotional attachment to a declining product preventing objective sunset decision.</description>
        <reason>Emotional attachment delays the inevitable, extends over-investment, and wastes capacity that could accelerate a Growth-stage product. Pre-committed numeric thresholds are the antidote.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No sunset plan drafted until Decline is obvious.</description>
        <reason>Sunset planning requires 6-12 months of lead time for customer communication, contract wind-down, and team transition. Waiting until Decline is confirmed leaves insufficient runway.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/lifecycle-assessment.md" purpose="Metrics table, stage indicator matrix, assessed stage block, transition plan"/>
      <template path="templates/stage-strategy-guide.md" purpose="Focus areas, key metrics, investment priorities, risks, success criteria per stage"/>
    </templates>
    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/stage-suggest.sh" purpose="Classifies products by lifecycle stage from quarterly MRR CSV; emits ambiguous rows for LLM review"/>
    </scripts>
  </content>
</methodology>
