<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Build vs Buy Decision Tree Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every decision-tree-build-vs-buy application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any build vs buy decision with a 3-year TCO exceeding $50k MUST include a formal TCO comparison. The TCO MUST cover: initial development/licensing, 3-year maintenance/subscription, integration effort, team training, and opportunity cost of engineering time diverted from core product.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Most build decisions undercount maintenance cost (typically 15-20% of build cost per year), security audit costs, and the ongoing engineering opportunity cost. Formal TCO analysis prevents these underestimates from driving incorrect decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-score-all-four-axes" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Decision MUST score all four axes (strategic differentiation, 3-yr TCO, time-to-value, lock-in risk). Partial scoring is blocked.</statement>
      <rationale source="TCO modelling discipline; ATAM scoring">Skipping an axis is the most common path to a regretted choice; the rule forces full evaluation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-differentiation-threshold" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Build is chosen ONLY when strategic_differentiation scores ≥4 on the 1-5 scale. Below 4 the default is buy or adopt-oss.</statement>
      <rationale source="Marc Andreessen - 'companies should only build what differentiates'">Below-threshold differentiation means the work creates no competitive moat; building it consumes capacity that should fund the actual moat.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-tco-3-year-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buy decisions MUST include a 3-year TCO model with realistic seat / API-call growth.</statement>
      <rationale source="Finance discipline; SaaS pricing-tier risk">Year-1 sticker price is misleading; tier transitions in year 2-3 frequently double the cost.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-lock-in-rollback" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Buy decisions with lock_in_risk = high MUST include a rollback path with engineering_weeks estimate and trigger conditions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Bezos 1997 - reversibility; vendor-failure case studies">Without a rollback path the buy is implicitly one_way_door_irrevocable; the rule surfaces the actual reversibility tier.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-23 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
