<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-protocol" title="Cognitive Walkthrough Protocol">
  <summary>The four-question protocol applied per step of a defined correct action sequence, with evaluator setup and issue-documentation rules.</summary>

  <section title="Prerequisites">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define persona, task, and the complete correct action sequence in writing before the walkthrough session begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a pre-agreed sequence the walkthrough devolves into freeform critique; you cannot answer Q4 without knowing what "progress" looks like.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Target persona: name, experience level, prior knowledge, goal.</item>
      <item>Task: single clear statement (e.g., "Create a new account and complete profile setup").</item>
      <item>Correct sequence: ordered list of actions with expected UI result for each step.</item>
      <item>Interface: prototype or live URL, accessible to all evaluators before the session.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Group size: 2-4 evaluators. Larger groups converge too quickly; smaller groups miss blind spots.</p>
    <reference path="templates/walkthrough-plan.md">Pre-session planning template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="The Four Questions (per step)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Answer all four questions for every step independently; do not skip steps where the answer seems obvious.</statement>
      <rationale>Evaluators with product familiarity skip steps that first-time users actually fail at — the methodology's value is systematic coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Q1: Will the user try to achieve the right effect? (Motivation and goal awareness)</item>
      <item>Q2: Will the user notice that the correct action is available? (Visibility and location)</item>
      <item>Q3: Will the user associate the correct action with the desired effect? (Label clarity and affordance)</item>
      <item>Q4: If the correct action is performed, will the user see that progress is being made? (Feedback adequacy)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Issue Documentation">
    <rule>
      <statement>For every "No" or "Partial" answer, document: problem description, question number, severity (H/M/L), and a one-sentence fix proposal.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a fix proposal the walkthrough produces a problem list with no actionable next step; forcing a proposal reveals whether the issue is real or cosmetic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/evaluation-form.md">Per-step evaluation form</reference>
    <reference path="templates/summary-report.md">Post-session summary report</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Severity Rubric">
    <list>
      <item>High — blocks task completion for the persona; must fix before launch.</item>
      <item>Medium — slows user by more than one additional turn or exchange; fix soon.</item>
      <item>Low — polish issue; fix when capacity allows.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
