<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Cognitive Walkthrough Calibration Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Rules for keeping evaluators calibrated and specific failure modes when AI agents run the four-question protocol.</summary>

  <section title="Evaluator Calibration Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each evaluator must answer each question independently before discussion; reveal answers simultaneously.</statement>
      <rationale>Group-think from fast consensus causes evaluators to adopt the first answer rather than their genuine assessment of the interface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use only the persona profile as the reference frame; ignore personal familiarity with the product.</statement>
      <rationale>Evaluators with product knowledge answer "Yes" to Q2 and Q3 because they know where the button is — the novice persona does not.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-walk the sequence after fixes are implemented; never assume a fix resolves the issue without verification.</statement>
      <rationale>Fixes for Q2 (visibility) sometimes introduce Q3 failures (label confusion); a re-walk catches regressions cheaply.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent-Specific Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM agent answers "Yes" to Q2 and Q3 without positive evidence from the screenshot or DOM.</description>
      <reason>Agents default to charitable interpretation; require "Yes only if the screenshot shows X" in the prompt to force grounding.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent conflates Q1 (does user know they need to act?) with Q3 (does label match the action?).</description>
      <reason>These are distinct failure types — Q1 is motivational, Q3 is labelling — separate prompts prevent cross-contamination.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent answers Q4 for the page transition rather than for the user's stated goal.</description>
      <reason>A page load is not progress feedback; the user's internal narrative ("did I complete step X?") is the correct reference.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Persona file not reseeded each step; agent forgets the persona midway through a long session.</description>
      <reason>LLMs drift from persona context over long conversations; reseed the persona description at each step.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent marks all issues as High severity.</description>
      <reason>Severity inflation renders prioritization meaningless; apply the H/M/L rubric explicitly: H = blocks task, M = extra turn, L = polish.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Known Limitations">
    <list>
      <item>Walkthrough finds learnability issues, not preference, satisfaction, or value — do not replace user research.</item>
      <item>Motivational issues ("user knows what to do, just does not want to") are invisible to the method.</item>
      <item>Accessibility is ignored unless the persona explicitly includes AT (assistive technology) use.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
