<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Methodologies Detail Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1200" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Methodologies Detail methodology. Every rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale, plus the universal skip-this-methodology gate.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="canonical-section-order" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Detail pages MUST emit sections in the canonical order (Summary, When-to-use, When-not-to-use, Core rules, Output contract, Failure modes, Procedure, Examples, Decision tree, Templates, Scripts, Related).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — section ordering">Inconsistent ordering forces readers to re-orient on every page.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="five-testable-rules-minimum" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Core rules table MUST contain at least 5 testable rules with id + statement + rationale + source.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec B2 01-core-rules">Fewer than 5 rules signals the methodology is under-specified.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="paired-examples" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output contract MUST show one valid + one invalid example side by side.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec B2 02-output-contract">Single examples leave the schema's negative space untested.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="validator-link" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Detail page MUST link to the validate-&lt;slug&gt;.py script when the methodology has an output contract.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec B4">Without the link, readers cannot run the schema check.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-tbd-in-published" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Detail page MUST contain zero TBD, TODO, or FIXME tokens at publish time.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — definition of done">Published TBDs reveal an unfinished methodology.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply this methodology only if all entries in `## Applies If` hold and none of `## Skip If` triggers; otherwise abort and route to the correct methodology.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 spec — decision tree minimum form">A misrouted methodology produces wrong-shape output; the explicit skip rule is the universal default branch from the decision tree.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
