<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-model-and-tiers" title="Subscription Model Types and Tier Design">
  <summary>Five subscription model types with best-fit guidance; billing frequency trade-offs; Good-Better-Best, Freemium, and Usage+Base tier structures; feature allocation rules.</summary>

  <section title="Subscription Model Types">
    <list>
      <item>SaaS — software access. Users pay for ongoing access to a platform or tool. Best for: tools, platforms, productivity software.</item>
      <item>Membership — community or content access. Users pay for belonging and exclusive content. Best for: education, professional communities, newsletters.</item>
      <item>Replenishment — regular physical product delivery. Best for: consumables, personal care, food.</item>
      <item>Curation — curated selections delivered periodically. Best for: discovery products (book clubs, music, fashion boxes).</item>
      <item>Access — exclusive availability (not content, but priority or privilege). Best for: premium services, concierge products.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Billing Frequency Trade-offs">
    <rule>
      <statement>Offer both monthly and annual billing. Present annual as "2 months free" (not "17% off"). For most SaaS, annual reduces churn by 3–5x compared to monthly-only.</statement>
      <rationale>Annual billing creates a 12-month commitment window before the next churn decision. "2 months free" is tangible (users can visualize two months); "17% off" is abstract.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Tier Structures">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Good-Better-Best (max 4 tiers) as default. Free tier must be limited enough that a real user would want to upgrade within 30 days of hitting the limit.</statement>
      <rationale>Too-generous free tiers eliminate upgrade motivation. The most common subscription failure pattern is a free tier that fully satisfies the core use case.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Good-Better-Best for a SaaS tool — core value limited on free, full access on Pro, collaboration on Team.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Basic ($9/mo):  Core features, 100 items limit
Pro ($29/mo):   Full features, unlimited (anchor tier)
Team ($79/mo):  Collaboration + priority support
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Usage + Base for API-driven product — base covers fixed costs, usage covers variable.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Base ($29/mo):  Platform access, 1K API calls included
Usage:          $0.01 per additional API call
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
