<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-lifecycle-and-examples" title="Customer Lifecycle and Real Examples">
  <summary>Five-stage customer lifecycle with intervention triggers; SaaS email tool and developer membership examples with tier decisions and outcomes.</summary>

  <section title="Customer Lifecycle Stages and Interventions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Instrument lifecycle stage transitions and trigger interventions at each: onboarding email Day 1, check-in Day 3, conversion offer Day 7 (for trials); usage-drop alert for at-risk; save offer at cancellation; win-back at Day 30 post-churn.</statement>
      <rationale>Each lifecycle stage has a different intervention ROI. Day 1 onboarding email has the highest open rate of any email the user will ever receive (50–70%). At-risk outreach is cheaper than win-back.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Trial Day 1: welcome email + first value action prompt.</item>
      <item>Trial Day 3: check-in email — did they complete the first action? Help if not.</item>
      <item>Trial Day 7: conversion offer — limited-time or exclusive bonus for upgrading now.</item>
      <item>Active monthly: usage report email — show them the value delivered this month.</item>
      <item>At-risk (usage drop 50%+ week-over-week): proactive outreach, offer help session.</item>
      <item>Cancel request: save offer (discount, pause, downgrade) before confirming cancellation.</item>
      <item>Churned Day 30: win-back campaign — announce new feature or offer re-entry discount.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Example 1: SaaS Email Marketing Tool">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Three-tier usage-based pricing; 115% NRR achieved through expansion (users growing their contact lists).</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tiers:
  Starter $19/mo:  1K contacts, 10K emails/mo
  Growth  $49/mo:  5K contacts, 50K emails/mo  (40% of users)
  Pro     $99/mo:  15K contacts, 150K emails/mo

Outcomes:
  40% choose Growth (anchor tier)
  Net Revenue Retention: 115%
  Monthly churn rate: 3%
  (Expansion from contact list growth offsets churn)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example 2: Developer Learning Membership">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Freemium + two paid tiers; small VIP tier generates outsized revenue share.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tiers:
  Free   $0:      Public content only
  Member $29/mo:  All courses + community
  VIP    $99/mo:  + Live sessions + mentorship

Outcomes:
  Free-to-paid conversion: 5%
  Annual retention (paid): 85%
  VIP = 2% of paid users, 15% of revenue
  (VIP LTV ~10x Member LTV)
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
