<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="performance-domains-overview">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>pm-agile</domain>
    <summary>Eight PMBOK 7 performance domains assess project health: Stakeholder, Team, Dev Approach, Planning, Project Work, Delivery, Measurement, Uncertainty.</summary>
    <category>frameworks</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>pmbok</tag>
      <tag>performance-domains</tag>
      <tag>project-management</tag>
      <tag>assessment</tag>
      <tag>outcomes</tag>
    </tags>
    <tools>
      <tool>claude-code</tool>
    </tools>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Performance Domains Overview (PMBOK 7)</title>

    <summary>PMBOK 7 organizes project management into eight concurrent, interconnected performance domains — Stakeholder, Team, Development Approach, Planning, Project Work, Delivery, Measurement, Uncertainty — each focused on outcomes rather than process steps. The domains are always active simultaneously; neglecting any one degrades the others through well-documented interaction chains. An eight-axis health check run on real project artifacts produces an actionable RAG snapshot that tells the PM which domain to address first to unblock the most other domains.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Traditional process-based PM produces compliance metrics while missing value delivery. Domains shift the question from "did we follow the process?" to "are we achieving results in each area?". An eight-axis health check run on real project artifacts (retros, risk registers, sprint logs) produces an actionable RAG snapshot that tells the PM which domain to address first to unblock the most other domains.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Initial project health scan: rapidly identify which of the eight domains is weakest.</item>
        <item>Onboarding a PM or agent into an existing project with a structured eight-axis mental model.</item>
        <item>Quarterly project audit or steering committee preparation.</item>
        <item>Choosing which methodology to load next (each domain points at concrete sub-methodologies).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-sprint feature work — too high-level; use Scrum ceremonies directly.</item>
        <item>Pure waterfall regulated projects with prescribed templates — use PMBOK 6 process groups.</item>
        <item>Personal or solo projects without stakeholders or external delivery commitments.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="eight-domains">
      <p>Each domain represents a distinct outcome area that must be actively managed throughout the project lifecycle.</p>

      <term name="Stakeholder">Managing engagement, expectations, and value perception across all project stakeholders. Outcomes: stakeholder satisfaction, alignment on value definition, managed expectations.</term>

      <term name="Team">Building, developing, and sustaining a high-performing, motivated project team. Outcomes: clear roles and responsibilities, psychological safety, collaborative culture, skill development.</term>

      <term name="Development Approach">Selecting and tailoring the right approach (predictive, adaptive, hybrid) based on project and organizational context. Outcomes: right methodology fit, scalable framework, explicit trade-offs documented.</term>

      <term name="Planning">Establishing and maintaining realistic, actionable plans that guide execution. Outcomes: clear work breakdown, resource allocation, realistic schedule, iterative refinement.</term>

      <term name="Project Work">Directing and managing actual work execution, problem-solving, and coordination. Outcomes: work progresses as planned, problems identified and resolved, team capacity utilized.</term>

      <term name="Delivery">Consistently producing deliverables and value to end users. Outcomes: incremental value realization, quality meets requirements, user adoption, feedback integration.</term>

      <term name="Measurement">Establishing metrics, collecting data, and using evidence to drive decisions. Outcomes: visible progress visibility, evidence-based decisions, continuous improvement.</term>

      <term name="Uncertainty">Identifying, analyzing, and responding to risks and opportunities. Outcomes: risks mitigated, opportunities captured, organizational adaptability, resilience.</term>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assess all 8 domains in a single sitting; partial assessments are misleading.</statement>
        <rationale>Domains are interdependent. Skipping domains creates a false picture and obscures causality across the system.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Anchor each color rating (green/yellow/red) with a quoted artifact (retro line, incident, missed milestone) — no vibes.</statement>
        <rationale>Without evidence, assessments become opinion theater. Every rating must point to data.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Run the assessment on a fixed cadence (monthly) AND on triggers (incident, scope change, leadership change).</statement>
        <rationale>Fixed cadence surfaces slow drift; trigger assessments catch sudden shifts.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="domain-interactions">
      <p>Domains are highly interconnected; strength in one can mask weakness in another, and weakness in one rapidly cascades.</p>

      <term name="Team → Delivery">Strong team culture and psychological safety enable transparent delivery (no hidden scope, honest forecasts). Weak team → deflection of bad news and missed dates.</term>

      <term name="Planning → Project Work">Clear, collaborative planning enables efficient execution. Vague plans → constant re-planning mid-project and context switching.</term>

      <term name="Stakeholder → Measurement">Aligned stakeholders agree on success metrics. Misaligned stakeholders fight over KPIs and goodhart's law (measure the wrong thing).</term>

      <term name="Uncertainty → Planning">Well-managed risk becomes input to plan buffer and iteration strategy. Unmanaged risk → surprises, delay accumulation, compressed schedules.</term>

      <term name="Development Approach → Team">Right approach fit enables team autonomy and mastery. Wrong approach → team grinding, burnout, high attrition.</term>

      <antipattern>
        <description>The 8 domains overlap heavily; teams waste time arguing where an issue "belongs."</description>
        <reason>That is the point. Issues usually cascade across domains. Use domain overlap to reveal root causes.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Domain colors (green/yellow/red) collapse multi-dimensional reality into a bumper sticker.</description>
        <reason>Colors are a snapshot. Pair with evidence quotes and trend arrows (is this domain improving or degrading?). Use sparklines to track direction.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Lacks prescribed cadence — easy to do the assessment once and never repeat.</description>
        <reason>Schedule monthly assessments (the same day each month) AND ad-hoc trigger assessments after major milestones or incidents.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Doesn't say which domain to fix first when several are red.</description>
        <reason>Use domain interaction knowledge to identify the domain that, if improved, unblocks the most others. Often Uncertainty (risks) or Team (morale/engagement).</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="assessment-procedure">
      <p>Structured assessment uncovers the project's health across all eight dimensions and identifies the highest-leverage intervention point.</p>

      <step>Gather evidence. Collect retros, status reports, risk register, sprint logs, incident reports, stakeholder feedback (NPS, comments), team retention metrics, delivery velocity/cycle time.</step>

      <step>Score each domain green (healthy), yellow (at-risk), or red (critical issue). Anchor each score with a quoted artifact or data point.</step>

      <step>Identify the single domain that, if improved, unblocks the most others. Use the domain interaction map above.</step>

      <step>For that domain, list the 3 PMBOK methodologies most likely to shift it from yellow to green, ranked by expected impact and ordered by dependency.</step>

      <step>Publish a one-page assessment with RAG snapshot, evidence per domain, priority actions, and next review date.</step>

      <example type="good" title="Assessment snapshot">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[# Performance Domain Assessment: ProjectX
**Date:** 2026-04-28

| Domain | Health | Key Evidence | Trend |
|--------|--------|--------------|-------|
| Stakeholder | 🟡 | "Still waiting for sign-off on roadmap priorities" (Confluence comment, Apr 26) | ↗ |
| Team | 🟢 | Zero attrition Q1, positive retro feedback, sprint planning runs smoothly | → |
| Dev Approach | 🟢 | Scrum ceremonies well-attended, burndown predictable | → |
| Planning | 🔴 | "Backlog refinement cancelled last 2 weeks, story estimates wildly variable" (retro, Apr 20) | ↘ |
| Project Work | 🟡 | PR review SLA consistently missed (avg 3.2d vs 1d target), 2 critical bugs from incomplete handoff | ↘ |
| Delivery | 🟡 | Value shipped on schedule but 3 bugs escaped QA (p0, p1, p2) | ↘ |
| Measurement | 🟢 | Dashboards updated daily, data-driven standup discussions | → |
| Uncertainty | 🔴 | Risk register hasn't been updated in 6 weeks, 2 unplanned escalations last sprint | ↘ |

**Weakest Domain:** Planning + Uncertainty (tightly coupled). Planning weakness (no refinement) allows unidentified risks to surface as surprises in execution.

**Priority Actions (ranked by leverage)**
1. **[URGENT]** Resume weekly backlog refinement; identify stories at risk due to missing analysis (Planning).
2. Update risk register and run a focused 30-min risk workshop with PO + tech lead (Uncertainty).
3. (Downstream) Adjust PR review SLA or hiring based on Team capacity (Project Work).]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflows">
      <p>Agent-driven domain assessment automates evidence collection, scoring, and action identification with human validation.</p>

      <list>
        <item>faion-pm-agent — drives the 8-domain scan from project artifacts and surfaces the weakest domain.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — converts assessment "priority actions" into SDD tasks with owners and milestones.</item>
        <item>General-purpose Claude subagent — pulls evidence from source docs (retros, status reports, risk registers) into the assessment.</item>
      </list>

      <example type="good" title="Domain assessment prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Read <retros, status reports, risk register>. Score each of the
8 PMBOK 7 performance domains green/yellow/red, with one
evidence quote per domain. Identify the single domain that, if
improved, unblocks the most others — and explain why.]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Methodology recommendation prompt">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[For domain <X>, list the 3 PMBOK methodologies most likely to
shift it from yellow to green, ranked by expected impact and
ordered by dependency (do A before B).]]></code>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents over-rate "Team" and "Stakeholder" green because retros are usually polite — counterweight with attrition / NPS data.</description>
        <reason>Retros capture team sentiment in the moment. Attrition and NPS lag but are more reliable signals.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Don't let a single agent both score AND prescribe actions in one pass; bias compounds. Split into two prompts.</description>
        <reason>Scoring agents are subject to anchoring bias. Separate assessment from recommendations to reduce compounding.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Force evidence-per-cell; without it, the agent produces a beige consensus assessment.</description>
        <reason>Evidence forces specificity. Agents without evidence anchors regress to "everything is yellow."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Watch for stale data: assessments must declare the time window of evidence consulted.</description>
        <reason>A green domain from January may be red now. Explicit time window prevents false positives.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Domain interactions table is high-value; agents tend to forget cross-domain cause/effect — prompt for it explicitly.</description>
        <reason>Agents default to siloed thinking. Explicit interaction prompting (e.g., "how do risks cascade to team morale?") yields better root causes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Assess all 8 domains in a single sitting; partial assessments are misleading.</item>
        <item>Anchor each color rating with a quoted artifact (retro line, incident, missed milestone) — no vibes.</item>
        <item>Run the assessment on a fixed cadence (monthly) AND on triggers (incident, scope change, leadership change).</item>
        <item>Never publish more than 3 priority actions; teams cannot work on more in parallel.</item>
        <item>Track domain health over time as a sparkline — direction matters more than absolute level.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pd-assessment.sh" purpose="Shell script: emits a fresh eight-row assessment skeleton with weakest-domain prompt."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/pmbok-guide/7th-edition"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standard-project-management-2021"/>
      <ref slug="scrum-ceremonies"/>
      <ref slug="kanban-scaled-agile-ceremonies"/>
      <ref slug="jira-workflow-management"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
