<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="code-review-cycle">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>sdd</group>
    <domain>sdd</domain>
    <summary>Human-AI code review pipeline: AI pre-screen, parallel reviewers, unified findings. Reflexion feeds review learnings into pattern and mistake memory.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>code-review</tag>
      <tag>quality-gates</tag>
      <tag>ai-assistance</tag>
      <tag>sdd</tag>
      <tag>reflexion</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Code Review Cycle</title>

    <summary>A structured human-AI collaboration for code review running as a 3-step pipeline: (1) AI pre-screen flags style, anti-patterns, and missing tests; (2) parallel review agents (Claude + cross-model) produce structured BLOCK/WARN/NOTE finding lists; (3) a merge step deduplicates findings and produces a unified report. Humans address BLOCK items; reflexion feeds review findings back into patterns.md and mistakes.md. AI assists but never replaces human judgment on business logic, architecture decisions, and security context.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Over 30% of senior developers now ship mostly AI-generated code, and PRs are 18% larger on average. Change failure rates increase 30% when AI output exceeds human verification capacity. AI pre-screening cleans up style issues before human review, reducing review fatigue. A separate review model catches blind spots the generation model cannot — the model that wrote the code is unreliable for reviewing its own output.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>After any SDD task execution, before marking the task done — run AI pre-screen + human spot-check</item>
        <item>When PRs consistently exceed 300 lines — AI pre-review reduces noise before human review</item>
        <item>Setting up a multi-model review pipeline (write with Claude, review with a separate model)</item>
        <item>Integrating SDD reflexion: post-review findings feed into patterns.md and mistakes.md</item>
        <item>After detecting a spike in change failure rates — add AI review as a quality gate in CI/CD</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Single-file configuration changes — linter is sufficient</item>
        <item>Trivial one-line bug fixes — peer review + merge is faster</item>
        <item>First pass in a new codebase where patterns are not yet established — establish patterns first</item>
        <item>When the human reviewer has deep domain knowledge and AI review produces high false positives</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="review-types">
      <p>Reviews are classified by reviewer and by focus area. AI assistance effectiveness varies significantly by focus area.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Self-review (author): completeness, obvious issues — before PR creation</item>
        <item>AI pre-review (LLM): style, patterns, missing tests, security red flags — on PR creation</item>
        <item>Automated (CI/CD): tests, lint, security scans — on PR creation</item>
        <item>Peer review (team member): logic, design, patterns — after automated checks pass</item>
        <item>Architectural review (senior/lead): system design, consistency — for complex changes</item>
        <item>Security review (security team): vulnerabilities, auth/authz — for sensitive code</item>
      </list>
      <p>AI assistance by focus area:</p>
      <list>
        <item>High AI effectiveness: readability, security pattern matching, style compliance</item>
        <item>Medium AI effectiveness: performance pattern detection, test coverage metrics</item>
        <item>Low AI effectiveness: business logic correctness, architecture decisions, edge cases</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="three-ai-assistance-levels">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use AI pre-screening (Level 1) on every PR before human review; use AI co-review (Level 2) for complex changes; use AI validation (Level 3) after human approval for safety-critical code.</statement>
        <rationale>Level 1 cleans up noise before human review, reducing review fatigue. Level 2 augments humans with explanations and pattern references. Level 3 provides final safety net. All three require human oversight — AI review without human review increases change failure rates 30%.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Level 1 (AI pre-screen): style compliance, common anti-patterns, missing tests, doc gaps, security red flags — runs before human sees the PR</item>
        <item>Level 2 (AI co-reviewer): inline comments during human review — explains complex code, suggests alternatives, highlights similar codebase patterns</item>
        <item>Level 3 (AI validation): post-human-approval — security scans, integration checks, AC verification against design doc</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="multi-model-strategy">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Use a different model for review than the model that generated the code.</statement>
        <rationale>The model that wrote the code has systematic blind spots for its own output. A separate review model catches different failure modes and provides genuine checks-and-balances.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Claude: code explanation, architecture review</item>
        <item>GPT-4: general review, documentation</item>
        <item>Specialized (Semgrep, CodeQL): security scanning</item>
        <item>CodeRabbit: structured PR review with 40+ linters</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-review-limitations">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Treat AI review findings as suggestions for humans to consider, not hard gates.</statement>
        <rationale>AI reviewers miss: business logic (no domain understanding), security implications (flags patterns, misses context), architecture decisions (no system-wide view), edge cases (misses what it has not seen), performance at scale (does not know load patterns).</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="review-pipeline">
      <p>The full review pipeline after task execution:</p>
      <list>
        <item>1. Task completion → self-review (author + AI assist)</item>
        <item>2. PR creation with AI pre-review (Level 1 pass)</item>
        <item>3. Automated CI/CD checks (lint, tests, security scan)</item>
        <item>4. AI co-review pass (CodeRabbit, Copilot, etc.)</item>
        <item>5. Human review (peer/senior) with AI explanations available</item>
        <item>6. Iterations addressing BLOCK findings</item>
        <item>7. Approval + merge</item>
        <item>8. Reflexion learning (update patterns.md and mistakes.md)</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>The review cycle is not complete until patterns.md is updated with learnings from the review.</statement>
        <rationale>Post-merge reflexion is the most frequently skipped step. If skipped, the same issues recur in subsequent tasks because they never enter the project's pattern memory.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="sdd-task-completion-checkpoints">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Every SDD task must pass two explicit quality checkpoints before marking done: self-review and PR review.</statement>
        <rationale>Checkpoints make quality gates explicit and verifiable, preventing the "it works on my machine" failure mode common in AI-assisted development.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Task completion checkpoint checklist">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
task_completion:
  self_review:
    - "All acceptance criteria met"
    - "AI review passed (no critical issues)"
    - "Tests added and passing"
  pr_review:
    - "Design doc alignment verified"
    - "Traceability links correct"
    - "No SDD deviations (or documented)"
        ]]></code>
        <note>These checkpoints are embedded in the task file, not left as implicit expectations.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="reflexion-learning-loop">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>After every PR merge, run a reflexion step: record what review patterns caught issues and what AI missed that humans found.</statement>
        <rationale>Reflexion (Shinn et al., 2023) demonstrates that verbal reinforcement from retained review examples measurably improves agent reliability on subsequent similar code. Skipping reflexion means each task starts with zero learning from prior reviews.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Reflexion learning loop example">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
reflexion:
  patterns_learned:
    - "What review patterns caught issues?"
    - "What did AI miss that humans caught?"
  improvements:
    - "Update AI rules for missed issues?"
    - "Add to self-review checklist?"
        ]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Authors: self-review with AI first before pushing; keep PRs small; mark AI-generated code for extra scrutiny</item>
        <item>Reviewers: review AI suggestions before deep dive; focus on what AI misses (business logic, architecture); do not rubber-stamp AI approvals</item>
        <item>Teams: configure AI to team-specific standards (custom ruff/eslint); track false positive rate quarterly; tune if rate exceeds 20%</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/prompt-review.txt" purpose="Prompts for AI pre-screen, thorough review, spec compliance check, and reflexion learning"/>
    </templates>

  </content>
</methodology>
