<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="SEO Basics Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5+ testable rules every SEO Basics application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-block-admin-paths" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Block admin paths, session ID parameters, and internal APIs; explicitly allow public API paths; add Sitemap directives; never block CSS or JS files.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Blocking CSS/JS prevents Google from rendering pages correctly, causing ranking loss. Unblocked session URLs create infinite crawl loops that waste crawl budget on non-indexable content.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-configure-ai-crawlers" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure AI crawlers (GPTBot, Claude-Web, PerplexityBot) separately from search crawlers — allow public content, disallow premium/paywalled content.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">AI crawlers serve a different purpose than search crawlers: they build training data and citation sources, not indexes. Blocking them entirely sacrifices AI search visibility; blocking only premium content is the balanced approach.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-include-only-indexable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include only indexable pages in the sitemap; update lastmod only when content actually changes; use sitemap index for sites with more than 50,000 URLs.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sitemaps with stale lastmod dates or non-indexable URLs train Google's crawler to distrust the sitemap, reducing crawl frequency for the whole site.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-include-hreflang-alternate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Include hreflang alternate links inside sitemap entries for multilingual sites.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Sitemap hreflang is a fallback for pages where HTML head injection is complex (SPAs, CDN-level rendering). Redundancy in hreflang signals is safe and preferred.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-redirect-http-to" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Redirect HTTP to HTTPS and non-www to www (or vice versa) with 301 permanent redirects; avoid redirect chains longer than one hop.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each redirect hop loses approximately 10-15% of PageRank. Chains of three or more hops can be abandoned by crawlers entirely, causing indexing failures for the destination page.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-use-subdirectory-url" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use subdirectory URL structure (/en/, /uk/) for multilingual sites — not query parameters (?lang=uk).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Query parameter language switching creates duplicate content that Google indexes inconsistently and cannot distinguish by language. Subdirectory structure gives each language version its own crawlable URL that accumulates PageRank independently.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r7-every-hreflang-implementation" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every hreflang implementation must include: self-referencing tag, bidirectional linking, ISO 639-1 language codes, x-default for the fallback page.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Missing self-reference causes Google to ignore the entire hreflang cluster. Missing bidirectional links (A points to B but B doesn't point to A) invalidates the signal. Missing x-default leaves users with no-match locale seeing an arbitrary language version.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r8-never-combine-hreflang" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Never combine hreflang with noindex on the same page.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A noindexed page cannot appear in search results, so its hreflang signals are worthless. Google may also ignore the hreflang signals pointing to noindexed pages, breaking the entire cluster.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r9-title-tags-and" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Title tags and meta descriptions must match the language of the page content — never leave English metadata on a Ukrainian-language page.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Mismatched language in metadata and content signals low quality to Google and creates a poor user experience when the snippet appears in localized search results.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r10-use-exactly-one" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use exactly one H1 per page containing the primary keyword; maintain logical heading hierarchy (H1 → H2 → H3); never skip heading levels.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Search crawlers use heading structure to understand page organization and extract key topics. Screen readers rely on headings for document navigation. Skipped levels confuse both.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r11-use-semantic-elements" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use semantic elements (header, main, footer, article, section, aside, nav) instead of generic divs for all structural containers.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Semantic HTML conveys meaning to crawlers, screen readers, and browsers without requiring ARIA overrides. Divs with ARIA roles are a workaround; semantic elements are the baseline.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r12-always-include-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always include explicit width and height attributes on img elements to prevent CLS; use WebP or AVIF format; lazy-load below-fold images.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Missing width/height causes layout shift as images load (CLS score degradation). WebP/AVIF are 25-35% smaller than JPEG/PNG at equivalent quality, improving LCP. Lazy loading defers non-critical image loading to reduce initial page weight.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r13-all-three-core" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All three Core Web Vitals must reach the "Good" threshold: LCP &lt;= 2.5s, INP &lt;= 200ms, CLS &lt;= 0.1.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Pages with all three metrics in "Good" range receive a page experience ranking boost. A single metric in "Poor" range cancels the boost. Monitor in Google Search Console, not just Lighthouse — lab data and field data diverge significantly.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-28 chunk-02 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
