<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-schedule-process" title="Schedule Development — Five-Step Process">
  <summary>How to build a project schedule: define activities from WBS, sequence with dependency types, estimate with PERT, identify the critical path with CPM, and add explicit CCPM-style buffers.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Activities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Convert each WBS work package into one or more specific activities. Activities are verb-led (unlike WBS packages which are noun-led) and describe the work, not the deliverable.</statement>
      <rationale>WBS packages answer "what"; activities answer "how and by whom". Keeping the two separate preserves the scope baseline while enabling scheduling flexibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Sequence Activities — Dependency Types">
    <list>
      <item>FS (Finish-to-Start): Activity B cannot start until A finishes. Most common.</item>
      <item>FF (Finish-to-Finish): B finishes at the same time as A (e.g., documentation finishes with development).</item>
      <item>SS (Start-to-Start): B starts when A starts (e.g., testing starts when dev starts on first unit).</item>
      <item>SF (Start-to-Finish): Rare — B cannot finish until A starts (e.g., night shift covers until day shift begins).</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Distinguish hard dependencies (technical, contractual) from soft dependencies (resource preference); soft dependencies can be broken if the schedule demands it.</statement>
      <rationale>Treating soft dependencies as hard creates false critical paths and hides schedule optimization opportunities.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Estimate Durations">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use three-point estimation (PERT) for any activity over 5 days: Duration = (O + 4M + P) / 6. Never use single-point estimates for complex or novel work.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-point estimates inherit the "optimistic by 30%" human bias. Three-point forcing requires a pessimistic scenario, which surfaces schedule risk early rather than at delivery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>O = 3 days, M = 5 days, P = 10 days → PERT = (3 + 20 + 10) / 6 = 5.5 days. The pessimistic estimate forces the team to articulate the "what if it goes wrong" scenario.</note>
    </example>
    <p>Analogous estimation: use similar past tasks as reference. Parametric estimation: use metrics (e.g., 1 API endpoint = 4 hours, 10 endpoints = 40 hours).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Identify Critical Path">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run CPM (forward and backward pass) to find activities with zero float; any delay on a critical activity delays the project by the same amount. Focus management attention here.</statement>
      <rationale>Without critical path analysis, teams give equal attention to all tasks. Delays on non-critical tasks are invisible until they cascade onto the critical path — by then, recovery costs multiply.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Flag activities with float less than 2 days as "near-critical"; these become the next critical path when the primary critical activity slips.</statement>
      <rationale>Critical path analysis is a point-in-time snapshot. Near-critical activities are the most likely successors to become critical when any small variance occurs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/cpm.py">CPM script: forward/backward pass, float, critical path from YAML activity list.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Add Explicit Buffers">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add a named project buffer at the end of the critical path (typically 15–25% of CP duration) and feeding buffers where non-critical paths join the critical path. Never embed buffers inside individual task estimates.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden individual buffers are invisible to the PM and cannot be managed. Named CCPM buffers make schedule risk explicit and allow the PM to release buffer intentionally rather than discover it was consumed silently.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/activity-list.md">Activity list table template for defining and tracking schedule activities.</reference>
</text>
