<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples-antipatterns" title="Schedule Development — Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Worked MVP schedule example and solopreneur time-allocation pattern, plus the five most common scheduling antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="Examples">
    <example type="good">
      <note>MVP schedule (9 weeks): Discovery 2w (no buffer), Design 2w + 2d feeding buffer, Sprint 1 2w, Sprint 2 2w, Testing 1w + 3d feeding buffer, Launch 3d + 2d project buffer. Named buffers are separate line items; they total 1 week and are managed as a pool, not as per-task slack.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Solopreneur schedule allocation: Morning (3h) = deep work on critical-path tasks. Afternoon (2h) = non-critical support tasks. Evening (1h) = admin held as personal buffer. Mon-Wed = Project A (critical). Thu-Fri = Project B (secondary). The critical path receives focused, uninterrupted time; non-critical runs on interruption-safe afternoon slots.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>No dependencies defined — every task appears to run in parallel on the plan.</description>
      <reason>Parallel-looking schedules hide sequential constraints. When a dependency causes a delay, the team learns about it at the dependency boundary, not during planning when it could have been mitigated.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Optimistic single-point estimates — every task is the best-case duration.</description>
      <reason>Projects almost never run at best-case. A schedule built on optimistic estimates has no slack for real-world variance, so the first delay propagates immediately to the end date.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring the critical path — treating all tasks as equally important.</description>
      <reason>Equal management attention on all tasks means critical tasks get insufficient focus. The project finishes late on the path that received the least attention.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No buffers — the schedule shows tasks back-to-back with zero slack.</description>
      <reason>A single delay anywhere on the critical path breaks the end date with no recovery option. The PM must re-negotiate scope or dates under pressure, in public, in crisis mode.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Resource conflicts — the same person is scheduled on parallel tasks simultaneously.</description>
      <reason>Theoretical parallel execution that ignores per-resource capacity produces a plan that is physically impossible. Resource leveling must be applied before baseline commitment.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
