<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-community-building">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>smm-manager</domain>
    <summary>A step-by-step playbook for building a product or professional community with lasting engagement via the SEED-NURTURE-SCALE-MONETIZE model with core rituals and health metrics.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>community</tag>
      <tag>engagement</tag>
      <tag>discord</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>retention</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>growth</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Community Building</title>

    <summary>A step-by-step playbook for building a product or professional community with lasting engagement. The four-stage model is: Seed (50 hand-picked members) → Nurture (rituals: daily standup, weekly office hours, monthly AMA) → Scale (member-to-member connections via pairing, breakout groups) → Monetize (community as product feature). Core rule: one platform, pre-seeded with 5-10 planted conversations before the first invitation wave.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Communities create acquisition moats: they generate organic content, handle peer support, and become the best sales force. Without rituals, communities become ghost towns — members visit once, find nothing happening, and never return. The DAU/MAU ratio is the leading health indicator: below 20% signals ritual failure. Most community failures stem from launching empty or opening too many spaces before existing ones are active.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Drafting launch materials: welcome messages, guidelines, onboarding sequences, ritual prompts.</item>
        <item>Generating invitation scripts tailored to specific member profiles.</item>
        <item>Producing weekly ritual content (standups, AMA question lists, challenge briefs, roundup newsletters).</item>
        <item>Analyzing community health metrics from platform exports to identify churn risk.</item>
        <item>Writing community guidelines and moderation playbooks.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Real-time community moderation — requires human judgment on nuance, context, and tone.</item>
        <item>Automated mass-invitation campaigns — platforms detect and ban bots; personal invitations require human send.</item>
        <item>Communities with fewer than 10 seeded members — agent-generated content in an empty community reads hollow.</item>
        <item>Replacing the community manager role entirely — member trust is built through perceived human presence.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="four-stage-framework">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Progress through stages in order — do not open invitations until the SEED stage has 5-10 planted conversations and 50 hand-picked members confirmed.</statement>
        <rationale>Launching empty is the single most common community failure. Visitors who arrive and see no activity leave immediately and never return. The first impression cannot be undone.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>SEED: invite 50 hand-picked members, plant 5-10 conversations before anyone else arrives.</item>
        <item>NURTURE: establish daily, weekly, and monthly rituals; personal welcome within 48 hours of each new join.</item>
        <item>SCALE: enable member-to-member connections via pairing, breakout groups, collaboration board.</item>
        <item>MONETIZE: community access becomes a product feature or paid tier.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="platform-selection">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Pick exactly one platform and build depth there before considering others — multi-platform splits both member attention and your management capacity.</statement>
        <rationale>Each platform requires a different engagement style and moderation approach. Running two platforms at 50% capacity produces two ghost towns instead of one thriving community.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Discord: real-time, rich features; best for tech, gaming, crypto; noisy, hard to search.</item>
        <item>Slack: familiar, searchable; best for B2B professional communities; expensive at scale.</item>
        <item>Circle: structured, monetizable; best for courses and memberships; less sticky.</item>
        <item>Reddit: SEO and organic growth; less control over experience.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="community-value-pillars">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Define the community's value proposition across all three pillars (Access, Connection, Content) before writing the first invitation — members join for one pillar and stay for another.</statement>
        <rationale>Communities that offer only one pillar churn when the founding hook loses novelty. The Access pillar (founder availability) is highest at launch but cannot scale; Connection and Content pillars must be established before Access fades.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Access: to you, experts, or exclusive information not available elsewhere.</item>
        <item>Connection: to peers with similar goals, industry, or stage.</item>
        <item>Content: educational, entertaining, or actionable material on a consistent schedule.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="seeding-first-members">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Hand-pick the first 50 members from existing engaged contacts — email subscribers, early users, engaged commenters — not the general public.</statement>
        <rationale>Quality of the founding cohort determines the culture and conversation norms for the entire community. Strangers with no prior engagement produce transactional interactions; engaged contacts produce genuine dialogue.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Invitation script for the founding cohort">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Hey [Name],

I'm building a small community of [description].

I loved your [recent post/project/comment] about [topic].

Would you like early access? We're keeping it small
(~50 people) to maintain quality conversations.

[Link]
]]></code>
        <note>Personalized script targeting engaged existing contacts.</note>
      </example>
      <reference path="templates/launch-checklist.md">Pre-launch / Launch Week / First Month checklist</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="ritual-cadence">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Establish at least one daily ritual, one weekly ritual, and one monthly ritual — vary wording each week even if the structure repeats to prevent ritual fatigue.</statement>
        <rationale>Rituals create the habit of checking the community. A member who skips two rituals in a row is unlikely to return; daily rituals make the community part of the daily workflow before the habit window closes.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Make rituals low-friction: a "what are you working on today?" standup beats a weekly essay prompt for participation rate by 5-10x.</statement>
        <rationale>High-friction rituals punish busy members and create participation guilt. Low-friction rituals include everyone, including lurkers who would otherwise disengage.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Daily: morning standup thread (what are you working on?), win/loss sharing.</item>
        <item>Weekly: office hours with you, member spotlight, weekly roundup newsletter.</item>
        <item>Monthly: guest AMA, challenge or hackathon, retrospective thread.</item>
      </list>
      <reference path="templates/community-guidelines.md">Community guidelines template with purpose, values, and moderation policy.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="member-connection-mechanisms">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Trigger a personal welcome within 48 hours of every new member joining — the first 48 hours are the highest-churn window.</statement>
        <rationale>New members who receive no personal contact in the first 48 hours have a 60-70% probability of never posting. A personal welcome converts lurkers into participants at the moment of highest receptivity.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Intro threads: new members introduce themselves with a structured prompt.</item>
        <item>Pairing: match members with similar goals for 1:1 conversations.</item>
        <item>Breakout groups: cohorts of 5-10 people around shared interests or stages.</item>
        <item>Collaboration board: members post help-wanted and help-offered items.</item>
      </list>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Do not open new channels or spaces until existing ones are consistently active — empty spaces signal low community health to every new visitor.</statement>
        <rationale>New members calibrate community quality by scanning visible activity. Five active channels look healthier than fifteen half-empty ones.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="health-metrics">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Track DAU/MAU (target 20%, great 40%+) and post rate (target 10% of members posting monthly, great 25%+) as the primary health signals — total member count is a vanity metric.</statement>
        <rationale>A community of 500 with 40% DAU/MAU is healthier and more monetizable than a community of 5,000 with 5% DAU/MAU. Growth strategy should optimize for ratio, not absolute count.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>DAU/MAU: good 20%, great 40%+.</item>
        <item>Post rate: good 10% of members, great 25%+.</item>
        <item>Average response time to posts: good &lt;4 hours, great &lt;1 hour.</item>
        <item>30-day retention: good 70%, great 85%+.</item>
        <item>NPS: good 30, great 50+.</item>
      </list>
      <reference path="templates/health-scorer.py">Python health scorer from Discord/Circle activity exports.</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Over-moderating: removing posts aggressively or requiring approval before posts are visible.</description>
        <reason>Heavy moderation kills spontaneity and signals distrust. Members self-censor when they feel monitored. Light touch moderation with clear guidelines produces better outcomes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Only the founder posting — treating the community as a broadcast channel.</description>
        <reason>If members can only receive content rather than contribute it, the community is a newsletter. Communities require member-generated content to produce the connection value that justifies membership.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Growing headcount faster than community health metrics support.</description>
        <reason>Rapid growth in a community with low DAU/MAU dilutes conversation quality and makes new members feel like they joined after the good times. Quality of engagement must precede scale of membership.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Seed the community with 5-10 planted conversations before inviting the first wave — an empty platform kills momentum before it starts.</item>
        <item>Rituals must be low-friction: a "what are you working on today?" standup beats a weekly essay prompt for participation rate.</item>
        <item>The first 48 hours after a new member joins are the highest-churn window — trigger a personal welcome within that window.</item>
        <item>Identify and invest in 3-5 ambassadors early; they create a self-sustaining culture before the founder steps back.</item>
        <item>Do not open new channels/spaces until existing ones are active — too many empty spaces signal low community health.</item>
        <item>Track reply rate per post, not just post count; a community where 30% of posts get zero replies is dying.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Platform rate limits: Discord bot API and Circle API have per-minute call limits; batch analytics pulls must be throttled.</item>
        <item>Privacy in analysis: Member activity data often contains email addresses and real names — scrub before feeding into external LLM calls.</item>
        <item>Ritual fatigue: Agent-generated ritual templates repeated verbatim week after week feel mechanical; vary wording and theme even if the structure repeats.</item>
        <item>Moderation edge cases: Agent moderation policy documents will not cover every real scenario; the first novel moderation call must be made by a human and then documented as precedent.</item>
        <item>Platform churn: Threads-linked communities (Threads/Instagram) have different feature sets than established platforms; agent advice based on Discord/Slack may not translate.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/community-guidelines.md" purpose="Guidelines template: Purpose / Values / Rules / Encouragements / Moderation policy."/>
      <template path="templates/launch-checklist.md" purpose="Pre-launch / Launch Week / First Month checklist."/>
      <template path="templates/health-scorer.py" purpose="Score community health from Discord/Circle export (DAU/MAU, post rate, churn risk)."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://communityroundtable.com/resources/"/>
      <link href="https://cmxhub.com/"/>
      <link href="https://orbit.love/blog"/>
      <link href="https://review.firstround.com/build-a-community-not-an-audience"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
