<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Customer Success Metrics and Health Scoring Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `ops-customer-success-metrics` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-weighted-health-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Compute a per-account health score that combines at least four dimensions: usage frequency, feature adoption breadth, support sentiment, and billing status. Single-dimension scores (usage only) are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer success operations practice (Gainsight / ChurnZero playbooks)">Single-dimension health scores miss the leading indicators (sentiment drop, billing failure, declining feature adoption) that precede churn. Multi-dimensional scoring matches the multi-causal nature of churn.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-cohort-retention-curves" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Track retention as cohort curves by signup month (or onboarding cohort), not as a single aggregated rate. Aggregated churn rate hides cohort-level decay.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaS metrics canon (David Skok, Jason Lemkin)">Aggregated churn rate mixes mature and immature cohorts, hiding both improvements and degradations. Cohort curves expose where retention actually changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-leading-indicator-alerts" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Configure alerts that fire BEFORE churn — usage drop &gt; 25% week-over-week, ≥3 support tickets in 7 days, billing failure. Alert on lagging indicators only (churn already happened) is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer success operations practice">Lagging-indicator alerts arrive after the save window has closed. Leading indicators give CSMs a chance to intervene.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-nps-csat-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run NPS / CSAT surveys on a fixed cadence (quarterly NPS, post-interaction CSAT) and tie response scores back to the health-score model. Ad-hoc surveys without integration into the score are research-theatre.</statement>
      <rationale source="Voice-of-customer practice (Fred Reichheld, Net Promoter)">Surveys disconnected from the operating health score produce vanity numbers that no one acts on. Tying them to the score forces consequence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-nrr-grr-reporting" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report Net Revenue Retention (NRR) and Gross Revenue Retention (GRR) monthly. Expansion ARR is reported separately from retention so the two motions are not conflated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Subscription-economy reporting standards (KeyBanc / OpenView benchmarks)">Conflating expansion and retention hides whether the business is retaining customers vs growing share-of-wallet on a shrinking base.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
