<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-health-score" title="Customer Health Score">
  <summary>Weighted 0–100 health score construction from five data sources, bucket thresholds, and alert automation logic.</summary>

  <section title="Health Score Components">
    <rule>
      <statement>Construct the health score from five weighted components: product usage frequency (30%), feature adoption breadth (25%), support sentiment (20%), email/activity engagement (15%), payment health (10%). Weight product usage highest — it is the strongest leading indicator of churn.</statement>
      <rationale>Usage frequency is the most reliable early-warning signal: a customer who stops logging in is 3–5x more likely to churn in the next 90 days than an active user with a support complaint. Payment problems lag churn intent and are a lagging indicator in most SaaS contexts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Scoring rubric: Usage (0–30): daily active=30, weekly=20, monthly=10, inactive=0. Feature adoption (0–25): min(features_adopted / total_core_features, 1.0) x 25. Support sentiment (0–20): positive=20, neutral=15, negative=5, escalated=0. Engagement (0–15): high=15, medium=10, low=5, none=0. Payment (0–10): current=10, minor_issue=7, overdue=3, failed=0.</p>
    <reference path="templates/health.py">Health score function and bucket classifier (Python)</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Health Buckets and Actions">
    <p>Health bucket thresholds and default actions: 80–100 (Healthy) → maintain relationship, watch for expansion signals; 60–79 (Stable) → monitor monthly, proactive engagement at 65-day mark; 40–59 (At-risk) → CSM outreach within 48 hours, root-cause investigation; 0–39 (Critical) → urgent outreach within 24 hours, daily monitoring, escalate to product/exec.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Rebuild health score thresholds quarterly. Thresholds calibrated to the current product state become miscalibrated after major feature launches or pricing changes. Validate by back-testing against churned accounts: if fewer than 70% of churned accounts were flagged "at-risk" at T-90 days, recalibrate.</statement>
      <rationale>Static thresholds reward past patterns, not present risk. A feature heavily adopted at launch becomes "new default" later; scoring it as advanced-adoption artificially inflates scores for all accounts.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Alert Automation">
    <p>Automated alert triggers: health drops below 60 → alert CSM, add to weekly review; health drops below 40 → urgent alert, immediate outreach required, daily monitoring; health rises above 80 for previously-stable account → expansion opportunity alert, schedule QBR or upgrade call.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every alert threshold with an owned playbook — a specific next action assigned to a named person. An alert system with no owned next-step is theater that erodes trust in the metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>Alert fatigue kills health-score programs. If CSMs see alerts they cannot act on, they stop treating the alert as meaningful signal. Each bucket must map to a concrete 24–48 hour action.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
