<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-key-metrics" title="Key Customer Success Metrics">
  <summary>NPS, CSAT, time-to-value, feature adoption, expansion rate, and Net Revenue Retention definitions with formulas and reliability caveats.</summary>

  <section title="Core Metrics">
    <p>NPS formula: % Promoters (9–10) minus % Detractors (0–6). Target: above 50. Reliability note: NPS requires 50+ responses for a margin of error below ±15 points; do not react to quarterly deltas of 3–5 points at small N.</p>
    <p>CSAT formula: (count of 4–5 ratings) / (total responses). Target: above 4.5/5 average. Survey at moments of value-delivery (post-onboarding, after first success, after resolved support ticket), not on calendar cadence. Survey fatigue from always-on CSAT kills both NPS and CSAT response rates.</p>
    <p>Time to Value (TTV): days from signup to first success metric (first key action completed for SaaS tools, first module for courses, first deliverable for services). Target: below 7 days. Track by cohort — TTV improvement is the clearest signal of onboarding improvement.</p>
    <p>Feature adoption: percentage of customers using each core feature. Two tiers: core feature adoption (critical for retention baseline) and advanced feature adoption (expansion signal). Track both breadth (% using at all) and depth (% using weekly).</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Revenue Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track Net Revenue Retention (NRR) as the primary CS program health metric: NRR = (Starting MRR + Expansion MRR - Churn MRR - Contraction MRR) / Starting MRR. Target above 100% (expansion offsets churn). Track NRR by cohort, not in aggregate.</statement>
      <rationale>Aggregate NRR above 100% can hide a retention problem inside fast new-logo growth. Cohort-level NRR exposes whether the product is retaining and expanding customers from specific acquisition periods, revealing lifecycle patterns that aggregate numbers obscure.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Expansion rate target: more than 20% of customers should expand (upgrade, add seats, add-on) within 12 months of signup. Below 20% signals either poor value delivery, incorrect tier structure, or absence of expansion triggers.</statement>
      <rationale>Expansion rate below 20% means the pricing structure captures less value than delivered. It also means new-logo revenue must fully offset churn with no expansion buffer.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Leading vs. Lagging Indicators">
    <rule>
      <statement>Focus CS operations on leading indicators (declining usage, support escalations, feature abandonment, payment issues) rather than lagging indicators (cancellation, downgrade). Lagging indicators are too late for meaningful intervention in most SaaS products.</statement>
      <rationale>By the time a customer submits a cancellation request, the decision was typically made 30–90 days earlier. Leading indicators provide the window for intervention. Lagging indicators provide post-mortems.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
