<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-automation-and-gotchas" title="Monthly Review Process and AI-Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Monthly CS review process, data collection setup, and agent-specific limitations for customer success metrics workflows.</summary>

  <section title="Monthly Review Process">
    <p>Monthly CS review steps: (1) review health distribution trends month-over-month, (2) identify cohort patterns (are specific signup cohorts churning faster?), (3) analyze at-risk segment root causes, (4) review expansion opportunity list from healthy accounts, (5) update playbooks based on learnings, (6) share insights with product and leadership.</p>
    <reference path="templates/health-dashboard.md">Monthly health distribution dashboard template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/metric-tracking.md">Monthly metrics tracking table: NPS, CSAT, TTV, adoption, expansion, NRR vs. targets</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Data Collection Setup">
    <p>Data source requirements by component: usage frequency (analytics platform event tracking — Mixpanel, Amplitude, Heap), feature adoption (analytics or feature-flag system), support sentiment (helpdesk ticket analysis — Zendesk, Intercom), engagement (email platform open/click data, CRM activity), payment health (billing platform — Stripe, Chargebee).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Fix telemetry before building a health score. Missing or malformed events produce scores that are meaningless and, worse, misleadingly confident. Spend the first iteration cycle validating event completeness against a sample of 20 accounts.</statement>
      <rationale>A health score built on incomplete data produces random alert patterns. CSMs will notice immediately when the score does not match their direct experience, and trust in the system collapses — harder to rebuild than to avoid.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="AI-Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLMs over-credit qualitative sentiment ("user said they love it") and discount quantitative usage decay.</description>
      <reason>Weight quantitative facts explicitly in every health-score prompt. One positive support ticket does not offset 30 days of declining login frequency.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent sends personalized customer-facing emails autonomously without human approval.</description>
      <reason>One mis-personalized "we noticed you stopped using X" to a power user who never stopped can permanently damage trust. Human approval is required for any CS outreach regardless of scoring confidence.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent produces a single NPS sentiment verdict per ticket rather than a per-message score chain.</description>
      <reason>Single-verdict sentiment is uncalibratable. Require per-message 1–5 scores with the underlying text, so calibration drift can be detected and corrected.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Health scores trained on currently-active customers underweight signals that drive early cohort churn.</description>
      <reason>Survivor bias: active accounts that made it to month 12 have systematically different feature-usage patterns than accounts that churned in month 2. Validate scores using churned accounts from T-90 days.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Passing full event histories into LLM context for health analysis.</description>
      <reason>Token cost and context contamination. Pre-aggregate events to weekly usage buckets before any LLM call. Health scoring on raw event streams is an agent-economics anti-pattern.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
