<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ops-customer-success-metrics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ops-customer-success-metrics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Computing health score on a per-CSM basis without a canonical formula, leading to score inflation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Inconsistent scoring breaks early warning systems. Formulaic scoring enables cross-team calibration and prevents subjective grade inflation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Running continuous always-on NPS surveys, polling every customer weekly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Continuous NPS creates survey fatigue; response rate collapses after 2-3 weeks. Quarterly cadence is the sweet spot: frequent enough to catch trends, sparse enough that customers don't tune out.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Only responding to customers who reach out via support; ignoring usage drops and silent warning signs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Reactive CS misses 60% of at-risk accounts that decline silently without contacting support. Proactive monitoring surfaces issues 30-60 days before churn, when interventions are still possible.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating expansion as a product or sales function; CS team is measured only on retention/churn, not revenue growth.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>CS teams closest to customers have the best visibility into expansion needs. When CS is excluded from expansion revenue tracking, they optimize for retention alone and miss revenue opportunities.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
