<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Ads Analytics Setup Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every application of Ads Analytics Setup MUST enforce. Rationale + source per rule. Rules referenced by id from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="event-spec-before-code" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Event specification (name, params, trigger, owner) MUST be written before any tracking code. Code-first implementations are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Analytics event-spec docs">Code-first events accumulate inconsistency; spec-first events stay coherent over years.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="consent-mode-v2-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Consent Mode v2 MUST be implemented from day one (not retrofitted). Without it, GDPR audit exposure is unbounded.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Consent Mode v2 docs + GDPR practice">Retrofit Consent Mode breaks historical data + invites compliance fines; from-day-one keeps both clean.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ga4-bq-link-day-one" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>GA4 → BigQuery export MUST be linked on day one of property creation. Late-link loses raw events permanently.</statement>
      <rationale source="GA4 / BigQuery docs">GA4 stores raw events only after BQ link; pre-link events are aggregated-only forever.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="utm-naming-standard" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>UTM naming MUST follow a documented convention (source/medium/campaign/term/content); free-form UTMs are rejected at tagging.</statement>
      <rationale source="GA4 / UTM convention practice">Free-form UTMs (case / typo / synonym variants) destroy attribution within 2 quarters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="verification-before-go-live" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>All events MUST be verified in DebugView before go-live. Un-verified events go to production silently broken.</statement>
      <rationale source="GA4 DebugView documentation">Silent broken events corrupt 30-60 days of data before discovery.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability preconditions are unmet (see AGENTS.md Skip If), the methodology MUST be skipped and a one-line skip-reason logged.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree convention">A named skip terminal keeps decision-tree leaves resolvable and prevents silent misuse on misfit inputs.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
