<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Immersive Design Principles Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the Immersive Design Principles methodology. Each pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale; HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="comfort-defaults" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Default comfort settings: snap turning enabled, vignette on, smooth-locomotion off-by-default. Smooth modes require opt-in.</statement>
      <rationale source="Oculus Comfort Guidelines">Default smooth-locomotion is the leading driver of new-user nausea.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="safe-locomotion-choice" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Experiences MUST offer at least two locomotion options including teleport (or arm-swing) AS THE DEFAULT. Smooth-only locomotion is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft MR comfort guidelines + IAAP XR">Locomotion preference is highly individual; forced choice excludes users.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="sensory-budget-per-minute" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Audio peak limited to -3 dBFS; visual flashing limited per WCAG SC 2.3.1 (≤3/s, no ≥25% of viewport); haptic events ≤6/min unless user-extended.</statement>
      <rationale source="WCAG SC 2.3.1 + Apple Vision sensory guidelines">Photosensitive epilepsy + sensory-overload exclusion.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="explicit-agency" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Forced gaze direction OR forced action without affordance is forbidden. Every required user action carries a discoverable trigger.</statement>
      <rationale source="WebXR Accessibility CG">Forced action models exclude users with motor / cognitive differences.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="retreat-option-always" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A retreat-to-safe-scene (return-home / take-a-break) shortcut MUST be persistently available and reachable within 2 inputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="IAAP XR Accessibility User Requirements">Users with anxiety / sensory overload need exit as a right.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in AGENTS.md "Applies If" do not all hold, OR any "Skip If" disqualifier is true, do not run this methodology — route to the named alternative.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Methodologies are pre-condition gated; running them out-of-scope produces noise and burns the agent's context budget.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold, execute the procedure in `content/04-procedure.xml` (or the rule set above when complexity is light), emit the artefact specified by `content/02-output-contract.xml`, and validate with `scripts/validate-immersive-design-principles.py` before returning.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology DoD (F-066)">Tying the entry rule to the validator script closes the loop between policy and machine check.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
