<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-workflow-rules" title="Research Workflow Rules">
  <summary>Sequential execution mandate, source citation requirement, loop guard, state persistence, and orchestration gotchas.</summary>

  <section title="Sequential Execution">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run research agents one by one, not in parallel. Each agent must complete and write its output file before the next agent starts. The orchestrator must Read the output file and verify non-empty before advancing.</statement>
      <rationale>Parallel execution in Deep mode (8-12 searches per module) hits rate limits and generates cross-module contradictions. Sequential execution prevents both. Agents lie about completion — only a non-empty file confirms the step is done.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Cap searches per module at the declared budget: 3-5 for Quick mode, 8-12 for Deep mode. Track the count in the orchestrator, not in the subagent — subagents undercount their own usage.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a hard cap, Deep mode in WebSearch-only environments exhausts context before synthesis. The orchestrator tracks because subagents do not reliably self-limit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Source Citation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every claim must have a source URL. If data is not found, write "Data not available" — do not infer, estimate, or synthesize a plausible answer.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs fabricate market sizes, statistics, and competitor features confidently. The "Data not available" policy is the only mechanical check that prevents hallucination from entering the research artifacts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Reject any source older than 24 months for pricing, market data, or competitor features without an explicit override.</statement>
      <rationale>Web search returns 2-3-year-old blog posts as if current. Stale data for pricing or market size misleads go/no-go decisions. Date-based rejection is the filter; human override is the exception.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Loop Guard">
    <rule>
      <statement>Wrap every loop-back step with max_iterations=3 (idea rejection, name rejection). If the user rejects twice, escalate to a different prompt or framework rather than re-rolling the same generator.</statement>
      <rationale>The workflows have loop-back steps with no exit condition. Without a guard, the orchestrator can loop indefinitely when user keeps rejecting. Three iterations is the practical limit before the approach needs to change.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="State Persistence">
    <rule>
      <statement>Write workflow state to .aidocs/product_docs/_workflow-state.json after every module completion. On resume, read the state file and skip completed modules.</statement>
      <rationale>Deep mode research runs involve 30-60 tool calls. Session crashes mid-run waste all prior API spend. State persistence enables resume without re-running completed modules.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Claude Code eagerly batches tool calls in parallel even when sequential execution is instructed.</description>
      <reason>Enforce sequential by chaining Task calls in a single orchestrator turn and awaiting each. Parallel batching violates the rate-limit protection and cross-contamination prevention that sequential execution provides.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>AskUserQuestion is ignored in headless or cron contexts, stalling the workflow.</description>
      <reason>Idea Discovery and Naming workflows assume an interactive user. Automated pipelines (n8n, cron) require a non-interactive mode that picks pre-configured defaults without user prompts.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
