<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-workflow-specs" title="Research Workflow Specifications">
  <summary>Step-by-step specifications for Idea Discovery, Product Research, and Project Naming workflows.</summary>

  <section title="Workflow: Idea Discovery">
    <p>Sequential workflow for generating and validating startup or product ideas. Output: idea-validation.md.</p>

    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Gather context: skills, interests, resources (AskUserQuestion)</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Generate 5-10 ideas using 7 Ps framework and other methods (mode: ideas)</item>
      <item>Step 3 — User selects 3-5 ideas to research (AskUserQuestion, multiSelect)</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Pain point research: Reddit, forums, reviews mining (mode: pains)</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Niche evaluation: market size, competition, barriers (mode: niche)</item>
      <item>Step 6 — User selects idea or loops back to Step 2 (max 3 iterations)</item>
      <item>Output — Write to .aidocs/product_docs/idea-validation.md</item>
    </list>

    <rule>
      <statement>Context questions must cover three dimensions: skills/experience, motivation (solve own problem / market opportunity / passion / side income), and available time investment.</statement>
      <rationale>Ideas generated without this context are generic and unlikely to match the founder's actual constraints, leading to selection of ideas they cannot execute.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow: Product Research">
    <p>Comprehensive research workflow for existing product concepts. Output: executive-summary.md plus per-module files.</p>

    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Parse project from ARGUMENTS</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Read: constitution.md, roadmap.md</item>
      <item>Step 3 — Ask user for modules and mode (quick/deep)</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Run selected research agents sequentially (not parallel)</item>
      <item>Step 5 — Write executive-summary.md with TL;DR, top-3 risks, top-3 opportunities, recommended next step</item>
    </list>

    <section title="Module Options">
      <list>
        <item>Market Research — TAM/SAM/SOM, trends → market-research.md</item>
        <item>Competitors — features, pricing, positioning → competitive-analysis.md</item>
        <item>Personas — pain points, JTBD → user-personas.md</item>
        <item>Validation — problem evidence → problem-validation.md</item>
        <item>Pricing — benchmarks → pricing-research.md</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <rule>
      <statement>Run faion-marketing-manager before faion-sdd when go-to-market unknowns dominate; run faion-sdd first when feasibility is the larger risk. Do not treat them as parallel options.</statement>
      <rationale>The two downstream consumers have different inputs. Marketing-manager needs market data; sdd needs technical feasibility. The order determines which blockers get resolved first.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Workflow: Project Naming">
    <p>Generate and validate project or product names with domain availability. Output: update to constitution.md.</p>

    <list>
      <item>Step 1 — Gather concept: description, tone (Professional/Playful/Technical/Premium)</item>
      <item>Step 2 — Generate 20 candidates using naming strategies (mode: names)</item>
      <item>Step 3 — User selects favorites or requests more (AskUserQuestion, multiSelect)</item>
      <item>Step 4 — Filter to 5 with cheap whois/HEAD checks, then run faion-domain-checker-agent on top 5 only</item>
      <item>Step 5 — User selects final name or loops back to Step 2 (max 3 iterations)</item>
      <item>Output — Update constitution.md with selected name</item>
    </list>

    <rule>
      <statement>Run cheap availability checks (whois, HTTP HEAD) on all 20 candidates first; call faion-domain-checker-agent only on the top 5. Do not run the full domain checker on all 20.</statement>
      <rationale>Running the full domain checker (Namecheap API, registrar calls) on 20 candidates burns quota. Two-pass filtering reduces API spend by 75% with negligible accuracy loss.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <section title="Naming Strategies">
      <list>
        <item>Descriptive — what it does (DropBox)</item>
        <item>Invented — made-up word (Spotify)</item>
        <item>Compound — two words joined (Facebook)</item>
        <item>Metaphor — symbolic meaning (Amazon)</item>
        <item>Portmanteau — blended words (Pinterest)</item>
        <item>Alliteration — same sound (PayPal)</item>
        <item>Acronym — letter combination (IBM)</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <reference path="scripts/check-names.sh">Bash script for batch domain and handle availability checks</reference>
  </section>
</text>
