<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="OKR Structure and Scoring">
  <summary>OKR anatomy, characteristics of good Objectives and Key Results, and the scoring scale.</summary>

  <section title="What OKRs Are">
    <p>OKRs combine a qualitative, inspiring Objective with 3–5 quantitative Key Results that prove the Objective was reached. The Objective answers "what we want to achieve"; the Key Results answer "how we will know we achieved it".</p>

    <rule>
      <statement>Limit to 3–5 Objectives per period, each with 3–5 Key Results. Exceeding this produces a priority list, not a focus mechanism.</statement>
      <rationale>OKRs work through focus. More than 5 Objectives means everything is equally important, which means nothing is actually prioritised.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Objective Characteristics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Objectives must be inspiring, qualitative, time-bound, ambitious, and memorable. If the Objective contains a number, it is a Key Result, not an Objective.</statement>
      <rationale>Numbers belong in Key Results. An Objective with a number ("increase signups by 20%") conflates aspiration with measurement and removes room for strategic flexibility.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Good Objective: "Delight our early adopters" — inspiring, qualitative, clear period</item>
      <item>Good Objective: "Build world-class onboarding" — ambitious, memorable</item>
      <item>Bad: "Increase signups by 20%" — that is a Key Result</item>
      <item>Bad: "Launch feature X" — that is a task</item>
      <item>Bad: "Improve stuff" — not testable, not inspiring</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Key Result Characteristics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Key Results must be measurable outcomes (not tasks or outputs), specific, time-bound, and set at 70% confidence — challenging but achievable without heroics.</statement>
      <rationale>The 70% confidence bar is empirically calibrated. 100% targets are sand-bagged; 40% targets are unrealistic stretch goals that demoralise. 70% keeps teams in the productive tension zone.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <list>
      <item>Good KR: "Reduce churn from 5% to 3% by end of Q2" — measurable, specific, time-bound outcome</item>
      <item>Good KR: "NPS score of 50+ by EOQ" — clear number, no ambiguity</item>
      <item>Bad KR: "Publish 12 blog posts" — that is an output/task, not an outcome</item>
      <item>Bad KR: "Activation rate improvement" — no number, not measurable</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Scale">
    <rule>
      <statement>Score Key Results 0.0–1.0 at period end. 0.0–0.3 = failed, 0.4–0.6 = progress made, 0.7–1.0 = success. A 0.7 score is the ideal outcome — it means the target was a real stretch.</statement>
      <rationale>Consistently scoring 1.0 signals targets were too easy (sandbagging). Consistently scoring below 0.5 signals targets were unrealistic. The 0.7 calibration is a process health indicator.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
