<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="OKR Setting Process">
  <summary>Six-step process from strategy alignment through weekly tracking cadence.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Align to Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before drafting, gather: company mission/vision, annual goals, previous period retrospective findings, and current market conditions. Ask: "What must we accomplish this period to move toward our vision?"</statement>
      <rationale>OKRs disconnected from strategy are just metrics. The upward connection is what makes them directional rather than operational.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Draft Objectives">
    <rule>
      <statement>Brainstorm answers to three questions: "What is most important right now?", "If we could only achieve one thing, what would it be?", "What would make this quarter a success?" Then cut to 3–5 Objectives maximum.</statement>
      <rationale>Starting from one-thing thinking forces prioritisation before phrasing. This prevents the common failure of treating every theme as equally urgent.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Define Key Results">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each Objective, answer three questions: "How will we know we achieved it?", "What metrics matter?", "What is the target number?" Test: can you answer with just a number at the end of the period?</statement>
      <rationale>If you cannot answer with a single number, the KR is still a task or a vague aspiration. The number test is the falsifiability test.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Validate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run four checks before publishing: Objectives are inspiring and qualitative, KRs are measurable outcomes not tasks, 70% confidence on each KR, all connect to higher-level goals, total count respects the limit.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipping validation produces OKRs that look correct but fail in practice. The most common failure is KRs that are tasks dressed up with numbers.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Communicate and Commit">
    <rule>
      <statement>Share OKRs with all stakeholders, get explicit buy-in, and make them visible — dashboard, wiki, or team channel. Visibility without commitment produces OKRs that are set and forgotten.</statement>
      <rationale>OKRs only work as coordination tools when everyone knows and accepts them. Private OKRs are just private goals.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Track and Adjust">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run weekly check-ins with progress percentage and confidence level per KR. Score monthly. Hold an end-of-period retrospective focused on accuracy, not just achievement.</statement>
      <rationale>Weekly check-ins surface blockers early. Monthly scoring maintains accountability without micromanagement. Retrospective on accuracy (not just score) improves the OKR-setting process itself.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/weekly-checkin.md">Weekly OKR check-in template</reference>
  </section>
</text>
