<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="OKR Examples and Antipatterns">
  <summary>SaaS product and solo creator OKR sets with full O/KR structure, and concrete antipatterns.</summary>

  <section title="SaaS Product OKRs">
    <example type="good">
      <note>O1: Achieve product-market fit. KR1: increase "very disappointed" survey response from 25% to 40%. KR2: improve Day-30 retention from 20% to 35%. KR3: reach 100 paying customers with less than 10% monthly churn.</note>
      <note>O2: Build scalable acquisition engine. KR1: achieve 5,000 monthly organic visitors. KR2: reduce CAC from $200 to $100. KR3: maintain content pipeline of 12 blog posts published.</note>
      <note>O3: Delight early adopters. KR1: NPS score of 50+. KR2: average support response time under 4 hours. KR3: 10 customer testimonials collected.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Solo Creator OKRs">
    <example type="good">
      <note>O1: Establish newsletter as primary channel. KR1: grow subscriber list from 500 to 2,000. KR2: maintain 45%+ open rate. KR3: convert 50 subscribers to paid product.</note>
      <note>O2: Launch first digital product. KR1: complete and launch course by [date]. KR2: generate $5,000 in first month. KR3: achieve 4.5+ star rating from first 20 customers.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Key Results that are tasks: "Publish 12 blog posts", "Launch feature X", "Run 5 user interviews".</description>
      <reason>Tasks measure output, not outcome. Completing the task does not prove the Objective was reached. Rewrite as the outcome the task enables: "Achieve 5,000 monthly organic visitors" instead of "Publish 12 blog posts".</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Too many OKRs: 7+ Objectives, each with 5 KRs.</description>
      <reason>Exceeding the 3–5 Objective cap destroys focus. With 7 Objectives, none gets the sustained attention needed to move metrics. Everything is equally urgent means nothing is actually prioritised.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting 100% confidence targets to guarantee achievement.</description>
      <reason>Sandbagged targets are not OKRs — they are delivery commitments with extra branding. A 100% score every quarter signals that targets need recalibration upward, not celebration.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting OKRs at the start of the quarter and not reviewing until the end.</description>
      <reason>Blocked KRs stay blocked without weekly visibility. Weekly check-ins catch blockers at week 3, not week 12.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>No baseline for Key Results.</description>
      <reason>A KR without a starting point is unmeasurable. "NPS of 50+" without knowing current NPS cannot be scored. Always establish the baseline before setting the target.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
