<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="RPO/RTO Negotiation Guide Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1150" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every RPO/RTO negotiation must enforce so the chosen numbers are owned by the buyer, not invented by engineering.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-stakeholder-owns-number" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The final RPO and RTO numbers are stated in the stakeholder's own words and signed (digital signature, email confirmation, or recorded acceptance in the meeting transcript). An architect-stated number with no stakeholder echo is rejected as not-yet-negotiated.</statement>
      <rationale source="Buyer-ownership principle">Numbers the stakeholder did not say out loud will be repudiated the moment they become inconvenient. Forcing the echo-and-sign step converts a quiet engineering assumption into an explicit business commitment.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-impact-before-cost" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The conversation must establish the cost of downtime (revenue/hour, SLA penalty/hour, reputational proxy) BEFORE presenting infrastructure cost. Presenting cost first anchors the stakeholder on cheapness and produces under-investment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Negotiation anchoring">Whichever number lands first dominates. Leading with "the DR upgrade costs $40k/yr" gets a reflexive no. Leading with "the current setup loses $9k for every hour we are down, and we have averaged 6 hours/yr" puts the $40k in proportion and lets the stakeholder make a real trade.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-tier-banded-options" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The architect must present at least three banded options (typically: current/baseline, +1 tier, +2 tiers) each with: RPO target, RTO target, annual cost delta, and one-sentence operational impact. Single-option proposals are rejected as not-a-negotiation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Choice architecture">A one-option proposal is a request for rubber-stamp, not a negotiation. Three banded options force the stakeholder to think in trade-offs and almost always surface that the middle option is the actual fit — a finding the architect alone could not have produced.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-signed-acceptance-record" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Output is a typed acceptance record per system carrying: system_id, chosen_rpo, chosen_rto, cost_band_chosen, stakeholder_handle, decided_at, evidence_link (meeting transcript or signed doc), and refresh_due. Free-form prose decisions are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decisionsas-data">Free-form decisions can't be queried, audited, or refreshed on schedule. The typed record makes the commitment a tracked obligation rather than a one-off conversation that fades from memory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-refresh-cadence" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every acceptance record carries a refresh_due of ≤12 months from decided_at. The negotiation must re-run before refresh_due. A record past refresh_due is treated as unsigned for any new design decision that depends on it.</statement>
      <rationale source="Anti-decay practice">Cost-of-downtime, customer expectations, and infra unit economics all change. A 4-year-old "we accepted 4-hour RTO" is an opinion, not a commitment. Forcing annual refresh keeps the negotiation honest as the business grows.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <example>
    <description>Closed acceptance record after a 45-minute negotiation.</description>
    <code language="yaml">
record_id: rpo-rto-2026-05-checkout
system_id: checkout-prod
chosen_rpo: 15min
chosen_rto: 1h
cost_band_chosen: tier-2 (+$28k/yr vs baseline)
options_presented:
  - tier-0 (current): rpo=24h, rto=8h, +$0
  - tier-1: rpo=1h, rto=4h, +$11k/yr
  - tier-2: rpo=15min, rto=1h, +$28k/yr
  - tier-3: rpo=&lt;1min, rto=&lt;15min, +$140k/yr
impact_basis: $9k/hr revenue lost; 6h/yr historical outage
stakeholder_handle: @cfo
decided_at: 2026-05-20
evidence_link: meet://transcripts/2026-05-20-dr-negotiation
refresh_due: 2027-05-20
    </code>
  </example>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../../infra/rto-rpo-measurement-template/AGENTS.md"/>
    <link path="../../infra/dr-drill-scenario-library/AGENTS.md"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
