<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-social-media-strategy">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>smm-manager</domain>
    <summary>The PACE framework for social media growth: choose one platform, define pillars, post consistently, engage daily. Master one platform first; track engagement rate, not follower count.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>social-media</tag>
      <tag>growth</tag>
      <tag>engagement</tag>
      <tag>strategy</tag>
      <tag>content-calendar</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Social Media Strategy</title>

    <summary>The PACE framework (Platform → Audience → Content → Engagement) for solopreneurs building an audience on social media. Master one platform before adding another; commit to six months before evaluating results. Track engagement rate, not follower count, as the primary KPI.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Most social media failures stem from platform sprawl, inconsistent cadence, and treating posts as broadcasts. The PACE framework forces sequencing: pick the platform where your ICP already spends time, define 3-5 content pillars, post on a fixed schedule, and spend daily time engaging. Engagement rate (likes + comments + shares / impressions) predicts content quality; follower count is a lagging indicator that follows engagement, not the other way around.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Choosing which platform(s) to invest in for a new product or personal brand</item>
        <item>Designing a content calendar with pillar distribution and posting frequency</item>
        <item>Batch-generating post drafts (threads, carousels, text posts) for a defined platform</item>
        <item>Running a monthly strategy review: what to double down on, what to cut</item>
        <item>Briefing an agent to produce a 4-week content calendar in JSON format</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Real-time trend hijacking — requires human judgment on brand safety and timing</item>
        <item>Community management and comment responses — relationship quality requires a human</item>
        <item>Generating content for all platforms simultaneously from one prompt — quality degrades</item>
        <item>Accounts under 1 month old with no ICP data — build ICP clarity first</item>
        <item>When the goal is paid acquisition; use ppc-manager methodology instead</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="platform-selection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Master ONE platform before adding a second. Choose based on where your ICP already spends time, not where it is easiest to post.</statement>
        <rationale>Follower migration across platforms is slow. Spreading across multiple platforms dilutes content quality and engagement time before momentum is built.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Score each platform 1-5 on four criteria: ICP audience present, content type match, competitor activity, organic reach potential. Pick the highest scorer.</statement>
        <rationale>Subjective platform preferences lead to choosing the wrong channel. The scorecard forces objective audience-first thinking.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Platform scorecard for B2B SaaS founder">
        <note>Twitter/X scores 18/20 (strong ICP, text content, active competitors, high organic reach). LinkedIn scores 14/20. Decision: start Twitter/X, add LinkedIn at 6 months.</note>
      </example>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Choosing a platform because "everyone is on it" or because competitors are there without verifying ICP presence.</description>
        <reason>Competitors being on a platform does not mean your ICP converts there. Audience presence is the only criterion that matters at launch.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="content-pillars">
      <rule>
        <statement>Define 3-5 content pillars with percentage allocations that sum to 100%. Reserve 10% for behind-the-scenes or personal content.</statement>
        <rationale>Pillars prevent random posting and ensure audience knows what to expect. The 10% personal allocation humanizes the brand and builds trust.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="SaaS founder content pillars">
        <note>Product updates 40%, Industry insights 30%, Building in public 20%, Personal wins/fails 10%. Every content decision maps to a pillar.</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Allocate at most 20% of posts to promotion. For accounts under 1K followers, use 95/5 value-to-promo ratio — trust is not yet established.</statement>
        <rationale>Promotional content before trust is built causes unfollows. Value content compounds: followers stay and refer others.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="posting-frequency">
      <rule>
        <statement>Batch content creation into 2-3 hour weekly sessions rather than creating single posts daily. Consistency improves and creative quality is higher in blocks.</statement>
        <rationale>Daily single-post creation leads to inconsistency when other priorities intervene. Batching decouples creation from posting.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Twitter/X: minimum 1/day, optimal 3-5/day</item>
        <item>LinkedIn: minimum 3/week, optimal 1/day</item>
        <item>Instagram: minimum 3/week, optimal 1/day feed + daily Stories</item>
        <item>TikTok: minimum 1/day, optimal 3/day</item>
        <item>YouTube: minimum 1/week, optimal 2/week</item>
      </list>

      <reference path="templates/content-calendar.md">Monthly content calendar with pillar distribution and daily posting slots</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="daily-engagement-5-5-5-method">
      <rule>
        <statement>Spend 5 minutes engaging with accounts you follow, 5 minutes replying to comments on your posts, and 5 minutes finding new accounts to engage with — daily.</statement>
        <rationale>For accounts under 10K followers, engagement time drives more growth than posting frequency. If forced to choose, engage over post.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Reply to comments within 1 hour. Ask questions at the end of posts. DM new followers with an authentic message, not a pitch.</statement>
        <rationale>Early comment engagement signals to algorithms that the post is generating conversation, boosting further distribution.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="kpi-targets">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track engagement rate, not follower count, as the primary KPI for the first 6 months. Follower growth is a lagging indicator.</statement>
        <rationale>Engagement rate reveals content quality and audience relevance. Follower count inflates via low-quality follows and does not predict conversion.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Engagement rate = (Likes + Comments + Shares) / Impressions * 100. Target: above 3% is good, above 6% is excellent.</statement>
        <rationale>Rates below 1% indicate content-audience mismatch or posting to an unengaged audience. Rates above 3% signal the content resonates.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/engagement-tracker.py">Parse platform analytics CSV to compute avg, median, and top post engagement rates</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Spreading across too many platforms in the first 90 days.</description>
        <reason>Dilutes content quality and engagement time before momentum builds on any single platform.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Giving up before 6 months of consistent posting.</description>
        <reason>Audience momentum is non-linear. Most accounts see exponential growth between months 4-8, not in the first 30 days.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Using platform analytics only after paying for third-party tools.</description>
        <reason>Native platform analytics are free and sufficient for the first 6 months. Third-party tools add value only when cross-platform reporting becomes necessary.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Repurposing content across platforms verbatim (e.g., Twitter thread copy-pasted to LinkedIn).</description>
        <reason>Each platform has distinct tone, format preferences, and algorithmic requirements. Verbatim cross-posting underperforms platform-native content by a significant margin.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <rule>
        <statement>Choose platform based on where the ICP already spends time, not where it is easiest to post — follower migration is slow.</statement>
        <rationale>Distributing effort across multiple channels before mastering one leads to weak presence everywhere rather than strong presence on one platform.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Batch content creation into 2-3 hour weekly sessions rather than daily single-post creation; consistency improves and creative quality is higher in blocks.</statement>
        <rationale>Batching decouples creation from posting and prevents quality degradation when other priorities intervene.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>The 80/20 value-to-promo rule is minimum; for accounts under 1K followers, go 95/5 — trust is not yet established.</statement>
        <rationale>Promotional content before trust is built causes unfollows. Value content compounds and builds audience loyalty.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Engagement time (5-5-5 method) drives more growth than posting frequency for accounts under 10K followers; if forced to choose, engage over post.</statement>
        <rationale>Algorithm distribution favors accounts that generate early conversation and engagement on others' posts.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Track engagement rate, not follower count, as the primary KPI for the first 6 months — follower growth is a lagging indicator.</statement>
        <rationale>Engagement rate reveals content quality and audience relevance; follower count is influenced by low-quality follows and third-party services.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Platform analytics are available natively and free; use them before paying for third-party tools.</statement>
        <rationale>Native analytics provide sufficient data for strategy decisions in the first 6 months; paid tools add value only when cross-platform reporting is necessary.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-integration-notes">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run strategy in two phases: (1) planning — a single Sonnet call produces platform selection, pillar definitions, frequency targets, and KPI baselines; (2) execution — a Haiku call batch-generates post drafts.</statement>
        <rationale>Separation of planning and execution allows human review and data injection between phases, improving content quality and alignment with brand voice.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Inject real engagement data monthly for a Sonnet strategy review. Human executes posting and engagement; agent handles content generation and analysis only.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents cannot observe actual post performance or current platform dynamics; monthly feedback loops prevent stale recommendations.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <p>Platform algorithm preferences change without documentation updates; agent recommendations on posting times and formats go stale within 3-6 months. Validate quarterly against native analytics.</p>

      <p>Content pillar distribution (40/30/20/10) is a starting heuristic, not a law; real performance data overrides it in strategy reviews.</p>

      <p>Cross-platform repurposing requires adaptation the agent often misses — a Twitter thread repurposed to LinkedIn verbatim underperforms. Run separate platform-specific prompts.</p>

      <p>Engagement rate spikes from a viral post skew monthly averages; flag outliers before using data to adjust strategy.</p>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/content-calendar.md" purpose="Monthly content calendar with pillar distribution and weekly plan"/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-content-calendar.txt" purpose="Agent prompt: 4-week calendar in JSON"/>
      <template path="templates/engagement-tracker.py" purpose="Parse platform analytics CSV → avg/median engagement rate"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://blog.hootsuite.com/social-media-marketing/"/>
      <link href="https://sproutsocial.com/insights/"/>
      <link href="https://buffer.com/resources/"/>
      <link href="https://blog.hubspot.com/marketing/social-media-strategy"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
