<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Experimentation at Scale Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Hypothesis-driven A/B experimentation program (&gt;=100 experiments/year) with pre-registered metrics, guardrails, statistical rigor, and an agent-assisted triage -&gt; readout -&gt; archive loop.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="hypothesis-pre-registered" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every experiment MUST have a written hypothesis with primary metric, secondary metrics, guardrails, MDE, and stop conditions registered BEFORE traffic is sent. No post-hoc primary swaps.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kohavi et al — Trustworthy Online Controlled Experiments; GrowthBook docs">Post-hoc primary swap is the #1 source of false positives in mature programs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="guardrail-floor" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each experiment ships with &gt;=3 guardrail metrics (revenue/user, error rate, latency, retention). Any guardrail crossing its floor auto-pauses the experiment regardless of primary lift.</statement>
      <rationale source="Microsoft ExP guardrail standards">Guardrails catch unintended damage that a single primary metric can mask.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="mde-power-pre-flight" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sample-size and runtime calc MUST be run before launch; experiments shipped with insufficient power are forbidden. Document the MDE assumption in the hypothesis doc.</statement>
      <rationale source="Kohavi A/B testing textbook">Under-powered experiments produce noise that the org learns to ignore, killing the program.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="srm-check-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sample Ratio Mismatch (SRM) check at p&lt;0.001 MUST run before any readout. SRM failure invalidates the readout — debug bucketing, do not interpret results.</statement>
      <rationale source="GrowthBook / Eppo SRM diagnostics">SRM points to bucketing / instrumentation bugs that make ALL downstream stats meaningless.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="readout-binary-decision" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every readout ends with a binary action: ship / kill / iterate. Inconclusive results auto-route to iterate or kill; never 'hold' indefinitely.</statement>
      <rationale source="Spotify / Booking experimentation post-mortems">Holding inconclusive experiments creates a queue of zombie variants and drains experiment slots.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="triage-agent-dedups" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>An agent ranks experiment proposals by expected-value-per-week before slot allocation; duplicates against past experiments are auto-rejected unless market context changed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — experimentation backlog audits">Without triage, slot allocation becomes politics and throughput collapses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — low-traffic product where MDE detection takes &gt;4 weeks; irreversible high-risk change; legally restricted variant; team without analytics platform), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
