<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="stakeholder-engagement">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Identify stakeholders, map them on Power/Interest grid, assign engagement strategies per quadrant, execute cadence in version-controlled register for auditable history and evidence-backed attitudes.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>stakeholder-management</tag>
      <tag>power-interest-grid</tag>
      <tag>engagement-strategy</tag>
      <tag>communication-plan</tag>
      <tag>register</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>pm</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Stakeholder Engagement</title>

    <summary>A structured process to identify all parties affected by or affecting a project, map each on the Power/Interest grid, assign an engagement strategy per quadrant, and execute a communication cadence — stored as version-controlled YAML register so changes produce a diff history and evidence-backed attitudes. Engagement is continuous; register must refresh quarterly minimum.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Projects fail when key stakeholders are ignored or mismanaged. Missed requirements from silent stakeholders, resistance from influential parties, scope creep from unmanaged expectations, and approval bottlenecks all trace back to a broken or absent engagement plan. The Power/Interest grid is the minimum viable model; the Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience overlay (power × legitimacy × urgency) is required when political risk is significant.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Project kickoff for any cross-functional initiative with more than 5 named parties</item>
        <item>Programs with significant political risk: M&amp;A integration, reorgs, vendor consolidation, regulated rollouts</item>
        <item>Multi-stakeholder transformation programs (cloud migration, ERP) with sponsors, champions, blockers, and external auditors</item>
        <item>Public-facing programs (government, NGO, infrastructure) with citizen/community stakeholders</item>
        <item>Pre-RFP or vendor-selection efforts where the buying committee has hidden influencers</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo founders or very small teams (under 5 stakeholders) — direct conversation beats matrix overhead</item>
        <item>One-off internal hotfixes or refactors with no business stakeholder change — RACI alone is enough</item>
        <item>Anonymous open-source community projects — power/interest axes are meaningless without identity</item>
        <item>Crisis or incident response — incident command structure replaces engagement plan during P0</item>
        <item>When stakeholder identification is still unsolved — do BA stakeholder-analysis first to get a register</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="five-step-process">
      <p>The engagement process follows five sequential steps from identification through monitoring and adaptation.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Step 1: Identify all stakeholders — sponsor, users, customers, team, regulators, suppliers, influencers. Seed from org chart, charter, RFP, and contract.</item>
        <item>Step 2: Analyze Power/Interest — map each stakeholder on the 2x2 grid; apply Mitchell-Agle-Wood (power × legitimacy × urgency) for political risk.</item>
        <item>Step 3: Plan engagement strategies — one strategy per quadrant; override only with explicit rationale.</item>
        <item>Step 4: Execute communication plan — cadence, channel, owner, content per stakeholder.</item>
        <item>Step 5: Monitor and adapt — refresh quarterly minimum; triangulate self-reported attitude with behavioural signals.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="quadrant-strategies">
      <p>The Power/Interest grid creates four quadrants, each requiring different engagement tactics.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the default cadence by quadrant: Manage Closely = weekly 1:1, Keep Satisfied = biweekly summary, Keep Informed = monthly digest, Monitor = release notes only.</statement>
        <rationale>Default cadence is empirically calibrated to stakeholder tolerance; deviating without rationale causes either fatigue (over-engagement) or surprises (under-engagement).</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>High Power + High Interest (Manage Closely): weekly meetings, direct updates, real-time dashboard access, early warning on delays.</item>
        <item>High Power + Low Interest (Keep Satisfied): monthly briefings, escalation path, fast response to queries, no unnecessary meetings.</item>
        <item>Low Power + High Interest (Keep Informed): newsletters, status reports, sprint demos where relevant.</item>
        <item>Low Power + Low Interest (Monitor): general announcements, release notes.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="attitude-model">
      <p>Attitudes capture the stakeholder's current disposition toward the project or initiative. Evidence is mandatory.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Require an evidence field on every attitude assertion — no evidence means attitude = "unknown", not "supportive".</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs over-classify everyone as "supportive" by default (politeness bias). Forcing evidence eliminates false positives that lead to missed resistors.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioural signal: meeting attendance, response time, escalations, or Slack sentiment.</statement>
        <rationale>People say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private; behavioural signals are less gameable than self-report.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Treating all Manage Closely stakeholders with the same tone and cadence.</description>
        <reason>A CFO and a regulator demand opposite communication styles even though both fall in the same quadrant — context-specific strategy is required.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="hidden-stakeholder-review">
      <p>Hidden stakeholders are systematically omitted from initial org charts and are the top source of late-stage blockers.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include a hidden stakeholder pass: legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream API consumers.</statement>
        <rationale>Systematically missed stakeholders are the top source of late-stage blockers in enterprise programs; they never appear in org-chart exports.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="register-as-code">
      <p>Storing the stakeholder register in version-controlled YAML creates an auditable history and enforces governance.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>Store the register in git (YAML), not a wiki — diffs become the engagement history; CODEOWNERS gate sponsor sign-off on attitude changes.</statement>
        <rationale>Wiki pages have no diff history, no access control per field, and no CI integration. Git provides all three and makes the history auditable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>The register (stakeholders/register.yaml) feeds a generated engagement-plan.md. The plan never auto-sends to executives — it drafts; humans deliver.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <p>An effective agentic workflow breaks engagement curation into specialised agents, each with clear scope and model selection.</p>
      <list>
        <item>register-curator-agent (sonnet): ingests org chart, kickoff transcripts, RFP; emits patch with new/changed entries; never overwrites existing entries silently.</item>
        <item>attitude-triangulator-agent (sonnet): cross-references self-reported attitude against meeting attendance, response time, escalations; flags drift.</item>
        <item>engagement-planner-agent (sonnet): converts register quadrants into Step-5 engagement table with cadence, channel, owner, content.</item>
        <item>salience-scorer-agent (opus): applies Mitchell-Agle-Wood (power × legitimacy × urgency); identifies definitive stakeholders requiring daily attention.</item>
        <item>engagement-sentiment-agent (sonnet): listens to feedback channels and updates attitude column with evidence trail.</item>
        <item>password-scrubber-agent: runs over engagement docs before commit; the register frequently leaks salaries, customer names, candid commentary.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="register-curator-prompt-pattern">
      <p>The register curator uses a strict JSON patch format that prevents silent overwrites and enforces evidence requirements.</p>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Strict JSON patch — prevents overwrite, enforces evidence requirement:</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You are the register-curator agent. Inputs:
1. Kickoff transcript / charter / RFP.
2. Org-chart export (names, titles, reporting lines).
3. Existing register (may be empty).

For each named or implied party, emit STRICT JSON patch:
{ "action": "add|update",
  "id": "S-NN",
  "name": "...",
  "category": "Sponsor|User|Customer|Team|Regulator|Supplier|Influencer",
  "power": "H|M|L",
  "interest": "H|M|L",
  "attitude": "+|0|-|unknown",
  "quadrant": "Manage Closely|Keep Satisfied|Keep Informed|Monitor",
  "evidence": ["quote or org-chart line"],
  "cadence": "daily|weekly|biweekly|monthly|quarterly|release",
  "channel": "1:1|email|digest|meeting|portal",
  "owner": "<role>",
  "rationale": "<= 2 sentences" }

Rules: do not invent people. attitude defaults to "unknown" without evidence.
quadrant must follow power x interest unless override rationale provided.
Flag hidden stakeholders (legal, infosec, works council, procurement,
downstream consumers) in suggested_to_verify.]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <p>LLMs have systematic biases in stakeholder analysis. These gotchas represent real deployment failures.</p>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent invents stakeholder names not found in org-chart or charter inputs.</description>
        <reason>LLMs hallucinate plausible-sounding personas; always seed with real org-chart export and reject any name not in the source list unless flagged suggested_to_verify.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent sends engagement communications directly to executives without human review.</description>
        <reason>Auto-send is forbidden to executives, regulators, customers, board. Agent drafts; sponsor or PM approves and sends.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Bulk reclassification of stakeholder quadrants in a single agent run.</description>
        <reason>Cap agent edits to 5 stakeholders per run and require human review on the diff — bulk changes destroy the evidence trail and can reverse carefully built relationships.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <list>
        <item>Mandatory human checkpoints: adding a stakeholder, changing attitude, escalating to sponsor, dropping a stakeholder from active engagement.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder data is regulated PII (GDPR Art. 9 if attitude implies political opinion). Never send the register to a third-party model without DPA.</item>
        <item>Registers with more than 50 stakeholders blow context — page by category (Internal/External/Regulator) and operate on slices.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="cli-tools">
      <p>Command-line tools enable register automation and analysis in CI pipelines.</p>
      <list>
        <item>git + git log — native history of relationship changes; replaces hand-rolled engagement history</item>
        <item>yq — read/patch register YAML in pipelines (apt install yq / brew install yq)</item>
        <item>jq — aggregate JSON exports from CRM/HR systems</item>
        <item>graphviz (dot) — render influence/impact graph and relationship network (apt install graphviz)</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli (mmdc) — generate 2x2 quadrant chart from YAML as PNG/SVG (npm i -g @mermaid-js/mermaid-cli)</item>
        <item>pandoc — convert register and engagement plan to PDF/DOCX for sponsor review (https://pandoc.org)</item>
        <item>pre-commit — block commits to attitude/quadrant changes without evidence: field</item>
        <item>gh / glab — mirror engagement actions as issues; CODEOWNERS gate sponsor sign-off</item>
        <item>op (1Password CLI) — pull sensitive contact info without committing it to git</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="services-and-integrations">
      <p>Enterprise systems and SaaS tools provide source data and distribution channels for engagement.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Microsoft Graph (Entra ID) — source of truth for internal org chart; required to seed register without inventing.</item>
        <item>Workday HCM / BambooHR — authoritative for level, span of control, manager; used for influence inference.</item>
        <item>Salesforce — authoritative for external (customer) stakeholders; REST + Bulk API.</item>
        <item>HubSpot — lighter SMB CRM; webhooks drive attitude triggers.</item>
        <item>Notion / Confluence — common register host; weak typing — schema-validate before commit.</item>
        <item>Jira / Linear — Stakeholder = issue with custom fields (less ideal but common).</item>
        <item>Smaply / UXPressia — Persona/journey tools; visual artifact, weak agent automation.</item>
        <item>Mural / Miro / FigJam — workshop canvas for matrix exercises; agents can post sticky notes via API.</item>
        <item>Slack / MS Teams — source for behavioural signal; use with explicit consent only.</item>
        <item>SurveyMonkey / Typeform / Qualtrics — periodic stakeholder pulse surveys feeding attitude triangulation.</item>
        <item>Calendly / SavvyCal — meeting load monitor for high-touch stakeholders (avoid burnout).</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <p>Proven practices prevent common pitfalls in stakeholder engagement at scale.</p>
      <rule>
        <statement>One canonical register in git; if Workday or Salesforce holds source data, mirror nightly — do not maintain two truths.</statement>
        <rationale>Two register sources diverge within weeks; the one not updated during a crisis is the one consulted, producing wrong engagement actions.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Treat the register as confidential — private repo, not a wiki page; run password-scrubber-agent before any commit.</statement>
        <rationale>Stakeholder attitude data leaking to the wrong stakeholder terminates relationships; candid commentary is common in these files.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Calendar audits prevent burnout — if any stakeholder appears in more than 3 weekly meetings, consolidate.</statement>
        <rationale>Well-meant high-touch engagement burns goodwill faster than under-engagement when it exceeds the recipient's tolerance.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Refresh quarterly minimum, monthly for volatile contexts (post-merger, leadership change, regulator activity).</item>
        <item>Triangulate self-reported attitude with at least one behavioural signal (attendance, Slack sentiment, response time, escalations).</item>
        <item>Apply the Mitchell-Agle-Wood salience overlay for political risk — flag "definitive" (power × legitimacy × urgency) stakeholders for daily attention.</item>
        <item>Tie cadence to quadrant by default: Manage Closely = weekly, Keep Satisfied = biweekly, Keep Informed = monthly, Monitor = release-only. Override only with rationale.</item>
        <item>Always include a "hidden stakeholders" review: legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream API consumers.</item>
        <item>Pair stakeholder weight with requirements-prioritization so high-influence support amplifies a requirement's score.</item>
        <item>Engagement plan is a living document with explicit ownership per stakeholder; rotate owners only on transition.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="pairing-with-related-methodologies">
      <p>Stakeholder engagement is most effective when integrated with complementary practices in communications, change, and risk.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Pair with communications-management/ (executable form of the engagement plan), stakeholder-register/, stakeholder-engagement-advanced/, change-control/, and risk-register.</item>
        <item>Pair with business-analyst stakeholder-analysis/ for the initial discovery phase if stakeholder identification is incomplete.</item>
        <item>Tie cadence to quadrant in the communications plan so one source of truth drives all engagement actions.</item>
        <item>Use the SDD-executor-agent to drive engagement as formal tasks: TASK_register_baseline, TASK_engagement_plan, TASK_cadence_setup, TASK_quarterly_refresh.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="limitations">
      <p>Be aware of the boundaries and failure modes inherent in stakeholder analysis methods.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Power/Interest 2x2 flattens multi-dimensional politics (urgency, legitimacy, salience). Mitchell-Agle-Wood overlay is needed for serious political risk.</item>
        <item>Static analysis goes stale fast (2–6 weeks in dynamic orgs); a register that is not refreshed is wrong, not just old.</item>
        <item>Self-reported attitude is unreliable — people say "supportive" in workshops and undermine in private. Triangulate against behaviour.</item>
        <item>Hidden stakeholders (works councils, security, procurement, downstream consumers) are systematically missed unless seeded with org-chart context.</item>
        <item>LLMs invent plausible-sounding personas that do not exist in the target organisation; outputs must validate against directory data.</item>
        <item>Cross-cultural blindness: high-context cultures (JP, KR, parts of EU/MEA) route influence through indirect networks the matrix does not represent.</item>
        <item>Engagement strategies that treat all "Manage Closely" stakeholders the same fail — a CFO and a regulator demand opposite tone, cadence, and content.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder fatigue: well-meant high-touch engagement burns goodwill if asks exceed the recipient's tolerance.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/register.yaml" purpose="Stakeholder register schema: id, power, interest, attitude, quadrant, cadence, last_engaged"/>
      <template path="templates/engagement-due.py" purpose="Script: flag stakeholders past their engagement cadence deadline"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stakeholder_analysis"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmistandardstoday.org/"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-register"/>
      <ref slug="stakeholder-engagement-advanced"/>
      <ref slug="communications-management"/>
      <ref slug="change-control"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
