<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Regulatory Uncertainty Buffer — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `regulatory-uncertainty-buffer` must enforce. The rules pin the discipline that turns a buffer from folklore into a reviewable, owned, version-controlled operating tool.</summary>

  <section title="Rules">
    <rule id="r1-named-inputs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The decision rule names its inputs (signal, threshold, source). &apos;Use judgment&apos; is not an input.</statement>
      <rationale source="Structured decision-making (Kahneman, Noise); checklist-driven decision practice">Unnamed inputs let bias dominate. Named inputs make the call reproducible and challengeable.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-published-thresholds" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each branch carries a published threshold (numeric or boolean). &apos;Significant&apos; and &apos;material&apos; are rejected without a number.</statement>
      <rationale source="Outcome-based decision practice; safety-critical thresholding (NTSB, FAA)">Threshold-free rules become whatever the decider felt that morning. Published thresholds make the rule a tool, not folklore.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-default-action" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The rule has a documented default for the unhappy path (timeout, missing data, ambiguous signal). Silent defaults are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Lasting-decisions practice; engineering-design defaults">Most decisions fail not on the happy path but on edge cases. A documented default removes ambiguity and shortens the meeting.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-recorded-call" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every invocation is logged with inputs, branch taken, and decider. The log is reviewable by anyone affected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Decision-journal practice (Annie Duke); ITIL change-management">Audit trails for decision rules turn a rule into an organisational asset. Without the log the rule is one person&apos;s opinion stamped with a name.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-review-on-failure" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If a logged call produces a bad outcome, the rule itself is reviewed in the next retro. The rule is not assumed correct.</statement>
      <rationale source="PDCA / continuous-improvement practice; postmortem-feedback loops">Static rules rot. The review-on-failure loop is the cheap mechanism that keeps the rule calibrated to reality.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
