<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-structure" title="Outcome Row Anatomy">
  <summary>Defines the required fields for each outcome row and the rule against single-solution commitments.</summary>

  <section title="Required Row Fields">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every outcome row must contain: problem (1 sentence), outcome_metric (the KPI being moved), baseline (current measured value), target (goal value), horizon (this quarter / next quarter), and candidate_solutions (minimum 2, maximum 5). Rows missing any of these fields are invalid and must be flagged or dropped.</statement>
      <rationale>Incomplete rows silently degrade the roadmap into a feature list. A row with a target but no baseline cannot be tracked. A row with a metric but no horizon is not time-bound and therefore not a commitment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a minimum of 2 candidate solutions per outcome row. A single-solution row is a feature roadmap in disguise — it has already committed to an implementation rather than preserving solution flexibility.</statement>
      <rationale>The entire point of outcome framing is to keep the solution space open while committing to the goal. One solution = already decided. Two or more solutions = the team has permission to discover what actually moves the metric.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pair every outcome with a kill criterion: "If [leading indicator] does not move by week 6, drop this outcome." The kill criterion is required at commit time, not at quarter end.</statement>
      <rationale>Kill criteria prevent outcome theatre — spending an entire quarter on an outcome that showed no signal in the first six weeks. Without a kill criterion, teams rationalize continuing indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Feature vs Outcome Comparison">
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Feature roadmap row: "Build chat feature." Commits to solution before validating the problem. No metric, no baseline, no flexibility to try a different solution.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Outcome roadmap row: problem = "Users contact support for questions answered in the product", outcome_metric = "support tickets / MAU", baseline = "0.18", target = "0.12", horizon = "Q2 2026", candidate_solutions = ["in-app contextual help tooltips", "searchable FAQ embedded in product", "proactive onboarding email sequence"].</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Outcome row with single solution: "Reduce churn by building a re-engagement email sequence." Sounds outcome-shaped but has already committed to one solution. Add at least one alternative candidate solution.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/outcome-row.yaml">Single outcome row schema with all required fields</reference>
</text>
