<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Translating a Feature Roadmap to Outcomes and Generating Audience Views">
  <summary>How to convert an existing feature roadmap to outcome rows and generate engineering vs. leadership views from a single source.</summary>

  <section title="Translation Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each row in the existing feature roadmap: (1) state the underlying problem in one sentence; (2) restate as an outcome — "[metric] from [baseline] to [target] by [horizon]"; (3) list 2-3 candidate solutions; (4) flag rows where you cannot identify an outcome — these are pet features or infrastructure items.</statement>
      <rationale>Infrastructure and pet features do not have outcomes because their value is not user-facing. Flag them explicitly so stakeholders understand they are funded on a different basis (technical debt, compliance, founder conviction) rather than on outcome impact.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Sort the translated roadmap by outcome impact, not by feature size or team affinity. Impact = magnitude of metric movement multiplied by strategic importance of that metric.</statement>
      <rationale>Feature roadmaps are often sequenced by development order or team availability. Outcome roadmaps must be sequenced by expected impact, which makes trade-offs explicit.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Audience Views">
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate two views from the same source: (a) Engineering view — each outcome with 2-3 candidate solutions, rough effort per option, current confidence; (b) Leadership view — each outcome with metric, baseline, target, current value, confidence, kill criterion. Both views must trace back to identical source rows via a row ID.</statement>
      <rationale>Traceability ID is essential. When a leadership view shows "churn" and the engineering view shows "re-engagement flow," the connection must be explicit. Views that drift from source produce inconsistent commitments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>The customer-facing view stays at problem-statement level only. Never expose internal outcome metrics or implementation details to customers — they ask "when does feature X ship?" and the answer is "we are working on [customer problem], here is what we know about our progress."</statement>
      <rationale>Outcome metrics are internal accountability tools. Exposing churn targets or activation rates to customers creates the wrong conversation and anchors customers to implementation commitments rather than problem resolution.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/validate-outcomes.py">Python validator: fails roadmap YAML with missing fields or fewer than 2 candidate solutions</reference>
</text>
