<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="outcome-based-roadmaps Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for outcome-based-roadmaps as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Outcome rewording: translating "Build chat" to "Improve communication outcomes." The words change but no metric, baseline, or target is added. The row is still a feature in disguise.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Outcome framing requires a measurable metric movement, not a rephrasing. "Improve communication outcomes" has no baseline and no target, making it untraceable and un-kill-criterion-able.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-solution rows: "Reduce churn from 8% to 5% by building a re-engagement email sequence." One solution means the team has already decided the implementation.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The value of outcome framing is preserving solution flexibility. A single committed solution collapses outcome framing back into feature roadmap behavior. Require at least 2 candidate solutions to maintain that flexibility.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Unbounded horizons: "Improve retention" with no time target. Teams can claim progress at any point without accountability.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>An outcome without a horizon is not a commitment. "Improve retention to 40% DAU/MAU" is a vibe until "by end of Q2" is added. All outcome rows require explicit horizon specification.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated baselines: outcome rows that list a baseline number that was never measured, because the metric is not yet instrumented.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Invented baselines destroy tracking credibility. If the metric is not instrumented, the row must say "TO BE INSTRUMENTED, owner=X" — never an invented number. Teams cannot improve a metric they cannot measure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Weekly roadmap rewrites. The agent re-translates the entire roadmap every week, losing the commitment history and making it impossible to track whether outcomes are improving.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Outcome roadmaps should be updated at two cadences: (1) weekly metric monitor for progress tracking; (2) quarterly re-decomposition for strategic revision. Rewriting weekly destroys the accountability record.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Stakeholders silently translating outcome rows back to feature commitments. Leadership hears "reduce support tickets by 30%" and immediately asks "which features will you ship to do that?" and anchors on the answer.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>This is an ongoing communication problem, not a one-time fix. PMs must actively police the framing in every stakeholder interaction, maintaining a "confirmed solutions" list as a strict subset of the roadmap for external timing commitments.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs translate features to outcomes by simply rewording ("Build chat" → "Improve communication outcomes"). That is not an outcome. Force a measurable metric movement per row.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Rephrasing is easier than finding metrics. Models lack the domain knowledge to identify outcome-relevant KPIs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents prefer 1 confident solution per outcome ("the obvious answer"). Force a minimum of 2 candidate solutions to preserve solution discovery.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models optimize for coherent single narratives, not exploring solution space.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Vague outcome verbs (improve, enhance, optimize) creep in. Add a banned-verb instruction or require numeric movement per outcome.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vague language is natural to language models; specificity requires explicit constraint.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>View-generator agents drift between leadership and engineering views — same row says different things. Require traceability ID per row across views.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models optimize for each-view coherence independently, not cross-view consistency.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-11" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents hallucinate baselines. If the metric is not instrumented, the row must say "TO BE INSTRUMENTED, owner=X" — never invented numbers.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Plausible numbers are easier to generate than admitting measurement gaps.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-12" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: outcome decomposition (goal → outcomes) is strategic; humans must own the final tree before any view is generated.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Strategic decomposition requires human judgment about impact and importance.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-13" severity="medium">
      <description>Human-in-loop checkpoint: kill criteria require human sign-off — agents are too quick to delete outcomes the moment metrics wobble.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models over-optimize for "success" signals; kill criteria require human judgment about acceptable risk.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-14" severity="medium">
      <description>Do not let the agent re-rewrite the roadmap weekly. Cadence: weekly metric monitor, quarterly re-decomposition.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Frequent rewrites destroy accountability and commitment history.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
