<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-execution" title="Diary Study Execution">
  <summary>Monitoring participant compliance, detecting low-quality entries, managing drop-off, and maintaining data quality during an active diary study.</summary>

  <section title="Monitoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor compliance daily and flag participants below 60% completion by day 4. Do not wait until study end to detect dropout.</statement>
      <rationale>Early dropout is recoverable with a human check-in call. Late detection produces data gaps that make cross-participant comparison unreliable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Check completion rates daily per participant.</item>
      <item>Send reminders at the scheduled cadence — switch from automated nudges to a single human-style DM after two missed days.</item>
      <item>Monitor data quality: look for generic entries, copy-paste repetition, off-topic content.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/qa-monitor.sh">Bash script flagging low-completion participants and suspected copy-paste entries.</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Entry Quality Checks">
    <rule>
      <statement>Compute text similarity across a participant's entries. Flag entries with cosine similarity above 0.9 as suspected copy-paste before including them in analysis.</statement>
      <rationale>Copy-paste entries inflate frequency counts for the copied text and suppress the genuine signal from days the participant did not engage. Counting them as real entries poisons temporal pattern analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Generic entries (same text, low detail): prompt participant for specifics in a follow-up message.</item>
      <item>Missed days (gap in submissions): send gentle reminder within 24 hours.</item>
      <item>Copy-paste entries (identical across days): schedule a recovery check-in call.</item>
      <item>Off-topic content: clarify study scope — never silently discard without documenting.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Validity Threats">
    <rule>
      <statement>Mitigate self-report bias by using signal-contingent prompts and keeping study duration under 21 days. Acknowledge remaining bias explicitly in the final report.</statement>
      <rationale>Social desirability, memory reconstruction, observation effect, and fatigue all systematically distort self-report data. Transparency about remaining bias prevents stakeholders from over-interpreting findings.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Social desirability: participants report what seems "right", not what actually happened.</item>
      <item>Memory reconstruction: entries written hours after events reconstruct rather than recall.</item>
      <item>Observation effect: behavior changes when participants know they are being studied.</item>
      <item>Fatigue effects: entry quality and detail decline over the second half of long studies.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Engagement and Drop-Off">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pay incentives in tranches (30% at week 1 completion, 70% at study end). Pre-paid full incentives correlate with mid-study dropout.</statement>
      <rationale>Tranche payment keeps commitment active through the critical second week when fatigue peaks. Pre-payment removes the ongoing motivation to continue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Send a personal check-in call (15 minutes) at the midpoint of the study. This single intervention lifts completion rates measurably.</statement>
      <rationale>Check-in calls rebuild commitment and catch confusion about entry expectations before the participant fully disengages. Automated reminders alone cannot substitute for this human contact.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
