<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-analysis" title="Diary Study Analysis">
  <summary>Codebook design, coding pass rules, thematic and temporal analysis, quantitative metrics, and report structure for diary study data.</summary>

  <section title="Codebook">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock the codebook before coding begins. Adding a theme mid-study invalidates earlier passes — re-run the coder agent on the full dataset if the codebook changes.</statement>
      <rationale>Cross-participant frequency counts are only valid when all entries are coded against the same taxonomy. Mid-study codebook additions create systematic gaps in earlier participant data.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the codebook to 6-12 themes with explicit definitions. Force the coder to return an empty themes array when no code fits rather than inventing a match.</statement>
      <rationale>Larger codebooks produce lower inter-rater reliability. Agents over-classify when forced to assign a code to every entry — a NULL result is real data about entry quality or scope drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Coding Pass Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Code each entry independently without exposing the coder to other participants' entries or prior hypotheses. Run two independent passes on a 10% sample and compute Cohen's kappa. Below 0.6 means the codebook is ambiguous.</statement>
      <rationale>Hypothesis exposure causes confirmation bias that amplifies in agents when the prompt mentions a research question upfront. Kappa below 0.6 indicates the codebook has ambiguous boundaries that will produce unreliable frequency counts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require the coder to cite verbatim text fragments per theme. This lets the synthesizer pull real quotes without re-reading raw entries.</statement>
      <rationale>Paraphrased quotes introduce researcher interpretation into participant voice. Verbatim extraction is the only defensible standard for evidence in a research report.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Temporal Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tag every entry with its study day and prompt type (signal-contingent vs event-contingent vs end-of-day). Compute per-day sentiment timelines with date metadata — not free-text dates from entry content.</statement>
      <rationale>Temporal patterns (e.g., day 3-5 frustration spike) are invisible to a single-pass summarizer. Free-text date parsing is unreliable; structured metadata is required for timeline visualizations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Temporal patterns: behavior changes over time, learning curves, habit formation points, drop-off triggers.</item>
      <item>Contextual patterns: location-based behaviors, device preferences, time-of-day patterns.</item>
      <item>Thematic patterns: recurring problems, common delighters, unmet needs, workarounds.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Report Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run rolling synthesis from day 3, not batch at study end. Late synthesis loses the chance to add follow-up probes while participants are still active.</statement>
      <rationale>Diary entries become the interview script for exit interviews. Themes identified early can generate targeted follow-up questions. Waiting until end produces a comprehensive analysis of an unprobed dataset.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/synthesis.md">Analysis synthesis skeleton: participation summary, theme blocks with verbatim quotes, temporal patterns, recommendations.</reference>
    <list>
      <item>Executive summary: key findings (3-5 bullets) and top recommendations.</item>
      <item>Method: study design, participant profile, data collection details.</item>
      <item>Findings: themes with evidence, temporal patterns, context patterns, quantitative summary.</item>
      <item>Recommendations: prioritized actions with evidence and success metrics.</item>
      <item>Appendix: full data, additional quotes, methodology details including bias mitigations.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
