<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-antipatterns" title="Diary Study Analysis Antipatterns">
  <summary>Five common analysis failures that undermine diary study validity: cherry-picking, ignoring outliers, losing context, over-quantifying, and confirmation bias.</summary>

  <section title="Cherry-Picking">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reporting only positive or interesting findings and omitting negative or null results.</description>
      <reason>Selective reporting produces recommendations that solve interesting problems rather than the most frequent or severe ones. Stakeholders make investment decisions on incomplete evidence and are surprised when predicted improvements do not materialize.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Report all findings, including null results and findings that contradict the research hypothesis. Document the evidence base for each finding, not just the finding itself.</statement>
      <rationale>The credibility of diary study research depends on the complete evidence record. A researcher who reports only supportive evidence is doing advocacy, not research.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Ignoring Outliers">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Excluding extreme or unusual participant experiences because they are "edge cases" without examining what causes them.</description>
      <reason>Outlier participants often reveal failure modes that affect a larger segment of users who simply do not voice their experience. A participant who fails dramatically often shows you what will happen at scale when less vocal users encounter the same condition.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Losing Context">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Analyzing entries as isolated data points without tracking the individual participant's journey over time.</description>
      <reason>A single negative entry from a participant who was positive on days 1-6 carries completely different meaning than the same entry from a participant who was negative throughout. Context-free analysis produces themes that misrepresent the actual experience trajectory.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always analyze at two levels: per-participant journey (individual arc) and cross-participant theme (aggregate pattern). Never report only aggregate themes without individual journey context.</statement>
      <rationale>Individual journey analysis catches the timing of experience change (when does positive turn negative). Aggregate analysis alone cannot reveal turning points.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Over-Quantifying">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Reducing all diary data to counts and averages and reporting only quantitative metrics without representative quotes.</description>
      <reason>Diary studies produce rich qualitative data because participants self-report in their own language. Converting all of it to frequency counts discards the behavioral detail and contextual nuance that differentiates diary studies from surveys.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Confirmation Bias">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Running the coding pass with the research hypothesis visible in the coding prompt, causing the coder to force entries into hypothesis-confirming categories.</description>
      <reason>LLM coding agents amplify confirmation bias when the prompt mentions a hypothesis upfront. The agent treats the hypothesis as a prior and interprets ambiguous entries as supporting it. This produces an inflated apparent confirmation rate.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <rule>
      <statement>Run the entry coding pass blind to prior hypotheses. Strip all hypothesis text from the coder prompt. Expose hypotheses only to the final synthesizer, and require it to report entries that contradict each hypothesis explicitly.</statement>
      <rationale>Blind coding is the standard for inter-rater reliability. The synthesizer's job is to assess whether the coded evidence supports, contradicts, or is neutral to each hypothesis — not to confirm them.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
