<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="diary-study-execution Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for diary-study-execution as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Reporting only positive or interesting findings and omitting negative or null results.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Selective reporting produces recommendations that solve interesting problems rather than the most frequent or severe ones. Stakeholders make investment decisions on incomplete evidence and are surprised when predicted improvements do not materialize.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Excluding extreme or unusual participant experiences because they are "edge cases" without examining what causes them.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Outlier participants often reveal failure modes that affect a larger segment of users who simply do not voice their experience. A participant who fails dramatically often shows you what will happen at scale when less vocal users encounter the same condition.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Analyzing entries as isolated data points without tracking the individual participant's journey over time.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A single negative entry from a participant who was positive on days 1-6 carries completely different meaning than the same entry from a participant who was negative throughout. Context-free analysis produces themes that misrepresent the actual experience trajectory.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Reducing all diary data to counts and averages and reporting only quantitative metrics without representative quotes.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Diary studies produce rich qualitative data because participants self-report in their own language. Converting all of it to frequency counts discards the behavioral detail and contextual nuance that differentiates diary studies from surveys.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Running the coding pass with the research hypothesis visible in the coding prompt, causing the coder to force entries into hypothesis-confirming categories.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>LLM coding agents amplify confirmation bias when the prompt mentions a hypothesis upfront. The agent treats the hypothesis as a prior and interprets ambiguous entries as supporting it. This produces an inflated apparent confirmation rate.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
