<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-reliability-security" title="Helm Chart Reliability and Security">
  <summary>Production checklist: HPA, PodDisruptionBudget, anti-affinity, health probes, and non-root security context — the gaps found in 83% of popular charts.</summary>

  <section title="Reliability Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set HPA minReplicas &gt;= 2. Never set minReplicas to 1 for production services.</statement>
      <rationale>minReplicas=1 defeats high availability: when the single pod is evicted or the node is drained, the service has zero replicas until HPA reacts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define PodDisruptionBudget with minAvailable=2 (or maxUnavailable=1) for all stateless services.</statement>
      <rationale>Without PDB, node drain during upgrades can evict all replicas simultaneously causing outage. PDB prevents the cluster from removing too many pods at once.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/hpa.yaml">HPA template</reference>
    <reference path="templates/pdb.yaml">PDB template</reference>
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure pod anti-affinity (soft by default, hard for critical services) to spread pods across nodes and zones.</statement>
      <rationale>Without anti-affinity, the scheduler may place all replicas on one node; a node failure takes the entire service down.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define all three probes: livenessProbe, readinessProbe, and startupProbe for slow-starting applications.</statement>
      <rationale>livenessProbe restarts deadlocked containers. readinessProbe prevents traffic to pods not yet ready. startupProbe prevents liveness from killing slow-start containers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always define resource requests and limits. Use configChecksum annotations to trigger pod restart when ConfigMap or Secret changes.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing requests break scheduling decisions. Without checksum annotations, config changes require manual rollout.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set runAsNonRoot: true, readOnlyRootFilesystem: true, allowPrivilegeEscalation: false, and drop ALL capabilities in securityContext.</statement>
      <rationale>Root containers can escape to the host. Read-only filesystem prevents runtime modification. Capability drop minimizes attack surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
securityContext:
  allowPrivilegeEscalation: false
  readOnlyRootFilesystem: true
  runAsNonRoot: true
  runAsUser: 1000
  capabilities:
    drop:
      - ALL
]]></code>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Enable NetworkPolicy to restrict ingress to only ingress-controller and same-namespace pods. Allow egress for DNS (UDP 53) and same-namespace pods.</statement>
      <rationale>Without NetworkPolicy, any compromised pod in the cluster can reach your service directly, bypassing ingress rules.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Create a dedicated ServiceAccount with automountServiceAccountToken: false unless the application needs the K8s API.</statement>
      <rationale>Default service account token is mounted automatically and can be used for cluster API access if the container is compromised.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Upgrade Safety">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always use --atomic flag for helm upgrade in CI/CD. Set --timeout appropriately. Configure rolling update strategy.</statement>
      <rationale>--atomic rolls back automatically on failure, preventing partial upgrades. Without it, a failed upgrade leaves the release in a broken state.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using helm upgrade without --atomic in CI/CD.</description>
      <reason>A failed upgrade without --atomic leaves the release in a degraded state requiring manual intervention. --atomic ensures clean rollback.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
