<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Weekly Cadence Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Solo Weekly Cadence Template application MUST enforce, plus a terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="two-artifacts-only" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each weekly run MUST produce exactly two artefacts: a `week-note` (what happened, what was learned) and a `next-week-plan` (≤5 items with explicit cuts). More than two = drift; fewer = no record.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo operator rhythm research">Solo operator rhythm research — anchors Solo Weekly Cadence Template rule `two-artifacts-only`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="four-mandatory-inputs" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sunday review MUST read these four inputs in order: KPI dashboard delta, last-week plan items pass/fail, support-inbox themes, backlog top-10. Skipping any input invalidates the run.</statement>
      <rationale source="Reviewed against solo-operator field reports">Reviewed against solo-operator field reports — anchors Solo Weekly Cadence Template rule `four-mandatory-inputs`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="memory-hook-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The week-note MUST close with a one-line &apos;next-week-watch&apos; that the following Sunday explicitly checks. No memory hook = each week is independent and the cadence stops compounding.</statement>
      <rationale source="Compounding-decision practice">Compounding-decision practice — anchors Solo Weekly Cadence Template rule `memory-hook-required`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sixty-minute-timebox" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Total time-box is 60 minutes: 30 min Sunday review + 30 min Monday prime. Overruns force a cut, not an extension; recurring overruns trigger a scope review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Calendar-discipline research">Calendar-discipline research — anchors Solo Weekly Cadence Template rule `sixty-minute-timebox`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="no-catchup-restart" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Three or more consecutive skipped weeks trigger a clean restart, not a retroactive catch-up. Retro-fill diaries are documentation, not signal.</statement>
      <rationale source="Habit-formation literature">Habit-formation literature — anchors Solo Weekly Cadence Template rule `no-catchup-restart`.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition or triggered skip, then route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology hygiene">Mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
