<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="North Star Metric Design Failure Modes" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 antipatterns from real deployments. Each pairs symptom + root cause + concrete fix.</summary>
  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern id="fm-anonymous-owner" severity="high">
      <symptom>Owner field set to &apos;team&apos;, &apos;us&apos;, &apos;tbd&apos;, or left blank. No one can be paged when the artefact drifts.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Agent declined to commit a named person because the brief didn&apos;t supply one.</root-cause>
      <fix>Reject the artefact. Require a single email / handle before persisting. If unknown, halt and ask the operator.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-fabricated-fields" severity="high">
      <symptom>Evidence array empty; field values plausible but not in the source brief / transcript / dashboard.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Model substituted statistical priors for real inputs.</root-cause>
      <fix>Reject. Require ≥1 verbatim citation per non-trivial field before persisting.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-prose-overrides-schema" severity="medium">
      <symptom>Field declared as list/dict in the schema receives a paragraph of prose instead.</symptom>
      <root-cause>LLM defaults to free-form prose when the prompt does not pin the structural type.</root-cause>
      <fix>Convert to the declared structured type. If ambiguous, reject and re-emit with explicit schema reminder.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-auto-approval" severity="high">
      <symptom>Agent sets status=&apos;approved&apos; on the North Star Metric Design output without any named human reviewer.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Agent treated &apos;I checked it&apos; as approval.</root-cause>
      <fix>Downgrade to &apos;ready_for_review&apos;. Block binding actions until a named reviewer signs off.</fix>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern id="fm-stale-carry-forward" severity="low">
      <symptom>Last cycle&apos;s values copied verbatim even though the source-of-truth has changed.</symptom>
      <root-cause>Cycle-N agent did not re-pull source.</root-cause>
      <fix>Re-pull from source-of-truth; mark carry-forward only if source_last_modified is unchanged.</fix>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
