<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-planning-steps" title="Business Analysis Planning: Six Steps and Approach Selection">
  <summary>Six-step BA planning procedure, approach-selection decision rules, elicitation technique table, and deliverable types.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Understand the Context">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before selecting an approach, answer four questions: what is the initiative scope, what type of change (new system/process/strategy), what is the organizational culture (formal vs. informal), and what constraints exist (time, budget, resources).</statement>
      <rationale>Approach selection without context produces plan-driven defaults for agile contexts and change-driven defaults for regulated projects — both are wrong. Context drives approach, not project phase or team preference.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Select Approach">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply this decision rule: if requirements clarity is high AND change frequency is low, select Plan-Driven; if clarity is low OR continuous discovery is active, select Change-Driven; otherwise select Hybrid and declare per-artifact which is baselined vs. living.</statement>
      <rationale>Plan-Driven vs. Change-Driven is not a team culture preference — it is a function of requirements uncertainty. The Hybrid case requires explicit artifact classification to prevent silent drift toward one extreme.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Plan-Driven — upfront baseline, sequential phases, extensive documentation; for stable regulatory or fixed-scope initiatives.</item>
      <item>Change-Driven — iterative, adaptive, just-enough documentation; for continuous discovery or evolving requirements.</item>
      <item>Hybrid — combination; declare each artifact as baselined (e.g., BRD v1.0) or living (e.g., stakeholder list) at plan time.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Identify Stakeholders">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a hidden-stakeholders review step covering: legal, infosec, procurement, works council/union, accessibility, downstream API consumers. The most common BA planning failure is missing a stakeholder discovered during elicitation.</statement>
      <rationale>Hidden stakeholders discovered after elicitation begins trigger scope changes that invalidate the plan; finding them at planning time costs a single conversation vs. re-elicitation, re-documentation, and re-validation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Sponsors — executives providing resources and authority.</item>
      <item>Users — direct solution users (employees, customers, partners).</item>
      <item>Implementers — team building the solution (developers, architects).</item>
      <item>Regulators — compliance bodies with mandatory requirements.</item>
      <item>Support — operations, help desk, maintenance teams.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Plan Elicitation Activities">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track actual vs. planned elicitation effort in a CSV alongside the plan and recalibrate every two weeks; the first estimate is always wrong because "1 workshop" hides 4 hours of prep, 2 hours of facilitation, and 6 hours of synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale>Elicitation effort is the most consistently underestimated BA activity; without actuals tracking, every plan iteration repeats the same underestimate and projects run over.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Interviews — for deep understanding of individual stakeholder needs.</item>
      <item>Workshops — for consensus building across multiple stakeholders in one session.</item>
      <item>Surveys — for broad input from many stakeholders when scheduling is infeasible.</item>
      <item>Observation — for process understanding when stated behavior differs from actual behavior.</item>
      <item>Document Analysis — for understanding existing state from existing artifacts.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Define Deliverables">
    <rule>
      <statement>Tie every BA activity to a deliverable ID (DEL-03) and every deliverable to a requirement set; this enables traceability querying and makes the plan auditable.</statement>
      <rationale>A plan with activities but no deliverable IDs cannot answer "what did the BA produce and when?" — the question every programme audit asks first.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Establish Governance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Name a single human approver in the BA Approach Document frontmatter (approver: name@domain) and enforce via CODEOWNERS; without a named approver the plan is unverifiable and unauditable.</statement>
      <rationale>BABOK v3 ch. 3 treats governance as mandatory, not optional; a plan without decision authority is a suggestion, and suggestions have no binding power over scope, timeline, or deliverable quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Who approves requirements — named role, not generic "leadership".</item>
      <item>How changes are handled — change request process with an owner.</item>
      <item>Review and sign-off cadence — specific schedule, not "as needed".</item>
      <item>Escalation path — defined chain when approval is blocked.</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/ba-approach-document.md">BA Approach Document with YAML frontmatter for all governance fields</reference>
  </section>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Governance section contains vague text ("approval by leadership") instead of named roles.</description>
    <reason>No named approver means no accountability; auditors and stakeholders cannot determine who has authority, and the BA cannot obtain binding sign-off.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
