<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ba-planning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ba-planning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Governance section contains vague text ("approval by leadership") instead of named roles.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>No named approver means no accountability; auditors and stakeholders cannot determine who has authority, and the BA cannot obtain binding sign-off.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM defaults to Plan-Driven for all engagements regardless of context flags.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Models anchor on whichever sample plan they last produced; always pass the engagement model and culture flags in the system prompt and validate that the output's approach matches the decision rule output for the given inputs.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent invents plausible-sounding stakeholders ("Director of UX Excellence") not present in the actual org chart.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Hallucinated stakeholders produce engagement plans with no real recipients; constrain to a stakeholder_seed list and flag additions as TODO(reason), not as entries.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent produces time estimates in the plan ("Discovery: 4 weeks").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Per repo policy, no time estimates in SDD docs; strip any time estimate from agent output and replace with complexity tier (S/M/L). Time estimates are inherently unreliable and create false expectations.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent conflates BA Planning with Project Planning, producing Gantt charts for BA activities.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>BA Planning covers analysis activities only; schedule integration and resource management belong to the project-manager skill. Mixing them produces a document that satisfies neither purpose.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
