<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Freelance Proposal Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>8 testable rules with rationale + source for freelance-proposal-template. Includes terminal skip-this-methodology rule.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="scope-envelope-explicit" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Proposal MUST contain a scope envelope: WHAT IS INCLUDED, WHAT IS EXCLUDED. Exclusions section is mandatory; absent exclusions is a forbidden pattern.</statement>
      <rationale source="Fixed-bid scope-control research">Fixed-bid scope-control research — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="assumptions-listed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each assumption the bid depends on MUST be listed with a confirm-by date; un-confirmed assumptions auto-trigger renegotiation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Assumption-management practice">Assumption-management practice — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="milestones-cap-payment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Payment is broken into at least three milestones; final milestone is at most 30% of total to align incentives.</statement>
      <rationale source="Freelance cash-flow research">Freelance cash-flow research — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="change-request-rate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Proposal pins a change-request hourly rate (usually 1.5× base rate) and a minimum block (often 1 hour); scope-creep is priced, not absorbed.</statement>
      <rationale source="Outsource governance practice">Outsource governance practice — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="late-payment-clause" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Late payment beyond NET-30 incurs interest at a stated rate; work pauses at NET-45.</statement>
      <rationale source="Freelance payment-protection practice">Freelance payment-protection practice — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="ip-ownership-on-payment" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>IP transfers to the client only upon final payment; pre-payment, all work remains the BA's IP.</statement>
      <rationale source="IP transfer best practice">IP transfer best practice — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="withdrawal-clause" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Proposal expires in 14 days; after that, terms (rate, availability) may change without notice.</statement>
      <rationale source="Sales-cycle hygiene">Sales-cycle hygiene — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If you are not bidding fixed-scope freelance work, return `skipped`.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology applicability">Methodology applicability — applies to Freelance Proposal Template.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml" />
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml" />
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml" />
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml" />
  </see-also>
</text>
