<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="feedback-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for feedback-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lock the taxonomy in a versioned file. Treat taxonomy changes as schema migrations: write a migration script and re-tag existing items before applying.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Taxonomy drift produces categorization inconsistency over time, making trend analysis unreliable. Versioning makes changes auditable and reversible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Weight feedback by ARR or segment, not raw mention count. One enterprise complaint can outweigh 50 free-tier votes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Volume bias: vocal free users post many tickets; at-risk enterprise accounts may post zero. Raw count ranking optimizes for the wrong population.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always store the verbatim alongside structured fields. Never lose the original quote.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Agent rewrites lose intent signals. Original wording reveals tone, context, and use case that structured fields cannot capture.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Auto-responding without human review is a brand risk. Default mode = draft and queue; human approves before send.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Wrong close-loop email (wrong feature attributed to wrong user, incorrect status) destroys trust harder than no email at all.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a quarterly drift audit: sample 50 LLM-categorized items, have a human re-tag, measure agreement rate. If below 80%, retrain or update the prompt.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLM categorization drifts as product evolves and language patterns change. Without periodic audit, the taxonomy gradually loses meaning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use embedding similarity (cosine &gt;= 0.85) for deduplication, not full-text match. Paraphrases of the same issue are the same issue.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Naive full-text dedup misses paraphrases. Counting "search is slow" and "search takes forever" as two separate requests undercounts the true signal by half.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Three mandatory human checkpoints: (1) before any outbound message, (2) before promoting feedback cluster to roadmap item, (3) before changing taxonomy.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Each of these has irreversible effects: sent email cannot be unsent, roadmap items create expectations, taxonomy changes invalidate historical analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
