<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Service Ownership Map Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules every service-ownership map must satisfy so triage tools can route alerts to a named human without ambiguity.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The map MUST be a single checked-in file (YAML or JSON) under version control; no wiki pages, no spreadsheets, no Notion docs as authoritative.</statement>
      <rationale>Triage routing needs a service→owner map; if the artefact lives in tribal knowledge it goes stale within a quarter. Version control gives diff history, code review, and machine-readable parsing for the alerting tool.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[# services.yaml — checked in at ops/services.yaml
services:
  checkout-api:
    primary_owner: "@alex.kim"
    escalation: "@team-payments"
    slack: "#payments-alerts"
    runbook: "https://wiki/runbooks/checkout-api"]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Each service entry MUST name a single primary_owner (handle of one human) plus exactly one escalation handle (team or named secondary). No bare "team" without a handle.</statement>
      <rationale>Plural ownership = no ownership. P6 teams repeatedly rediscover that "@platform" channels go unanswered at 02:00 unless one human owns the page.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The map MUST be refreshed on every service create/rename/retire and reviewed quarterly; entries with last_reviewed &gt;90 days fail CI.</statement>
      <rationale>Ownership maps decay fastest of any infra artefact (people leave, teams reorg). Forcing a CI failure converts decay from invisible to visible.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The alerting tool MUST consume the map programmatically (via Sentry "owners" file, Datadog tag, or webhook lookup) — never via copy-paste into the tool UI.</statement>
      <rationale>Manual sync between two sources guarantees drift. A single ingestion path keeps the file authoritative.</rationale>
      <example type="bad">
        <description>Engineer edits Datadog monitor "notify" field directly in the UI while services.yaml says someone else.</description>
        <reason>Two sources of truth → triage routes to the stale UI value; the on-call owner in YAML never learns the alert fired.</reason>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every entry MUST link to a runbook URL that exists and renders; broken runbook links fail CI.</statement>
      <rationale>A named owner with no runbook still wastes triage time at 02:00. Pairing the two converts "who do I page" into "who do I page AND what do they do first".</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
