<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="MoSCoW Framework: Categories and Rules">
  <summary>Defines the four MoSCoW categories, the fail-test for Must Have, and the 60/20/20 effort allocation rule.</summary>

  <section title="Category Definitions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Must Have: items that, if absent, cause the product to fail completely. Apply the fail-test verbatim — "if we don't have this, does the product work?" A "yes" means it is not Must.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a binary test, teams default to calling everything Must. The fail-test forces explicit articulation of the viability condition per item.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Should Have: important but not critical. A reasonable workaround exists. Users can accomplish their goals without it, but the experience degrades noticeably.</statement>
      <rationale>The workaround test distinguishes Should from Must. If the answer is "users can still proceed," it is Should.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Could Have: nice-to-have enhancements with low cost. First category to cut when Must+Should exceed capacity. Absence does not affect core functionality.</statement>
      <rationale>Explicit "first to cut" designation protects Must and Should from false trade-offs when capacity is tight.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Won't Have: explicitly excluded from this release. Document every Won't item with a one-line reason and optionally a future-release target.</statement>
      <rationale>Won't Have is the framework's primary scope defense. Undocumented exclusions re-enter as scope creep. The discomfort of writing Won't is the value of the exercise.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Capacity Allocation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Must Have must target 60% of capacity. Must + Should must not exceed 80%. The remaining 20% absorbs Could items or overflow.</statement>
      <rationale>Empirical heuristic from DSDM. If Must alone exceeds 60%, the release is over-scoped before a single Should item is considered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always require a capacity number before running MoSCoW. Without a timebox (eng-weeks, person-days, or sprint budget), categories are meaningless — you are producing a wish list, not a prioritization.</statement>
      <rationale>MoSCoW categories are release-scoped, not absolute. The same feature can be Must in one release and Won't in the next depending on capacity and goal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Must Inflation Prevention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Force at least one item into Won't Have per session. If every item passes the fail-test, the fail-test is being applied too loosely — reapply with a contrarian perspective.</statement>
      <rationale>Must inflation is the universal failure mode. A contrarian re-application ("a competitor ships without this and wins — still Must?") surfaces weak Musts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Invoice app MVP: "User authentication" passes fail-test — the product cannot work at all without identity. Must Have.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>"Password reset" is often called Must, but users can use support as a workaround. Should Have is correct unless compliance requires it.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
</text>
