<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="MoSCoW 6-Step Process">
  <summary>Sequential steps for running a MoSCoW session from requirement gathering to locked categories.</summary>

  <section title="Process Steps">
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 1 — List all requirements from stakeholder requests, user research, technical needs, and competitive analysis. Do not pre-filter.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-filtering before categorization embeds hidden prioritization. The full list enables transparent trade-offs.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 2 — Define the timebox explicitly: time horizon ("this sprint", "this quarter"), team capacity in person-days, and any budget constraints. Announce the number before categorization begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a published capacity number, participants anchor categories to desires rather than constraints.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 3 — Initial categorization: for each item, apply the four questions in order: (1) fails without it? → Must; (2) painful but workable without? → Should; (3) nice but not needed? → Could; (4) out of scope? → Won't.</statement>
      <rationale>Ordered questions prevent skipping directly to Could or Won't for items that should be Must.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 4 — Validate effort allocation. Sum effort per category. If Must + Should exceeds 80% of capacity, move Should items to Could, Could to Won't. Never move Must to Should.</statement>
      <rationale>The allocation check is the only mechanism that enforces scope discipline after categorization. Skipping it produces a MoSCoW list that still overflows capacity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 5 — Stakeholder alignment: share categorization, surface disagreements, document decisions and rationale. Every Must item needs explicit stakeholder sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale>Unresolved categorization disagreements resurface as mid-sprint scope changes. Documenting decisions creates the accountability record.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Step 6 — Lock and track. Lock Must and Won't after sign-off — changes require escalation. Should and Could remain editable. Re-run MoSCoW per release, not per quarter.</statement>
      <rationale>Locking Must prevents "just one more Must" additions. Locking Won't prevents scope creep from excluded items being re-introduced without a full re-prioritization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/moscow-matrix.md">MoSCoW matrix template for documenting categories with effort tracking</reference>
  <reference path="templates/moscow-capacity-validator.sh">Bash capacity validator to check Must+Should proportion</reference>
</text>
