<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="feature-prioritization-moscow Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for feature-prioritization-moscow as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Must inflation: 60-80% of items end up categorized as Must Have.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The fail-test is applied loosely. Teams interpret "important" as "must." Without a contrarian pass, no item survives downgrade to Should.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>No Won't Have category. Teams skip documenting exclusions because it is uncomfortable.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Won't Have is the primary mechanism for preventing scope creep. An empty Won't list means every excluded item is implicitly negotiable, re-entering as "just one more thing."</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>No timebox declared. MoSCoW session runs without a stated capacity number.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Without capacity as a constraint, categories reflect desires rather than trade-offs. The 60/20/20 allocation cannot be validated, so the output is a wishlist, not a scoped plan.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Treating the 60/20/20 allocation as a law rather than a heuristic, and using it to mechanically assign exact effort budgets.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The allocation is a directional check. Forcing exactly 60% Must effort produces false precision. The check is: "are Must+Should within 80%?" not "is Must exactly 60%?"</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Changing Must Have items mid-sprint without escalation. PMs add scope by re-categorizing Could items as Must.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Must changes after lockdown destroy the entire value of the exercise. Every Must change must require explicit stakeholder escalation and re-validation of capacity allocation.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Using MoSCoW for long-horizon roadmaps (more than one quarter).</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>MoSCoW categories are release-scoped. Over a quarter, business context shifts enough that Must items become irrelevant and Won't items become Must. Rerun per release, not per quarter.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
