<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-error-handling" title="Error Handling and Rate Limiting">
  <summary>Common Google Ads API error codes, retry-with-exponential-backoff pattern, and per-day token-bucket rate limiter.</summary>

  <section title="Common Error Codes">
    <list>
      <item>AUTHENTICATION_ERROR — invalid credentials; check tokens, refresh OAuth</item>
      <item>AUTHORIZATION_ERROR — insufficient permissions; verify account access</item>
      <item>REQUEST_ERROR — malformed request; check request structure</item>
      <item>QUOTA_ERROR — rate limit exceeded; implement exponential backoff</item>
      <item>INTERNAL_ERROR — server error; retry with backoff</item>
      <item>RESOURCE_NOT_FOUND — invalid resource name; verify resource exists before mutating</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Retry Policy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Retry QUOTA_ERROR and INTERNAL_ERROR with exponential backoff (initial delay 1s, multiply by 2, max 3 attempts); never retry AUTHENTICATION_ERROR or AUTHORIZATION_ERROR.</statement>
      <rationale>Quota and internal errors are transient. Auth errors will not resolve without intervention and retrying them wastes quota and delays diagnosis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Retrying quota errors in a tight loop without backoff delay.</description>
      <reason>Tight-loop retries on quota errors hammer the limit further, guaranteeing that all subsequent calls in the same window also fail.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <reference path="templates/daily-runner.py">Daily runner with exponential backoff on quota errors and hard fail on non-retryable errors</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Rate Limiting">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track API calls with a per-day token bucket (max 15,000 operations/day for Basic Access); share the bucket across all workers for the same account.</statement>
      <rationale>Basic Access tier has a 15,000 operations/day limit per account. Reporting agents pulling data hourly can consume the daily limit before mutation agents can execute.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/rate-limiter.py">Thread-safe per-day token bucket rate limiter for Google Ads API</reference>
  </section>
</text>
