<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Architect PR Review Checklist Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every architect-pr-review-checklist application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-six-section-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every architect review MUST address all six sections relevant to the PR: (1) Module boundaries, (2) Public contracts (APIs, events, schemas), (3) Data flow (sources, transformations, sinks), (4) Failure modes (errors, retries, fallbacks), (5) Performance budget, (6) Security posture. A section is "addressed" with one of: pass / fail / N/A-with-reason. Skipping a section silently is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Software Architecture: The Hard Parts (Richards/Ford), architectural decision research">Architects who go line-by-line miss architectural issues. Architects who skim miss the same issues but faster. Six-section coverage forces the right altitude — the things only an architect can catch.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-fifteen-min-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The review SHOULD complete in 15 minutes for a typical PR (&lt;= 500 lines changed). If the PR cannot be reviewed in 15 min, the PR is too large — request a split. Splitting is a valid review outcome, NOT a failure to review.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google Eng Practices, code-review time-distribution research">Reviews longer than 60 min show steeply declining defect-finding rate. PRs that are too large get rubber-stamped even by senior reviewers. The 15-min cap on architect review is achievable because the scope is architectural surface, not every line.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-escalate-not-stall" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If a finding has cross-team or strategic implications (e.g., introduces a new framework, breaks a public API, costs significant infra), the architect ESCALATES the PR to a broader architecture discussion rather than blocking it in review comments. The PR is paused (status=needs-architecture-discussion), not iteratively reviewed.</statement>
      <rationale source="ADR practice, ICR (Inverse Conway) literature">Stalling a big decision in PR comments produces multi-day ping-pong with no resolution. Escalation forces a 30-min ADR conversation, after which the PR either lands or gets restructured with a documented decision. Faster + better record.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-ai-generated-flag" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the PR is partially or fully AI-generated (Claude, Cursor, Copilot, etc.), the review MUST explicitly check for AI-specific failure modes: hallucinated APIs (function names that don't exist in the actual library), missing error paths (AI defaults to happy path), boilerplate inflation (unnecessary abstraction), and pattern drift (style/naming that doesn't match the codebase). Mark each as checked.</statement>
      <rationale source="Empirical studies of LLM code (Hendel, Anthropic internal eval data, Google AI Code Review reports)">AI-generated code has a distinctive failure surface that overlaps with but is not identical to human-written code. Treating it like human code misses the AI-specific bugs; treating it as "all bad" misses the genuine value. Specific checks catch the specific defects.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-adr-honoring" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For each section finding, the reviewer must reference the relevant ADR (if one exists) or note "no ADR governs this; consider documenting if pattern recurs". Findings that contradict an ADR MUST either propose an ADR update OR block the PR — silent contradictions ("we'll deal with it later") are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ADR maintenance research, organizational learning literature">Silent ADR violations decay the ADR system: future developers see contradictory code and assume the ADR is dead. Forcing either explicit update or block keeps the ADR system honest and useful.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-23 chunk-00 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
