<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="BA Methodologies Detail Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the methodologies-detail methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 1 (classify ask): Determine which of the 12 frameworks the ask requires.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the classify ask gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 2 (select frameworks): Lock the framework set; document why each.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the select frameworks gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 3 (emit deliverables): Generate template skeletons; assign owners + due.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the emit deliverables gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 4 (fill and review): Per-framework SME fills; peer review against checklist.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the fill and review gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 5 (publish): Commit to version control; link from KA routing record.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the publish gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for methodologies-detail do not hold, do not apply this methodology; route to an alternative as the decision tree suggests.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Methodologies misapplied to wrong contexts create overhead without value; explicit skip preserves the agent's budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
