<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-framework" title="Cost Estimation Framework">
  <summary>Five-step process for building a defensible cost baseline: categorize costs, estimate bottom-up, apply PERT uncertainty, add risk-driven contingency, and separate management reserve.</summary>

  <section title="Cost Categories">
    <rule>
      <statement>Classify every cost line into one of four categories before summing: direct, indirect, fixed, variable.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing categories causes budget gaps; indirect costs (overhead, management) are the most-often forgotten and typically add 30-50% above direct labor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Direct: salaries, contractors, software licenses. Indirect: office overhead, utilities, management loading. Fixed: base salaries, subscriptions. Variable: overtime, cloud usage, contractor hours.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 1: Bottom-Up Estimation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Estimate each WBS work package independently: identify roles, apply hours, multiply by fully-loaded rate (salary x 1.3-1.8 depending on tax jurisdiction).</statement>
      <rationale>Bottom-up is more accurate than analogical or parametric when scope is known; it forces explicit decomposition that surfaces missing work packages.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always cite the source of every rate (vendor quote, internal rate card version, market survey). Reject any estimate line that lacks a rate source.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs and humans both invent plausible rates; without a source the number cannot be defended or audited.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Three-Point PERT Estimation">
    <rule>
      <statement>For uncertain cost lines, collect three estimates (Optimistic, Most Likely, Pessimistic) and compute Expected = (O + 4M + P) / 6.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-point estimates anchor on optimistic outcomes; PERT forces acknowledgment of the worst case and weights the most-likely scenario correctly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>If Pessimistic / Most Likely is less than 1.8, flag the estimate for human review — pessimistic values are systematically underestimated.</statement>
      <rationale>Anchoring bias causes humans and LLMs to set pessimistic estimates too close to most-likely; a ratio below 1.8 is a signal the tail risk was not considered.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Cloud hosting 3-point: O=$200/mo, M=$350/mo, P=$800/mo. Expected = (200 + 4x350 + 800) / 6 = $400/mo. Ratio P/M = 2.3, passes the review gate.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Contingency Reserve (Known Unknowns)">
    <rule>
      <statement>Size contingency reserve using the risk register: sum each open risk's (probability x impact), then round up. Do not use a flat percentage.</statement>
      <rationale>Flat percentages (10-15%) ignore actual risk distribution; risk-driven reserves are defensible to sponsors and scale correctly with project uncertainty.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Guidance when no risk register exists: 10-15% for well-defined scope; 20-25% for innovative projects; 30-40% for high-uncertainty work. These are starting points, not substitutes for a register.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Contingency reserve is PM-controlled; document it in the Cost Baseline. Management reserve is sponsor-controlled and stays outside the baseline.</statement>
      <rationale>Blending the two removes the governance layer that protects the project from scope escalation without authorization.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Cost Baseline and BAC">
    <rule>
      <statement>Cost Baseline = Direct Costs + Indirect Costs + Contingency Reserve. BAC = Cost Baseline + Management Reserve.</statement>
      <rationale>Standard PMI formula; separating the two allows EVM tracking (CPI, SPI) against the baseline while keeping major-scope buffer separate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-baseline at every approved change-control event; version the baseline with the change-request ID.</statement>
      <rationale>Never letting the original estimate persist past a scope change is the only way to maintain a valid audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/pert_estimate.py">PERT mean, std-dev, P80, P95 from WBS JSON</reference>
  <reference path="templates/cost-worksheet.md">Full cost breakdown template</reference>
</text>
