<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Cost Estimation Examples and Anti-Patterns">
  <summary>Worked examples for SaaS MVP phased cost and solopreneur build-vs-buy analysis; common failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="SaaS MVP Phased Estimate">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Five-phase estimate: Discovery 2wks=$8,200; Design 2wks=$6,300; Development 8wks=$48,900; Testing 2wks=$8,300; Launch 1wk=$4,300. Subtotal=$76,000. Add 20% contingency=$15,200. Total=$91,200. Contingency sized at 20% because requirements are partially defined (innovative project band).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Solopreneur Build-vs-Buy">
    <rule>
      <statement>For solopreneurs, treat own time at market hourly rate as an explicit cost line; never mark it as "free".</statement>
      <rationale>Opportunity cost is real; 100 hours at $150/hr = $15,000. A SaaS at $99/mo x 12 = $1,188 often wins once the line is visible.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Build: 100 hours x $150 opportunity cost + $500 tools = $15,500. Buy: $99/mo x 12 + 5hr setup x $150 = $1,938. Decision: Buy unless building creates unique competitive advantage.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Patterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Salary equals total cost — applying no overhead multiplier to labor.</description>
      <reason>Employer taxes, benefits, and facilities add 30-50% above salary. Omitting them produces a baseline that is structurally underfunded from day one.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Flat contingency percentage applied without a risk register.</description>
      <reason>15% on a $500K project with three high-probability risks is likely insufficient; 15% on a low-risk maintenance project is padding. Risk-driven reserves calibrate to actual exposure.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Fixed price contract with variable scope.</description>
      <reason>Any scope addition without a corresponding price increase produces silent budget erosion that neither party acknowledges until it becomes a dispute.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Single-point estimates with no uncertainty range.</description>
      <reason>Empirically, software estimates are systematically optimistic by 50-100%. Without a pessimistic case, the cost baseline has no resilience to the most-likely outcome.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Re-estimating but not re-baselining after a scope change.</description>
      <reason>The original baseline remains the reference; EVM metrics compare against it even though scope changed, making all variance numbers meaningless.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="../earned-value-management/">Tracking cost performance against the baseline using CPI/SPI</link>
    <link path="../change-control/">Managing scope changes that trigger baseline updates</link>
  </see-also>
</text>
