<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="cost-estimation Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for cost-estimation as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Salary equals total cost — applying no overhead multiplier to labor.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Employer taxes, benefits, and facilities add 30-50% above salary. Omitting them produces a baseline that is structurally underfunded from day one.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Flat contingency percentage applied without a risk register.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>15% on a $500K project with three high-probability risks is likely insufficient; 15% on a low-risk maintenance project is padding. Risk-driven reserves calibrate to actual exposure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Fixed price contract with variable scope.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Any scope addition without a corresponding price increase produces silent budget erosion that neither party acknowledges until it becomes a dispute.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Single-point estimates with no uncertainty range.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Empirically, software estimates are systematically optimistic by 50-100%. Without a pessimistic case, the cost baseline has no resilience to the most-likely outcome.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Re-estimating but not re-baselining after a scope change.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The original baseline remains the reference; EVM metrics compare against it even though scope changed, making all variance numbers meaningless.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
