<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GCS and Cloud CDN Configuration Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>≥5 testable rules grounding the gcp-storage-cdn methodology, each paired with rationale and source reference.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="lifecycle-rules-mandatory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Set lifecycle rules on every production bucket: NEARLINE after 30 days idle, COLDLINE after 90, optionally ARCHIVE after 365.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Lifecycle rules are the single highest-leverage GCS cost lever; absence means full STANDARD cost forever.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="versioning-for-mutable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Enable object versioning on buckets that hold mutable critical data and cap retained versions at 3-5 via lifecycle.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Versioning is the cheap recovery path for accidental overwrite; uncapped versions become a runaway cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="retention-policy-write-once" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply a retention policy + bucket lock on regulated buckets (audit, finance, healthcare) sized to the legal hold period.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Bucket lock is the only WORM mechanism GCS exposes; retention policy without lock is advisory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="cdn-cache-key-strict" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>On Cloud CDN, set custom cache keys explicitly including host + path + query allow-list, never the default 'include everything'.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Loose cache keys split or duplicate cache entries — wrecking hit-rate and amplifying origin cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="signed-url-default" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Serve user-uploaded or sensitive assets via signed URLs / signed cookies with short expiry; never make those buckets public.</statement>
      <rationale source="faion-network methodology base v1.1">Public buckets are the dominant GCS leakage source; signed-URL flows are the documented safe default.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions in `Applies If` are not all true, do NOT run this methodology — return early with reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree's negative branch must terminate cleanly without partial output.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions hold AND scope is explicit, run the methodology end-to-end and produce the canonical artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 decision-tree contract">Decision tree positive-branch terminus; aliases the apply-end-to-end verdict.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
