<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="iac-patterns-dry Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for iac-patterns-dry. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ALL naming conventions, common tag maps, CIDR derivations, and environment conditionals MUST be defined in locals. Resource blocks reference locals, never raw variables or inline expressions.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Centralizing computed values in locals means a naming change requires one edit; scattered inline expressions mean N edits with N opportunities for drift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use for_each with a typed map when creating 2+ similar resources. NEVER use count for resources where the set membership can change — count-indexed resources shift when items are inserted or removed, forcing unnecessary destroy/recreate cycles.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">for_each assigns identity by map key; Terraform can add, remove, or update individual items without touching siblings. count-based addressing breaks on any insertion before the last element.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use dynamic blocks when a resource has N identical nested blocks that differ only in values. Define the block configuration as a list/map variable; the dynamic block iterates over it.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Hard-coded repeated nested blocks cannot be parameterized without copy-paste; dynamic blocks make the block set a first-class input to the module.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use Terragrunt generate blocks to produce provider.tf and backend.tf in every child directory from path-derived locals (environment, region, account_id). NEVER hand-write backend.tf or provider.tf per environment — any difference between environment configs must be explicit in the root terragrunt.hcl, not duplicated in leaf files.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A 10-environment project has 10 copies of provider.tf and backend.tf if written manually — the first time an org changes its AWS region or state bucket, 9 of 10 will be forgotten.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
