<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="cross-tool-migration Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for cross-tool-migration. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always run two loading passes: Pass 1 creates all issues and captures the source-ID to target-ID mapping. Pass 2 re-creates links (blocks, relates, parent-child) using the id-map. Single-pass migrations lose all issue relationships.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Issue links require both endpoints to exist before the link can be created; any migration that creates links in the same pass as issues will fail silently for any issue created after the linked issue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Define rollback triggers with hard thresholds before cutover: data loss detected = immediate rollback; critical integration failure = immediate; team productivity drop over 50 percent = 48-hour review; user adoption under 30 percent at one week = planned rollback. Do not roll back on vibes.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without pre-defined thresholds, rollback decisions are made under pressure with incomplete data; the threshold forces a structured assessment rather than a panic response.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Any field the mapping engine cannot match with confidence above a defined threshold must appear in a low_confidence list requiring human review before the load runs. Never silently drop or merge fields.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Silent field collapse is the most common cause of data integrity failures; "In QA" and "In Review" merged to "Review" looks correct but loses status granularity that teams depend on.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
