<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-phases-and-rules" title="Migration Phases and Execution Rules">
  <summary>Six-phase ETL process (Planning, Preparation, Pilot, Full Migration, Cutover, Stabilization), two-pass load rule, identity remapping requirement, read-only window, and rollback triggers.</summary>

  <section title="Six Phases">
    <p>Phase 1 Planning (2-4wks): stakeholder alignment, tool selection, scope definition, risk assessment. Phase 2 Preparation (2-3wks): target tool setup, field mapping design, test environment. Phase 3 Pilot (1-2wks): one project under 200 issues, validate, gather feedback, adjust. Phase 4 Full Migration (1-4wks): waves with validate-and-pause between each. Phase 5 Cutover (1wk): source read-only at T-4h, final sync, enable target, support. Phase 6 Stabilization (2-4wks): active support, fix issues, training, log lessons.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Pilot one project (under 200 issues) before any production wave. Pause for a retro between pilot and full migration; adjust the mapping design before proceeding.</statement>
      <rationale>Pilot failures are cheap; production-wave failures require rollback under pressure. The retro between phases is the quality gate that prevents small mapping errors from becoming bulk data loss.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Two-Pass Load Rule">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Always run two loading passes: Pass 1 creates all issues and captures the source-ID to target-ID mapping. Pass 2 re-creates links (blocks, relates, parent-child) using the id-map. Single-pass migrations lose all issue relationships.</statement>
      <rationale>Issue links require both endpoints to exist before the link can be created; any migration that creates links in the same pass as issues will fail silently for any issue created after the linked issue.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Identity Remapping">
    <rule>
      <statement>Build an explicit user identity map (email-based, not display-name-based) before loading. Get HR sign-off on the map before any load. Deactivated accounts must be resolved to an active substitute before the wave runs.</statement>
      <rationale>Display-name matching silently assigns issues to the wrong person when names conflict or when accounts share a display name. Email is the only unambiguous identifier across tools.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Read-Only Window and Cutover">
    <rule>
      <statement>Set source to read-only at T-4h before go-live, not T-0. Keep source live in read-only for 30 days minimum after cutover. Decommission only after no team has needed the source for 2 weeks.</statement>
      <rationale>T-0 read-only means last-minute writes are lost; T-4h provides a clean final-sync window. The 30-day read-only period is the rollback buffer — once decommissioned, data is unrecoverable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Auto-cutover (agent-declared go-live) is forbidden. The agent prepares and validates the runbook; a human types explicit confirmation before any cutover action executes.</statement>
      <rationale>Cutover is irreversible once source is set read-only and communications go out; auto-execution removes the final human verification that the system state is correct.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Rollback Triggers">
    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Define rollback triggers with hard thresholds before cutover: data loss detected = immediate rollback; critical integration failure = immediate; team productivity drop over 50% = 48-hour review; user adoption under 30% at one week = planned rollback. Do not roll back on vibes.</statement>
      <rationale>Without pre-defined thresholds, rollback decisions are made under pressure with incomplete data; the threshold forces a structured assessment rather than a panic response.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="scripts/migrate_dry_run.sh">Dry-run gate: extract, transform, count-diff, field-drift audit</reference>
  <reference path="templates/cutover-checklist.md">Cutover runbook from T-24h to T+1w</reference>
</text>
