<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="cross-tool-migration Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for cross-tool-migration as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent-fabricated field maps for unknown custom fields.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents produce plausible-sounding mappings (legacy_id to external_id) that are wrong; unmapped or pattern-matched fields must be reviewed by a human before any load.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Running full API load at maximum rate without backoff.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Vendor APIs throttle at sustained high rate (429 responses); agents misinterpret these as transient and burn token budget retrying. Implement exponential backoff in the engine, not in prompts.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>PII and credentials in migration exports not scrubbed before pushing to target.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Issues frequently contain pasted credentials, customer PII, and internal URLs; bulk migration amplifies one ticket's exposure across the entire corpus. Run a scrubber pass before any load.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Feeding the entire issue export into a single LLM prompt for mapping.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Long-context drift causes the model to lose accuracy on issues processed later in the window; page by 50–200 issues and let the engine hold full state, not the model.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
