<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules-and-gotchas" title="Continuous Discovery: Severity Rubric, Rules, and Gotchas">
  <summary>Severity rubric for signal prioritization, source-decay rules, anti-hallucination constraints, best practices, and AI-agent gotchas for continuous market scanning.</summary>

  <section title="Severity Rubric">
    <rule>
      <statement>Apply severity 0-5 to every signal: 5 = pricing/packaging move; 4 = positioning shift / new ICP; 3 = new feature in core wedge; 2 = peripheral feature; 1 = blog/PR; 0 = cosmetic.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a severity rubric, every blog post registers as "competitor activity" and buries severity-5 pricing moves in noise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Every severity-4+ signal must produce a "respond / monitor / ignore" decision in the next weekly cycle, written into threat-board.md.</statement>
      <rationale>A continuously scanned market that nobody acts on becomes a research graveyard and burns tokens without strategic value.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Source-Health Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a quarterly source-health audit. When a source goes 30 days without change or returns errors 3 consecutive runs, escalate to human audit and log in dead-source.md.</statement>
      <rationale>SaaS competitors disable RSS, hide changelogs behind login, and move to gated Slack — the scan rots silently without detection.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Capture pricing from at least 2 geos + logged-out + incognito. Require ≥2 geo confirmations before flagging a price change.</statement>
      <rationale>Pricing pages A/B-test by region and cookie — single-shot scrapes give a misleading reading.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Diff content blocks, not raw DOM. Use readability/trafilatura extraction before diffing to strip nav, footer, and cookie banners.</statement>
      <rationale>Boilerplate generates 90% of false-positive diffs; full-DOM diff makes cosmetic CSS changes register as full-page changes.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Anti-Hallucination Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pin one strategic Outcome before any scan. Without it, agents track 40 competitors instead of the 5 that move the SOM.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents cheerfully expand scope unless capped by an explicit outcome anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a versioned competitor-registry.json. All additions/removals via PR — never silent edits — to tie signals to stable competitor_id values.</statement>
      <rationale>Signal correlation across cadences requires stable IDs; silent registry edits break the audit trail.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Gotchas">
    <antipattern>
      <description>LLM hallucinating competitor pricing or changelog entries when scrapes fail, reporting "$49 → $99 price hike" without a source.</description>
      <reason>Without source_url + fetched_at + raw_hash triple enforced at schema level, fabricated diffs are indistinguishable from real ones. Enforce the triple and reject completions missing any field.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Daily haiku watchers overwriting shared files instead of appending.</description>
      <reason>Concurrent agents writing to the same file produce corrupt outputs. Use atomic JSONL append + lock file, never Write on shared logs.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Bi-weekly synthesis with full week's signals exceeding context window.</description>
      <reason>Pre-summarize per-day with haiku, feed only summaries to opus for synthesis — never pass raw haiku dumps directly to the synthesizer.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Review-mining agent asserting "competitor X has churn" from headlines rather than verbatim quotes.</description>
      <reason>Require quote-level evidence (verbatim text + source URL) before any sentiment claim — summary paraphrases hallucinate sentiment direction.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>"New entrant" agent over-triggering on rebrands of existing players.</description>
      <reason>Match on domain + founders + funding history, not just name. A rebrand of a known competitor is not a new entrant.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
