<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="k8s-resource-requests-limits">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>infra</group>
    <domain>infrastructure-engineer</domain>
    <summary>Set CPU/memory requests and limits on every container; understand QoS classes (Guaranteed/Burstable/BestEffort) and right-size values from observed P50/P99 metrics.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>kubernetes</tag>
      <tag>resource-management</tag>
      <tag>qos</tag>
      <tag>cpu-limits</tag>
      <tag>memory-limits</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>infra</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
    <related>
      <ref slug="k8s-limitrange"/>
      <ref slug="k8s-resource-quota"/>
      <ref slug="k8s-scaling-availability"/>
    </related>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Kubernetes Resource Requests, Limits, and QoS Classes</title>

    <summary>Every container in production MUST declare CPU and memory requests and limits. Requests drive scheduler placement (guaranteed minimum); limits drive kubelet enforcement (maximum). The ratio of requests to limits determines the pod's QoS class, which controls eviction order under node pressure. According to 2025 benchmarks, 99.94% of clusters are over-provisioned with average CPU utilization at just 10% — right-sizing is the single biggest lever for cost and stability.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Without requests, the scheduler cannot make placement decisions; pods land on arbitrary nodes and compete for resources without any guarantee. Without limits, a single runaway container can OOMKill or CPU-starve its neighbors. The QoS class system (Guaranteed → Burstable → BestEffort) gives the kubelet a deterministic eviction order: BestEffort pods die first, Guaranteed pods survive longest. Misconfigured resources are the root cause of the three most common K8s production incidents: OOMKill loops, CPU throttling degradation, and scheduling failures due to Insufficient resources.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Every container in every Deployment, StatefulSet, DaemonSet, or Job in a non-trivial environment.</item>
        <item>When a pod is OOMKilled repeatedly — diagnose and raise memory limit.</item>
        <item>When CPU throttling metrics show &gt;10% throttled periods — raise or remove CPU limit.</item>
        <item>When pods fail to schedule with "Insufficient resources" — lower requests or add nodes.</item>
        <item>When right-sizing using VPA in recommendation mode before locking values.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Throwaway local dev containers — overhead of tuning exceeds value; use a LimitRange default instead.</item>
        <item>Init containers in simple scenarios — they run once and exit; defaults from LimitRange suffice unless they do heavy work.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="units-and-fields">
      <p>Kubernetes uses two resource types: CPU (compressible — throttled, never killed) and memory (incompressible — OOMKilled when exceeded).</p>
      <rules>
        <rule>
          <statement>CPU values MUST use millicores (e.g., 250m = 0.25 vCPU, 1000m = 1 vCPU). Memory values MUST use binary suffixes (Mi, Gi) not decimal (M, G) to avoid ambiguity.</statement>
          <rationale>Millicores allow fine-grained allocation below 1 vCPU. Binary suffixes (Mi = 2^20 bytes) are what the kernel actually uses; decimal M causes subtle off-by-5% errors in limit enforcement.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>requests.cpu sets the scheduler guarantee (minimum CPU shares); limits.cpu sets the CFS quota ceiling (throttling threshold). requests.memory sets the scheduler guarantee; limits.memory sets the OOMKill threshold. NEVER set limits lower than requests.</statement>
          <rationale>Limits below requests are rejected by the API server. Requests above node capacity cause unschedulable pods.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section name="qos-classes">
      <p>Kubernetes automatically assigns one of three QoS classes to every pod based on how requests and limits are configured. This class determines eviction priority when a node runs low on memory.</p>
      <rules>
        <rule>
          <statement>Critical services (databases, primary APIs, stateful workloads) MUST use Guaranteed QoS: every container in the pod must have requests.cpu == limits.cpu AND requests.memory == limits.memory.</statement>
          <rationale>Guaranteed pods are evicted last. They are never CPU-throttled because the limit equals the request and CFS scheduling treats them as reserved. OOM score is -998, making the OOM killer avoid them.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>Standard workloads (web servers, background workers) SHOULD use Burstable QoS: set both requests and limits with requests &lt; limits. Variable workloads benefit from burst capacity without monopolizing node resources.</statement>
          <rationale>Burstable allows the container to use spare CPU/memory when available, absorbing traffic spikes without requiring provisioning at peak. Eviction priority is middle — they survive longer than BestEffort.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>BestEffort QoS (no requests/limits) is ONLY acceptable for batch jobs and dev/disposable workloads. NEVER use BestEffort in production namespaces without explicit justification.</statement>
          <rationale>BestEffort pods are evicted first. They provide no scheduling guarantees; they can starve unexpectedly when any node faces memory pressure.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section name="right-sizing">
      <p>Setting requests and limits requires observed metrics, not guesses. The standard procedure: run VPA in recommendation mode for 7+ days, then lock values derived from P50 (request) and P99+headroom (limit).</p>
      <rules>
        <rule>
          <statement>Set requests.cpu = observed P50 CPU usage. Set limits.cpu = observed P99 usage x 2-3 for variable workloads, or equal to requests for steady workloads (Guaranteed). Set requests.memory = working set size (P50). Set limits.memory = max heap/buffer + overhead (P99 + 20%).</statement>
          <rationale>P50 requests ensure the scheduler places pods accurately for typical load. P99-based limits prevent runaway containers while absorbing legitimate spikes without triggering OOMKill or excessive throttling.</rationale>
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <statement>JVM applications MUST align container memory limits with JVM flags: limits.memory = -Xmx + MetaspaceSize + thread stacks + NIO buffers. Set -Xmx = limits.memory * 0.75 as a starting point.</statement>
          <rationale>The JVM does not respect container limits natively before Java 11 with -XX:+UseContainerSupport. Without alignment, the JVM heap expands past the container limit causing OOMKill from the kernel, not a graceful OutOfMemoryError.</rationale>
        </rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <example type="good" title="Burstable web API">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
resources:
  requests:
    cpu: 250m
    memory: 256Mi
  limits:
    cpu: 500m
    memory: 512Mi
# QoS: Burstable (requests < limits)
# Can burst to 0.5 CPU under load
]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Guaranteed QoS for PostgreSQL">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
resources:
  # requests = limits → Guaranteed QoS
  requests:
    cpu: "2"
    memory: 4Gi
  limits:
    cpu: "2"
    memory: 4Gi
]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="JVM service with aligned memory">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
resources:
  requests:
    cpu: 500m
    memory: 1Gi
  limits:
    cpu: "2"
    memory: 2Gi
env:
- name: JAVA_OPTS
  value: "-Xms512m -Xmx1536m -XX:MaxMetaspaceSize=256m"
# -Xmx 1536m = 75% of 2Gi limit, leaving headroom for metaspace + buffers
]]></code>
    </example>

    <example type="good" title="Multi-container pod with sidecar sizing">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
containers:
- name: web
  image: nginx:1.25
  resources:
    requests: {cpu: 200m, memory: 256Mi}
    limits: {cpu: 500m, memory: 512Mi}
- name: fluentbit
  image: fluent/fluent-bit:2.2
  resources:
    requests: {cpu: 50m, memory: 64Mi}
    limits: {cpu: 100m, memory: 128Mi}
initContainers:
- name: init-db
  image: busybox:1.36
  resources:
    requests: {cpu: 10m, memory: 16Mi}
    limits: {cpu: 50m, memory: 32Mi}
]]></code>
      <note>Sidecars should be sized minimally — they share the pod's node allocation. Init containers can use more because they run sequentially before main containers start.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Missing resources (BestEffort in production)">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
containers:
- name: api
  image: myapp:1.0.0
  # No resources block — BestEffort QoS
  # Will be evicted first under any node pressure
]]></code>
      <note>99.94% of clusters are over-provisioned because developers leave resources blank. This workload will be the first casualty of any node memory pressure event.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="CPU limit too tight causing throttling">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
resources:
  requests:
    cpu: 100m
    memory: 256Mi
  limits:
    cpu: 100m   # Limit = request: zero burst capacity
    memory: 512Mi
# CPU is compressible; this container will be throttled on any spike
# Observe: container_cpu_cfs_throttled_seconds_total rising
]]></code>
    </example>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting identical ResourceQuota for all namespaces regardless of team size or workload type.</description>
      <reason>One-size-fits-all quotas either over-constrain small teams or under-constrain large ones. Quota should be proportional to team need with 15-20% headroom for burst.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting limits without requests (limits-only).</description>
      <reason>The scheduler ignores limits; it uses only requests for placement. A pod with limits but no requests gets BestEffort QoS despite having a limit, and the scheduler cannot guarantee the pod lands on a node with sufficient resources.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Ignoring CPU throttling metrics after setting limits.</description>
      <reason>CPU throttling degrades latency silently — the pod stays Running but response times increase. Monitor container_cpu_cfs_throttled_seconds_total and alert at &gt;10% throttled periods.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <section name="observability">
      <p>Essential Prometheus metrics for resource monitoring:</p>
      <list>
        <item>container_cpu_usage_seconds_total — actual CPU usage</item>
        <item>container_memory_working_set_bytes — memory actually in use (not cached)</item>
        <item>container_cpu_cfs_throttled_seconds_total — CPU throttling events</item>
        <item>kube_pod_container_resource_requests — configured requests</item>
        <item>kube_pod_container_resource_limits — configured limits</item>
      </list>
      <p>Key alerts: CPU throttling &gt;10% for 10m (warning), memory near limit &gt;85% for 5m (warning), OOMKill event (critical).</p>
    </section>

    <section name="right-sizing-tools">
      <p>Tools for automated right-sizing:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Goldilocks (Fairwinds) — VPA recommendations dashboard per namespace</item>
        <item>Kubecost — cost allocation and optimization recommendations</item>
        <item>CAST AI — automated rightsizing with cluster autoscaler integration</item>
        <item>VPA (vertical-pod-autoscaler) in updateMode: "Off" — recommendations without applying</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <checklist>
      <check>Never leave resources blank in production (results in BestEffort QoS).</check>
      <check>Set requests based on observed P50 usage from metrics.</check>
      <check>Set limits based on observed P99 usage + headroom.</check>
      <check>Use VPA in recommendation mode before locking values.</check>
      <check>Test under load before finalizing limits.</check>
      <check>For JVM: set limits.memory = Xmx + metaspace + stack + buffers.</check>
      <check>Monitor container_cpu_cfs_throttled_seconds_total after setting CPU limits.</check>
      <check>Alert on OOMKill events (critical) and memory near limit &gt;85% (warning).</check>
    </checklist>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/deployment-resources.yaml" purpose="Deployment with Burstable and Guaranteed QoS resource blocks."/>
    </templates>

    <prompt purpose="Analyze and right-size container resources"><![CDATA[
Analyze the following Kubernetes resource configuration and provide recommendations:

[PASTE DEPLOYMENT/POD YAML HERE]

Consider:
1. Are requests/limits appropriately sized?
2. What QoS class will this pod receive?
3. Are there any potential issues (OOM risk, CPU throttling)?
4. Suggest optimized values based on workload type.

Workload type: [web service / background worker / batch job / database]
Expected traffic pattern: [steady / bursty / variable]
]]></prompt>

    <prompt purpose="Right-size from observed metrics"><![CDATA[
Help right-size resources based on observed metrics:

Application: [APP_NAME]
Current configuration:
[PASTE CURRENT RESOURCES]

Observed metrics (last 7 days):
- CPU: P50=[X]m, P95=[Y]m, P99=[Z]m, Max=[W]m
- Memory: P50=[A]Mi, P95=[B]Mi, P99=[C]Mi, Max=[D]Mi

Requirements:
- QoS class desired: [Guaranteed/Burstable]
- Cost priority: [minimize cost / balance / maximize performance]
- Stability priority: [high / medium / low]

Output:
1. Recommended requests and limits
2. Rationale for each value
3. Expected savings or performance impact
]]></prompt>

    <see-also>
      <ref slug="k8s-limitrange"/>
      <ref slug="k8s-resource-quota"/>
      <ref slug="k8s-scaling-availability"/>
      <link href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/configuration/manage-resources-containers/"/>
      <link href="https://aokumo.io/blog/kubernetes-resource-management-2025/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
