<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Decision Analysis Process Rules">
  <summary>Six-step process rules for structured option evaluation: criteria lock-before-scoring, evidence URL requirement, scoring-direction normalization, and sensitivity-analysis trigger.</summary>

  <section title="Criteria Lock Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock criteria and weights before scoring any option. Record the weight-setter name and timestamp. No weight changes after scoring begins.</statement>
      <rationale>Stakeholders who want a specific option will lobby to raise weights for criteria where it wins. Weights locked before scoring with a named author prevent post-hoc manipulation and make manipulation visible to reviewers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap the criteria list at 7 items. More than 7 and stakeholders cannot hold them in working memory; weights become arbitrary.</statement>
      <rationale>Cognitive load above 7 criteria produces weight assignments that do not reflect real priorities. The cap forces the BA to consolidate collinear criteria (cost + TCO + subscription price → total cost).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Check for collinear criteria before weights are set. If two criteria have correlation above 0.6 (e.g., "cost" and "TCO"), merge them. Collinearity secretly inflates one axis to 2× or 3× its stated weight.</statement>
      <rationale>Collinearity is the most common invisible error in decision matrices. "Cost (25%) + TCO (20%) + subscription price (15%)" is really "cost 60%" in a matrix labelled as "cost 25%".</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Evidence Requirement">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every cell in the evaluation matrix must cite at least one evidence URL (vendor docs, pricing page, GitHub repo, measured uptime data). A score without a source is a vote, not data. Reject cells without evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs hallucinate vendor capabilities and pricing confidently. Evidence URLs make claims falsifiable and enable post-decision calibration reviews.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Score evidence must be dated. Evidence older than 90 days must be re-fetched before use. Vendor pricing and uptime data stale quickly.</statement>
      <rationale>A CRM priced at $50/seat in January may be $80/seat in September. Stale evidence produces wrong scores that compound into wrong recommendations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Score one criterion across all options before moving to the next criterion. Never score one option fully then the next. Scoring per-criterion prevents anchoring on the first option scored.</statement>
      <rationale>When one option is scored fully first, later options drift toward 3 (regression to median) because the first option becomes the implicit anchor. Per-criterion scoring breaks the anchor.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Scoring Direction Normalization">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define direction for every criterion: higher_better or lower_better. Score 5 = best for this criterion in every row. Never mix directions within a matrix. Include this field in the criteria definition.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing directions silently breaks the math: "cost: 5 = expensive" in one row and "cost: 5 = cheap" in another produces a nonsensical total. The criterion definition must encode direction before any scoring begins.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Sensitivity Analysis Trigger">
    <rule>
      <statement>After scoring, run Monte Carlo sensitivity analysis with ±20% weight perturbation over 2000 trials. If the top option wins fewer than 70% of trials, the recommendation is fragile — escalate to human or gather more evidence before committing.</statement>
      <rationale>A 3.85 vs 3.70 weighted total is well within rater noise (±0.5 on a 1-5 scale). Without sensitivity analysis, the "winner" may be statistical noise. The 70% threshold converts this judgment into a concrete go/no-go criterion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include a "do nothing / status quo" option, even when it feels unnecessary. It calibrates the rest of the matrix and forces the team to state what they lose by stalling.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a status-quo option, the matrix proves that one of the presented options is better than the others — but not that any of them is better than doing nothing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/sensitivity.py">Monte Carlo sensitivity: 2000 trials with ±20% weight noise; prints robustness % per option with escalation threshold.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
