<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ba-planning">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>ba</group>
    <domain>ba-core</domain>
    <summary>BABOK Knowledge Area 1: defines how BA work will be performed across five tasks — plan BA approach, plan stakeholder engagement, plan BA governance, plan BA information management, and identify BA performance improvements. Produces five task-scoped artifacts that seed all other ba-core methodologies.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>ba</tag>
      <tag>babok</tag>
      <tag>planning</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
      <tag>monitoring</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Business Analysis Planning</title>

    <summary>BABOK Knowledge Area 1 defines the five seeding tasks that govern all BA work: plan BA approach, plan stakeholder engagement, plan BA governance, plan BA information management, and identify BA performance improvements. Each task produces one artifact with its own approver, cadence, and lifecycle. Without KA1, downstream methodologies (stakeholder-analysis, ba-governance, requirements-lifecycle, elicitation-techniques) use inconsistent assumptions and produce incoherent outputs.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>BA work performed ad-hoc without structure results in inconsistent analysis, missed stakeholders, uncoordinated activities, and unclear deliverables. KA1 is the seeding ceremony that governs everything downstream — without it, stakeholder-analysis, ba-governance, requirements-lifecycle, and elicitation-techniques each use different assumptions and produce incoherent outputs.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A new initiative crosses from discovery to planned delivery and needs an explicit BA approach, stakeholder map, governance, information management, and performance plan.</item>
        <item>Programs that must demonstrate BABOK conformance to certifying bodies or internal QA (CCBA/CBAP audits, IIBA-aligned PMOs).</item>
        <item>Hybrid plan-driven + change-driven engagements where per-task baselined vs. living artifact declarations are needed.</item>
        <item>Activating sibling ba-core methodologies — KA1 is their prerequisite seeding ceremony.</item>
        <item>When introducing BA performance metrics (rework rate, requirement defect density, elicitation throughput).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Solo MVP, prototype, or research spike — five KA1 tasks are heavier than the work itself; use a one-page lean canvas.</item>
        <item>Pure backlog-driven Scrum where the Definition of Ready already encodes the BA approach.</item>
        <item>Continuous-discovery contexts where requirements churn weekly — KA1 baselines go stale faster than they can be reviewed.</item>
        <item>When the sponsor will not name a governance approver — without one, KA1 governance becomes decorative.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="five-ka1-tasks-and-ordering">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Produce five separate task-scoped artifacts (T1 through T5), not one consolidated BA plan; each artifact has its own approver, cadence, and lifecycle.</statement>
        <rationale>Collapsing five tasks into one document loses the monitoring half (T5) and makes the governance and information management tasks implicitly optional — they are not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Execute KA1 tasks in sequence: T1 approach → T2 stakeholders → T3 governance → T4 information management → T5 performance; dependencies flow forward.</statement>
        <rationale>Governance (T3) depends on knowing who the stakeholders are (T2); information management (T4) depends on governance decisions (T3); performance metrics (T5) depend on knowing what artifacts exist (T4). Out-of-order execution produces incoherent plans.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>T1 — Plan BA Approach: approach selection (plan-driven/change-driven/hybrid), methodology, constraints, rationale. One named approver required.</item>
        <item>T2 — Plan Stakeholder Engagement: stakeholder list, categories, engagement technique per type, availability.</item>
        <item>T3 — Plan BA Governance: decision rights, change control process, approval thresholds, escalation paths, sign-off requirements.</item>
        <item>T4 — Plan BA Information Management: artifact repository path, retention policy, access list, versioning approach.</item>
        <item>T5 — Identify BA Performance Improvements: at least 3 measurable metrics listed on day one even with null baselines and targets.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="approach-selection">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Declare the approach as a combination of plan-driven and change-driven percentages per artifact, not as a binary choice.</statement>
        <rationale>Real programs are 70/30 hybrids; pure-binary approach outputs produce artifacts that are either over-planned or under-baselined for their actual volatility.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Plan-Driven indicators: clear scope, stable requirements, high documentation expectation, low change frequency, limited stakeholder availability.</item>
        <item>Change-Driven indicators: uncertain evolving requirements, continuous stakeholder availability, higher risk tolerance, "just enough" documentation norm.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="stakeholder-categories">
      <list>
        <item>Sponsors: executive funding the initiative — decision authority for scope and budget changes.</item>
        <item>Users: people who will use the solution — primary source for functional and usability requirements.</item>
        <item>Implementers: team building the solution — source for feasibility and technical constraints.</item>
        <item>Regulators: compliance bodies — source for mandatory requirements and audit expectations.</item>
        <item>Support: operations and help desk — source for operational and transition requirements.</item>
      </list>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Listing plausible-sounding stakeholder roles without confirming they exist in the org chart.</description>
        <reason>LLMs invent plausible stakeholders ("Director of UX," "VP of Platform"); gap to reality causes missed sign-offs and broken escalation paths at critical decision points.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="elicitation-technique-selection">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Select elicitation techniques by information type and stakeholder count, not by default preference; document the technique-to-session mapping before any session is scheduled.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents default to "interview everything" regardless of context; workshops are more efficient for group consensus, surveys for broad input across large stakeholder populations.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Interviews: deep individual understanding, SME knowledge extraction, 1-3 participants.</item>
        <item>Workshops: consensus building, requirements that need group negotiation, 4-15 participants.</item>
        <item>Surveys: broad input, many stakeholders, quantitative preference data, 15+ respondents.</item>
        <item>Observation: process understanding, gap between documented and actual behavior, 1-2 observers.</item>
        <item>Document Analysis: existing-state artifacts, regulatory documents, system specifications.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="monitoring-cadence">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Assign different review cadences per task; do not use a single global review frequency for all five KA1 artifacts.</statement>
        <rationale>Performance metrics (T5) go stale weekly; stakeholder and governance artifacts drift fortnightly; approach and information management artifacts are stable monthly. A single cadence either over-reviews stable artifacts or under-reviews volatile ones.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>T5 Performance Improvements: weekly cadence — compute BA metrics and emit CR patches if triggers fire.</item>
        <item>T2 Stakeholder Engagement: fortnightly cadence — reconcile stakeholder list against project actuals.</item>
        <item>T1 Approach, T3 Governance, T4 Information Management: monthly cadence.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="replan-triggers">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Encode replan triggers as machine-readable YAML in triggers.yml, not prose; prose triggers only fire when a human reads and interprets them.</statement>
        <rationale>The monitor agent reads trigger conditions automatically; prose conditions require an LLM to interpret them, introducing interpretation errors and silent misses.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Stakeholder added or removed from the project.</item>
        <item>Scope change request merged into the requirements baseline.</item>
        <item>Two or more missed elicitation sessions within one cadence period.</item>
        <item>Performance metric breach (a KPI missing its threshold for two consecutive reviews).</item>
        <item>last_reviewed date older than the task's cadence threshold.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="t5-performance-requirements">
      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>List at least three measurable BA performance metrics in T5 on the first cycle with baseline=null and target=null; do not invent baselines before two cycles of data exist.</statement>
        <rationale>Invented baselines are post-hoc rationalizations — the first cycle is for measurement establishment, the second for improvement comparison. Skipping T5 entirely means no monitoring loop exists.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>T5 first-cycle metrics: (1) requirement defect density = defects found in validation / total requirements; baseline: null; target: null. (2) elicitation throughput = requirements documented per session; baseline: null. (3) rework rate = requirements changed after baseline / total baselined; baseline: null.</note>
      </example>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Omitting T5 on the first cycle because "we don't have baselines yet."</description>
        <reason>Without T5, there is no instrumentation; the second cycle cannot improve because it has nothing to improve from. Baselines are collected during the first cycle, not before it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="llm-failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM merges the five BABOK KA1 tasks into a single "BA Plan" document and silently drops T4 and T5.</description>
        <reason>Information management and performance improvement are the least visible KA1 tasks; LLMs drop them because they appear in fewer training examples. Validate output against the five-task schema; reject if any task is missing.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM produces vague governance approvers ("leadership," "the product team") in T3.</description>
        <reason>Vague approvers cannot sign off on anything; escalation paths point to a role, not a person. Require an email or @-handle; reject role-only outputs.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>LLM rewrites full artifact content during monitoring instead of emitting CR patches.</description>
        <reason>Full-doc overwrites destroy the approver's ability to review changes incrementally; CR patches force explicit diff review. Cap monitor agent at 5 changes per artifact per run.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>Model KA1 as five task-scoped artifacts in a single git directory under the project's `.product/` or `.aidocs/` tree, one Markdown file per BABOK task, each with YAML frontmatter (`task_id`, `version`, `approver`, `last_reviewed`, `baselined`). A planning subagent runs once at engagement kickoff producing v0.1 of all five; a monitoring subagent runs on a fixed cadence (weekly for performance, fortnightly for stakeholder/governance/info-management drift) diffing the artifact set against actuals (commits, sessions held, CRs merged, defects logged) and emitting CR patches. Replan triggers are deterministic and encoded in `triggers.yml`: stakeholder added, scope CR merged, two missed elicitation sessions, performance metric breach, or `last_reviewed` older than the cadence threshold. Every CR is reviewed by the named approver via PR; agents never push to the baseline branch.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-sdd-executor-agent — drives the 5 KA1 tasks as 5 SDD tasks (TASK-01..05) with their own commits, lifecycle (todo → in-progress → done) and execution reports. Plan reviews are PRs reviewed by the approver named in governance frontmatter.</item>
        <item>faion-brainstorm — diverge/converge for two specific KA1 decisions: approach selection (Plan-Driven / Change-Driven / Hybrid) and stakeholder engagement technique mix. Both benefit from explicit alternative generation.</item>
        <item>faion-sdd-execution (skill) — quality gates per KA1 task: did the approach task name an approver? does information management declare a retention policy? does performance plan list at least 3 measurable metrics?</item>
        <item>Custom ba-kickoff-agent (sonnet) — owns one-shot generation of all 5 KA1 artifacts from an initiative brief plus org chart.</item>
        <item>Custom ba-monitor-agent (haiku) — runs weekly via cron, computes the monitoring metrics, emits a status JSON and CR patches when triggers fire.</item>
        <item>Custom ba-performance-agent (opus) — runs at engagement boundaries (sprint, phase, milestone) to compute BA performance KPIs from git history and elicitation logs, and propose process improvements for the next cycle.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Treat KA1 as five artifacts, not one. One file per BABOK task, each with its own approver, cadence, and lifecycle. Collapsing them into a single doc loses the monitoring half.</item>
        <item>Order the kickoff sequence: T1 approach → T2 stakeholders → T3 governance → T4 information management → T5 performance. Dependencies flow forward; out of order produces incoherent plans.</item>
        <item>Cadence-per-task (not one global review): performance weekly, stakeholder fortnightly, approach/governance/info-mgmt monthly. Encode in `triggers.yml`.</item>
        <item>T5 (performance) must list metrics on day one even if baselines are null. First cycle measures; second cycle improves. Skipping T5 = no monitoring.</item>
        <item>Reference, do not duplicate: the stakeholder list lives in `stakeholder-analysis/`, governance in `ba-governance/`, requirements architecture in `ba-requirements-mgmt/`. KA1 holds links and IDs only.</item>
        <item>Encode replan triggers as YAML the monitor agent reads, not prose. "Replan if X" only fires automatically if it's machine-readable.</item>
        <item>For regulated programs, pandoc each KA1 artifact to PDF and gpg --detach-sign it; auditors accept the signed bundle.</item>
        <item>Drive the BABOK conformance check from `ka1_check.py` in CI so the plan set cannot regress unnoticed.</item>
        <item>Use complexity tiers (S/M/L) instead of hours/days for elicitation effort — per repo policy, no time estimates in SDD docs.</item>
        <item>Pair each KA1 task with one and only one approver; CODEOWNERS by directory (e.g. `T3-governance.md` owned by sponsor email) makes this enforceable.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="ai-agent-gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>Task collapse: LLMs merge the 5 BABOK tasks into one document and silently drop T4 and T5. Validate output keys against the 5-task schema; reject if any task is missing.</item>
        <item>Stakeholder hallucination: agents invent plausible stakeholders ("Director of UX") that do not exist. Constrain to a `stakeholder_seed`; flag every gap as `TODO(reason)`.</item>
        <item>Governance dilution: agents produce vague approvers ("leadership", "product team"). Require an email or @-handle; reject role-only outputs.</item>
        <item>Performance metric confabulation: agents invent baselines for T5 on first cycle. Force `baseline: null` and `target: null` until two cycles of data exist; only the human approver may set them.</item>
        <item>Monitoring drift: the monitor agent silently rewrites artifacts when the approver is offline. Force unified diffs / CR patches, never full-doc overwrites; cap CRs at 5 changes per run.</item>
        <item>Information-management default leakage: agents default T4 to "all in Notion" regardless of org policy. Pass the org's storage/retention policy in the system prompt and reject Notion if not allowed.</item>
        <item>BABOK / PMBOK confusion: agents borrow PMBOK schedule language and produce Gantt charts for everything. KA1 governs analysis, not delivery; defer schedule integration to `project-manager`.</item>
        <item>Plan-Driven / Change-Driven binary: real programs are 70/30 hybrids. Force per-artifact baselined/living flags; reject pure-binary outputs.</item>
        <item>Frontmatter parse failures on smart-quote / em-dash injection from copy-paste. Pre-commit hook must reject non-ASCII in YAML keys.</item>
        <item>Token budget: at >50 stakeholders or >5 sibling methodology refs, do not load the whole KA1 set into context. Index frontmatter via `yq` and load full sections on demand.</item>
        <item>Human-in-the-loop checkpoints (mandatory): all 5 artifacts at v1.0 sign-off, every approach change, every governance/approver change, every CR adding or removing a stakeholder, every change to T5 baselines and targets.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/ba-approach-document.md" purpose="BA approach document covering initiative overview, approach selection, stakeholders, elicitation plan, deliverables, governance."/>
      <template path="templates/ka1_check.py" purpose="Python script validating that all five BABOK KA1 artifacts are present, coherent, and within review cadence."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/standards-and-resources/babok/"/>
      <link href="https://www.iiba.org/career-resources/agile-extension/"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/practice-guides/business-analysis"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/72089.html"/>
      <link href="https://strictdoc.readthedocs.io"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
