<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="error-recovery">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Error messages must state what happened, why it happened, and how to fix it in plain language without error codes. Every error must offer a recovery path as a button or link, not just a description.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>error-messages</tag>
      <tag>microcopy</tag>
      <tag>usability</tag>
      <tag>heuristic-9</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Help Users Recognize, Diagnose, and Recover from Errors</title>

    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #9: error messages must state what happened, why it happened, and how to fix it in plain language, without error codes, without blaming the user. Every error must offer a recovery path (button or link), not just a description. Inline placement next to the problematic element is required for form errors; system errors use modal or banner with a retry action.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Cryptic or vague errors (Error 403, "Something went wrong") leave users stuck and trigger support tickets or abandonment. The three-part structure (what / why / how) directly resolves the failure by giving users the information and action needed to continue. Recovery actions as clickable elements — not instructions — reduce the cognitive load of figuring out what to do next.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing existing UI error messages for clarity and actionability before a release.</item>
        <item>Writing microcopy for form validation, network errors, 404 pages, and payment failures.</item>
        <item>Code review: checking that API error strings are user-presentable before surfacing in UI.</item>
        <item>When support tickets reveal users confused by a specific error message.</item>
        <item>Systematic pre-launch sweep of all error states in a feature.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Preventing errors in the first place — use Heuristic #5 (Error Prevention) instead.</item>
        <item>Designing empty states or onboarding flows — different UX domain.</item>
        <item>Performance or reliability issues causing errors — fix the root cause, not the message.</item>
        <item>Silent background errors that auto-retry without user involvement.</item>
        <item>Good error messages cannot fix bad IA — if users reach the wrong place, clarity is irrelevant.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="three-part-error-framework">
      <p>Three-part error message framework (what/why/how), placement rules, and handling patterns for validation, system, 404, and network errors.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every error message must answer three questions: what happened, why it happened, and how to fix it.</statement>
        <rationale>Users cannot act on "Error occurred." They need context (what/why) to understand the problem and a specific action (how) to resolve it. Missing any part creates a dead end.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Express errors in plain language. Use no error codes, no technical terms, no blame language directed at the user.</statement>
        <rationale>Technical codes and blame language ("you entered invalid data") shift cognitive burden to the user without helping them recover. Plain language with a calm, helpful tone preserves trust and reduces support load.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every error above cosmetic severity must include a recovery action as a button or link, not as a text instruction.</statement>
        <rationale>"Try again" as a clickable button requires zero interpretation. "Please try again" as text requires the user to figure out how. Buttons also confirm the recovery path is available right now.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="placement-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Place form field errors inline, adjacent to the problematic field. For multi-field forms, also show a top-of-form summary with link anchors to each error.</statement>
        <rationale>Inline placement eliminates the need to search. Summaries help users understand scope before scrolling. Both together serve keyboard and screen-reader users who may not reach inline messages before submitting.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Show system errors (failed operations) as a modal or top banner with a retry action and, where relevant, a fallback action (e.g., Work Offline).</statement>
        <rationale>System errors affect the whole operation, not one field. Modal or banner placement signals scope. Two actions (retry + fallback) avoid dead ends when retry is likely to fail again.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="error-type-patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Validation errors: show immediately on blur or as the user types; place inline next to the field; message = what is wrong plus exactly how to fix it.</statement>
        <rationale>Early feedback prevents users from completing a form incorrectly. Immediate inline placement removes the need to remember which field had the problem after submission.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>404 Not Found: show a full-page message explaining the page is gone or the URL is wrong; provide links to home, search, and 2-3 common destinations.</statement>
        <rationale>Dead-end 404 pages are one of the highest abandonment points. Recovery links keep users in the product and give them a concrete next step.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Network errors: show a banner with connection status and a Retry button; offer an offline mode if the product supports it.</statement>
        <rationale>Network errors are transient. Users need a clear retry path and visibility into whether the product is still usable offline.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="accessibility-requirements">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never rely on color alone for error indication. Pair color with an icon and text. Use ARIA live regions so screen readers announce errors on state change. Move focus to the error summary or first error field.</statement>
        <rationale>Color-only errors are invisible to color-blind users and screen readers. Focus management is required so keyboard users do not have to search for the error after a failed submission.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="examples">
      <example type="good" title="Payment error (Stripe pattern) — clear what, context why, two recovery actions">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Your card was declined

Your card number is incorrect. Please check
the number and try again.

[Try a different card]  [Contact bank]]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="404 page (GitHub pattern) — acknowledges the problem, provides navigation back">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[This is not the web page you are looking for.

The page you requested doesn't exist. You may have
typed the address incorrectly or the page may have moved.

[Go to GitHub.com]  [Search GitHub]]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Progressive password validation — real-time, specific, actionable">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Password must contain:
✓ At least 8 characters
✗ One uppercase letter (add one)
✗ One number (add one)]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Network error — identifies cause, offers retry and fallback">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Cannot connect to server.
Please check your internet connection and try again.

[Retry]  [Work Offline]]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Access control — raw HTTP status">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Error 403]]></code>
        <note>No context, no action, leaves user stuck.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Same error, three-part structure">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[You don't have permission to view this page.
Contact your administrator for access.

[Request Access]]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Form field — vague">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Invalid input]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Same error, specific and instructional">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[This email address is missing the @ symbol.
Example: name@company.com]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Error codes as the entire message: "Error 403" or "ECONNREFUSED"</description>
        <reason>Error codes carry zero actionable information for non-technical users. They increase anxiety and support tickets without helping recovery.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Generic messages: "Something went wrong" or "An error occurred"</description>
        <reason>Tells the user nothing about what failed, why, or what to do. Erodes trust by suggesting the product does not know what happened.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Blame language: "You entered invalid data" or "Your request was malformed"</description>
        <reason>Shifts responsibility to the user even when the error is partially system-caused. Damages trust and increases frustration. Prefer neutral phrasing: "This field needs a valid email address."</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Dead-end errors: error message with only an [OK] button and no recovery path</description>
        <reason>Forces the user to figure out recovery independently. Every error must have at minimum one recovery action — retry, go back, or contact support.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Payment-specific: "Your card is fraudulent" or "Suspicious transaction detected"</description>
        <reason>Legally and commercially dangerous. Use neutral phrasing: "Your card was not accepted. Please try a different card or contact your bank."</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/error-message-design.md" purpose="Per-error-type design doc: trigger, content (what/why/how), placement, actions"/>
      <template path="templates/error-audit.md" purpose="Audit table: current message, issues, improved message, placement, recovery path"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/error-message-guidelines/"/>
      <link href="https://uxdesign.cc/how-to-write-better-error-messages-b0fdc07e60dc"/>
      <link href="https://www.uxmatters.com/mt/archives/2010/08/avoiding-catastrophe-design-for-prevention-and-recovery.php"/>
      <link href="https://material.io/design/communication/confirmation-acknowledgement.html"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
