<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="help-documentation">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>ux-ui-designer</domain>
    <summary>Effective help is contextual, task-focused (not feature-based), searchable, and kept current via regular review cycles.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>help-documentation</tag>
      <tag>onboarding</tag>
      <tag>usability</tag>
      <tag>heuristic-10</tag>
      <tag>support</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Help and Documentation</title>

    <summary>Nielsen's Usability Heuristic #10: even though it is better if a system needs no documentation, help must be provided when needed. Effective help is contextual (placed where users need it), task-focused (organized by user goals not feature names), searchable, concise, and kept current. The help hierarchy: fix the interface first, then inline hints, then tooltips, then FAQs, then documentation, then human support.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Users who cannot find help give up. Increased support ticket volume is the measurable signal of help failure. Good contextual help reduces support costs, improves feature adoption, and shortens the time to proficiency for new users.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Auditing an existing product for help gaps during a UX review sprint.</item>
        <item>Generating first-draft contextual tooltips, inline hints, or FAQ entries for a new feature.</item>
        <item>Analyzing support ticket logs to identify recurring help needs not covered by existing docs.</item>
        <item>Producing a help article from a list of step-by-step procedures.</item>
        <item>Creating onboarding tour scripts tied to specific UI actions.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>When the interface itself needs a redesign to eliminate confusion — fix the root, not the docs.</item>
        <item>Replacing qualitative usability testing — help audits do not substitute for observing real users.</item>
        <item>Generating legally binding product documentation without human legal review.</item>
        <item>When the feature set is still unstable and help content will be outdated before it ships.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="help-hierarchy">
      <p>Prioritized from best to last resort:</p>
      <p>1. Interface design that needs no explanation (best — eliminate confusion at source).</p>
      <p>2. Inline help — field hints, placeholder text visible during interaction.</p>
      <p>3. Tooltips — on-hover explanation for icons and controls.</p>
      <p>4. Guided tours — onboarding walkthroughs for new users.</p>
      <p>5. FAQs — answers to common questions (5 max per page).</p>
      <p>6. Documentation — detailed task-focused articles with numbered steps.</p>
      <p>7. Human support (last resort — tickets, chat, email).</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Fix the interface before adding help content; help that compensates for a broken design is a band-aid, not a solution.</statement>
        <rationale>Help content that explains a confusing flow treats the symptom; redesigning the flow eliminates the need. Documentation is more expensive to maintain than a clear UI.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="contextual-help-patterns">
      <p>Inline hints (always visible): label + hint text below field, placeholder text in inputs.</p>
      <p>Tooltips (on demand): [?] icon hover → brief explanation, [i] icon hover → feature context.</p>
      <p>Contextual panels: collapsible sidebar with page-specific help for complex features.</p>
      <p>Onboarding tours: step-by-step overlay anchored to specific UI elements with [Skip] and [Next] options.</p>

      <example type="good" title="Stripe dashboard: contextual tooltip on each metric explains what it measures and how to improve it">
        <note>Help appears where the user is, not in a separate help center.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Help buried in footer with no contextual help anywhere in the app">
        <note>Users who get stuck mid-task must navigate away to find answers, losing their context.</note>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="content-types-by-use-case">
      <p>
        Onboarding: welcome tour (first login), empty states (new sections), progress checklist (guide setup).
        In-context: tooltips (hover), inline hints (always visible), [?] icons (on demand).
        Reference: FAQs (quick answers), how-to articles (numbered steps), reference docs (complete detail).
        Support: search (self-service), chat (real-time help), email (complex issues).
      </p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Organize help content by user tasks (verbs), not product features (nouns).</statement>
        <rationale>Users search for what they want to accomplish ("how to reset password"), not what the feature is called internally ("Authentication Settings"). Task-based organization matches search intent.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="authoring-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Test search discoverability by typing the phrase a frustrated user would type, not the feature name.</statement>
        <rationale>Users search by task context ("why is my payment failing") not by feature name ("Payment Processing Module"); discoverability testing must use user-language queries.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Add a "Last reviewed" date to every help article and schedule quarterly reviews in the project backlog.</statement>
        <rationale>Help content decays as the product changes; undated articles have no signal about staleness, and users lose trust when steps no longer match the UI.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Keep FAQs to five questions maximum per page; create separate detailed articles for depth.</statement>
        <rationale>Long FAQ pages become unscannable; five questions per page with links to detail articles maintains scannability while enabling depth.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Link related articles bidirectionally; users reading "password reset" also need "two-factor authentication".</statement>
        <rationale>Single-article dead ends force users back to search; bidirectional links keep users in the help flow until their question is answered.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="measuring-help-effectiveness">
      <p>
        Help searches — what users are looking for (unmet needs signal).
        Search success rate — do users find answers? (gaps in coverage).
        Support tickets — questions that help should answer but does not.
        Feature adoption — does contextual help increase usage of complex features?
        Deflection rate — tickets created after reading an article = help failure.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Help content not maintained after feature changes.</description>
        <reason>Outdated screenshots and broken step sequences are worse than no documentation; they waste user time and erode trust.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Documentation written for experts, not users.</description>
        <reason>Jargon without explanation excludes the users who need help most; documentation must assume the minimum viable context.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>No help exists at the point of confusion — only a footer link to a help center.</description>
        <reason>Users who encounter confusion mid-task need help in context, not after navigating away and losing their progress.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-usage-rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>Every agent-generated step sequence must be verified against actual product flows before publishing.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs generate plausible-sounding but incorrect step sequences without product access; factual accuracy requires human verification against the live product.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Articles touching billing, security, or account deletion require legal/compliance review before publishing.</statement>
        <rationale>Incorrect information in these areas creates legal and reputational risk; human review is mandatory regardless of how accurate the agent output appears.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Instruct the agent to keep help articles under 500 words and audit length in a follow-up pass.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs over-enumerate steps; long articles are not read to completion and fail to answer the user's specific question quickly.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-workflow">
      <p>A Claude subagent is most useful for drafting help content at scale: given a feature description or support-ticket dump, it can produce structured articles following the help content template. A second agent can then audit coverage by cross-referencing a list of product features against existing articles. Human review is mandatory before publishing to catch factual errors. Agents do not have access to the live product UI; every step they generate must be verified against actual flows before publishing. LLMs tend to over-enumerate steps — instruct the agent to keep articles under 500 words and audit length in a follow-up pass. If the agent references screenshots or UI labels, those must be validated; UI text changes break accuracy.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Screenshots and video captions require human production tooling — an agent cannot produce them.</statement>
        <rationale>Visual content creation requires design tools agent access lacks; plan separate workflow for images.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Help content decay is invisible to agents: they will not detect that a previously generated article became stale.</statement>
        <rationale>Automated review schedules and human audits are required; agent-generated content has no built-in freshness detection.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>SEO optimization of help articles requires search volume data that an agent cannot query without tool access.</statement>
        <rationale>Search-driven prioritization requires analytics; agent recommendations are based on content patterns, not user search behavior.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule>
        <statement>Agents cannot test search functionality; include a manual search QA step in the workflow.</statement>
        <rationale>Help content is only valuable if users find it; search indexing and keyword matching must be tested by humans.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/help-article.md" purpose="Help article structure: overview, numbered steps, result, troubleshooting, related"/>
      <template path="templates/help-audit.md" purpose="Help audit: feature × coverage/type/quality + gap table + priority improvements"/>
      <template path="templates/help_gap_finder.py" purpose="Python script to find features missing help coverage"/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/help-and-documentation/"/>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/self-service-support/"/>
      <link href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/information-architecture"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
