<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="pricing-research">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>research</group>
    <domain>market-researcher</domain>
    <summary>Six-step pricing framework combining value quantification, competitor analysis, Van Westendorp method, billing model selection, tier design, and sales validation.</summary>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <tags>
      <tag>pricing</tag>
      <tag>revenue</tag>
      <tag>saas</tag>
      <tag>market-research</tag>
      <tag>billing</tag>
    </tags>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Pricing Research</title>
    <summary>A six-step pricing framework: quantify value delivered, build a competitor pricing matrix, apply Van Westendorp price sensitivity (4 questions), choose a billing model, design tier structure with feature distribution, and validate via real sales. Output: recommended price bands with model rationale, not a single number to hard-code.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Pricing set without research produces underpricing (leaving margin on the table) or overpricing (losing customers) and wrong model selection (subscription when one-time fits). The Van Westendorp method produces an acceptable price range from real respondents; the value-based ceiling (10-20% capture of value delivered) provides an upper bound independent of competitor anchoring. Agents fabricate both if given insufficient real data.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-launch: validating tier structure and price points before publishing pricing page.</item>
        <item>Quarterly pricing review after a market shift (new competitors, new category entrants).</item>
        <item>Pivoting model (one-time to subscription, freemium to paid trial).</item>
        <item>Setting enterprise/custom price floor for first sales call.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Fewer than 50 paying customers — talk to them directly; agent output is confabulation at this scale.</item>
        <item>B2B enterprise contract negotiation — relationship/procurement-driven, not formula-driven.</item>
        <item>Heavily regulated pricing (insurance, prescription, utility) — agent will not know jurisdiction rules.</item>
        <item>Marketplace/two-sided pricing — supply-and-demand dynamics need real telemetry, not survey output.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="value-analysis-and-competitors">
      <p>Five types of value to quantify before setting price:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Time saved: hours/week freed up, monetized at user's hourly rate</item>
        <item>Money saved: direct cost reduction</item>
        <item>Money earned: new revenue the tool enables</item>
        <item>Risk reduced: problems prevented, cost of incidents avoided</item>
        <item>Quality improved: better outcomes that translate to user revenue or retention</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Compute the value-based price ceiling as (Value Delivered per Month x Capture Rate) minus Switching Cost. Use capture rate 10-20% for productivity SaaS; 1-3% for devtools; 15-25% for vertical SaaS.</statement>
        <rationale>The folk number of 10-20% is frequently applied outside its valid range. Devtools users are price-sensitive and have many free alternatives; vertical SaaS buyers pay a premium for domain-specific value.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good" title="Value-based price ceiling calculation">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tool saves: 5 hours/week
User's time value: $50/hour
Monthly value: 5 x $50 x 4 = $1,000/month
Capture rate (productivity SaaS): 10%
Price ceiling: $1,000 x 0.10 = $100/month
]]></code>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>Build a pricing matrix with at least 5-8 competitors before drawing any conclusions. Mark "sales-led" explicitly for contact-form-only pricing; never estimate hidden prices.</statement>
        <rationale>Fewer than 5 data points produces misleading range estimates. Estimating "contact us" prices introduces fabrication into the analysis and corrupts the median calculation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Randomize competitor processing order to prevent anchoring. Agents given the same list consistently over-weight the first competitor's price when synthesizing the range.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs anchor on first-processed values. Randomizing the order averages out this bias across the synthesis step.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Analyze annual discount structure, included limits per tier, and free tier availability. Pricing pages are A/B tested — public list prices may not match effective prices for converted customers.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="van-westendorp-price-sensitivity">
      <p>The Van Westendorp Price Sensitivity method generates an acceptable price range from real respondents.</p>
      <p>The four questions:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Too expensive: "At what price would this be too expensive to consider?" (upper bound)</item>
        <item>Expensive but worth it: "At what price would this be expensive but worth considering?"</item>
        <item>Good deal: "At what price would this be a good deal?"</item>
        <item>Too cheap: "At what price would this be too cheap to trust?" (lower bound)</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Run Van Westendorp only on engaged trial users who have hit the upgrade modal, not on cold leads or survey respondents who have never used the product.</statement>
        <rationale>Cold leads systematically low-ball because they are optimizing for a hypothetical purchase. Engaged users who have experienced the value anchor to their actual willingness to pay.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Require N>=30 real respondents before running Van Westendorp synthesis. Below 30, return raw quotes only; refuse to compute a recommended price range.</statement>
        <rationale>Agents fabricate Van Westendorp distributions when given fewer than 30 responses, producing price points centered on training-data anchors ($29, $49, $99, $299) regardless of actual input.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>The acceptable price range runs from the point where "Too Cheap" and "Too Expensive" curves cross. The optimal price is the intersection of "Cheap" and "Expensive" curves (Point of Marginal Cheapness and Point of Marginal Expensiveness). In practice: aim for the upper end of the acceptable range to maximize revenue without significant conversion loss.</p>
      <p>When N&lt;30, use three direct interview questions instead of full Van Westendorp:</p>
      <list>
        <item>"What would you expect to pay for this?" (reference point)</item>
        <item>"Would you pay $X?" (test specific price point)</item>
        <item>"What would make $X feel like a bargain?" (value anchoring)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="billing-models-and-tier-design">
      <p>Billing model selection table:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Subscription: ongoing value, sticky usage, requires retention focus (SaaS tools)</item>
        <item>One-time: discrete deliverable, no ongoing obligation (courses, templates, guides)</item>
        <item>Usage-based: variable consumption, scales with value delivered (API calls, storage, seats)</item>
        <item>Freemium: growth-first, network effects, PLG products — requires free tier that creates upgrade pressure</item>
        <item>Tiered: different customer sizes, different budgets — most B2B products</item>
        <item>Hybrid: subscription base + usage overage — complex value delivery with floor and upside</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Design tiers backwards from desired ARPU. The middle tier should have 70-80% of Pro features at 40-50% of Pro price; this is where most users land (decoy effect).</statement>
        <rationale>The decoy effect makes the middle tier appear as the rational choice. Designing backwards from ARPU ensures the middle tier conversion actually achieves revenue targets.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use a 2-3x price jump between adjacent tiers. Smaller jumps do not create sufficient upgrade motivation; larger jumps create a dead zone where no tier fits mid-market customers.</statement>
        <rationale>Price jump magnitude sets the perceived value gap between tiers. A 2-3x jump is psychologically separable; a 1.2x jump is not.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Do not give everything in the middle tier. Reserve at least one compelling feature for Pro that addresses a real pain of mid-tier users.</statement>
        <rationale>Without a genuine Pro upgrade trigger, the middle tier becomes the permanent stopping point and upgrade conversion collapses.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Frame annual pricing as "2 months free" rather than "17% off" or "20% discount". Identical math; "2 months free" has significantly higher take-up in A/B tests.</statement>
        <rationale>Concrete gift framing (months free) is more actionable than percentage savings. The equivalent math does not change retention or cash flow but does change conversion rate.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Implement explicit grandfather policy for price increases: "we honor your price for 12 months". Silent grandfathering forever erodes margin; silent removal destroys trust.</statement>
        <rationale>Documented, time-limited grandfathering is predictable and builds trust with early adopters without permanently subsidizing them at new-customer CAC.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="pricing-research-agent-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent suggests 10-15% capture rate regardless of product category or market context.</description>
        <reason>The 10-20% folk number appears frequently in startup content. LLMs apply it uniformly without category adjustment.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <rule>
        <statement>Override capture rate with category-specific priors: devtools 1-3%, productivity 5-10%, vertical SaaS 15-25%. Apply these as hard overrides when the agent suggests a generic range.</statement>
        <rationale>Category-specific priors are derived from actual SaaS benchmarks (OpenView, ProfitWell). Generic 10-20% systematically overestimates devtools pricing potential and underestimates vertical SaaS.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent computes annual price as "12 x monthly x 0.83" (17% off) instead of "10 x monthly" (2 months free).</description>
        <reason>Percentage-discount framing triggers percentage math. The "2 months free" framing should produce 10 x monthly but agents revert to percentage calculation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <rule>
        <statement>Force the formula in the prompt: annual_price = monthly_price x 10. Do not describe it as a percentage discount.</statement>
        <rationale>Explicit formula prevents the recalculation error. The math is identical to "2 months free" and "16.7% off" but the agent will compute it correctly only when given the multiplier form.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use three separate agents for competitor scraping, value modeling, and tier design. Never let a single agent do all three — pricing logic compounds errors across stages.</statement>
        <rationale>Each stage has a different fabrication risk. A single agent accumulates errors from competitor confabulation into value modeling, then into tier recommendations. Separation provides natural checkpoints.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Serve EUR/INR/BRL prices adjusted for PPP, not 1:1 USD conversion. Agents routinely miss regional pricing adjustments and produce USD-only recommendations.</statement>
        <rationale>Flat USD pricing in markets with significantly lower purchasing power dramatically reduces conversion. PPP-adjusted bands are standard for SaaS products targeting global markets.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Actual price commits (creating Stripe price objects, publishing pricing page) are human decisions. Agent output is "recommended bands"; the button-press is not delegated.</statement>
        <rationale>Pricing errors are hard to reverse — raising prices costs customer trust; refunding grandfathered customers costs margin. The final decision requires human judgment that accounts for current business context.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Reject any Van Westendorp synthesis computed from fewer than 30 real respondents.</item>
        <item>Reject any competitor feature row without a source_quote from the actual pricing page.</item>
        <item>Mark all "contact us" tiers as negotiated and exclude from median calculations.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pricing-report.md" purpose="Full Pricing Research Report with value, competitor, VW, and recommendation sections."/>
      <template path="templates/pricing-quick-check.md" purpose="Quick pricing check for low-stakes decisions."/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.profitwell.com/pricing"/>
      <link href="https://stripe.com/resources/more/pricing-tables"/>
      <link href="https://www.openview.com/resources/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
