<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="GitOps — Secrets and Security Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules including a `skip-this-methodology` rule. Each pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="no-plaintext-secrets-in-git" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Secrets MUST NEVER appear as plaintext in Git. Use SOPS-encrypted manifests, Sealed Secrets, or External Secrets Operator (ESO).</statement>
      <rationale source="Compliance baseline">Plaintext secrets in Git are the #1 leak class — once committed, presume compromised.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="kms-or-age-keyring" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Encryption keys MUST be backed by cloud KMS (AWS KMS / GCP KMS / Azure Key Vault) OR an audited age keyring. Storing the encryption key in the same repo is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Defense in depth">If both ciphertext and key live in Git, encryption is theatre; key custody must be external.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rotate-secrets-on-schedule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each secret class MUST have a documented rotation cadence (e.g. tokens 90d, passwords 180d, certs 365d) with automation for at least token rotation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Rotation discipline">Static secrets accumulate exposure; rotation caps the time window of compromise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="rbac-least-privilege" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>ServiceAccounts MUST be scoped to the minimum verbs + resources required. ClusterRole/*/* assignments rejected outside infra controllers.</statement>
      <rationale source="Least privilege">Broad RBAC turns one compromised pod into cluster takeover; least privilege caps blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="agent-secret-policy" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>AI agents operating on the GitOps repo MUST follow an explicit secret policy: read decrypted secrets only when required, never log them, never echo to chat. Policy MUST be enforced via guardrails.</statement>
      <rationale source="AI agent ops">AI agents are a new exfil class — they can read, transform, and surface secrets across contexts; explicit policy + guardrails are mandatory.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip when secrets never live in manifests (CSI-injected) OR single-dev cluster with no compliance obligation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scope guard">Below threshold the methodology adds ceremony without risk reduction.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
