<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Strategy Methods Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding this methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale; the skip-this-methodology rule is the authoritative stop signal.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce the decision-record artefact required by this methodology with every required field of the JSON Schema in 02-output-contract.xml populated and non-null.</statement>
      <rationale source="Output Contract / JSON Schema 2020-12">Missing required fields propagate to downstream consumers as silent gaps; the validator script enforces this rule at CI time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Apply the decision tree in 06-decision-tree.xml before authoring; record the leaf reached so reviewers can replay the routing.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — methodology authoring discipline">Skipping the decision tree leads to misapplied methodologies (e.g. running deep procedure on light scope); recording the leaf makes the application auditable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Detect and prevent the antipattern 'default-swot': Require fit scores per candidate; reject SWOT when other methods score higher.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — failure-modes audit (severity=medium)">Root cause: Author has no method experience beyond SWOT.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Detect and prevent the antipattern 'limitation-less': Force limitations array; minItems=1.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — failure-modes audit (severity=medium)">Root cause: Author treats method choice as one-shot.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Detect and prevent the antipattern 'evidence-less-scores': Require rationale ≥30 chars per score axis.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — failure-modes audit (severity=high)">Root cause: Author invents scores.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When the decision tree resolves to skip-this-methodology, halt authoring; do NOT emit a partial artefact and do NOT proceed downstream with this methodology's outputs.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Skip-If discipline">Partial artefacts produced after a skip signal pollute downstream consumers and waste reviewer cycles; the skip leaf is an authoritative stop signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
