<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-options-scoring" title="Solution Options Scoring">
  <summary>Weighted multi-criteria scoring rules: options identification, criteria weighting, anchored scoring rubric, sensitivity analysis, and recommendation constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Options Identification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always include status-quo (do-nothing) as a numbered option in the scoring matrix and weighted totals; never omit it.</statement>
      <rationale>Without status-quo as Option A, leadership cannot see the cost of inaction; the recommendation reads as advocacy rather than analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Generate 3-7 alternatives before scoring; do not begin scoring with a single option and a strawman.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-option matrices are decorative; sponsors recognize them as advocacy and the technique gets discredited for the next real decision.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Criteria and Weight Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Lock criteria weights before options are scored, in a separate step with named stakeholders; never let the scoring agent set weights.</statement>
      <rationale>Weights drift to make the math agree with the pre-decided recommendation. The weight-setting step must be documented separately so the rationale survives later challenge.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat any weight sum that does not equal 100% as an error; do not silently normalize.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent normalization hides input errors and changes the effective weight of every criterion without the stakeholder knowing.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Cap the criterion list at 5-7; more criteria collapse to ties and double-counting.</statement>
      <rationale>Above 7 criteria, marginal criteria carry less than 3% weight — they add noise, not signal, and often encode the same underlying dimension twice.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Criteria that partially overlap (e.g., Cost, Time to value, and Risk all encoding capital exposure).</description>
      <reason>Double-counting inflates one dimension and makes the matrix systematically biased toward options that score well on capital risk, even when that was not the intent.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Anchored Scoring">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor every score on the 1-5 rubric to a measurable definition before scoring begins; free-form 1-5 produces clustering at 3-4.</statement>
      <rationale>Without anchors, every option scores 3 or 4 on every criterion; differences wash out and the matrix produces no ranking signal.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Anchored rubric for "Strategic fit": 5 = exceeds strategic target by &gt;=20%, 4 = meets target, 3 = neutral/unclear, 2 = partial misalignment, 1 = direct conflict with strategy.</note>
    </example>
    <rule>
      <statement>Require at least one evidence_url per (option, criterion) cell; mark any cell without evidence confidence=low and force score to 3.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs cluster scores at 3-4 and will hallucinate vendor pricing or TCO numbers that "feel right." Evidence anchors prevent fabrication.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Sensitivity Analysis">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run ±10% and ±25% weight perturbation and single-criterion-removal on every published matrix; if the winner flips under &lt;=10% perturbation, set brittleness=high and require human review before publishing.</statement>
      <rationale>A recommendation that flips on a 10% weight wobble is statistically a coin-flip; publishing it without the brittleness flag misleads sponsors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/sensitivity.py">Python script for weight perturbation and brittleness detection.</reference>
    <reference path="templates/scoring-matrix.md">Solution options analysis with criteria, scoring matrix, and recommendation.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
