<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-limitation-assessment" title="Solution Limitation Assessment">
  <summary>Limitation identification, root-cause requirements (5-whys minimum), severity derivation formula, and remediation option constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Limitation Identification">
    <rule>
      <statement>Extract limitations from defect logs, support tickets, and at least one user-research source; never from team memory alone.</statement>
      <rationale>Tickets-only over-weights the loudest 5 customers; user-research corroboration identifies silent majority pain points that tickets never surface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Functional gaps: features that do not work as specified or are missing.</item>
      <item>Performance issues: speed, reliability, scalability below threshold.</item>
      <item>Usability problems: users cannot complete tasks without workarounds.</item>
      <item>Security: known vulnerabilities or compliance violations.</item>
      <item>Data: quality, integrity, or access issues affecting business decisions.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Root Cause Requirements">
    <rule>
      <statement>Require a minimum 3-entry 5-whys chain for every limitation row; reject any row where the root_cause restates the symptom description.</statement>
      <rationale>Remediation that lands on symptoms produces the same defect next quarter; only root-cause-anchored remediation is durable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Limitation: "Export fails for large datasets." Root cause: "Export fails for large datasets." — This is symptom restatement, not root cause. Reject this row and re-run with 5-whys drill.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>5-whys chain: (1) Export fails → (2) timeout at 30s → (3) synchronous processing → (4) no async job queue → (5) batch design was never planned for &gt;10k rows. Root cause category: technical. Remediation: implement async export job.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Severity Derivation">
    <rule>
      <statement>Derive severity from a numeric formula (users_affected x frequency x business_impact); never assert severity without showing the math.</statement>
      <rationale>Without a numeric formula, every limitation is tagged "High" within a week of the register opening — prioritization breaks entirely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Critical: affects &gt;50% of users, occurs daily, blocks core business process.</item>
      <item>High: affects &gt;20% of users, occurs weekly, creates significant workaround burden.</item>
      <item>Medium: affects &lt;20% of users, occurs monthly, has viable workaround.</item>
      <item>Low: affects &lt;5% of users, rare, cosmetic or minor inconvenience.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Remediation Options">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document "Accept" remediation only when every cheaper option (fix, workaround, defer) is explicitly listed and rejected with rationale.</statement>
      <rationale>Accepting without exhausting alternatives is not a decision — it is inaction dressed up as analysis.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/limitation-register.md">Limitation register with root cause, severity formula, and remediation columns.</reference>
  </section>
</text>
