<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-unit-economics" title="Unit Economics and Stress Tests">
  <summary>CAC/LTV/payback formulas, P10/P50/P90 scenario model, churn floor rules, and five stress tests that define model viability.</summary>

  <section title="Core Formulas">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always compute LTV with a lifetime cap of 60 months — the formula 1/churn explodes at low churn rates and produces fantasy LTVs.</statement>
      <rationale>1% monthly churn implies 100-month (8.3 year) average lifetime. SaaS products rarely sustain customers that long. Cap at 60 months unless backed by a 10-K showing 5-year cohorts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>CAC = total marketing + sales spend / new customers acquired (use paid CAC for LTV:CAC, not blended)</item>
      <item>LTV = ARPU * gross_margin * min(1/churn, 60 months)</item>
      <item>LTV:CAC ratio target: 3:1 or higher. Below 1:1 = burning cash on acquisition. Below 3:1 = marginal at scale.</item>
      <item>Payback period = CAC / (ARPU * gross_margin). Target: &lt;12 months. &gt;24 months requires exceptional retention evidence.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="P10/P50/P90 Scenario Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Run unit economics in three scenarios (P10 pessimistic, P50 base, P90 optimistic) before writing any verdict; the P10 verdict is the only one that matters for runway and hiring decisions.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-point LTV:CAC hides the distribution. Investors and operators need to know if the model survives a bad quarter (P10), not just a median one. Refusing to average ranges is a hard rule.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>P10: ARPU $20, churn 6%, CAC $80 → LTV $280, LTV:CAC 3.5:1, payback 20mo. P50: ARPU $29, churn 3%, CAC $50 → LTV $773, LTV:CAC 15:1, payback 9mo. P90: ARPU $38, churn 2%, CAC $35 → LTV $1267, LTV:CAC 36:1, payback 5mo. Verdict based on P10: model survives at minimum threshold.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Five Stress Tests">
    <rule>
      <statement>The model passes only if it survives all five stress tests at P50 and does not go below 1:1 LTV:CAC at P10.</statement>
      <rationale>A model that passes only 4 of 5 tests at P50 has a known failure mode that will materialize as the business scales. Documenting the failure mode is more valuable than optimistic forecasting.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Scale: does unit economics hold at 10x, 100x customers? (Watch: marginal infrastructure costs, support load)</item>
      <item>Competition: what if prices drop 50%? (Check: can gross margin absorb a 50% ARPU cut?)</item>
      <item>Churn: what if monthly churn doubles? (Run: P10 with churn * 2 applied)</item>
      <item>CAC: what if acquisition costs rise 3x? (Check: channel saturation, Apple ATT, cookie deprecation)</item>
      <item>Time: how long until profitable at P50? (Calculate: break-even customer count = fixed costs / contribution margin)</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Churn Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Refuse to compute LTV with monthly churn below 1% unless backed by a public 10-K — sub-1% churn is a unicorn claim requiring evidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Agents accept 0.5%/month churn from a blog post; LTV explodes 5x and the model looks viable when it is not. Baremetrics benchmarks show median SaaS monthly churn at 2-4%.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Model churn as cohort-variable, not flat — month-1 churn is 3-10x month-12 churn. Flat churn assumptions understate early-cohort losses.</statement>
      <rationale>New users churn at much higher rates than retained users. A flat 3%/month model dramatically underestimates first-month losses and overestimates LTV.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/unit-econ-scenarios.sh">P10/P50/P90 LTV:CAC and payback from four command-line arguments.</reference>
</text>
