<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Modern BA Framework: BABOK for Agile, AI/ML, Cloud, and Platform Delivery Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules grounding the modern-ba-framework methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced from `content/06-decision-tree.xml`.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 1 (declare perspectives): List explicit perspective set; reject 'agile' as the default-without-justification.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the declare perspectives gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 2 (adapt kas): For each KA, list perspective-specific tasks/deliverables.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the adapt kas gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 3 (template deliverables): Pick correct template variants per perspective.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the template deliverables gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Step 4 (review): Cross-functional review; verify each perspective has concrete deliverables.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Skipping or reordering this step breaks the methodology's invariants; it is the review gate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If preconditions for modern-ba-framework do not hold, do not apply this methodology; route to an alternative as the decision tree suggests.</statement>
      <rationale source="BABOK v3 + F-066 wave-9 author">Methodologies misapplied to wrong contexts create overhead without value; explicit skip preserves the agent's budget.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
