<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-production-config" title="Kubernetes Production Configuration">
  <summary>Resource requests/limits, health probes, security context hardening, PodDisruptionBudget, and image policy.</summary>

  <section title="Resource Requests and Limits">
    <rule>
      <statement>Always set resource requests AND limits on every container; base requests on P95 observed usage, not guesses.</statement>
      <rationale>Without requests, the scheduler cannot make correct node placement decisions. Without limits, a runaway process can consume all node memory and evict neighboring pods. Requests set to P95 usage prevent 99.94% over-provisioning seen in typical clusters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
resources:
  requests:
    memory: "256Mi"
    cpu: "250m"
  limits:
    memory: "512Mi"
    cpu: "500m"  # consider omitting CPU limit to avoid throttling
]]></code>
      <note>CPU limits cause throttling even when node capacity is available. Many teams omit CPU limits and rely on requests for scheduling. Memory limits remain critical — OOMKill is a hard boundary.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting requests equal to limits (Guaranteed QoS) for all pods.</description>
      <reason>Guaranteed QoS is appropriate for latency-sensitive workloads. For most workloads, Burstable QoS (requests lower than limits) allows better bin-packing and handles traffic spikes without OOMKill.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Health Probes">
    <rule>
      <statement>Configure all three probes: startupProbe for slow-starting apps, readinessProbe to gate traffic, livenessProbe to restart deadlocked containers.</statement>
      <rationale>Without startupProbe, livenessProbe can kill a container during initialization before it is ready. Without readinessProbe, load balancers send traffic to pods that are not yet serving. Without livenessProbe, deadlocked processes accumulate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
startupProbe:
  httpGet:
    path: /healthz
    port: 8080
  failureThreshold: 30  # up to 5 minutes to start
  periodSeconds: 10
readinessProbe:
  httpGet:
    path: /ready
    port: 8080
  initialDelaySeconds: 5
  periodSeconds: 5
  failureThreshold: 3
livenessProbe:
  httpGet:
    path: /healthz
    port: 8080
  initialDelaySeconds: 30
  periodSeconds: 15
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Context">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every container must have all four security context fields set: runAsNonRoot: true, readOnlyRootFilesystem: true, allowPrivilegeEscalation: false, capabilities.drop: ["ALL"].</statement>
      <rationale>These four together prevent the most common container escape paths. runAsNonRoot prevents trivial UID 0 exploitation. readOnlyRootFilesystem prevents persistence. drop ALL capabilities removes Linux kernel attack surface. allowPrivilegeEscalation: false prevents setuid escalation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
securityContext:
  runAsNonRoot: true
  runAsUser: 1000
  readOnlyRootFilesystem: true
  allowPrivilegeEscalation: false
  capabilities:
    drop: ["ALL"]
  seccompProfile:
    type: RuntimeDefault
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="High Availability and Disruption">
    <rule>
      <statement>Define a PodDisruptionBudget for every Deployment with more than one replica; set minAvailable to at least 1 (or maxUnavailable to 1 for larger deployments).</statement>
      <rationale>Without a PDB, a node drain during maintenance can remove all replicas simultaneously, causing a complete outage. PDB ensures at least one replica stays healthy during voluntary disruptions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use latest as image tag in production; pin to a specific immutable tag (digest or version).</statement>
      <rationale>latest is mutable — the image it points to can change between pod restarts. A node restart can pull a different image version than the currently running pods, causing split-brain versions in a Deployment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/deployment-secure.yaml">Production Deployment with full security context, probes, PDB</reference>
  </section>
</text>
