<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-scaling-observability" title="Kubernetes Scaling and Observability">
  <summary>HPA/VPA/Karpenter autoscaling, deployment strategies (rolling/blue-green/canary), and RED metrics with GitOps checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Autoscaling">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use HPA for request-based workloads, VPA for right-sizing resource requests, Karpenter (or Cluster Autoscaler) for node-level scaling — they complement each other.</statement>
      <rationale>HPA adds/removes pods based on load. VPA adjusts the resources per pod based on observed usage. Karpenter provisions/deprovisioned nodes based on pending pods. All three are needed for fully elastic clusters.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
apiVersion: autoscaling/v2
kind: HorizontalPodAutoscaler
spec:
  scaleTargetRef:
    apiVersion: apps/v1
    kind: Deployment
    name: my-app
  minReplicas: 2
  maxReplicas: 20
  metrics:
    - type: Resource
      resource:
        name: cpu
        target:
          type: Utilization
          averageUtilization: 70
    - type: Resource
      resource:
        name: memory
        target:
          type: AverageValue
          averageValue: 400Mi
]]></code>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Setting HPA minReplicas to 1 for production services.</description>
      <reason>A single replica has no redundancy during rolling updates, node maintenance, or pod restarts. Use minReplicas: 2 minimum; add PodAntiAffinity to spread across nodes.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Deployment Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use Rolling Update (default) for most deployments; use Argo Rollouts for canary or blue-green when needing traffic control and automatic rollback based on metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>Native blue-green requires two full Deployments and manual Service switching. Argo Rollouts automates traffic splitting, analysis, and rollback based on error rate thresholds — reducing human error during production deploys.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Rolling Update: gradual pod replacement, zero downtime, simple — default for most</item>
      <item>Blue/Green: instant traffic switch, full environment switch, instant rollback — use for breaking changes</item>
      <item>Canary (Argo Rollouts): % traffic split, metric-based promotion, automatic rollback — use for high-risk changes</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Observability">
    <rule>
      <statement>Instrument every service with RED metrics (Rate, Error rate, Duration) and expose them on /metrics for Prometheus scraping.</statement>
      <rationale>RED metrics answer the three most important production questions: how much traffic, how many errors, how slow. Without them, diagnosis requires log parsing which is slower and less precise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Rate: requests/second — detect traffic spikes and drops</item>
      <item>Errors: 5xx/4xx per second — detect regressions immediately after deploy</item>
      <item>Duration: P50/P95/P99 latency — detect performance degradation before users complain</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define SLO-based alerts on error budget burn rate rather than raw threshold alerts on individual metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>A 1% error rate at 1000 RPS means 10 errors/s — critical. At 1 RPS it means 0.01 errors/s — negligible. Burn rate alerts scale with traffic and prevent alert fatigue.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/hpa.yaml">HPA with CPU and custom metric targets</reference>
    <reference path="templates/networkpolicy-default-deny.yaml">Default-deny NetworkPolicy with explicit ingress/egress</reference>
  </section>
</text>
