<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-anchoring-strategies" title="AR Anchoring Strategies">
  <summary>Anchoring type matrix for AR experiences — horizontal surface, vertical surface, image tracking, object recognition, and geo — with use cases, fallback chains, and tracking quality rules.</summary>

  <section title="Anchoring Types">
    <rule>
      <statement>Choose an anchoring type based on the use case and always define a fallback chain for when primary tracking fails.</statement>
      <rationale>AR tracking degrades with poor lighting, low-texture surfaces, or underpowered devices. Without a fallback the user sees a blank screen or a jittering object.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Anchoring Type    | Best Use Case                      | Fallback
Horizontal plane  | Furniture try-on, floor navigation  | vertical plane → manual placement
Vertical plane    | Wall posters, window overlays        | image marker
Image tracking    | Product packaging, business cards    | object recognition → GPS/compass
Object recognition| Tools, vehicles, printed logos       | image marker
Geo (VPS/GPS)     | Outdoor navigation, city guides      | GPS + compass only
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Tracking Quality Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Give the user scanning feedback within 2 seconds of AR mode launch; fall back to the next anchor type if tracking is not established within 8 seconds.</statement>
      <rationale>Waiting silently erodes trust. Users do not understand why nothing appears. Progressive feedback ("Move device slowly") sets correct expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Minimum 200 lux for indoor horizontal-plane tracking; warn user if environment is too dark.</item>
      <item>High-contrast, non-reflective images work best for image tracking; warn and offer fallback on reflective surfaces.</item>
      <item>Show "Looking for surfaces..." indicator during scan phase; replace with "Good tracking" confirmation on anchor.</item>
      <item>Let user re-scan if tracking quality drops — expose a "Reset AR" control.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Surface Placement Best Practices">
    <rule>
      <statement>Snap AR content to detected surfaces; do not leave objects floating mid-air, as unstable placement causes motion discomfort and looks broken.</statement>
      <rationale>Floating objects drift as tracking updates and appear unanchored, destroying the "AR feel" that makes spatial interfaces useful.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Horizontal surfaces (tables, floors): documents, 3D models, navigation paths.</item>
      <item>Vertical surfaces (walls, doors): posters, dashboards, labels.</item>
      <item>Respect physical boundaries — content should not clip through detected geometry.</item>
      <item>Match content scale to detected surface size; provide user resize with pinch gesture.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="WebAR Constraints">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying ARKit-spec patterns directly to WebAR without checking browser support.</description>
      <reason>iOS Safari does not support WebXR Device API; AR on iPhone must use AR Quick Look (model-viewer) or a native wrapper. WebAR has the worst tracking parity across platforms.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <p>For WebAR: use &lt;model-viewer&gt; for iOS Quick Look + Android Scene Viewer as the baseline; upgrade to 8th Wall or Niantic Lightship for richer tracking where commercial license is available.</p>
  </section>
</text>
