<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-interaction-and-safety" title="AR Interaction Patterns, Safety, and Accessibility">
  <summary>Touch, gaze, voice, and controller interaction patterns for AR, plus safety rules for obstacle avoidance and AR-free zones, accessibility requirements, and performance constraints.</summary>

  <section title="Interaction Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every AR interaction must have a voice-command alternative; gaze-based selection provides a hands-free path for motor-limited users.</statement>
      <rationale>W3C XAUR requires multiple input modalities for XR. Touch-only AR excludes users with motor disabilities and users who are multitasking (e.g., holding a tool while viewing maintenance overlays).</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Interaction  | Touch gesture           | Voice alternative
Select       | Tap                     | "Select [object name]"
Move         | Drag                    | "Move [object] to [location]"
Scale        | Pinch                   | "Make bigger" / "Make smaller"
Rotate       | Two-finger rotate       | "Rotate [degrees]"
Open menu    | Long press              | "Show menu"
Dismiss      | Swipe off screen        | "Cancel" / "Hide AR"
      ]]></code>
    </example>
    <p>Gaze-based selection: dwell time 1-2 seconds, show visual countdown ring on gaze target, allow cancel by looking away. Require an explicit confirmation before destructive actions.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Safety Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never use AR overlays to obscure safety hazards, moving obstacles, or exit paths; always provide a one-tap "Exit AR" control that is always visible.</statement>
      <rationale>Users walking while using phone AR or wearing AR glasses can collide with real-world objects. Obscuring hazards creates physical danger, not just a UX problem.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Provide a "Safety mode" that dims or hides AR content — activate automatically when device detects motion.</item>
      <item>Emit audio warnings for detected obstacles (requires Depth API or semantic segmentation).</item>
      <item>Include an "AR-free zone" toggle that pauses overlays in sensitive areas.</item>
      <item>Keep AR content minimal — every additional layer raises cognitive load and obscures real-world cues.</item>
    </list>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Hiding the "Exit AR" button once the AR experience starts.</description>
      <reason>Trapping users in AR is both a safety issue and an accessibility failure. Exit must always be one tap away.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Accessibility Requirements">
    <list>
      <item>High contrast AR elements; user-adjustable contrast mode.</item>
      <item>Color-blind safe palettes for all AR indicators.</item>
      <item>Adjustable text size in spatial UI (minimum 44dp tap targets on mobile AR).</item>
      <item>Option to disable AR entirely and use a 2D fallback experience.</item>
      <item>Reduce AR when device detects walking or rapid movement (motion comfort).</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use environmental lighting estimation to match AR shadow direction and color temperature to the real scene.</statement>
      <rationale>Without light estimation, AR objects look pasted onto the world ("uncanny valley"), reducing depth perception and increasing cognitive load — particularly for users with visual processing difficulties.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Performance Constraints">
    <rule>
      <statement>Maintain a minimum 30 FPS; degrade AR content quality automatically if FPS drops below threshold rather than letting the frame rate drop further.</statement>
      <rationale>Inconsistent frame timing is a leading cause of AR-induced motion sickness and vestibular discomfort. Battery and thermal limits typically cap phone AR sessions at 10-20 minutes.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Target 60 FPS; minimum 30 FPS; display a warning and quality-reduction prompt if FPS drops below 25.</item>
      <item>Show battery status; provide a "low-power mode" that reduces texture resolution and particle effects.</item>
      <item>Display thermal warnings before device throttles the AR session.</item>
      <item>Always provide a non-AR alternative path — some users cannot or will not enter AR (motion sensitivity, low-end device, battery).</item>
    </list>
    <reference path="templates/ar-anchor-schema.json">Anchoring decision schema with performance, accessibility, and lifecycle fields</reference>
  </section>
</text>
