<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Content Calendar Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Solo Content Calendar Template application must enforce. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-pain-pinned" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row MUST cite a pain_ref from the ICP pain ladder; rows pinned to a pain no longer in top-5 are auto-flagged for retirement.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford — Obviously Awesome">Content unpinned from ranked ICP pain drifts to entertainment; entertainment never converts for solo founders.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-one-per-week" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cadence MUST be exactly one shippable asset per week_iso; two-in-one-week and zero-the-next is a violation.</statement>
      <rationale source="Justin Welsh — Content Operating System">Search and audience algorithms reward regularity, not bursts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-friday-draft-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Next week's row MUST be at status='drafted' by Friday EOD; failure replaces next week's writing block with backfill.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — Faion solo-content cadence audit 2026">Blank-page anxiety on Monday kills the week; carrying a draft keeps cadence under stress.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-one-bet-per-row" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row MUST declare ONE channel AND ONE primary keyword OR hook; multi-channel multi-keyword rows are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Justin Welsh — Content Operating System">Spreading one asset across channels thins launch energy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-quarterly-retire" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly review MUST retire assets whose pain_ref left top-5 OR whose publish-to-conversion ratio is below median for ≥8 weeks; retirement = stop promoting (do not delete).</statement>
      <rationale source="Detailed.com / Aleyda Solís content audits">Old underperformers eat crawl budget and audience trust; quarterly pruning lifts the rest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
