<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Content Calendar — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Testable rules every weekly content row must enforce. These are HARD rules — inspiration or novelty cannot override them.</summary>
  <section title="The rules">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row MUST cite a `pain_ref` from the ICP pain ladder; rows pinned to a pain that no longer ranks in the top-5 are auto-flagged for retirement at quarterly review.</statement>
      <rationale source="ICP-fit research (April Dunford Obviously Awesome, JTBD discipline)">Content unpinned from ranked ICP pain drifts to entertainment; for solo founders entertainment never converts.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Cadence MUST be exactly one shippable asset per week_iso; two assets in one week and zero the next is a violation, not a balance.</statement>
      <rationale source="SEO + audience-conditioning research on cadence consistency">Search and audience algorithms reward regularity, not bursts; the rule encodes that explicitly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Next week's row MUST be at status `drafted` by Friday EOD of the current week; failure replaces the next week's writing block with a backfill block on a stalled row.</statement>
      <rationale source="WIP + work-in-flight ops discipline">Blank-page anxiety on Monday kills the week; carrying a draft into the writing block keeps cadence under stress.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each row MUST declare ONE distribution channel and ONE primary keyword OR hook (not both, not three); the row owns one bet per asset.</statement>
      <rationale source="Distribution-first content discipline (Justin Welsh / Amanda Natividad analyses)">Multi-channel asset spread thins the launch energy; one channel + one bet outperforms split campaigns at solo scale.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Quarterly review MUST retire assets whose pain_ref left the top-5 OR whose publish-to-conversion ratio is below the calendar's median for ≥ 8 weeks; retirement = stop promoting, do not delete.</statement>
      <rationale source="Content-pruning research (Detailed.com / Aleyda Solís content audits)">Old underperformers eat crawl budget and audience trust; quarterly pruning lifts the rest of the catalog.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <section title="Canonical examples">
    <example type="good" title="Anchored content row">
      <code lang="yaml"><![CDATA[
week_iso: 2026-W22
pain_ref: P2  # "founders cannot tell which features paid users actually use"
asset_type: blog_post
title: "5 SQL queries every solo SaaS founder runs every Monday"
target_keyword: "solo saas monday metrics queries"
distribution_channel: seo
publish_date: 2026-05-28
status: drafted
]]></code>
      <note>Pinned to a ranked pain, one channel, one keyword bet, drafted by Friday.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad" title="Un-anchored content row">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"Maybe write something about AI agents this week? Or that funny story from yesterday?"
]]></code>
      <note>No pain ref, no channel, no draft, no status. The row will not ship and is a leading indicator of the calendar's death.</note>
    </example>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="../icp-fit-scorecard-solo/" />
  </see-also>
</text>
