<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Gumroad Ops Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every Gumroad listing must satisfy. Hard rules; designed to prevent cover-blur, MoR confusion, broken affiliate flows, and unattributed listings.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-six-field-listing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every listing carries 6 mandatory fields: cover_url (≥1280×720), subtitle (≤280 chars), price (fixed | pwyw | tiers), product_type (file | license | link), refund_policy (one of Gumroad's 4 enums), tags (1-5 from Gumroad's allowlist).</statement>
      <rationale source="Gumroad listing-conversion data (public seller dashboards 2024-2025)">Listings missing cover, subtitle, or tags convert &lt;30% of the median; the six-field minimum is empirically the conversion floor.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-mor-not-self-vat" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Gumroad acts as Merchant of Record. You do NOT collect VAT/GST yourself on Gumroad-billed transactions. Your invoicing system must NOT issue a separate VAT invoice to the buyer for those sales.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gumroad MoR terms; EU VAT framework">Double-taxing the buyer is the most expensive Gumroad mistake — leads to chargebacks and account suspension. Gumroad remits VAT to the relevant tax authority on your behalf and provides MoR receipts.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-license-api-for-software" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For software / license-keyed products, license key delivery uses Gumroad's License API (`/v2/licenses/verify`). Each download includes a unique key; your client validates at startup and on a daily cadence.</statement>
      <rationale source="Gumroad License API docs; SaaS piracy mitigation patterns">Hard-coded keys in the download bundle defeat the point. License API also lets you revoke on refund without rebuilding the binary.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-affiliate-commission-band" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Affiliate commission is set between 30% and 50% for indie launches. Below 30% does not motivate; above 50% leaves the founder margin-thin on Gumroad's 10% + payment fees.</statement>
      <rationale source="Affiliate-marketing benchmarks (ShareASale + indie-launch postmortems)">30% is the floor where affiliates promote; 50% is the ceiling where founder still nets positive after platform + payment fees.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-ab-copy-two-week-minimum" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Gumroad copy A/B experiments run minimum 14 days OR until 100 conversions per variant — whichever comes first. Variants flipped earlier are inconclusive and burn the test slot.</statement>
      <rationale source="A/B-test discipline; Gumroad seller-forum experiment threads">Most indie products see &lt;50 sales/wk; below this threshold, two weeks is the minimum window for any kind of signal.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r6-monthly-review-with-promotion" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Monthly: pull Gumroad dashboard CSV. For each listing, compute conversion rate, refund rate, affiliate share, and rank by 30-day revenue. Promote the top 2 to feature spots (Gumroad Discover, your own site hero); demote the bottom 2 (archive or unbundle).</statement>
      <rationale source="Indie-product portfolio management practice">Without monthly pruning, the catalogue rots and dashboard noise hides the few products that actually compound.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="run-the-checklist" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies-If hold and no Skip-If trigger applies, walk the 6-step procedure end-to-end and run the validator before publishing the listing.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory run leaf">Decision-tree run leaf for canonical execution path.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skip this methodology when the Applies-If preconditions are not met OR any Skip-If disqualifier holds.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 v3 B5.6 — mandatory skip leaf">Decision-tree skip leaf so non-applicable inputs route cleanly out.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
