<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Egress Cost Hidden Budget Guide Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules grounding the Egress Cost Hidden Budget Guide methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-enumerate-all-egress-sources" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every egress path MUST be enumerated: internet egress per service, cross-AZ per service, NAT-gateway processing, VPC peering, transit gateway. Path graph attached to the report.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Cost Explorer usage types">Hidden paths cause bill surprises; enumeration surfaces them before launch.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-attribute-to-feature" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each egress source MUST be attributed to a feature / customer-tier / job type. 'platform overhead' is not an attribution; trace to the feature.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps attribution practice">Without attribution, optimisations target the wrong feature; with attribution, the costly feature surfaces.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-per-region-budget-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Per-region egress cap MUST be set with alert at 80% + freeze action at 100%. Cap calibrated to product margin (e.g. egress / revenue ratio ceiling).</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps budget patterns">Caps stop runaway spend; alert + freeze enforce them.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-worst-case-traffic-model" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Egress model MUST include worst-case (4x peak) traffic scenario; report shows what egress + cost would be at the spike. Reserved budget covers the spike.</statement>
      <rationale source="capacity-planning best practice">Without worst-case, the spike triggers freeze actions or bill panic.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-nat-gateway-alternatives" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When NAT-GW processing &gt; $1k/month, evaluate alternatives: VPC endpoints for S3/DynamoDB, NAT instance for low volume, or direct internet via public subnet for non-private resources.</statement>
      <rationale source="AWS Well-Architected Cost">NAT-GW processing is per-GB; VPC endpoints are free. Many setups overspend on NAT-GW by 10x.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6-quarterly-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Egress budget MUST be reviewed quarterly + per release with measurable traffic delta. Reviews update budgets + alerts.</statement>
      <rationale source="FinOps lifecycle">Traffic drifts; quarterly review keeps budget calibrated.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
