<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ops-contractor-basics Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ops-contractor-basics. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Delegate when: the task is a specialized skill where others perform better, it is time-consuming and repetitive, and the contractor rate is less than 60% of the founder's effective hourly rate.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Core competency work (your competitive advantage) stays with the founder. Everything else is a candidate for delegation. The 60% threshold ensures the ROI exceeds overhead and management time.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Always run a paid test task on a real deliverable before any ongoing engagement. The test task budget is marketing spend, not work owed. Never ask for unpaid sample work.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">The test task is the only reliable signal of real work quality AND communication style. Portfolios and interviews are necessary but not sufficient filters. Unpaid work filters out quality candidates who have options.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Document the role's quality bar with 2-3 "good output" and "bad output" examples before posting the job. This artifact is harder to produce than the job post but is the highest-leverage filter.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Without an explicit quality standard, applicant scoring becomes subjective and LLM shortlisting optimizes for surface signals (grammar, buzzwords) rather than output quality.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Treat contractors as contractors: they control how they work (not just what they deliver), use their own tools, set their own schedule, and have other clients. Never dictate working hours, mandate specific tools, or require daily standups.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Misclassifying a contractor as an employee exposes the business to US penalties of $1K-$25K per contractor plus back taxes. CA AB5 and EU dependent-contractor tests apply even more strictly. Each of the listed behaviors is a misclassification indicator.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Agent must not send a contract, sign an agreement, or make any payment commitment autonomously. Human approval is required at every commitment point (test task commissioning, contract signing, first invoice approval).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Misclassification penalties ($1K-$25K per contractor), unenforceable contract terms from training data, and incorrect scope commitments are not LLM-recoverable errors.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When scoring applicants, output a ranked top-3 for human review and explicitly state "Do NOT recommend a hire — surface candidates for human decision". Never select the contractor.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">LLMs over-weight grammatical fluency in applicant summaries. For design and dev roles, portfolio quality (requiring human judgment) matters more than communication polish. The selection is a human call.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Before publishing any job post with a budget range, WebSearch current rates for the specific role and region (e.g. "UI designer Ukraine hourly rate 2025"). Never use hardcoded rate tables from training data.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Market rates shift significantly by year and region. The illustrative rate tables in the source README are anchors, not current market data.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
