<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-examples" title="Contractor Basics — Worked Examples">
  <summary>Two real hiring examples: UI designer from Dribbble/Twitter and virtual assistant from Upwork, with process and outcomes.</summary>

  <section title="UI designer hire">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Need: UI design for new product pages. Process: posted on Dribbble and Twitter; received 40 applications; shortlisted 5 with strong portfolios; paid test: redesign one page ($150, real deliverable, could ship); selected best result. Outcome: $75/hr, 10 hrs/month, ongoing relationship, freed 15+ hours/month of founder time.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Virtual assistant hire">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Need: admin, scheduling, email management. Process: posted on Upwork; filtered on reviews and demonstrated experience; 20-minute interview for communication quality; 2-week trial at 10 hours/week; promoted to ongoing. Outcome: $20/hr, 15 hrs/week, handles all admin, saved 20+ hours/week, ROI estimated 10x on investment.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Founder hires without a paid test task because "the portfolio looked great".</description>
      <reason>Portfolio shows past work on past problems with past clients. The test task reveals how the contractor handles YOUR problems, YOUR feedback, and YOUR communication style. Skipping it is the most common expensive hiring mistake.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent sends a contract or offer letter to a contractor without human approval.</description>
      <reason>Contract signing creates legal obligations. Misclassification flags embedded in the contract language are not reliably detected by LLMs. Mandatory human-in-loop at every commitment point.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent publishes a job post with a specific hourly rate range derived from training data without current market verification.</description>
      <reason>Contractor market rates vary significantly by region, skill, and current demand. Hallucinated rates either deter qualified applicants or attract applicants expecting different compensation. Always WebSearch current rates before publishing.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
