<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Legal Compliance Routing and Overview Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every application of `ops-legal-compliance` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1-routing-decision-record" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Produce a written routing decision-record naming which sub-methodology applies (`ops-legal-basics` for foundation, `ops-legal-compliance-checklist` for stage-gated implementation). Skipping the routing record is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Compliance-as-code practice">Without a routing record, work duplicates between the foundation and the implementation tracker. The routing record names the sub-methodology and the owner of each sub-track.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2-regulations-inventory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>List every regulation applicable to the business (GDPR, CCPA, CAN-SPAM, COPPA, ADA, PCI-DSS) with an explicit applies/not-applies status per regulation. 'Will-check-later' status is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Compliance-program canon (ISO 19600, NIST CSF)">Unknown applicability is the dominant cause of inadvertent non-compliance. Forcing applies/not-applies status surfaces gaps before regulators do.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3-policy-stack-inventory" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Inventory ToS, Privacy Policy, Cookie Policy, and Refund Policy with `last_reviewed` per policy. Any policy with `last_reviewed` &gt; 12 months is treated as stale and routed to refresh.</statement>
      <rationale source="Documentation-as-code practice (Diátaxis maintainability model)">Policies drift faster than products. Stale policies expose the operator to enforcement based on outdated text that the team no longer follows.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4-contractor-vendor-track" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain a separate contractor / vendor contract inventory with NDA, scope, payment terms, and IP clause per row. Treating contractor agreements as out-of-scope of compliance is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Vendor-risk-management practice">Contractor and vendor breaches cascade into the operator's compliance posture (SOC 2, GDPR processor obligations). The vendor track is part of compliance, not a side channel.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5-quarterly-routing-review" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Review the routing record quarterly and update which sub-methodology applies as the business grows (entity change, new market, new payment processor). Routing once and never again is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Compliance-program practice">Compliance applicability changes with business growth (new market triggers new privacy law; new payment method triggers PCI-DSS). Quarterly review keeps routing accurate.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in `Applies If` fail OR any item in `Skip If` triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact's parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
