<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="six-core-principles">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>PMBoK 8 consolidates twelve principles into six: Holistic View, Value, Quality, Accountability, Sustainability, Empowered Teams. Every PM artefact audited as binary pass/fail.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>pmbok</tag>
      <tag>principles</tag>
      <tag>governance</tag>
      <tag>value</tag>
      <tag>sustainability</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-25</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>PMBoK 8 Six Core Principles</title>
    <summary>PMBoK 8 consolidates the PMBoK 7 twelve principles into six: Adopt Holistic View, Focus on Value, Embed Quality, Lead Accountably, Integrate Sustainability, Build Empowered Teams. Every PM artefact or decision is audited against these six as binary pass/fail questions — "passed: true" requires positive evidence, not merely absence of failure. Any failing principle stops the stage gate.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Abstract principles degrade into platitudes without a concrete decision framework. The six-question audit converts principles into a rejection gate: if any principle is violated, the artefact must be fixed or escalated before proceeding. Paired with measurable indicators (outcomes table for Value, CO2 proxy for Sustainability, DoD for Quality), the audit becomes testable rather than decorative.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Drafting or reviewing a project charter, decision log, or change request</item>
        <item>Auditing an existing plan for principle gaps (no sustainability section, no value statement)</item>
        <item>Anchoring any PM-domain LLM call with a six-question self-check step at the end</item>
        <item>Migrating a PMBoK 7 twelve-principle plan to PMBoK 8 six-principle structure</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Tactical execution work (sprint planning, ticket triage) — principles are too abstract to give tactical guidance; use methodology checklists</item>
        <item>Non-PMI environments (PRINCE2, IPMA, SAFe) — vocabulary clashes; map to those frameworks' own principles</item>
        <item>Audit/compliance contexts requiring a specific named standard (ISO 21500, ISO 21502) — PMBoK principles are guidance, not certification</item>
        <item>Technical deep-dives (architecture review, security) — principles do not substitute for domain expertise</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="The Six Principles">
      <list>
        <item>Adopt Holistic View — see the project as part of a larger system; consider upstream and downstream effects on organisation and stakeholders. Indicator: context section in charter referencing organisational goals.</item>
        <item>Focus on Value — deliver outcomes and benefits, not just outputs. Indicator: outcomes table mapping each deliverable to a named stakeholder benefit.</item>
        <item>Embed Quality — quality is built into process and definition of done, not inspected in at the end. Indicator: DoD / acceptance criteria present before work starts.</item>
        <item>Lead Accountably — ethical, transparent leadership with clear escalation paths. Indicator: decision log with rationale and RACI with named accountability per deliverable.</item>
        <item>Integrate Sustainability — consider environmental, social, and governance impact throughout. Indicator: at least one measurable sustainability proxy (CO2 estimate, accessibility score, social impact metric).</item>
        <item>Build Empowered Teams — trust, autonomy, psychological safety, and distributed leadership. Indicator: team working agreements exist and team charter was co-created with the team.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="PMBoK 7 to PMBoK 8 Consolidation">
      <p>PMBoK 7 had 12 principles; PMBoK 8 reduces to 6. Key collapses: "Stewardship" + "Leadership" + "Ethics" → Lead Accountably; "Systems Thinking" + "Complexity" → Adopt Holistic View; "Team" + "Leadership" → Build Empowered Teams. The PMBoK 7 "Quality" principle becomes Embed Quality. Sustainability is new and explicit.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Decision Framework">
      <p>Apply at every significant PM decision point. Ask in order:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Does this deliver value? (stakeholder benefit, not just task completion)</item>
        <item>Does this consider the whole system? (upstream/downstream effects)</item>
        <item>Is quality embedded? (DoD, acceptance criteria, not post-hoc testing)</item>
        <item>Am I leading accountably? (transparent rationale, named accountability)</item>
        <item>Is it sustainable? (at least one numeric proxy)</item>
        <item>Does it empower the team? (autonomy, not control; working agreements honoured)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="Principle Audit Rules">
      <rule>
        <statement>"Passed: true" requires positive evidence quoting the artefact; absence of failure is not a pass.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs default to all-green outputs because they want to be helpful. Forced evidence prevents silent compliance inflation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Any principle that fails must block the stage gate; the artefact must be fixed or escalated before the review concludes.</statement>
        <rationale>Audit without a rejection consequence is theatre; the gate must actually stop work when a principle is violated.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use exactly the six canonical names when auditing: Adopt Holistic View, Focus on Value, Embed Quality, Lead Accountably, Integrate Sustainability, Build Empowered Teams.</statement>
        <rationale>Renamed principles produce inconsistent diffs and confuse cross-team governance reviews.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Integrate Sustainability requires a numeric proxy (CO2 estimate, accessibility WCAG level, social impact scope statement); a paragraph about sustainability values does not pass.</statement>
        <rationale>Narrative sustainability is unmeasurable; numeric proxies create accountability and enable progress tracking.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Lock the PMBoK edition ("PMBoK 8, six principles") in every system prompt that runs a principle audit; never let the agent infer the edition.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs conflate PMBoK 7 twelve principles with PMBoK 8 six principles; edition ambiguity produces incorrect audits.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>All six principles pass without any explicit evidence quotes from the artefact.</description>
        <reason>All-pass outputs without quotes are LLM politeness artefacts; require citations for every passed principle.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Invoking "Build Empowered Teams" to justify removing governance or oversight.</description>
        <reason>Empowerment requires working agreements and decision rights, not absence of process; require an offsetting governance artefact.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Using "Quality" as a standalone domain label (PMBoK 6 vocabulary) inside a PMBoK 8 audit.</description>
        <reason>PMBoK 8 does not have a Quality domain; quality is the Embed Quality principle applied across all domains.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>Every PM-domain agent ends with a self-check: re-read the produced artefact and answer six binary questions, with one-sentence evidence each. Output the artefact + the six-line audit. If any principle is violated, regenerate or escalate. Keep the rubric short: one paragraph, six bullets — not a long policy.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents: principle-auditor (define inline) takes any PM artefact and returns 6 × {principle, pass/fail, evidence, fix-if-fail}. value-checker maps deliverables to stakeholder outcomes. sustainability-tagger proposes sustainability metrics per phase. faion-improver feeds audit fails into periodic remediation. faion-sdd-executor drives fixes as code tasks.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Limitations">
      <p>Six principles are abstract; without a concrete decision framework they degrade into platitudes ("focus on value"). "Sustainability" measurement is unspecified; teams adopt the word and skip the metric (CO2, accessibility, social impact proxies). Principles overlap (Holistic View ↔ Systems Thinking; Lead Accountably ↔ Build Empowered Teams) — agents weight them inconsistently across runs.</p>
      <p>"Empowered teams" can be invoked to justify lack of governance; counter-pressure required. LLMs treat the six as a checklist and tick all six even when one is clearly violated; needs forced negative evidence.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="CLI Tools and Services">
      <p>Key tools for principle audit and governance:</p>
      <list>
        <item>yq — Validate audit YAML in CI</item>
        <item>pandoc — Convert audit markdown to DOCX / PDF for governance pack</item>
        <item>markdownlint-cli — Catch missing principle sections in charter docs</item>
        <item>mermaid-cli — Render principle-violation summaries as heatmaps</item>
        <item>gh pr comment — Post audit results back into a PR</item>
      </list>
      <p>SaaS platforms: Confluence / Notion (REST, where audit results live), Jira / Linear (REST, audit failures as issues with principle label), GitHub / GitLab PRs (REST, audit posted as PR comment), Power BI / Looker (SQL, cross-portfolio principle compliance), WatershedClimate / Persefoni (partial REST, sustainability metrics), Plan A / Greenly (partial REST, CO2 footprint per project).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Keep the rubric to six bullets in any system prompt — one principle per line — to make it scannable</item>
        <item>Pair each principle with a concrete indicator (Value → "outcomes table"; Sustainability → "CO2 proxy"; Quality → "DoD"); avoid measuring abstractions</item>
        <item>Embed the audit in the gate-review pack so steering committees see it without asking</item>
        <item>For fast / lightweight projects, run the audit once at charter and once at closure — six checks, twelve minutes</item>
        <item>Use the audit as a rejection gate, not a score: any "fail" stops the gate</item>
        <item>Refresh sustainability indicators yearly as standards evolve (GHG Protocol scope updates, ESRS, ISSB)</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs default to "all six pass" because they want to be helpful — force negative evidence and reject all-pass outputs without quotes</item>
        <item>Sustainability is treated as a paragraph, not a measurement; require a numeric proxy</item>
        <item>"Empowered teams" gets invoked to justify lack of process; require an offset (working agreements, decision rights)</item>
        <item>Principles get reordered between runs; pin canonical order so diffs are readable</item>
        <item>"Quality" leaks back as a separate domain (PMBoK 6 muscle memory); reject any audit that names a Quality domain</item>
        <item>Agents conflate "Holistic View" with "Systems Thinking" (former is PMBoK 8, latter is PMBoK 7); lock the edition in the prompt</item>
        <item>Audit verdicts drift over time toward all-green; calibrate by sampling a fixed % for human review</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/principle-audit.md" purpose="Six-row audit table: principle / evidence / pass-fail / fix"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <ref slug="scope-management"/>
      <ref slug="project-integration"/>
      <ref slug="risk-management"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/standards/pmbok"/>
      <link href="https://www.iso.org/standard/50003.html"/>
      <link href="https://ghgprotocol.org/"/>
      <link href="https://www.efrag.org/"/>
      <link href="https://www.ifrs.org/groups/international-sustainability-standards-board/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
