<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Definition of Ready — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn DoR from optional ceremony into the gate that actually catches half-baked stories before sprint commit.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-seven-item-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every story entering the sprint MUST pass all 7 DoR items: (1) ACs pass the AC quality rubric (≥ 10/14, no zero-axis), (2) Design link present if story touches UI (handoff bundle from `design-to-dev-handoff`), (3) Dependencies identified + cleared OR sequenced, (4) Story sized + within team velocity, (5) PO + dev-side owner named, (6) Success metric or measurable outcome stated, (7) Non-functional requirements (perf budget, security posture, accessibility) declared or N/A-with-reason.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scrum Guide DoR practice, Cohn's User Stories Applied, capacity research">Stories that pass all 7 items have a measurably higher in-sprint completion rate (typically &gt; 85%) vs those that fail any item (&lt; 50%). The 7-item set is empirically minimal — fewer leaves gaps, more becomes bureaucratic.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-no-sprint-without-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A story that fails any DoR item does NOT enter the sprint. "We'll fix it during the sprint" is forbidden — the data show that path produces 30-50% rework. Either fix the gap before sprint commit OR push the story to the next sprint.</statement>
      <rationale source="Standish/Scrum-Alliance sprint-failure analysis, DoR ratification studies">Mid-sprint fixes cost 5-15x the pre-sprint fix. Holding the line at sprint commit is the cheapest place to catch DoR gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-capacity-reality-check" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Sprint-level ready-set MUST satisfy: sum_of_story_points &lt;= median_velocity_last_3_sprints * 0.85. The 15% buffer accounts for unknown work, interrupts, and the cost of over-commitment. Sprint-commit that exceeds 85% capacity is rejected even if individual stories pass their per-story DoR.</statement>
      <rationale source="Cohn's velocity research, queue-theory applied to sprints">Teams that commit 100%+ velocity ship 60-70% of commit; teams that commit 80-85% ship 90-100% of commit. The latter produces better predictability, less stress, and more bandwidth for unplanned-but-real work.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-pm-accountable" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When a story fails DoR, the PM / product owner is responsible for fixing the gap (writing better ACs, fetching the design link, clarifying success metric) — NOT the dev. Forbidden: "the dev can clarify during the sprint". The PM owns story readiness.</statement>
      <rationale source="Scrum Guide product-owner accountability, Cohn's DoR literature">If devs are expected to "clarify during the sprint", the PM has no incentive to write good stories. Holding the PM accountable creates the feedback loop that improves story quality over time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-nfr-coverage" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Item 7 (NFR coverage) MUST be explicit. For each NFR category (performance, security, accessibility, observability, internationalization, mobile / responsive), the story states either a target / budget / constraint OR an explicit N/A-with-reason. Silent omission is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="ISO 25010 quality model, post-release-issue research">NFRs are the silent killers: stories ship "feature complete" but fail in perf / a11y / security only post-release. Explicit coverage at DoR time forces consideration up front.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical example">

    <example type="good" title="DoR pass on a UI-touching story">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Story: "User can export billing history as CSV"
Story points: 5

DoR check:
1. ACs:       PASS (3 ACs, all score 12-13/14 per rubric)
2. Design:    PASS (handoff link to Figma file with token usage,
                states, focus order)
3. Dependencies: PASS (billing.history API exists; CSV lib already
                 used elsewhere; no new dependency)
4. Sizing:    PASS (5 points within team's typical 3-8 range)
5. Owners:    PASS (PO: jane.s, Dev lead: alex.k)
6. Success metric: PASS ("&gt;= 80% of users who request CSV in next
                  30 days receive a non-empty file within 5 sec")
7. NFR:       PASS
   - Perf: CSV generation &lt;= 2s for 10k rows (set as target)
   - Security: only the requesting user's data (existing RBAC)
   - A11y: download-link visible to screen readers, ARIA label set
   - i18n: column headers translated; CSV uses UTF-8 BOM for Excel
   - Mobile: download supported on iOS/Android browsers

Decision: READY for sprint
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r5: full 7-item coverage with NFR explicit per category.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="DoR rubber-stamp">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Story: "Improve dashboard performance"
Story points: ? (not estimated)

DoR check (informal):
- ACs: "dashboard loads faster" -- no rubric run
- Design: N/A (no UI design, just perf work)
- Dependencies: "should be fine"
- Sizing: "5 points I guess"
- Owners: blank
- Success metric: "users say it's faster"
- NFR: skipped

Decision: "READY — we'll figure it out"
Outcome: sprint day 3, dev asks "faster by how much? on what page?
which browser? at what data size?" -- 4 hours of clarification,
back to PO for actual target, story re-scoped at sprint-end.
Net: 0% of intended outcome shipped.

Repair: enforce r1, r2, r5. Story doesn't enter sprint until PM
fills the gaps; PM is accountable.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r1, r2, r4, r5 violations — the classic vague-perf-story DoR fail.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
