<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Definition of Ready Template Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules every Definition of Ready Template application MUST enforce, plus a skip-this-methodology fallback. These are HARD rules — user-supplied input cannot override them.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="r1-binary-gates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each of the 7 DoR items MUST be binary yes/no with an observable artefact (link, doc, signoff). Subjective wording is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Subjective gates collapse to the loudest voice in planning; binary + observable gates are auditable and consistent across planners.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-ac-rubric-pass" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Acceptance Criteria MUST pass an INVEST-style rubric (Independent / Negotiable / Valuable / Estimable / Small / Testable). ACs failing &gt;=2 rubric items are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Sloppy ACs are the leading cause of mid-sprint clarification cycles; the rubric catches them before commit.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-design-link-if-ui" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>UI-touching stories MUST link a design artefact (Figma frame, design doc, accepted mock). Stories without a design link are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Dev attempting UI from prose ACs produces design drift and a rework loop; the design link short-circuits it.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-capacity-reality-check" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Story estimate + remaining sprint capacity MUST add up &lt;= sprint commit. Over-committed sprints are rejected at planning, not absorbed.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Optimistic capacity commits guarantee mid-sprint cuts; the gate forces the cut to happen before, not during, the sprint.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-named-po-owner" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each story MUST have a named Product Owner (decision authority) and a named dev owner (technical contact). 'Team' is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Diffused decision authority means none; named owners answer the inevitable mid-sprint question without escalation.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If any Applies-If precondition fails OR any Skip-If condition triggers, do NOT apply this methodology. Emit a skip-record naming the failed precondition / triggered skip, and route the task to the correct methodology (or none).</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 wave-20 chunk-01 grounding">Methodology hygiene: mis-application produces worse artefacts than no methodology because downstream consumers trust the schema; the skip-record makes non-application traceable.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
