<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Gce Instance Templates Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>5 testable rules for the gce-instance-templates methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale + concrete remediation hook.</summary>
  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="immutable-versioned-templates" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Instance templates are immutable; ANY change MUST produce a new template version (suffixed v2/v3 or by date).</statement>
      <rationale source="GCE instance template docs">Editing in place is not supported; treating templates as versioned artefacts makes rollbacks trivial.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="least-privileged-service-account" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Templates MUST assign a dedicated service account with least-privileged scopes — never the default compute SA with full cloud-platform scope.</statement>
      <rationale source="GCE SA docs">Default SA grants broad project-wide access; per-template SA contains blast radius.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="os-login-iap-no-metadata-keys" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Templates MUST enable OS Login + IAP TCP forwarding; SSH keys in instance metadata are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="OS Login docs">Metadata-key SSH bypasses IAM and audit; OS Login ties access to IAM identities with full logging.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="startup-script-idempotent" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Startup scripts MUST be idempotent and check current state before mutating (no blind `apt install` loops without check).</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — VM bootstrap audit">Non-idempotent scripts fail re-execution after auto-heal, producing partially configured instances.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="metadata-no-secrets" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Secrets MUST NOT be embedded in instance metadata or startup scripts; use Secret Manager + Workload Identity instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="GCE security docs">Metadata is readable from inside the VM by any process; embedded secrets leak via local-account compromise.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the input fails ALL "Applies If" preconditions or matches ANY "Skip If" disqualifier, do not apply this methodology — route the task to the adjacent sibling instead.</statement>
      <rationale source="F-066 requirements-checklist B5.6">Even flat checklists need an explicit skip leaf in the decision tree; this rule is the universal terminal.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
