<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-adr-structure" title="ADR Structure and Lifecycle">
  <summary>Nygard format fields, status lifecycle, immutability principle, and storage conventions.</summary>

  <section title="Nygard Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every ADR must include: sequential number (NNNN), title, date, deciders, status, Context, Decision, and Consequences sections.</statement>
      <rationale>The Nygard format is the minimum viable ADR. Skipping Context means future readers cannot evaluate whether the decision still applies. Skipping Consequences means risks are hidden.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <example type="good">
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[# ADR-0001: Use PostgreSQL as primary database

**Status:** Accepted
**Date:** 2024-01-15
**Deciders:** @ruslan, @arch-team

## Context
Service requires ACID transactions and JSON querying. Team has strong PostgreSQL expertise.
SQLite ruled out due to write concurrency limits at expected scale.

## Decision
We will use PostgreSQL 16 as the primary database for all transactional data.

## Alternatives Considered
- **SQLite:** Rejected — no multi-process write concurrency.
- **MongoDB:** Rejected — team unfamiliarity; no strong schema benefit here.

## Consequences
- Positive: ACID guarantees, mature ecosystem, team expertise.
- Negative: Requires managed instance in prod (vs. embedded).
- Risk: Schema migrations must be backward-compatible (mitigated by migration tooling).]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Status Lifecycle">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use exactly these statuses: Proposed, Accepted, Rejected, Deprecated, Superseded. When superseding, add "Superseded by ADR-NNNN" to the old ADR's status field.</statement>
      <rationale>Consistent status vocabulary lets tooling and agents filter active vs. historical decisions. Free-form status strings break filtering.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Never modify the Context, Decision, or Consequences of an Accepted ADR. Only the Status field may be updated. Create a new ADR to record a changed decision.</statement>
      <rationale>Immutability preserves the historical record. Editing an accepted ADR erases the original reasoning, which is the primary value of the document.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Storage Convention">
    <rule>
      <statement>Store ADRs in version control at `docs/adr/NNNN-short-title.md`. Use 4-digit zero-padded numbers. Never reuse a number, even for superseded ADRs.</statement>
      <rationale>Co-location with code ensures ADRs evolve with the codebase and are visible in pull requests. Wikis and Confluence pages drift out of sync.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule>
      <statement>Keep ADRs to 1-2 pages. If the decision requires more explanation, put supplementary material in a linked design doc, not in the ADR body.</statement>
      <rationale>Long ADRs are not read. The goal is a scannable record of the decision, not a comprehensive design guide.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
