<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-writing-process" title="ADR Writing Process and Agent Limitations">
  <summary>Pre-writing gate, alternatives research requirements, quality checks, and agent-specific failure modes.</summary>

  <section title="Pre-Writing Gate">
    <rule>
      <statement>Before writing an ADR, verify: (1) decision has significant architectural impact, (2) decision is hard to reverse, (3) at least 2 alternatives have been considered. If none of these hold, use a code comment or commit message instead.</statement>
      <rationale>ADR overhead is not justified for trivial decisions. Over-using ADRs dilutes the signal — teams stop reading them when every minor choice has one.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Alternatives Research">
    <rule>
      <statement>Document at least 2 rejected alternatives with explicit rejection reasons. "Do nothing" counts as an alternative if it was genuinely considered.</statement>
      <rationale>An ADR without alternatives is just an assertion. The value of documenting rejected options is preventing future re-debates of the same tradeoffs.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent writes ADR with only the chosen option and no alternatives section, or with alternatives that are clearly strawmen.</description>
      <reason>LLMs default to validating the chosen option rather than steelmanning alternatives. Require the agent to explicitly argue for each alternative before explaining rejection. If an alternative has no strong case, it was not seriously considered.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Quality Checks">
    <rule>
      <statement>An ADR passes quality review when: a new team member could understand why the decision was made without any additional context, and all consequences (including negative ones) are listed.</statement>
      <rationale>ADRs written for current insiders become useless within 6-12 months as context fades. Writing for future outsiders forces clarity.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Agent lists only positive consequences or downplays negative ones to make the decision look better.</description>
      <reason>LLMs are trained to be helpful and tend to justify chosen options. Negative consequences are not failures — they are honest tradeoffs. Require the agent to list at least one negative consequence for any non-trivial decision.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Review Process">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use pull requests for ADR review. Set status to Proposed until at least one reviewer approves. Update status to Accepted only after merge.</statement>
      <rationale>PR review creates a searchable discussion thread attached to the ADR, preserving objections and amendments alongside the final document.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
