<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="ops-tax-basics">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>US solopreneur tax framework: tax types, entity selection, deduction tracking, tax-advantaged accounts, and quarterly estimated payments.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>tax</tag>
      <tag>solopreneur</tag>
      <tag>self-employment</tag>
      <tag>financial-planning</tag>
      <tag>accounting</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>ops</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-29</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Tax Basics for Solopreneurs</title>
    <summary>A US-centric framework for solopreneur tax management: understanding tax types (income, self-employment, state, sales), selecting a tax-efficient business structure, tracking deductible expenses, maximizing tax-advantaged accounts (SEP-IRA, Solo 401k, HSA), and computing quarterly estimated payments. The core rule: set aside approximately 30% of net profit monthly to a dedicated tax-savings account and compute quarterly estimates using the IRS safe-harbor rule (90% current-year or 110% prior-year for AGI over 150K).</summary>
    <why>
      <p>Solopreneurs who ignore taxes scramble at year-end and pay avoidable penalties. Self-employment tax is 15.3% on top of income tax — effective rates of 30–40% on profit are common. S-Corp election above 80K profit can save 5K–10K/year in SE tax. Retirement contributions (SEP-IRA, Solo 401k) reduce taxable income dollar-for-dollar. These savings require proactive monthly habits, not a once-a-year scramble.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>First year in business: choosing entity type, setting up expense tracking.</item>
        <item>Monthly bookkeeping: categorizing transactions, computing tax reserve.</item>
        <item>Mid-year: evaluating S-Corp election threshold.</item>
        <item>Quarterly: computing estimated tax payment due dates and amounts.</item>
        <item>Year-end: generating CPA prep package (P&amp;L, deduction log, retirement contributions).</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Filing tax returns — agent prepares supporting docs only; CPA or EA must sign.</item>
        <item>Multi-state nexus / sales-tax compliance per state — specialist domain.</item>
        <item>Crypto / DeFi / NFT tax treatment — unsettled law, high hallucination risk.</item>
        <item>Non-US jurisdictions — methodology references US Code only (Schedule C, SE tax, S-Corp, SEP-IRA).</item>
        <item>Audit response — IRS/state correspondence is human-only with CPA/EA/tax attorney.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="tax-types">
      <rule>
        <statement>Set aside approximately 30% of net monthly profit to a dedicated tax-savings account and never spend it on business operations.</statement>
        <rationale>Effective solopreneur tax rates (federal income + self-employment + state) typically reach 30–40% of net profit. Founders who do not separate reserves scramble at quarterly estimate deadlines and face underpayment penalties.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <p>Self-employment tax is 15.3% on 92.35% of net profit (12.4% Social Security on first approximately 160K, 2.9% Medicare with no cap, 0.9% additional Medicare above 200K). This is on top of federal and state income tax.</p>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Effective tax rate for 100K net profit: SE tax 14,130 + federal income approximately 15,000 + state approximately 5,000 = approximately 34,000 (34%). Reserving 2,833/month covers this.</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="entity-selection">
      <rule>
        <statement>Evaluate S-Corp election when consistent net profit exceeds 80K. Run the math annually mid-year, not at year-end when election filing windows may have passed.</statement>
        <rationale>S-Corp election allows splitting profit into salary (subject to SE tax) and distributions (not subject to SE tax). At 100K profit with 50K reasonable salary, SE tax savings are approximately 7,650/year. Below 80K, the added payroll complexity erodes the benefit.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>100K LLC (default): 15,300 SE tax. 100K with S-Corp, 50K salary: 7,650 SE tax on salary + 0 on distribution. Net savings: approximately 7,650/year.</note>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never recommend an S-Corp salary split below 40% of profit without explicitly flagging IRS "reasonable compensation" risk.</statement>
        <rationale>The IRS can reclassify distributions as salary and assess back SE tax plus penalties if salary is unreasonably low relative to the work performed.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="deductions">
      <rule>
        <statement>Use actual-method home office deduction (square footage ratio applied to rent, utilities, internet) only when the space is used exclusively and regularly for business; flag that this method creates depreciation recapture on home sale.</statement>
        <rationale>The simplified method (5/sq ft, max 1,500) is audit-safer and avoids recapture. Actual method is better only for high-rent situations with large dedicated office space.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Home office: dedicated space required; simplified (5/sqft, max 300 sqft, max 1,500) or actual (% of home costs).</item>
        <item>Equipment: computer, monitors, phone — deduct via Section 179 in year of purchase or depreciate.</item>
        <item>Software: all business-use subscriptions and tools.</item>
        <item>Marketing: ads, content creation, design — keep receipts.</item>
        <item>Professional services: legal, accounting, consulting — business-related only.</item>
        <item>Education: courses, books directly related to the business.</item>
        <item>Travel: must have documented business purpose.</item>
        <item>Health insurance premiums: self-employed deduction (check spouse employer-plan interaction).</item>
        <item>Retirement contributions: SEP-IRA, Solo 401k — reduce taxable income dollar-for-dollar.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="retirement-accounts">
      <rule>
        <statement>Prioritize retirement contributions as a tax planning tool, not just savings: SEP-IRA allows up to approximately 25% of net SE income (max approximately 66K); Solo 401k allows 22.5K employee deferral plus 25% employer contribution.</statement>
        <rationale>At a 24% marginal bracket, a 10K SEP-IRA contribution produces 2,400 in immediate federal tax savings. This is risk-free return that cannot be achieved elsewhere.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>100K net profit. SEP-IRA contribution approximately 18,500. Tax savings at 24%: 4,440. Plus SE tax deduction on half of SE tax adds approximately 2,000 more in federal savings.</note>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>HSA (Health Savings Account) requires a high-deductible health plan but provides a triple tax benefit: deduction + tax-free growth + tax-free withdrawal for medical expenses. Use it when eligible.</statement>
        <rationale>2024 limits: 4,150 (individual), 8,300 (family). No other account type has the triple tax benefit.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="worked-examples">
      <title>First-year solopreneur</title>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Situation: side business, 30K profit, still employed (W-2 income). Strategy: keep sole prop (simple), claim home office at 1,500 simplified, track all expenses, set aside 25% of profit for taxes, no quarterly estimates needed because W-2 withholding covers safe-harbor. Result: taxable SE income approximately 28,500, SE tax approximately 4,350, income tax at marginal W-2 rate, deductions offset some income.</note>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>When a founder has both W-2 and self-employment income, check whether W-2 withholding satisfies safe-harbor before setting up quarterly estimates.</statement>
        <rationale>Quarterly estimates are only required when expected tax liability exceeds 1,000 after withholding. Over-estimating complexity adds administrative burden without reducing liability.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <title>Full-time solopreneur at scale</title>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Situation: 150K LLC profit, considering S-Corp. Strategy: elect S-Corp, pay 75K reasonable salary, distribute 75K, max SEP-IRA (approximately 14K on salary portion), use home-office actual method. Result: SE tax savings approximately 7,600, retirement contribution 14K, tax savings from retirement approximately 3,360, total optimization approximately 11K vs default LLC treatment.</note>
      </example>
      <rule>
        <statement>For S-Corp with SEP-IRA, contribution limit is based on W-2 salary, not total profit. At 75K salary, max SEP-IRA is approximately 14K (not the approximately 28K that would apply to 150K profit on a sole prop). Verify before projecting retirement savings.</statement>
        <rationale>Many founders over-estimate S-Corp retirement benefits because the base for SEP-IRA switches from net SE income to W-2 wages. This is a common miscalculation.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Founder assumes the simplified home-office deduction method and the actual method can both be applied in the same year.</description>
        <reason>Only one method can be used per year. Switching methods annually is allowed but requires full recalculation. Applying both double-deducts.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agent hardcodes 2024 contribution limits (Solo 401k 22.5K, SEP-IRA 66K, HSA 4,150/8,300) without flagging the year.</description>
        <reason>Contribution limits are indexed to inflation and change annually. Hardcoded limits produce wrong advice after the tax year changes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="automation-safety">
      <rule>
        <statement>Never move money or initiate bank transfers autonomously. Tax reserve sweeps are recommendations requiring explicit per-transfer human approval.</statement>
        <rationale>Autonomous fund movement from operating accounts has irreversible consequences. The agent's role is computation and recommendation, not execution.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Use rules-based transaction categorization first; fall back to LLM only for unmatched rows. Require a source cue (memo, vendor history) for every LLM classification. Route confidence below 0.8 to human review queue. Never silently drop uncategorized transactions.</statement>
        <rationale>LLM-classified transactions hallucinate categories. "Software subscription" can be logged as marketing; "client lunch" as travel. Determinism beats probability for ledgers.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Quarterly estimate due dates are Q1 April 15, Q2 June 15, Q3 September 15, Q4 January 15 (following year). Never use calendar quarters.</statement>
        <rationale>IRS quarterly estimate deadlines do not align with calendar quarters. A cron job on March 31, June 30, September 30, December 31 misses three of four deadlines.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Apply the correct safe-harbor rule: 90% of current-year liability OR 100% of prior-year (110% if prior-year AGI exceeded 150K), whichever is lower, divided by 4, minus payments-to-date. Show which rule was applied and flag when any input is estimated rather than actual.</statement>
        <rationale>Using the wrong safe-harbor variant (e.g. 100% instead of 110% for a high-AGI founder) produces underpayment penalties. Transparency about input certainty is mandatory.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="privacy-and-data-handling">
      <rule>
        <statement>Tax data includes SSN, EIN, full income, and bank account numbers. Encrypt at rest. Scrub from logs. Never paste into a non-private LLM session. Use local models for raw transaction data; send only summary metrics through external APIs.</statement>
        <rationale>Tax data is among the highest-sensitivity PII categories. Exposure carries identity-theft and regulatory risk.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Never let the agent reply to IRS notices on behalf of the founder. Even routine-appearing letters can have signature, assessment, or penalty implications.</statement>
        <rationale>IRS correspondence has legal deadlines and consequences. Auto-replies that waive rights or make admissions create unrecoverable situations.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>Always include the tax year explicitly in prompts. Refuse to compute if the year is not specified or if the year's limits are not in scope.</statement>
        <rationale>Contribution limits, SE wage base, standard mileage rates, and Section 179 caps change annually. Stale computations decay silently.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Correct prompt pattern: "Goal: compute Q3 estimated tax payment. Inputs: YTD net profit, prior-year tax liability, prior payments, filing status, state. Method: safe-harbor lower of (90% current-year, 100% prior or 110% if AGI greater than 150K) divided by 4, minus payments-to-date. Output: payment amount + due date + rule applied; flag if any input is estimated."</note>
      </example>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/tax-reserve-calc.py" purpose="Monthly tax-reserve calculator: net profit → set-aside amount"/>
      <template path="templates/tax-planning-checklist.md" purpose="Year-end checklist: entity review, deductions, retirement contributions"/>
      <template path="templates/annual-tax-summary.md" purpose="CPA prep table: income sources, deduction categories, tax calculations"/>
    </templates>
    <how-to>
      <p>When using this methodology with agents for tax automation:</p>
      <step>Maintaining a monthly tax-reserve calculator: pull revenue + deductible expense data from accounting software, compute set-aside, recommend (never auto-execute) transfer to a separate savings account.</step>
      <step>Auto-categorizing transactions into deduction buckets (home office, software, marketing, professional services, equipment) with a human-review queue for ambiguous lines.</step>
      <step>Tracking quarterly estimate due dates and pre-computing payment amounts based on YTD profit.</step>
      <step>Comparing entity tax treatments (Sole Prop vs LLC vs S-Corp) at year-end based on actual numbers, surfacing when the S-Corp election threshold is crossed.</step>
      <step>Generating a year-end tax-prep package for the CPA: P&amp;L, deduction summary, mileage log, equipment register, retirement contribution log.</step>
    </how-to>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed"/>
      <link href="https://www.irs.gov/forms-pubs/about-publication-535"/>
      <link href="https://www.irs.gov/forms-pubs/about-publication-587"/>
      <link href="https://www.irs.gov/forms-pubs/about-form-1040-es"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
