<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="learning-speed-competitive-moat">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>product</group>
    <domain>product-manager</domain>
    <summary>Organizational learning velocity as the primary competitive advantage in markets where AI lets competitors clone product experiences in weeks.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>learning-velocity</tag>
      <tag>competitive-moat</tag>
      <tag>product-strategy</tag>
      <tag>decision-velocity</tag>
      <tag>belief-systems</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Learning Speed as Competitive Moat</title>
    <summary>A framework for treating organizational learning velocity as the primary competitive advantage in markets where AI lets competitors clone product experiences in weeks. The core metric is: Learning Velocity = (Signals Noticed × Update Speed × Execution Quality) / Time. At the PM level it operates as a per-bet bet.md system with weekly bet-reviewer cycles, kill criteria, and a quarterly personal calibration scorecard.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>In 2026, feature parity is achievable in weeks via AI codegen. The durable moat is how fast an org notices market changes, updates beliefs, and ships different answers. Teams that run weekly belief-update rituals outmaneuver quarterly-review orgs regardless of headcount — because the bottleneck is decision latency, not execution capacity.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>A PM owns a product area against a well-funded competitor where the differentiation thesis depends on shipping the right thing next, not the most things.</item>
        <item>Preparing for a quarterly business review and need to defend "what we changed our minds about" with evidence.</item>
        <item>Setting OKRs where learning velocity (not feature throughput) is the contested promotion criterion.</item>
        <item>Inherited a roadmap built on stale assumptions — need a 30-day belief-audit before committing to next quarter.</item>
        <item>Post-PMF squad where the bottleneck has moved from "does anyone want this?" to "which of 8 plausible bets do we make first?"</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Pre-PMF founder or PM — the bottleneck is one working hypothesis, not learning velocity across many.</item>
        <item>Highly regulated domains (medical devices, defense, certain fintech) where weekly belief updates conflict with regulatory commitment cycles.</item>
        <item>A PM whose squad has not shipped in 8+ weeks — fix delivery first, then add meta-process.</item>
        <item>Feature-factory orgs where roadmap is set top-down by sales — personal learning velocity does not move the moat at squad level.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="learning-velocity-formula">
      <rule>
        <statement>Measure and report Learning Velocity as: (Signals Noticed x Update Speed x Execution Quality) / Time. Treat it as an OKR-level metric, not a qualitative goal.</statement>
        <rationale>In 2026, AI lets competitors clone product experiences in weeks. The durable moat is decision latency — how fast the org notices changes, updates beliefs, and ships different answers. Feature parity is achievable; learning-speed advantage compounds over time.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="four-elements-to-improve">
      <list>
        <item>Signal Collection: automate market and competitor monitoring; pull thousands of signals daily rather than relying on human curation.</item>
        <item>Belief Updates: run strategy reviews weekly, not quarterly; maintain a versioned beliefs.yaml that diffs between reviews.</item>
        <item>Decision Speed: reduce approval chains; pre-commit decision rules so verdicts are mechanical, not political.</item>
        <item>Execution: ship experiments in days via feature flags, not weeks via full deploys; time-box every bet.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="weekly-learning-rituals">
      <rule>
        <statement>Cap synchronous learning rituals at 2 hours per week total. More than 2 hours of rituals crowds out user research and decision execution.</statement>
        <rationale>Ritual stacking (Monday discovery + Tuesday roadmap + Wednesday competitor + Thursday OKR + Friday retro) fills the PM's calendar without producing decisions. Ritual time is overhead; decision time is value.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Monday: share customer interview insights from the previous week across the squad.</item>
        <item>Wednesday: review competitor updates — changelog, pricing, job postings.</item>
        <item>Friday: analyze experiment results; update bet.md files; broadcast changed beliefs.</item>
        <item>Immediately: communicate any strategy adjustment triggered by a new signal — do not batch for the next ritual.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="ai-powered-signal-processing">
      <list>
        <item>AI scans thousands of market signals daily — competitor changelogs, pricing pages, job postings, review sites, niche newsletters.</item>
        <item>Surfaces whitespace and emerging trends before they become obvious to competitors.</item>
        <item>Flags competitor launches and pricing shifts on the day they occur.</item>
        <item>Synthesizes customer sentiment from support themes, social, and review sites automatically.</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Route AI-collected signals through a classifier that tags each signal to a specific roadmap bet or belief. Untagged signals are noise; tagged signals are evidence.</statement>
        <rationale>A signal that reaches a PM without a bet or belief tag requires manual routing and is often ignored. Pre-tagging connects signals to decisions automatically.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="organizational-infrastructure">
      <list>
        <item>Insight Repository: shared across all teams, AI-indexed, searchable by topic and bet ID.</item>
        <item>Learning Loops: rapid feedback cycles between signal, belief update, and execution.</item>
        <item>Knowledge Management: AI-indexed, searchable; no signal silo per team.</item>
        <item>Decision Logs: track predictions vs. outcomes per bet; calibration requires a log.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="per-bet-system">
      <rule>
        <statement>Maintain one bet.md per active roadmap bet in .aidocs/product/bets/. Treat it as code: PR-reviewed, diff-able, version-controlled. Cap active bets at 8 per PM; more is not manageable with the review cadence.</statement>
        <rationale>If bets live in Slack threads or Notion with no version history, belief changes are invisible. A diff of bet.md between commits is the audit trail that proves a PM is learning, not documenting busywork.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Every bet.md must contain, before any work starts: hypothesis, kill criterion (measurable, time-bound, single number), leading indicator, owner, check-back date, and the two strongest opposing signals seen so far.</statement>
        <rationale>A bet without a kill criterion is a project, not a bet. The kill criterion is the only thing that forces the org to reverse a bad decision before it sinks the quarter.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="weekly-bet-reviewer-cycle">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run a bet-reviewer agent (Sonnet) weekly on each active bet. Output must be one of: keep | accelerate | kill | reframe — with cited evidence. Accept or reject the recommendation, document the decision, move on.</statement>
        <rationale>A weekly mechanical review prevents the two most common PM failure modes: (1) ignoring a bet that should be killed; (2) killing a bet that just needs reframing. The agent surfaces the evidence; the PM decides.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>keep: 3+ cited supporting events in last 30 days AND no kill criterion tripped.</item>
        <item>accelerate: 3+ supporting events AND a leading indicator above target.</item>
        <item>kill: any kill criterion tripped OR fewer than 2 supporting events in last 30 days.</item>
        <item>reframe: 2+ events supporting a coherent alternative hypothesis.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="personal-calibration">
      <rule>
        <statement>Run personal calibration quarterly against the decision log. Compute: kill/reframe ratio (target >= 30%), prediction hit rate (target 55-75%), mean time to check-back (target &lt;= 21 days). A hit rate above 75% means the PM logs only easy bets; below 55% means guessing.</statement>
        <rationale>Without calibration, fast-learning PMs are often fast-talking PMs. The scorecard proves whether the belief-update rituals produce decisions, not documents.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <reference path="templates/pm-learning-velocity.py">Python script computing kill/reframe ratio, reversal rate, and prediction hit rate from decisions.yaml.</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="failure-modes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Performance theater: PMs publish a "weekly insights" newsletter, count it as learning velocity, and never change a roadmap line.</description>
        <reason>Learning velocity is measured by decisions reversed or accelerated, not by document volume. The audit trail must show bet.md diffs, not newsletter archives.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hero PM trap: all signals route through the most-learning PM, who becomes the bottleneck.</description>
        <reason>Personal learning velocity is not org learning velocity. PMs must explicitly delegate belief ownership to squad members so the loop is distributed, not individual.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Confirmation engine: PMs usually classify their own evidence. Without a peer or red-teamer, every event becomes "evidence for the belief I already had".</description>
        <reason>The methodology is silent on this; PMs must build the social loop. Pair-review belief changes: every "kill" or "reframe" requires a peer PM or EM signoff.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Ritual stacking: Monday discovery, Tuesday roadmap, Wednesday competitor, Thursday OKRs, Friday retro — soon the PM is in rituals 4 days a week and never makes a decision.</description>
        <reason>Cap rituals at ≤2 hours/week of synchronous time. More than this crowds out user research and decision execution.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Calibration debt: PMs rarely grade their own past predictions, so personal confidence drifts. Without quarterly self-calibration, the "fast-learning PM" is just a fast-talking PM.</description>
        <reason>Quarterly personal calibration is non-optional. Run pm_learning_velocity.py on your own decisions. If you cannot, you have not been logging.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Cross-PM drift: in a multi-PM product, each PM's belief registry diverges; a customer hears three different stories.</description>
        <reason>The PM-Lead must enforce a shared belief schema even if individual beliefs differ. Read the org-wide beliefs.yaml weekly even if you do not own it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Output-trained orgs: if # of features shipped is the PM's review metric, no amount of learning ritual changes incentives.</description>
        <reason>The methodology requires the manager and skip-level to also be on learning velocity as a metric, otherwise it dies.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Discovery-debt accumulation: PMs who delegate signal collection to agents stop talking to users; their "fast learning" decays into "fast theorizing on stale data" within ~6 weeks.</description>
        <reason>Force a human-touched discovery floor (≥3 user conversations/week). Without it, the agent loop runs on stale truth.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Bet inflation: agents propose new bets on every signal cluster, producing 30 bets per PM that nobody can maintain.</description>
        <reason>Hard cap (e.g. 8 bets in flight per PM) enforced in the bet-reviewer prompt.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Citation laundering: an LLM cites the same Slack thread three times under three event_ids.</description>
        <reason>Dedupe by (channel, message_ts) before counting "independent" supports.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Premature kill on weekend lulls: agent runs Monday, sees zero events_for from the weekend, recommends kill.</description>
        <reason>Always evaluate over a rolling 30-day window, not the last sprint.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Reframe loops: a bet that gets reframed every week is not learning, it is drifting.</description>
        <reason>Lint: reframes_in_last_quarter &lt;= 1 per bet, otherwise flag for human strategy review.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Decision-log fabrication for promo: an LLM asked to "summarize my year for promo" will invent decisions you never made.</description>
        <reason>Use the log to verify the narrative; never let the agent author it.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Stale collector outputs leaking into bets: a competitor scrape returns a 2024 page; the agent dates it today.</description>
        <reason>Always preserve source_published_at and reject events older than the bet's check-back window.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>PM tone homogenization: agents draft all bet updates in the same voice across all PMs in the org; execs notice.</description>
        <reason>Per-PM tone fingerprint or human-author the upward broadcasts.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Single-LLM monoculture: using one model family for collector + classifier + reviewer creates correlated errors.</description>
        <reason>At least the reviewer should be a different model class than the classifier. Consider an alternative provider for the reviewer's red-team pass.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Privacy in user transcripts: PM bets often cite named customers; do not let the bet-reviewer ingest raw PII into a shared belief registry.</description>
        <reason>Strip PII at the classifier stage.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Auto-broadcasting kill decisions: an agent posts "we killed feature X" before sales, support, and partnership were notified.</description>
        <reason>Force a 24-hour human-review delay on kill broadcasts; not on keep or accelerate.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Calibration as ritual instead of feedback: agent emits a calibration scorecard, PM glances and ignores.</description>
        <reason>Tie the scorecard to OKR review; otherwise it has no behavioral effect.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Rubric drift: if quarterly calibration suggests prompt-rubric updates and the PM rewrites the bet-reviewer prompt every quarter, comparability across quarters is lost.</description>
        <reason>Version the rubric; A/B-shadow new rubrics for one quarter before switching.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Discovery atrophy via agentification: tracking "events ingested" rises while "user conversations had" falls.</description>
        <reason>Force the dashboard to display both side-by-side; alert if conversations drop.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>One bet.md per roadmap bet, in .aidocs/product/bets/. Treat it as code: PR-reviewed, diff-able, audit-logged. Slack threads do not count.</item>
        <item>Every bet has a written kill criterion before any work starts. "We will stop if X by Y" — measurable, time-bound, ideally a single number. No kill criterion ⇒ not a bet, just a project.</item>
        <item>Tie learning velocity to OKRs explicitly: e.g. "≥30% of bets killed/reframed per quarter, prediction hit rate in the 55–75% band". Without an OKR, no incentive, no behavior change.</item>
        <item>Cap rituals at 2 synchronous hours/week (45-min Friday review + 30-min Monday digest read + 15-min daily skim). Anything more crowds out user research.</item>
        <item>Maintain a discovery floor per PM: ≥3 user conversations/week, transcripts in Dovetail/Gong with bet tags. Without it, the agent loop runs on stale truth.</item>
        <item>The PM-Lead enforces a shared bet.md schema across PMs, but does not normalize bets themselves. Diversity of bets, uniformity of evidence schema.</item>
        <item>Pair-review belief changes: every "kill" or "reframe" requires a peer PM or EM signoff. Self-classification is the #1 source of confirmation bias.</item>
        <item>Quarterly personal calibration is non-optional. Run pm_learning_velocity.py on your own decisions. If you cannot, you have not been logging.</item>
        <item>Distinguish evidence-driven belief changes from taste-driven product calls; both are legitimate, but conflating them rots the audit log. Tag each decision.</item>
        <item>Promote with the audit trail. "I killed bet X based on evidence Y on date Z" beats any narrative essay in a senior-PM packet.</item>
        <item>Run an annual anti-moat audit: which competitors have a faster learning loop than us, why, and what would it cost to match? Reframe roadmap accordingly.</item>
        <item>Read the org-wide beliefs.yaml weekly even if you do not own it. Cross-bet collisions (PM-A's bet rests on a belief PM-B's evidence is killing) are caught only by reading across.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/pm-learning-velocity.py" purpose="Python script: scores a PM's learning velocity from a decisions.yaml decision log (kill/reframe ratio, reversal rate, prediction hit rate)."/>
    </templates>
    <section name="cli-tools">
      <list>
        <item>gh (GitHub CLI): Version bet.md files; PR-review belief changes; gh pr view as the audit trail. https://cli.github.com</item>
        <item>lookerctl / looker-sdk: Pull leading-indicator queries per bet on a fixed schedule. https://cloud.google.com/looker</item>
        <item>posthog CLI: Per-bet cohort exports without writing dashboards. https://posthog.com/docs/api</item>
        <item>gong-cli (community) / Gong API: Pull deal-stage transcript snippets per bet's ICP. https://app.gong.io/api</item>
        <item>dovetail-cli (community) / Dovetail API: Pull tagged interview clips into bet evidence. https://developers.dovetailapp.com</item>
        <item>notion-cli / Notion API: Render bet.md into the exec-shareable bet board. https://developers.notion.com</item>
        <item>linear-cli / Linear GraphQL: Tie experiments and discovery tasks to bet IDs; close the loop. https://developers.linear.app</item>
        <item>dbt: Per-bet metric models so leading indicators are versioned, not ad-hoc. https://docs.getdbt.com</item>
        <item>yq / jq: Diff bet.md frontmatter between commits to flag belief drift. https://github.com/mikefarah/yq</item>
        <item>pre-commit + custom hook: Block PRs on bet.md without kill_criteria, check_back_date, decision_owner. https://pre-commit.com</item>
        <item>claude (Anthropic SDK): Bet-reviewer, broadcast, calibration agents. https://docs.anthropic.com</item>
        <item>mailmerge: Send the per-stakeholder bet update from a CSV (no marketing tool). pip install mailmerge</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="services-and-apps">
      <list>
        <item>Productboard (SaaS, API yes): Bet-as-objective; integrates roadmap and feedback inboxes.</item>
        <item>Aha! Roadmaps (SaaS, API yes): Strong "outcome → initiative → epic" hierarchy; fits PM bets cleanly.</item>
        <item>Roadmunk / airfocus (SaaS, Partial API): Lightweight bet boards for solo PMs.</item>
        <item>Reforge Artifacts (SaaS, No API): Reference templates for PM bet frameworks; copy patterns, do not integrate.</item>
        <item>Maze (SaaS, API yes): Continuous discovery experiments scoped per bet.</item>
        <item>Sprig (SaaS, API yes): In-product surveys triggered by bet's leading-indicator cohort.</item>
        <item>UserTesting / UserInterviews (SaaS, API yes): Recruit per-bet ICP for fast qualitative signal.</item>
        <item>Statsig / Eppo / GrowthBook (SaaS / OSS, API yes): Per-bet experiment results into the reviewer prompt.</item>
        <item>Dovetail (SaaS, API yes): Tagged interview corpus per bet.</item>
        <item>Glean (SaaS, API yes): Cross-tool semantic search; finds prior internal discussions of a hypothesis.</item>
        <item>Pendo / Heap / Mixpanel (SaaS, API yes): Per-bet behavioural cohorts.</item>
        <item>Gainsight PX (SaaS, API yes): CS-driven signals for B2B PMs.</item>
        <item>Lattice / 15Five (SaaS, API yes): PM personal-OKR alignment with learning velocity metric.</item>
        <item>Quantive (Gtmhub) (SaaS, API yes): OKR layer that can host learning velocity as a first-class objective.</item>
        <item>Plane / OpenProject (OSS, API yes): Self-hosted bet board + decision log.</item>
        <item>Otter.ai / Fireflies (SaaS, API yes): Auto-transcribe user calls; PM-flavored review extracts hypothesis-supporting clips.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>The PM-flavored loop is bet-per-bet, not belief-per-org. For each roadmap bet (typically 4–8 in flight), the PM maintains a one-page bet.md with: hypothesis, kill criteria, leading indicator, owner, check-back date, and the two strongest opposing signals seen so far. A daily collector agent (Haiku) scoped to that bet's segment scrapes the relevant analytics slice, support tags, and one external corpus (competitor changelog, subreddit, niche newsletter). A bet-reviewer agent (Sonnet) runs at squad weekly, scores each bet against its kill criteria, and outputs keep | accelerate | kill | reframe with citations. The PM owns two judgment moments only: (1) accept/reject the reviewer's recommendations on Friday, (2) communicate belief changes upward via the monthly exec brief. Everything else is mechanical and delegated. The PM's promotion narrative is the audit log of bet.md changes; "I killed bet X on date Y because of evidence Z" is unambiguous senior-PM evidence.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="recommended-subagents">
      <list>
        <item>faion-pm-agent: owns bet.md files in .aidocs/product/bets/, refuses to mark a bet keep without ≥3 cited supporting events from the last 30 days. Sole writer of the per-bet status field.</item>
        <item>faion-research-agent: runs targeted competitor / segment refreshes that the PM agent's collector cannot script (paywalled reports, expert interviews, niche communities). PM consumes; research agent produces.</item>
        <item>faion-business-analyst: extracts hypotheses from raw user interviews into structured event records that feed the bet's evidence stream. PM-Lead arbitrates conflicts before they hit bet.md.</item>
        <item>brainstorm: used in the Friday reframe path: when bet-reviewer outputs reframe, brainstorm diverges on alternative framings before the PM converges. Prevents premature kill of bets that just need re-shaping.</item>
        <item>signal-classifier: reused as-is; the PM's per-bet collector pipes events into the org-wide classifier rather than re-implementing classification.</item>
        <item>decision-logger: reused; every PM bet decision (keep|accelerate|kill|reframe) is a row in the decision log with a prediction and a check-back date.</item>
        <item>password-scrubber-agent: non-negotiable before any bet.md ships to a public artifact (board pre-read, fundraising deck); bets often cite individual customer names, deal sizes, and internal pricing experiments.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="prompt-patterns">
      <p>Per-bet weekly review (Sonnet, structured output):</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[<role>bet-reviewer</role>
<bet>{{ bet_md }}</bet>
<kill_criteria>{{ bet.kill_criteria }}</kill_criteria>
<events_last_30d>{{ events_for_this_bet_jsonl }}</events_last_30d>
<rules>
  Output one of: keep | accelerate | kill | reframe.
  - keep: >=3 cited events_for in last 30d AND no kill_criterion tripped.
  - accelerate: >=3 events_for AND a leading indicator above target.
  - kill: any kill_criterion tripped OR <2 events_for in last 30d.
  - reframe: >=2 events_against from a coherent alternative hypothesis.
  Cite event_ids per claim. Refuse to recommend without citations.
</rules>
<output_schema>
  {recommendation, rationale, cited_events:[event_id], confidence,
   proposed_kill_criterion_update, check_back_date}
</output_schema>]]></code>
      <p>PM personal calibration (quarterly, Opus):</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[<role>pm-calibration</role>
<decision_log>{{ decisions_last_quarter_yaml }}</decision_log>
<deliverable>For each decision: predicted vs actual, calibration score
(0..1), specific lesson. Aggregate: which decision types I am over/under
confident on. Recommend 3 prompt-rubric updates for bet-reviewer for next
quarter.</deliverable>
<constraint>No qualitative praise. Every claim cites a decision_id.
If under 10 decisions logged, output "insufficient sample" — do not
fabricate trend.</constraint>]]></code>
      <p>Squad belief broadcast (Haiku, terse):</p>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[<role>belief-broadcast</role>
<changed_beliefs>{{ diff_of_bets_yaml }}</changed_beliefs>
<audience>squad-engineers</audience>
<format>3 bullets max. Lead with what we now believe (not what we
debated). Link the bet.md and the decision_id. No exec hedging.</format>]]></code>
    </section>
    <section name="python-learning-velocity-scorecard">
      <p>The product-operations variant ships belief_update.py for the org-wide loop — reuse it, do not duplicate. The PM-flavored gap is a learning-velocity scorecard the PM can attach to a quarterly review and to OKRs. Here is the reference implementation:</p>
      <code lang="python"><![CDATA[# pm_learning_velocity.py — score a PM's learning velocity from their decision log.
# Inputs:
#   decisions.yaml  (list of {id, ts, bet_id, decision, prediction, check_back_date, outcome})
# Usage: python pm_learning_velocity.py decisions.yaml [--quarter 2026Q2]
import sys, yaml, datetime, argparse, statistics

ap = argparse.ArgumentParser()
ap.add_argument("path")
ap.add_argument("--quarter", default=None)
args = ap.parse_args()

decisions = yaml.safe_load(open(args.path)) or []
if args.quarter:
    decisions = [d for d in decisions if d.get("quarter") == args.quarter]
if not decisions:
    sys.exit("no decisions in scope")

n = len(decisions)
reversed30 = sum(1 for d in decisions
                 if d.get("reversed_within_days") and d["reversed_within_days"] <= 30)
graded = [d for d in decisions if d.get("outcome") in ("hit", "miss")]
hit_rate = sum(1 for d in graded if d["outcome"] == "hit") / len(graded) if graded else None
kills = sum(1 for d in decisions if d["decision"] == "kill")
reframes = sum(1 for d in decisions if d["decision"] == "reframe")
mean_time_to_check = statistics.mean(
    [(datetime.date.fromisoformat(d["check_back_date"])
      - datetime.date.fromisoformat(d["ts"][:10])).days
     for d in decisions if d.get("check_back_date")]
) if decisions else 0

print(f"Decisions logged       : {n}")
print(f"Kill / reframe ratio   : {(kills+reframes)/n:.0%}  (target >=30%)")
print(f"Reversed within 30 days: {reversed30/n:.0%}      (target <=15%)")
print(f"Mean time to check-back: {mean_time_to_check:.0f} days  (target <=21)")
if hit_rate is not None:
    print(f"Prediction hit rate    : {hit_rate:.0%}  (target 0.55-0.75 — outside = miscalibrated)")
else:
    print("Prediction hit rate    : insufficient graded sample")]]></code>
      <p>A high Decisions logged with a near-zero Kill / reframe ratio is the signature of a PM who is documenting busywork, not learning. Hit rates above ~75% mean the PM is only logging easy bets; below ~55% means they are guessing.</p>
    </section>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.reforge.com/blog/learning-velocity"/>
      <link href="https://www.lennysnewsletter.com"/>
      <link href="https://cutlefish.substack.com"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
