<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-patterns" title="Flexibility and Efficiency Implementation Patterns">
  <summary>Flexibility mechanisms for novice and expert users — keyboard shortcuts, command palette, progressive disclosure, customization, and batch operations.</summary>

  <section title="User Spectrum">
    <p>The interface must serve: novice (occasional users, need guided paths), intermediate (regular users, learning accelerators), power users (daily use, need shortcuts and automation). Design layers for all three simultaneously.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement a command palette (Ctrl+K / Cmd+K) as the single discoverability surface for all shortcuts.</statement>
      <rationale>A command palette serves novice (can search for actions) and expert (can type known shortcut) users from the same UI surface; it is the most efficient single investment in flexibility.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Keyboard Shortcuts">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show keyboard shortcuts in menu items and tooltips; shortcuts that are not discoverable do not exist for most users.</statement>
      <rationale>Undiscoverable shortcuts are used only by users who read documentation; visible shortcuts in context menus teach users passively during normal use.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Never override Ctrl+W, Ctrl+N, Ctrl+T, or Ctrl+F in a web application.</statement>
      <rationale>These browser-native shortcuts (close tab, new window, new tab, find) are deeply ingrained; overriding them creates severe friction and breaks platform expectations.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Layered accessibility: Level 1 = menu item (visible to all); Level 2 = keyboard shortcut shown in menu; Level 3 = expert knows by heart. All three levels from the same menu item.</p>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Figma: Cmd+/ opens quick actions (command palette), showing all shortcuts with labels. New users discover shortcuts passively; experts use them daily.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Complex dashboard with no keyboard shortcuts, requiring mouse navigation for every action. Power users forced into slow click-only workflows daily.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Disclosure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Expose the 3-5 most-used settings immediately; place the remaining 80% behind an "Advanced" toggle.</statement>
      <rationale>Showing all settings at once overwhelms novice users; hiding primary settings frustrates experts. The 80/20 split satisfies both.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Batch Operations">
    <rule>
      <statement>For each action that affects a single item, design a batch variant as an accelerator layer.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-item actions work for novices; batch operations unlock expert-level efficiency for high-volume workflows without adding complexity to the basic flow.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/flexibility-audit.md">Flexibility audit table template</reference>
  <reference path="templates/find-shortcuts.sh">Extract keyboard event listeners from JS/TS codebase</reference>
</text>
