<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Flexibility and Efficiency Rules and Agent Gotchas">
  <summary>Platform convention requirements, measuring efficiency, common mistakes, and agent limitations for flexibility audits.</summary>

  <section title="Platform Convention Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Follow platform shortcut conventions; validate agent shortcut recommendations against the specific framework and browser environment.</statement>
      <rationale>Shortcut conflicts with browser/OS defaults (Ctrl+W, Ctrl+F) create severe friction; agent recommendations must be verified against target platform before implementation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Compute segment results only for pre-specified segments — post-hoc shortcut adoption analysis inflates false positives.</statement>
      <rationale>Shortcut usage varies by user type; analyzing only segments that look good post-hoc misrepresents adoption.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Measuring Efficiency">
    <p>Metrics to track: task completion time by user experience level, shortcut usage vs. mouse-click ratio per action, customization adoption rate (% who change defaults), error rate by user experience level, time on task over multiple sessions (learning curve slope).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Track keyboard vs. mouse event source per action before investing in additional shortcuts.</statement>
      <rationale>If 95% of users use mouse for an action, keyboard shortcut investment has low ROI; data-driven shortcut prioritization is more effective than comprehensive coverage.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Expert-only interface — all options always visible, no progressive disclosure.</description>
      <reason>Overwhelming novice users causes abandonment before they reach the point of becoming regular users; progressive disclosure is not optional for complex tools.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Novice-only interface — no accelerators, every action requires full guided flow.</description>
      <reason>Power users who repeat the same guided flow dozens of times daily experience significant productivity loss and frustration.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Over-customization — too many configuration options confuse users.</description>
      <reason>Customization beyond the 20% of settings users actually change adds cognitive load without benefit; limit customization to high-frequency actions and layout.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Agent Usage Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>PM or lead must approve power-user feature recommendations before implementation; agent does not account for build complexity or support burden.</statement>
      <rationale>Custom shortcuts, saved layouts, and command palettes have significant implementation cost; agent recommendations are feature ideas, not implementation decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Filter agent-generated command palette action lists for internal or admin-only actions before exposing to end users.</statement>
      <rationale>Agent may include operations from the full action inventory without distinguishing between user-facing and admin actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/find-shortcuts.sh">Extract keyboard event listeners from JS/TS codebase</reference>
</text>
