<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-market-stats" title="VUI Adoption Statistics Schema and Refresh Rules">
  <summary>Canonical stat schema, current adoption figures, citation requirements, and mandatory refresh rules.</summary>

  <section title="Stat Schema">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every market statistic must carry four fields: value, year, source URL, and geographic scope. Stats without scope or year are not citable.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice adoption varies 3-5x between US and global figures. A "62% use voice assistants" claim without geographic scope is meaningless and misleads strategy decisions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Distinguish these three denominator categories: smart-speaker households, voice-assistant users, voice-search query share. These are not interchangeable and come from different measurement methodologies.</statement>
      <rationale>Mixing denominators produces false comparisons. Smart-speaker household penetration tracks device ownership; voice-assistant users tracks intent sessions; voice-search share tracks query-type on a specific engine. Conflating them inflates or deflates the picture arbitrarily.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Current Baseline (2025-2026)">
    <p>Reference figures as of 2025-2026 (verify and refresh via refresh-script.py before use): 8.4B+ voice assistants in use globally; 20%+ of internet queries use voice search; 62% of US adults use a voice assistant; 55% of US households own a smart speaker; 71% of users prefer voice over typing for some tasks. All figures: US/global mixed — verify geo before reusing.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Stamp every market brief with a refreshed_at date. Refuse to publish if the brief is older than 90 days. Voice adoption statistics moved sharply post-2024 with LLM-native voice agents.</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-native voice agents (ChatGPT Voice, Claude voice mode) are reshaping the landscape faster than canonical 2024-25 sources track. Stats older than 90 days may be wrong on direction, not just magnitude.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/refresh-script.py">Python script to refresh market stats via web search</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="Trusted Sources">
    <list>
      <item>Statista — primary canonical source for voice adoption stats (some behind paywall)</item>
      <item>Voicebot.ai — voice industry tracking, free annual surveys</item>
      <item>Edison Research / Infinite Dial — US adoption baselines, annual PDF</item>
      <item>Nielsen Norman Group — UX-focused voice interaction analysis</item>
      <item>Pew Research — US technology adoption baselines (free)</item>
      <item>Gartner — hype cycle and enterprise predictions (paywalled)</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Restrict web-search queries to the trusted-source list. Reject SEO content-farm listicles ("10 voice assistant statistics") that cite each other without primary sources.</statement>
      <rationale>LLMs default to ranking high-traffic listicles, which are recycled secondary aggregations. Requiring the agent to return primary-source URLs eliminates circular citation.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
