<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-platform-comparison" title="Voice Platform Comparison and Selection Rules">
  <summary>Platform comparison (Alexa, Google, Siri, Bixby, custom LLM-VUI) and decision rules for platform selection by geo and use case.</summary>

  <section title="Platform Landscape">
    <p>Five platforms as of 2025-2026: Alexa (Amazon devices, smart home — developer access via Alexa Skills Kit); Google Assistant (Android, Nest, web — Actions on Google; note: Conversational Actions deprecated 2023); Siri (Apple ecosystem — SiriKit, restricted intent set, requires native iOS app); Bixby (Samsung devices — Bixby Developer Studio, small reach outside Korea); Custom LLM-VUI (any platform via API — OpenAI Realtime, Claude voice, ElevenLabs Conversational — bypasses skill stores and certification entirely).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Weight platform reach by target geo, not global share. Alexa dominates US smart speakers; Google Assistant dominates Android phones globally; Siri dominates iOS. These rankings invert across geos.</statement>
      <rationale>A platform that reaches 40% of US smart-speaker households reaches a very different population than one reaching 40% of Android phones in APAC. Geo-specific reach is the decision-relevant variable, not headline global figures.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="LLM-Native Platform">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat LLM-native voice agents as a fifth platform category, not a feature. They bypass skill stores and certification, support open-domain dialog, and have different design requirements (no intent/slot NLU, state managed by model or tool use).</statement>
      <rationale>LLM-native voice agents (Pipecat, Vapi, Retell, Claude voice) represent a different architectural paradigm from intent-based platforms. Conflating them with Alexa/Google design patterns produces broken systems: intent/slot design applied to open LLM dialog, or unconstrained LLM dialog applied where deterministic state is required.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Platform Selection Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>For platform selection: (1) identify target geos and primary user device type; (2) check developer SDK health (commit activity, deprecation notices); (3) assess LLM integration openness; (4) evaluate certification requirements against timeline. Document the tradeoff, not just the winner.</statement>
      <rationale>Platform decisions are long-term bets. A platform with better current reach but a deprecated SDK or a shrinking developer community may be the wrong choice for a two-year product horizon.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
