<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="learning-speed-competitive-moat Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for learning-speed-competitive-moat as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Synthesizer generating insights at digest-of-digest-of-digest compression, losing original wording.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Re-grounding every synthesizer run on the raw events.ndjson is mandatory. Previous digests anchor on prior framing and lose the original signal over time.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Memory rot: belief-updater pulled into context-window compaction loses last week's reasoning.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Persist beliefs.yaml and beliefs.history.ndjson outside the LLM and re-inject on every run. Never rely on LLM memory for belief continuity across sessions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Evidence laundering: sonnet rewrites the same event into 3 different "independent" supports for a belief.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dedupe by event_id hash before counting independent signals. Three occurrences of the same event do not count as three independent signals.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Prompt bias: "summarise this week's competitor wins" yields wins. Use neutral framing: "score evidence-based threat 1-5, default 1".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Leading prompts pre-load the model to find wins. Neutral framing with default scores prevents confirmation bias.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Hallucinated event_ids: model invents event_42 that does not exist in events.ndjson.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Run a fact-checker pass that looks up every cited id in events.ndjson before publishing. Uncited event_ids are fabrications.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Token blow-up from dumping 10k events directly into Opus weekly.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Pre-cluster with haiku, hand 50–100 archetypal events to opus. Full event streams at opus cost is wasteful and counterproductively degrades reasoning quality.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Action-less insight loop: agent surfaces 200 insights per week, no decision_owner, nobody acts.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force schema field decision_owner on every event that reaches the belief-updater. Drop events without an owner rather than surfacing them without action.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-publishing risk: an agent-generated digest claiming a competitor is "in trouble" leaks via Slack screenshot.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Add a human review gate before any cross-org distribution. Agents should draft for internal consumption; humans approve before external sharing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Calibration neglect: nobody scores last quarter's predictions, confidence weights become superstition.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Quarterly grading job is not optional. It is the feedback loop that prevents belief drift from reality.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
