<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Team Development Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Six testable rules grounding team-development. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="tuckman-confidence-score" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When staging a team from indirect signals the report MUST emit a `tuckman_confidence` score in [0.0, 1.0] AND `tuckman_evidence` (≥ 2 distinct observables: throughput shape, conflict signal, retro theme, 1:1 note). A stage stated without confidence is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="Tuckman 1965; Lencioni — Five Dysfunctions; PMI PMBOK 7 Team Performance Domain">Tuckman is a model, not a measurement instrument. Confident staging from sparse signals leads to wrong PM actions (e.g. delegating during Storming).</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="charter-co-authored" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The team charter MUST be co-authored in a ≥ 60-minute workshop with the team. An agent-generated charter is a DRAFT marked `co_authored: false`; it never ships to the team as the final artefact.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google re:Work — five keys to a successful team; Lencioni team-cohesion research">Agent-authored charters are generic and lack the buy-in that only participation creates. Working agreements without team input are rules nobody follows.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="retro-action-owner-deadline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every retro action item MUST have a single named owner role AND a sprint-bounded deadline. Items reading "the team will look into this" are rejected and re-prompted.</statement>
      <rationale source="Atul Gawande — The Checklist Manifesto; Agile retrospective best-practice (Derby/Larsen)">Actions without owners are not actions; they are intentions that expire at the end of the retro. Deadline-less items live forever in a parking lot.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="no-individual-naming" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Synthesised retro outputs, theme files, and `TeamDevelopmentReport` MUST NOT contain individual names. Names present in raw input are stripped before synthesis.</statement>
      <rationale source="Psychological-safety literature (Edmondson 1999); ICO / GDPR Article 6 data-minimisation guidance">Individual naming in retro summaries chills honest participation and can cause interpersonal harm. The redact step is part of the methodology, not an HR add-on.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="pattern-needs-two-sprints" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>A recurring theme MUST be observed in ≥ 2 distinct sprints before being labelled a pattern. Single-sprint observations are emitted as `single_sprint_observations`, not `patterns`.</statement>
      <rationale source="PMI PMBOK 7 Lessons-Learned register; Lean retro-pattern research (Derby/Larsen, 2006)">Single-sprint observations are noise; patterns require recurrence to be actionable. Labelling noise as pattern produces over-fitted interventions.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="training-before-hire" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Skills-gap recommendations MUST evaluate training + pairing options BEFORE proposing a hire. The report carries `gap_options_evaluated: [training, pairing, contracting, hiring]` with explicit cost/time per option.</statement>
      <rationale source="Buckingham — Now, Discover Your Strengths; PMI knowledge-area cost-management chapter">Agents default to "hire" because it is the clearest action; training and pairing are faster, cheaper, and improve retention. Skipping the evaluation locks in the most expensive option by default.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/05-examples.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
