<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-tuckman-stages" title="Tuckman Team Development Stages">
  <summary>Five-stage model with characteristics, PM actions, and transition signals for each stage.</summary>

  <section title="Forming">
    <p>Team is polite, cautious, and dependent on the PM for direction. Roles unclear, goals abstract, conflict avoided.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: clarify roles and responsibilities, set expectations, facilitate introductions, produce team charter</item>
      <item>Transition signal: members begin asking each other questions rather than always going to the PM</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Storming">
    <p>Conflict, competition, and frustration surface as individuals push back on roles and process. This is healthy and expected; suppressing it delays Norming.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: facilitate structured discussion with ground rules, mediate with focus on shared goals, document agreed decisions</item>
      <item>Transition signal: conflict becomes task-focused rather than interpersonal; throughput stabilises</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Norming">
    <p>Trust builds, cooperation replaces competition, norms are established. Team starts self-organising.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: delegate more, reinforce positive norms, support team decisions, encourage cross-training</item>
      <item>Transition signal: team resolves minor issues independently without escalating to PM</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Performing">
    <p>High productivity, autonomy, distributed leadership. PM shifts to removing obstacles and shielding from external disruption.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: empower and trust, remove blockers, protect team from scope thrash, focus on outcomes</item>
      <item>Transition signal: velocity or throughput is stable and predictable over multiple sprints</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Adjourning">
    <p>Project ends or team dissolves. Emotional closure, knowledge preservation, and individual transition support.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: celebrate achievements, conduct final retrospective, document lessons learned, facilitate career transitions</item>
      <item>Transition signal: project closure milestone reached; team members reassigned</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Staging Confidence">
    <rule>
      <statement>When staging a team from indirect signals, emit a confidence score (0.0-1.0) and list the evidence; do not state the stage as fact without observable data.</statement>
      <rationale>Tuckman is a model, not a measurement instrument; overconfident staging from sparse signals leads to wrong PM actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
