<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-rules" title="Team Development Rules and Antipatterns">
  <summary>Concrete rules for charter authoring, skills matrix use, retrospective quality, and agent safety constraints.</summary>

  <rule>
    <statement>Co-write the team charter with the team in a 60-minute workshop; never let an agent author it solo without team input.</statement>
    <rationale>Agent-authored charters are generic and lack the buy-in that only participation creates.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Every retrospective action item must have a single named owner and a sprint-deadline; reject "the team will look into this".</statement>
    <rationale>Actions without owners are not actions; they are intentions that expire at the end of the retro.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Refresh skills matrix quarterly; treat it as planning input, not performance data.</statement>
    <rationale>Skills matrices used for performance review create gaming; used for planning they create learning opportunities.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Retro outputs must not name individuals; preserve psychological safety in all summarised outputs.</statement>
    <rationale>Individual naming in retro summaries chills honest participation and can cause interpersonal harm.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Retro themes must be backed by evidence from at least two distinct sprints before being called a pattern.</statement>
    <rationale>Single-sprint observations are noise; patterns require recurrence to be actionable.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <rule>
    <statement>Evaluate training and pairing options before proposing a hire to close a skills gap.</statement>
    <rationale>Agents default to "hire" because it is the clearest action; training and pairing are faster, cheaper, and improve retention.</rationale>
  </rule>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Recommending "more standups" or "better communication" as the fix for most retro themes.</description>
    <reason>This is an LLM default; it rarely addresses the root cause and wastes ceremony time on the wrong intervention.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Setting skills matrix scores to 3 (median) when the agent has no information about a person.</description>
    <reason>Unknown should be "unknown", not a guess; phantom scores drive incorrect gap-planning decisions.</reason>
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern>
    <description>Flagging recurring themes as "new" each sprint because the agent has no session memory.</description>
    <reason>Pass last N synthesised theme files into context; without history the agent cannot detect patterns.</reason>
  </antipattern>
</text>
