<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="flexibility-efficiency">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>ux</group>
    <domain>accessibility-specialist</domain>
    <summary>Heuristic #7: accelerators (shortcuts, bulk ops) for experts, simple novice paths. Layered flexibility via progressive disclosure and multiple paths serves the full user spectrum.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>ux</tag>
      <tag>heuristics</tag>
      <tag>keyboard-shortcuts</tag>
      <tag>efficiency</tag>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
    </tags>
    <category>ux-design</category>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-27</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Flexibility and Efficiency of Use</title>

    <summary>Nielsen Heuristic #7: design for both novice and expert users simultaneously by providing accelerators (keyboard shortcuts, bulk operations, templates) that novices can ignore but experts use daily, plus progressive disclosure and multiple paths for the same goal. Interfaces tuned only for beginners frustrate power users who repeat the same tasks hundreds of times per day. Interfaces tuned only for experts overwhelm newcomers. Layered flexibility — visible affordances plus hidden accelerators — lets one interface serve the full user spectrum without cognitive overload at either end.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Interfaces tuned only for beginners frustrate power users who repeat the same tasks hundreds of times per day. Interfaces tuned only for experts overwhelm newcomers. Layered flexibility — visible affordances plus hidden accelerators — lets one interface serve the full user spectrum without cognitive overload at either end.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Designing or auditing productivity tools, admin panels, developer tools, or any app with repeat-use workflows.</item>
        <item>Adding keyboard shortcut coverage to an existing web application.</item>
        <item>Auditing whether an interface serves both novice onboarding and power-user acceleration.</item>
        <item>Planning customization features (saved layouts, quick actions, pinned items) for SaaS products.</item>
        <item>Evaluating CLI tools or APIs for efficiency affordances.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>One-time-use flows (checkout, onboarding wizard, password reset) — shortcuts add no value here.</item>
        <item>Consumer apps with mostly casual, infrequent users — shortcut investment is wasted.</item>
        <item>Early prototype stages before task flows are validated — optimizing efficiency before correctness is premature.</item>
        <item>Accessibility-first flows where additional modalities must be layered carefully to avoid screen reader conflicts.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="keyboard-shortcuts">
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide keyboard shortcuts for all frequently repeated actions; display them in menus, tooltips, and a discoverable shortcut panel.</statement>
        <rationale>Shortcuts without discoverability give zero efficiency gain. Layered exposure (menu label → tooltip → panel) ensures novices learn them gradually while experts use them immediately.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Follow platform conventions before inventing custom shortcuts: Ctrl+S = Save, Ctrl+Z = Undo, Ctrl+C/V = Copy/Paste, Ctrl+F = Find.</statement>
        <rationale>Custom shortcuts that conflict with platform standards cause errors and erode trust. Conventions are non-negotiable.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Test all custom shortcuts against NVDA+Chrome and VoiceOver+Safari before shipping — screen readers capture many key combinations.</statement>
        <rationale>Accessibility tools intercept keyboard events at the OS level; untested shortcuts silently break screen reader workflows.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="multiple-paths">
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide at least two paths to accomplish each primary task (e.g., menu click, double-click, right-click context menu, keyboard shortcut).</statement>
        <rationale>Different users have different motor skills, device types, and learned habits. A single path is an accessibility and efficiency bottleneck.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Ensure that all paths to the same goal produce identical outcomes — diverging behavior between paths fragments user mental models.</statement>
        <rationale>If double-click edits inline but right-click opens a modal, users cannot build a reliable mental model of how editing works.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="progressive-disclosure">
      <rule>
        <statement>Show essential options by default; hide advanced options behind a clearly labeled toggle or "Advanced" section.</statement>
        <rationale>Exposing all options simultaneously overwhelms novices without benefiting experts, who know where to find advanced controls.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Show contextual options based on the current selection — hide unrelated options, do not grey them out in long lists.</statement>
        <rationale>Greyed-out irrelevant options create visual noise and force users to filter mentally what should be filtered by the system.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="bulk-operations">
      <rule>
        <statement>For any action that can be performed on a single item, provide a bulk version that operates on a user-defined selection.</statement>
        <rationale>Power users managing 50+ items cannot afford per-item actions; bulk ops are the primary efficiency multiplier for high-volume workflows.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always show a count confirmation before executing destructive bulk operations: "Delete 14 items?"</statement>
        <rationale>Irreversible bulk actions without confirmation introduce data loss risk that no shortcut convenience justifies.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="customization">
      <rule>
        <statement>Provide customization (saved layouts, pinned items, custom shortcuts) only after default shortcuts and workflows are proven insufficient.</statement>
        <rationale>Premature customization multiplies QA surface and creates its own cognitive load for novice users who encounter a non-default state.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <rule>
        <statement>Always expose a "Reset to defaults" option alongside any customization to prevent users from getting permanently lost.</statement>
        <rationale>Users who customize and then forget their changes have no recovery path without a reset option.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="good-examples">
      <example type="good" title="Figma">
        <p>Keyboard shortcuts for all tools, Quick Actions panel (Ctrl+/), custom keyboard shortcuts, plugins for power users, simple drag-and-drop for beginners. Layered acceleration at every level of expertise.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="VS Code">
        <p>Command palette (Ctrl+Shift+P) as universal accelerator, customizable everything via settings JSON, extension ecosystem, multiple keybinding profiles, settings sync. A single interface serving both casual text editing and professional development workflows.</p>
      </example>
      <example type="good" title="Gmail">
        <p>Keyboard shortcuts (opt-in in settings, respects novice/expert split), quick settings vs. all settings (progressive disclosure), canned responses, filters and rules for automation, basic vs. advanced search.</p>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>No shortcuts: complex application where every action requires mouse navigation through nested menus.</description>
        <reason>Power users who perform the same actions hundreds of times per day are permanently blocked from efficiency gains. Adoption among expert users drops.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Expert-only interface: all options visible at all times, no progressive disclosure, new users overwhelmed on first use.</description>
        <reason>Novice abandonment rate is high when the cognitive load of first use exceeds the perceived value of the product. Onboarding completion drops.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>No customization: fixed layout, cannot hide unused features, cannot pin frequently used actions.</description>
        <reason>Power users with established workflows cannot optimize the interface for their repeating task patterns. Efficiency plateau is set by the default configuration.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Hidden accelerators: shortcuts exist but are not documented in menus, tooltips, or any discoverable location.</description>
        <reason>Undiscoverable shortcuts provide zero efficiency gain to users who have not memorized them from external documentation. The investment in building them is wasted.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Inconsistent shortcuts: Ctrl+D deletes in one part of the app but duplicates in another.</description>
        <reason>Inconsistent shortcuts violate user trust in the shortcut system; users stop using shortcuts entirely to avoid unexpected outcomes.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <section name="user-spectrum-framework">
      <p>Design techniques by user type:</p>
      <list>
        <item>Novice: defaults that work without configuration, wizards for guided multi-step tasks, templates as starting points, tutorials, progressive disclosure</item>
        <item>Expert: shortcuts for frequent actions, batch operations, macros and automation, customization for personalized workflow, direct manipulation to skip wizards</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="best-practices">
      <list>
        <item>Ship shortcuts in menus first (visible), then tooltip (hover), then shortcut panel (? or Ctrl+/) — layered discoverability</item>
        <item>Follow platform conventions before inventing new ones: Ctrl+S = Save, Ctrl+Z = Undo are non-negotiable</item>
        <item>Test shortcuts against NVDA + Chrome and VoiceOver + Safari before shipping — screen readers capture many key combinations</item>
        <item>Implement customizable shortcuts only after default shortcuts are proven insufficient; premature customization multiplies QA surface</item>
        <item>Batch operations should always show a count confirmation ("Delete 14 items?") before executing destructive actions</item>
        <item>Expose a "reset to defaults" option alongside any customization to prevent users from getting permanently lost</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="agentic-workflow">
      <p>An agent receives a feature description or existing UI component list and produces a Flexibility Audit from the audit template: for each key action it checks whether a keyboard shortcut exists, whether it is discoverable, whether bulk operations are available, and whether the default suits a novice. A second pass checks for platform-standard shortcut conflicts. Output is a gap table with remediation priority. Agents can also generate the shortcut-reference panel content from a component inventory.</p>
      <p>Recommended subagents include faion-sdd-executor-agent for driving structured flexibility audit from a task file, and general Claude subagent (Sonnet) for generating keyboard shortcut tables and checking for platform conflicts given an action list.</p>
      <p>Typical prompt pattern: "You are a UX engineer auditing [product] for Flexibility and Efficiency of Use (Nielsen Heuristic #7). Given the following list of user actions: [list], for each action: (1) Does a keyboard shortcut exist? If yes, is it listed in menus/tooltips? (2) Does it conflict with standard OS/browser shortcuts (Ctrl+W, Ctrl+T, Alt+F4, etc.)? (3) Is there a bulk version for operating on multiple items? (4) Does the feature have a "default that works for novices" path? Output: a markdown table with columns: Action | Shortcut | Discoverable | Conflict Risk | Bulk Op | Novice Path."</p>
      <p>Shortcut panel generator prompt: "Given this list of actions and their keyboard shortcuts, generate a keyboard shortcut reference panel in Markdown table format grouped by category (Navigation, Editing, File Operations, View). Flag any shortcut that conflicts with common browser shortcuts."</p>
    </section>

    <section name="tools-and-services">
      <p>CLI tools for keyboard shortcuts include hotkeys-js (browser keyboard shortcut library with conflict detection), tinykeys (lightweight shortcut binding with sequence support), axe-core (checks keyboard accessibility including focus traps and tab order), and Playwright (automated keyboard shortcut integration tests).</p>
      <p>SaaS services include FullStory for revealing shortcut usage rates and click-vs-keyboard ratios per action (no direct API), Heap Analytics for event tracking of shortcut usage adoption over time, LaunchDarkly for feature-flagging new shortcut sets for power-user beta groups (REST API available), and Intercom/Pendo for in-app shortcut discovery banners with Pendo offering REST API for flow management.</p>
      <p>Inline script for extracting keyboard shortcut bindings from a JS bundle uses grep-based pattern matching to find Ctrl, Alt, Meta, and Shift combinations in TypeScript and JavaScript files, filtering out node_modules and test files, producing a sorted unique list of shortcut candidates across the codebase.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-limitations-and-gotchas">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents generating shortcut tables often produce conflicts with Ctrl+W (close tab), Ctrl+T (new tab), Ctrl+P (print).</description>
        <reason>Common browser shortcuts are not always top-of-mind for agents; always run a conflict check pass before shipping.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>"Multiple paths" generated by agents may silently diverge in behavior (e.g., double-click edits inline, right-click opens modal).</description>
        <reason>Behavioral divergence between paths fragments user mental models; flag these for human review before implementation.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agents cannot observe actual shortcut adoption; efficiency gains claimed in an audit are hypotheses until measured.</description>
        <reason>Shortcut effectiveness must be validated through usage analytics; audit recommendations are feature hypotheses, not proven optimizations.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Human checkpoint required for irreversible bulk operations: agent can design the UX pattern, but confirmation dialogs and undo mechanisms must be verified by a developer.</description>
        <reason>Data loss risk is too high to implement bulk destructive operations without developer review of the confirmation flow and undo mechanism.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/flexibility-audit.md" purpose="Audit table for shortcuts, customization options, alternative paths, and power-user features."/>
    </templates>

    <scripts>
      <script path="scripts/find-shortcuts.sh" purpose="Grep-based script to extract keyboard shortcut bindings from a JS/TS codebase."/>
    </scripts>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/flexibility-efficiency-heuristic/"/>
      <link href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2021/09/keyboard-shortcuts-web-applications/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/keyboards"/>
      <link href="https://m3.material.io/foundations/navigation"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
