<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="agile-hybrid-approaches">
  <metadata>
    <tier>pro</tier>
    <group>pm</group>
    <domain>project-manager</domain>
    <summary>Decision framework for selecting delivery mode (predictive, agile, or named hybrid) based on six scored dimensions. Approach mismatch detected via metrics and re-evaluated mid-project.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>hybrid</tag>
      <tag>waterfall</tag>
      <tag>scrum</tag>
      <tag>kanban</tag>
      <tag>delivery-mode</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>advanced</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-28</created>
    <category>approach</category>
  </metadata>
  <content>
    <title>Agile and Hybrid Approaches</title>
    <summary>A decision framework for selecting and tailoring a delivery mode — predictive (waterfall), agile (Scrum/Kanban), or a named hybrid pattern — based on six scored dimensions: requirement clarity, stakeholder engagement, risk tolerance, team agility, contract flexibility, and regulatory burden. "Hybrid" is never a hand-wave; the selected pattern must be named (Water-Scrum-Fall, agile-discovery-then-predictive, predictive-governance-over-agile-execution). LLMs default to "agile" for almost any prompt — force balanced scoring.</summary>
    <why>
      <p>No single approach fits every project. Pure waterfall is too rigid for uncertainty; pure agile fails on fixed-price compliance work. The mismatch creates rework, missed gates, and client disputes. The six-dimension scoring model makes the approach selection auditable — the decision is traceable to project inputs, not PM preference.</p>
    </why>
    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Choosing a delivery mode at project kickoff given a known project context</item>
        <item>Re-evaluating mid-project when symptoms appear (waterfall slipping repeatedly, Scrum failing on fixed-price compliance)</item>
        <item>Designing a tailored hybrid for fixed-price clients</item>
        <item>Authoring the Development Approach section of a PMBoK 8 plan</item>
        <item>Coaching a team transitioning between approaches with explicit ceremony and artefact mappings</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>
    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Tiny projects under 4 weeks with a single well-scoped team — any methodology overhead beats the work itself; use a checklist</item>
        <item>Mandated-by-contract approaches (DoD waterfall, FDA validated software) — no degrees of freedom</item>
        <item>Pure operations / BAU work with no defined start/end — use Kanban + SLAs, not project methodology</item>
        <item>Research-heavy pre-PMF startups — approach selection is premature</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>
    <section name="Selection Dimensions">
      <rule>
        <statement>Score the project on all six dimensions before recommending an approach. Never recommend based on team preference or default to agile without scoring.</statement>
        <rationale>LLMs have a heavy agile bias from training data. Unscored recommendations are PM preference, not project fit. Scoring creates an auditable decision record.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Requirement clarity — stable and well-defined favours predictive; evolving and emergent favours agile</item>
        <item>Stakeholder engagement — limited access favours predictive; highly engaged favours agile</item>
        <item>Risk tolerance — low (must work first time) favours predictive; high (can experiment) favours agile</item>
        <item>Team agility — less experienced favours predictive; self-organising favours agile</item>
        <item>Contract flexibility — fixed price/scope favours predictive; time and materials favours agile</item>
        <item>Regulatory burden — high (FDA, DoD, banking phase gates) favours predictive; low favours agile</item>
      </list>
      <reference path="templates/approach-score.py">Six-dimension scoring script, outputs recommendation JSON</reference>
    </section>
    <section name="Named Hybrid Patterns">
      <rule>
        <statement>When recommending "hybrid", always name the specific pattern. Generic "hybrid" in output must be rejected and re-prompted.</statement>
        <rationale>Generic hybrid recommendations produce mixed signals — teams implement waterfall with daily standups (overhead without benefit). A named pattern specifies which phase uses which method.</rationale>
      </rule>
      <list>
        <item>Water-Scrum-Fall: Plan phase (predictive) → Build phase (Scrum) → Deploy phase (predictive). Caps agile benefit — total cycle time is still long.</item>
        <item>Agile-discovery-then-predictive: Agile discovery phase to clarify requirements → Waterfall implementation once scope is locked. Good for fixed-price contracts with unclear initial scope.</item>
        <item>Predictive-governance-over-agile-execution: Phase gates and funding approvals are predictive; sprint execution within each phase is agile. Two reporting cadences — sprint review + phase gate.</item>
      </list>
      <example type="good">
        <note>Hybrid for a $100K fixed-price contract over 4 months.</note>
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
Phase 1: Discovery (2 weeks) — Agile
  - User story workshops, prototype key screens, finalise scope
Phase 2: Development (10 weeks) — Scrum
  - 5 two-week sprints, weekly client demos, backlog refinement
Phase 3: Deployment (2 weeks) — Predictive
  - Fixed test plan, staged rollout, documentation

Governance:
  - Monthly steering committee (predictive gate)
  - Weekly sprint reviews (agile cadence)
  - Change requests required for scope changes (predictive control)
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section name="Failure Modes and Antipatterns">
      <antipattern>
        <description>Agile-in-name-only: daily standups plus a waterfall plan.</description>
        <reason>Standups without a working sprint backlog and empirical planning produce the overhead of both methods with the benefit of neither.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Recommending agile on a fixed-price contract without a scope-envelope warning.</description>
        <reason>Fixed-price plus agile only works with a scope-envelope contract (range of stories, change budget, exit clauses). Without it, every backlog refinement is a contract dispute.</reason>
      </antipattern>
      <antipattern>
        <description>Adopting SAFe to fix a single-team velocity problem.</description>
        <reason>SAFe is a multi-team scaling framework. Applying it to a one-team problem adds PI planning, ARTs, and RTEs without solving the velocity root cause.</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>
    <section name="Scrum Framework">
      <p>Product Backlog → Sprint Planning → Sprint (2 weeks) → Sprint Review → Sprint Retrospective → repeat.</p>
      <list>
        <item>Sprint Planning (2-4 h): select stories for sprint goal, break into tasks</item>
        <item>Daily Scrum (15 min): synchronise, surface blockers — not a status report</item>
        <item>Sprint Review (1-2 h): demo increment to stakeholders, update backlog</item>
        <item>Sprint Retrospective (1-2 h): inspect process, commit to one improvement</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>A sprint review without a working software demo is a status meeting. A daily standup without an updated sprint board is a social call. Name the artefact, not just the ceremony.</statement>
        <rationale>Ceremony names without evidence of their output signals agile-in-name-only — the team gets overhead without feedback loops.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Kanban Principles">
      <list>
        <item>Visualise the workflow — every work item on the board, every state visible</item>
        <item>Limit WIP per column — enforce with card-colour rules or tooling, not social pressure</item>
        <item>Manage flow — measure lead time and cycle time; optimise throughput, not utilisation</item>
        <item>Make policies explicit — Definition of Done per column is written, not assumed</item>
        <item>Improve collaboratively — retrospect on flow metrics, not feelings</item>
      </list>
      <rule>
        <statement>Set WIP limits in the tool, not in a policy document. Limits enforced only by culture collapse under deadline pressure within two weeks.</statement>
        <rationale>WIP limits are the primary Kanban control mechanism. Visual enforcement in the tool makes violations visible to the whole team without a PM having to call them out.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Approach-Fit Metrics">
      <rule>
        <statement>Track these metrics to detect approach mismatch: lead time (total end-to-end), velocity stability (coefficient of variation), change-request rate per sprint, and defect-escape rate. If two consecutive sprints trend wrong on any metric, re-run approach scoring.</statement>
        <rationale>Approach mismatches manifest in metrics before they manifest in project reports. Early re-evaluation avoids a 3-month commitment to a failing pattern.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>
    <section name="Agentic Workflow">
      <p>The agent is a methodology selector + tailor. Phase 1: a `methodology-selector` reads a project context YAML (requirement clarity, stakeholder availability, contract type, team experience, risk tolerance, regulator presence) and returns a recommended approach with rationale. Phase 2: a `methodology-tailor` produces the concrete artefact list (charter / backlog / sprints / gates) and ceremony cadence. Human review between phases. Re-run on every steering committee that changes the inputs.</p>
      <p>Agile-in-name-only is the most common failure: daily standups + waterfall plan = no benefit, doubled overhead. Water-Scrum-Fall caps the agile benefit: the build is iterative but plan and deploy phases are rigid, so total cycle time is still long. Fixed-price + agile only works with a "scope envelope" contract; LLMs miss this nuance and recommend agile to fixed-price clients without warning. Hybrid governance creates two reporting cadences (sprint review + phase gate) that both consume PM time; not free. Scrum at scale (SAFe, LeSS, Nexus) is its own beast and is *not* a generic hybrid; agents conflate them. Kanban WIP limits get violated under deadline pressure; methodology guidance does not enforce them — needs tooling. "Choose by team experience" advice creates a chicken-and-egg: junior teams default to predictive but never learn agile.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Prompt Pattern for Agent Selection">
      <p>Score the project on each axis (1-5): requirement_clarity, stakeholder_engagement, risk_tolerance, team_agility, contract_flexibility, regulatory_burden. Recommend ONE of: [predictive, scrum, kanban, scrumban, water-scrum-fall, predictive-governance-over-agile, agile-discovery-then-predictive]. Output JSON: { "scores": {...}, "recommendation": "...", "rationale": ["...", "..."], "ceremonies": [{"name":"...", "cadence":"weekly"}], "artefacts": ["...", "..."], "risks_of_recommendation": ["..."], "fall_back": "..." }. Constraints: Cite at least one risk if recommending agile on a fixed-price contract. Never recommend "pure scrum" if regulatory_burden ≥ 4.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Best Practices">
      <list>
        <item>Pick the smallest approach that solves the symptom; do not adopt SAFe to fix a one-team velocity problem.</item>
        <item>Make the choice explicit and dated in the project charter; write down the trigger that would force a re-evaluation.</item>
        <item>For hybrids, pick *one* primary cadence (sprint OR gate) and make the other an overlay; running both at equal weight burns out the PM.</item>
        <item>Translate ceremonies, not labels: a "sprint review" with no demo is just a status meeting.</item>
        <item>For fixed-price agile, write a scope-envelope contract: range of stories, change-budget, exit clauses.</item>
        <item>Track approach-fit metrics: lead time, velocity stability, change-request rate per sprint, defect-escape; if they trend wrong, revisit.</item>
        <item>Solopreneur: default to personal Kanban with WIP=3; only graduate to Scrum once you have ≥ 2 collaborators.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <section name="AI-Agent Gotchas">
      <list>
        <item>LLMs default to "agile" for almost any prompt; bias toward agile is heavy in training data. Force balanced scoring.</item>
        <item>Agents conflate Scrum, SAFe, and "agile" — pin a fixed vocabulary.</item>
        <item>"Hybrid" is used as a hand-wave; agents should always name a specific pattern (Water-Scrum-Fall, agile-discovery-then-predictive, etc.).</item>
        <item>Agents recommend daily standups for solo work — guard with team-size threshold.</item>
        <item>Compliance / regulator constraints are dropped silently; require explicit input field and reject "pure agile" when burden ≥ 4.</item>
        <item>"Fixed price + agile" gets recommended without a scope-envelope warning; force a risks-of-recommendation field.</item>
        <item>For approach changes, agents skip the transition cost (training, tool migration); always include a transition-cost section.</item>
        <item>Sprint length defaults to 2 weeks regardless of context; for distributed / regulated teams, 3-4 weeks is often better.</item>
      </list>
    </section>
    <templates>
      <template path="templates/sprint-planning.md" purpose="Sprint planning document with capacity table, backlog, dependencies, risks"/>
      <template path="templates/kanban-board.md" purpose="Kanban board state template with WIP limits"/>
      <template path="templates/approach-score.py" purpose="Python: score six dimensions, recommend predictive/agile/hybrid"/>
    </templates>
    <see-also>
      <link href="https://scrumguides.org/scrum-guide.html"/>
      <link href="https://kanbanguides.org/"/>
      <link href="https://scaledagileframework.com/"/>
      <link href="https://less.works/"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/pmbok-guide-standards/practice-guides/agile"/>
      <link href="https://www.pmi.org/disciplined-agile"/>
      <link href="https://agilemanifesto.org/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
