<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Affiliate Program Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five hard rules for a solo founder running an affiliate program without a marketing team or fraud-prevention vendor.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-platform-native-first" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If your payment platform has a built-in affiliate module (Lemon Squeezy, Gumroad, Paddle), use it. Don't add Rewardful or a custom solution unless the native option blocks a specific requirement (multi-tier commissions, custom payout currencies, niche-specific reporting).</statement>
      <rationale source="solo-founder time-budget reality; LS / Gumroad affiliate adoption data 2024">Custom affiliate tooling costs 20-40 hours setup + ongoing maintenance. LS native costs 30 minutes. For &lt; 50 affiliates the native option is always net-positive. Graduating later to Rewardful is cheap once you have a working program.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-commission-within-margin" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Affiliate commission % must leave you a positive gross margin AFTER payment-processor fees + commission + refund reserve. Formula: max_commission = gross_margin - processor_fee - refund_reserve - operating_margin. Use compute-commission-from-margin.py.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaS unit economics; LTV/CAC literature">Indie hackers routinely pick "30% recurring" because they saw it elsewhere, without computing margins. At 70% gross margin and 5% refund reserve and 4% Stripe fee, 30% commission leaves 31% operating margin — fine. At 50% margin and 30% commission, you're underwater. The formula must precede the policy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-fraud-guards-required" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every program has 4 fraud guards: (1) anti-self-referral (block payouts when affiliate's IP / email / payment-method matches the converted customer), (2) cookie window cap (≤ 60 days), (3) payout-hold (≥ refund_window + 7 days before commission paid), (4) review queue for new affiliates' first 3 conversions.</statement>
      <rationale source="affiliate fraud reports - Forrester 2024 (~10% fraud rate in unaudited programs); Rewardful fraud-prevention guides">Without guards, fraud eats 10-30% of payouts. Self-referral is the #1 abuse (~6% of solo-program payouts). Cookie window caps prevent "I clicked once 2 years ago" attribution. Payout hold lets refunds clawback before money leaves. New-affiliate review catches the bad-actor cluster.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-refund-clawback-binding" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If a referred customer refunds within your refund window, the affiliate commission is clawed back. This is written into the affiliate terms BEFORE the affiliate signs up. No retroactive policy changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="LS / Rewardful default behavior; legal contract enforceability">Affiliates who don't expect clawback dispute it loudly. The terms page must specify clawback explicitly. Retroactive policy = lost affiliates AND lost legal standing. The payout-hold (r3.3) makes clawback frictionless: nothing has been paid yet.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-disclose-terms-in-writing" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every program has a public terms page (or a sign-up agreement) covering: commission %, cookie window, payout schedule, payout minimum, clawback policy, prohibited promotion (no PPC bidding on your brand, no incentivized clicks, no email spam), and an FTC-style disclosure requirement for affiliates to disclose their relationship.</statement>
      <rationale source="FTC 16 CFR Part 255 (endorsement guides); EU UCPD 2005/29/EC">FTC fines for non-disclosure run $5k-$50k per violation in the US. Solo founder is legally responsible for affiliate disclosure. The terms page is the contract that lets you terminate non-compliant affiliates. EU follows similar disclosure law via UCPD.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Canonical examples">

    <example type="good" title="Commission compute respecting margins">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Product: SaaS at $29/mo
Gross margin (after hosting + support proportional): 76%      = $22.04
Stripe fee: 2.9% + 30¢ on $29                                 = $1.14
Refund reserve (5% of MRR refunds within window):             = $1.10
Operating margin target (you keep):                            ≥ 35% = $7.65
Available for commission: $22.04 - $1.14 - $1.10 - $7.65       = $12.15
Commission as % of $29:                                         = 41.9%

Set commission at 30% recurring (safe headroom).
Set first-month bonus at 40% (acquisition push).
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r2: formula-driven not vibes-driven commission setting.</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Commission set by aspiration">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"I saw a competitor offers 50% recurring so I'll match it."

Product: $19/mo, gross margin 55% = $10.45
50% commission = $9.50
Stripe fee + refund reserve = $1.74
Operating margin: -$0.79 per referred sale, EVERY MONTH.

Problem: each affiliate sale is a loss. Volume of affiliate sales is the
fastest way to bankrupt the business.
Repair: max safe commission at this margin is ~20% recurring or 30%
first-month-only. Match competitor only after raising prices or cutting COGS.
      ]]></code>
      <note>The "match competitor" pattern is the canonical margin-killer.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
