<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-inclusivity-rules" title="VUI Inclusivity — Core Design Rules">
  <summary>Concrete design rules for building voice interfaces that work across accents, speech impediments, age groups, languages, and noisy environments.</summary>

  <section title="Dataset and Recognition Diversity">
    <rule>
      <statement>Train or select ASR models on datasets that include multiple accents, dialects, age ranges (children to elderly), gender diversity, speech impediments, and real-world noise conditions.</statement>
      <rationale>Systems trained on narrow datasets systematically fail non-native speakers, elderly users, and people with stutters or lisps — creating an exclusionary interface.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Support regionally distinct language variants (e.g., US English, UK English, Australian English, Indian English) with local vocabulary and pronunciation models.</statement>
      <rationale>Vocabulary and pronunciation differences between variants cause high error rates when only a single locale model is used.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide an accent calibration flow at onboarding: have the user read sample phrases, adapt to their speech pattern, and allow manual sensitivity adjustment.</statement>
      <rationale>Individual calibration reduces recognition errors significantly for users whose accent is underrepresented in general models.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Allow users to teach the system their pronunciation for misrecognized words ("I meant [correct word]") and learn from those corrections permanently.</statement>
      <rationale>Persistent learning closes the gap for edge-case vocabularies that cannot be addressed in general training.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Speech Variation Tolerance">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never interrupt or timeout mid-utterance for users who pause, use filler words ("um", "uh"), repeat, self-correct, or speak slowly.</statement>
      <rationale>Premature timeouts exclude users with stutters, hesitant speakers, and non-native speakers who construct sentences while speaking.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Make silence thresholds configurable; default to a longer dwell than typical ASR defaults.</statement>
      <rationale>Standard ASR silence thresholds are tuned for fluent native speakers and cut off slower speakers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Show what the system heard (live transcription) and what it understood (intent) as separate visual elements so users can verify and correct.</statement>
      <rationale>Separating heard vs understood lets users spot recognition errors before they cause unwanted actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Multimodal and Alternative Input">
    <rule>
      <statement>Never build a voice-only path. Every VUI feature must be reachable via touch or keyboard, and every voice response must have a visual equivalent.</statement>
      <rationale>WCAG requires perceivable and operable interfaces via multiple modalities; voice-only interfaces exclude deaf users and fail in loud environments.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Always display available commands or a "help" prompt so users do not need to memorize the grammar.</statement>
      <rationale>Discoverability is the primary learnability problem in VUI; users abandon systems they cannot explore.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide multi-channel confirmation for critical actions: voice response, visible status, haptic feedback, and/or sound cue — all conveying the same information.</statement>
      <rationale>Redundant channels ensure confirmation reaches users regardless of context (noisy room, visual impairment, hands occupied).</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Privacy and Trust">
    <rule>
      <statement>Make the mute button permanently visible and provide a "stop listening" voice command. Allow users to delete recordings and disable always-on listening per feature.</statement>
      <rationale>Privacy concerns are the top barrier to VUI adoption; transparent control builds the trust required for continued use.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>State clearly what voice data is stored, for how long, and who has access — before the user enables voice features.</statement>
      <rationale>Opaque data practices cause abandonment and regulatory exposure under GDPR and similar laws.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Inclusive Testing">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include diverse testers in usability sessions: varied accents, non-native speakers, people with speech impediments, children, elderly users, and quiet vs noisy environments.</statement>
      <rationale>Recognition accuracy metrics from homogeneous lab conditions do not predict real-world failure rates for underrepresented groups.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
