<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-patterns" title="VUI Inclusivity — Interaction Patterns">
  <summary>Concrete dialogue and interaction patterns for inclusive voice interfaces: prompt design, error recovery, progressive disclosure, and accessibility benefit mapping.</summary>

  <section title="Prompt Design">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"What would you like to do? You can say 'send message',
'check calendar', or 'play music'."
      ]]></code>
      <note>States purpose and gives three concrete examples of valid commands — covers discoverability without overwhelming.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>"What do you want?" with no examples or hints.</description>
      <reason>Users unfamiliar with the command grammar have no way to discover valid inputs and abandon the interface.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Progressive Disclosure of Help">
    <rule>
      <statement>Start prompts minimal ("Say 'help' for options"), escalate to medium detail on first confusion, and offer full command lists only on explicit request.</statement>
      <rationale>Dumping all available commands in the first prompt overwhelms users; progressive disclosure matches cognitive load to user need.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Confirmation for Critical Actions">
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
User: "Delete all emails"
VUI:  "I heard 'delete all emails'. This will delete 1,247 emails.
       Say 'confirm' to proceed or 'cancel' to stop."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Repeats what was heard, states the consequence, and requires explicit confirmation — prevents destructive actions from recognition errors.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Error Recovery Hierarchy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use a three-tier error recovery sequence: (1) simple retry prompt, (2) retry with example phrases, (3) handoff to visual interface or human agent.</statement>
      <rationale>Three-tier recovery gives the system multiple chances to succeed while setting a clear escalation path that avoids infinite loops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Tier 1 (no input heard):
  "Sorry, I didn't catch that. Could you say it again?"

Tier 2 (speech not matched):
  "I'm not sure what you mean. Try saying something like
   'send a message' or 'set a reminder'."

Tier 3 (still failing):
  "Let me show you your options on screen."
      ]]></code>
      <note>Each tier adds information. Tier 3 switches modality rather than repeating the same failure path.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Saying "I didn't understand" more than twice without offering new information or a different interaction path.</description>
      <reason>Repeating the same error message with no new guidance traps the user in a loop and damages trust.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Multimodal Feedback">
    <rule>
      <statement>Confirm every completed action across all available channels: voice response, visual indicator, haptic feedback, and audio cue — all conveying identical information.</statement>
      <rationale>Redundant channels ensure confirmation reaches users regardless of sensory context or environmental interference.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Voice:  "Message sent to John"
Visual: Check mark + "Message sent"
Haptic: Short confirmation vibration
Audio:  Success chime
      ]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="User Group Benefits">
    <list>
      <item>Visual impairment: audio-first design, rich spoken feedback, no visual-only paths</item>
      <item>Motor disabilities: voice-only paths for every feature, no required touch</item>
      <item>Elderly users: patient response timing, simple command grammar, familiar metaphors</item>
      <item>Non-native speakers: multi-language support, visual transcription confirmation</item>
      <item>Cognitive disabilities: clear prompts, guided conversation flow, no time pressure</item>
      <item>Dyslexia: spell out confirmations, read back entered text, no mandatory reading</item>
      <item>Busy contexts (driving, cooking): eyes-free operation, interruption handling, short responses</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
