<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Churn Prevention Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>6 testable rules every application of `Churn Prevention` must enforce. Each rule pairs a binary check with a sourced rationale.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="three-phase-not-discount-spray" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Prevention MUST follow three phases: early intervention (pre-decision) -&gt; save offer (in cancel flow) -&gt; win-back (post-cancel). Discount-only blasts at random users are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Profitwell retention playbook 2023">Discount sprays kill margin without addressing reason. Phased approach targets users at the moment of maximum intent + minimum cost-to-save.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="segment-by-cancel-reason" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Save offers MUST be matched to cancellation reason segment, not a generic flow. Minimum: price-objection, missing-feature, low-usage, competitor-switch, lifecycle-end (&gt;= 5 segments).</statement>
      <rationale source="save-offer A/B test corpus">A &apos;too expensive&apos; user wants a discount or downgrade; a &apos;missing feature&apos; user wants a roadmap commitment or refund. Same offer to both loses both.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="save-offer-cost-cap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each save offer MUST have a documented unit-economics cap: max discount × months &lt;= 50% of LTV of the saved customer. Offers above the cap require sign-off.</statement>
      <rationale source="SaaS finance / Profitwell cohort LTV math">Unbounded save offers are a worse outcome than the original churn — you save the logo but lose the unit economics. Cap forces a deliberate tradeoff.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="win-back-90-day-window" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Win-back campaigns MUST run within 30-90 days of cancel. Beyond 90 days conversion drops &gt; 70% based on Iterable / Klaviyo benchmarks.</statement>
      <rationale source="lifecycle-marketing benchmarks 2024">Recency matters. The user still remembers the product; the alternative is still imperfect; the unsubscribe wound is still warm. After 90 days they&apos;re cold leads, not win-back.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="stop-loss-on-margin" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Playbook MUST define a stop-loss: if blended save-offer margin drops below 30% gross over a 4-week window, pause the offer and re-segment.</statement>
      <rationale source="Profitwell save-flow casework">Save offers can scale unprofitable retention. Without a stop-loss the playbook silently turns into a discount factory.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>When preconditions in Applies If fail OR any item in Skip If triggers, do not run this methodology. Document the skip rationale in the artefact&apos;s parent log.</statement>
      <rationale source="Methodology-routing discipline">Misapplied methodologies are worse than no methodology — they consume review cycles and produce false confidence.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
