<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Shadow Handover Session Core Rules">
  <summary>Five testable rules that turn an offshore-to-onshore handover from a demo into a verified transfer of operational ownership.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The receiver MUST drive the keyboard, terminal, and decisions for the entire session; the outgoing engineer never touches input devices except to recover an explicitly-stuck session.</statement>
      <rationale>The receiver-does / outgoing-watches inversion is the whole point — when the outgoing engineer drives, the receiver memorises ritual without internalising mechanism, then cannot reproduce post-rotation.</rationale>
      <example type="bad">
        <description>Outgoing engineer says "let me just show you", grabs the keyboard, runs three commands in 30 seconds.</description>
        <reason>The receiver did not type, did not hit any error path, did not learn anything. The session became a screencast.</reason>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The outgoing engineer MUST stay silent by default; they answer only when the receiver explicitly asks a question. No spontaneous "actually you also need to…".</statement>
      <rationale>Spontaneous corrections rob the receiver of the chance to fail and recover, which is the only durable form of knowledge transfer. Silence forces the receiver to either know it or ask, both of which surface gaps.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>Every question the receiver asks MUST be logged verbatim in a written "gap log" with answer + linked permanent doc; questions without a doc link are open action items.</statement>
      <rationale>Tribal knowledge is exactly the set of facts that get answered verbally and never written down. Forcing each question into a doc-or-action converts tribal knowledge into a captured artefact one session at a time.</rationale>
      <example type="good">
        <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[# Gap log — 2026-05-20 session
| Q | Answer | Doc link | Action |
|---|--------|----------|--------|
| Where does the prod DB password live? | 1Password vault "prod-db" | wiki/secrets#prod-db | — |
| How do I restart the worker pool? | systemctl restart worker@* | (none) | TODO: add to runbook |]]></code>
      </example>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The session MUST end with a written sign-off by both engineers naming (a) tasks the receiver successfully drove unaided, (b) tasks that still need a second session, (c) any single-point-of-failure facts not yet documented.</statement>
      <rationale>Without an explicit sign-off, both parties walk away assuming "I think they got it" and the first incident reveals the gap. The artefact also gates the outgoing engineer's rotation date.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule testable="true">
      <statement>The task list MUST be defined before the session starts and the session is NOT considered complete until every task has been driven by the receiver OR explicitly logged as "deferred to session N+1"; tasks are never silently skipped.</statement>
      <rationale>Skipped tasks are the most common post-mortem finding: "we never actually walked through restore-from-backup". A pre-agreed list with explicit deferral prevents the receiver from agreeing they understood something they never touched.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>
</text>
