<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-feed-management" title="Feed Quality, Optimization, and Merchant Center Management">
  <summary>Feed quality rules, title optimization, disapproval diagnosis, campaign structure by product segment, and bidding progression for Shopping campaigns.</summary>

  <section title="Feed Quality Rules">
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat the product feed as the campaign; 80% of Shopping optimization is feed quality (titles, images, categories, GTINs), not bid adjustments.</statement>
      <rationale>Shopping has no ad copy — Google assembles the ad from the feed. A product with a vague title and missing GTIN will receive few or no impressions regardless of bid, because the query matching quality is determined by the feed, not bids.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Place the most search-relevant terms in the first 60 characters of the product title; mobile truncation cuts anything beyond that.</statement>
      <rationale>Mobile Shopping results truncate titles at ~60 characters. The most important differentiating attributes (brand, model, color, size) must be front-loaded to appear before truncation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Title pattern: [Brand] [Product Type] [Color/Size/Material] [Model] [Key Feature]</item>
      <item>Avoid: "BEST", "SALE", all-caps, special characters, promotional copy in titles</item>
      <item>GTIN required for branded products — materially improves impression eligibility</item>
      <item>Google Product Category required — improves matching and reporting</item>
      <item>High-quality images: minimum 800x800 for standard, 1200x1200 preferred</item>
      <item>Update price and availability at least daily; stale data triggers Merchant Center suspension</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Campaign Structure">
    <rule>
      <statement>Structure Shopping campaigns by product margin tier or category, not arbitrarily; bidding strategy needs clusters with similar ROAS targets.</statement>
      <rationale>A single Shopping campaign mixing high-margin and low-margin products cannot optimize bids for both simultaneously. Separate campaigns or ad groups with different bids per margin tier produce materially better ROAS.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Use campaign priority settings when running multiple Shopping campaigns over the same SKUs; without priority settings, Google chooses the campaign randomly and budget allocation becomes unpredictable.</statement>
      <rationale>Priority (Low/Medium/High) determines which campaign wins the internal auction when multiple campaigns target the same product. Using it enables a branded-vs-non-branded or promotional-vs-standard split that is otherwise uncontrollable.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Bidding Progression">
    <list>
      <item>Start: Manual CPC — full per-product-group bid control</item>
      <item>After 30+ conversions per campaign: switch to Target ROAS</item>
      <item>Adjust bids by product performance: high-ROAS groups up, low-ROAS groups down</item>
      <item>Bid adjustments available: device, location</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not pause and unpause Shopping campaigns frequently; each pause disrupts auction history and Smart Bidding learning.</statement>
      <rationale>Shopping's Smart Bidding model is built on conversion history per product. Frequent pausing erases the optimizer's signal and restarts the learning phase, producing inefficient bids for 1-2 weeks after each restart.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
