<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="DORA + Reliability Metrics Report Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>7 testable rules grounding the dora-metrics methodology. Each rule pairs a binary check + sourced rationale and is referenced by the decision tree.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="ingest-deploy-event-cdevents" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deploy events MUST be ingested in a CDEvents-compatible schema (or equivalent: timestamp, service, env, commit SHA, success bool); ad-hoc CSV is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="CDEvents spec, DORA Accelerate book">Without a typed event schema, lead-time/MTTR computation drifts and cannot be reconciled across teams.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="lead-time-from-commit-to-prod" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Lead Time for Changes MUST be `prod_deploy_timestamp - commit_timestamp` for the latest commit in the deployed SHA; merge-time approximations are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="DORA Accelerate book ch.3">Merge-time hides queueing in CI/CD; commit-to-prod is the true user-felt lead time.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="deploy-frequency-rolling-7-day" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deployment Frequency MUST be reported as a rolling 7-day count per service; monthly aggregates hide regressions.</statement>
      <rationale source="DORA 2024 report">Long aggregation windows mask the very degradation the metric is meant to surface.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="change-failure-rate-from-incidents" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Change Failure Rate MUST be computed as `incidents_within_24h / deploys` where incidents reference a deploy commit; opinion polls are forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="DORA Accelerate book ch.4">Self-reported CFR is biased low; deploy-linked incident data is the only objective source.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="mttr-includes-detection-time" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>MTTR MUST include detection-to-mitigation, not just response-to-mitigation; clock starts when the incident's first symptom is observable.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google SRE Book ch.14">Hiding detection time turns MTTR into a vanity metric that improves while user-visible outage time stays flat.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="reliability-as-fifth-metric" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Report MUST include Reliability (SLO attainment %) alongside the four DORA metrics; the 2024 update positions Reliability as the fifth pillar.</statement>
      <rationale source="DORA 2024 report">Pure throughput metrics encourage shipping at the expense of stability; Reliability is the counterbalance.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If the team has no production deploys yet (pre-product), this methodology MUST be skipped.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal scope review">Computing DORA on zero deploys yields noise.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/04-procedure.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
