<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-concepts" title="DORA Metrics: Definitions and Benchmarks">
  <summary>The four DORA metrics, their performance tiers, data sources, and 2025 evolution including a fifth reliability metric and AI code generation impact.</summary>

  <section title="Four Key Metrics">
    <rule>
      <statement>Measure all four DORA metrics as a set — throughput (DF + LT) and stability (CFR + MTTR) together reveal the full delivery health picture.</statement>
      <rationale>Optimizing only throughput metrics drives risky large batches; only stability metrics drives slow but safe delivery. Elite performers achieve high scores on all four simultaneously.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <p>Performance tiers (from DORA research):</p>
    <list>
      <item>Deployment Frequency: Elite = multiple/day; High = weekly–monthly; Medium = monthly–6mo; Low = 6mo+</item>
      <item>Lead Time for Changes: Elite = &lt;1 hour; High = 1 day–1 week; Medium = 1–6 months; Low = 6mo+</item>
      <item>Change Failure Rate: Elite = 0–15%; High = 16–30%; Medium = 31–45%; Low = 46%+</item>
      <item>Mean Time to Restore: Elite = &lt;1 hour; High = &lt;1 day; Medium = 1 day–1 week; Low = 1 week–1 month</item>
    </list>

    <rule>
      <statement>Track trends, not absolute values — week-over-week improvement matters more than hitting exact elite thresholds.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams in different domains (embedded, banking) have structural constraints that prevent elite DF; improvement trajectory predicts organizational outcomes better than absolute tier.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Metric Definitions and Data Sources">
    <p>Deployment Frequency: count of successful production deployments per time period. Data: CI/CD pipeline events, deployment logs.</p>
    <p>Lead Time for Changes: time from first commit to successful production deployment. Data: Git commit timestamps + CI/CD deployment timestamps.</p>
    <p>Change Failure Rate: percentage of deployments requiring rollback, hotfix, or causing an incident. Data: incident tracking system + deployment records.</p>
    <p>Mean Time to Restore: average time from incident detection to resolution. Data: incident management (PagerDuty, Opsgenie) resolved timestamps.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="2025 Evolution">
    <rule>
      <statement>Add Reliability (SLO achievement rate) as a fifth metric alongside the four core DORA metrics.</statement>
      <rationale>DORA 2025 research shows SLO achievement and error budget consumption predict organizational outcomes independently of the four delivery metrics.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor batch size when using AI code generation tools; expect a ~7% reduction in delivery stability with heavy AI adoption.</statement>
      <rationale>AI-generated code encourages larger commits and pull requests, which violates the small-batch principle underlying elite DORA performance.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Business Impact">
    <p>Research findings from Accelerate (Forsgren, Humble, Kim, 2018):</p>
    <list>
      <item>Elite performers are 2x more likely to exceed organizational performance goals</item>
      <item>Elite vs low: 208x higher deployment frequency</item>
      <item>Elite vs low: 106x faster lead time</item>
      <item>Elite vs low: 2,604x faster recovery time</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
