<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Product Lifecycle Management Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Four-stage diagnostic (Introduction -&gt; Growth -&gt; Maturity -&gt; Decline) matching stage signals to investment strategy, with explicit transition checkpoints and end-of-life sunset plan.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="stage-classification-quantitative" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stage tag MUST be derived from quantitative signals: growth rate, churn, NPS, market share. Qualitative 'feels mature' tagging is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="BCG Growth-Share Matrix; Boston Consulting lifecycle research">Vibes-based stage tagging hides decline and over-invests in maturity.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="stage-investment-matched" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Investment strategy MUST match the tagged stage: Introduction = learn fast, Growth = scale, Maturity = retain + efficiency, Decline = harvest or sunset.</statement>
      <rationale source="Theodore Levitt — Product Lifecycle (HBR)">Growth budgets on Maturity products produce no acceleration.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="transition-checkpoint-written" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Stage transitions MUST be marked with a written transition memo ('why we believe X -&gt; Y now').</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — portfolio retro patterns">Without checkpoints, teams stay in the previous stage's strategy long after the metrics moved.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sunset-plan-mandatory-on-decline" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Tagging a product Decline MUST trigger a sunset plan within 30 days: migration timeline, customer comms, EOL date, data-export commitments.</statement>
      <rationale source="Google / Microsoft EOL playbooks">Open-ended Decline products drain budget and frustrate customers.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="portfolio-review-pre-roadmap" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every product MUST be lifecycle-tagged BEFORE roadmap sequencing for the year. Tagging after the roadmap is a rationalization.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — portfolio review failure modes">Post-hoc tagging is reverse-engineered to justify the roadmap.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — single-product team; pre-PMF; agency projects; recent tag without trigger events), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
