<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-stages" title="Product Lifecycle Stages">
  <summary>Defines the four lifecycle stages — Introduction, Growth, Maturity, Decline — with characteristics, focus areas, key metrics, and stage-appropriate investment strategies.</summary>

  <section title="Introduction">
    <p>Low revenue, negative profit, early adopters only, high uncertainty, frequent pivots.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>In Introduction, maximize learning and product-market fit validation over revenue extraction. Invest 70%+ in iteration and PMF, 0% in sunset activities.</statement>
      <rationale>Pre-PMF, every dollar on acquisition before fit is wasted CAC. The stage ends only when activation and early retention signal demand.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Key metrics: activation rate, early retention (Day 7), NPS from early users.</item>
      <item>Stage signal: MRR &lt; $10k OR growth &gt; 50% YoY AND profitability negative AND &lt;12 months since launch.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Growth">
    <p>Rapidly increasing revenue, market acceptance, competition increasing, scaling challenges.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>In Growth, invest 60%+ in customer acquisition and feature expansion to capture market share before competition intensifies. Build team and infrastructure in parallel.</statement>
      <rationale>Growth windows close fast; under-investing in acquisition during Growth produces a smaller Maturity base from which to defend.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Key metrics: growth rate, CAC, LTV, market share, revenue.</item>
      <item>Stage signal: growth &gt;= 20% YoY for 2+ quarters AND profitability improving AND competition increasing.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Maturity">
    <p>Stable or slowing revenue, market saturation, intense competition, optimization focus.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>In Maturity, shift 50%+ of investment to retention and optimization; cap new acquisition at &lt;30%. Measure profitability and efficiency ratios, not growth rate.</statement>
      <rationale>New customer acquisition becomes expensive in saturated markets; retaining existing customers and extracting margin is the highest-ROI lever.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Key metrics: profitability, churn rate, NPS, cost efficiency ratios.</item>
      <item>Stage signal: growth &lt; 15% YoY AND profitability at peak AND saturated market signals.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Decline">
    <p>Decreasing revenue, technology shift, customer migration, resource reallocation.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>In Decline, invest 60%+ in optimization and sunset activities; stop new acquisition investment. Focus on cash harvesting, migration support, and sunset timeline.</statement>
      <rationale>Continued acquisition spend in Decline produces negative-ROI customers who still need support through the sunset window.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Key metrics: cash flow, migration rate, support cost, timeline to sunset.</item>
      <item>Stage signal: growth &lt; 0 for 2+ quarters AND customer migration evidence.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Stage-Appropriate Strategies">
    <rule>
      <statement>Anchor every stage label to at least two evidence sources (e.g., MRR series + cohort retention). Single-metric staging is the #1 cause of misclassification.</statement>
      <rationale>Single metrics are gamed or misread; two independent sources provide triangulation.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-classify quarterly. SaaS stage transitions can happen in two quarters; annual reviews apply the wrong strategy for 9-12 months.</statement>
      <rationale>Stage transitions are not annual events; quarterly cadence matches the speed at which market conditions shift.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying growth acquisition tactics to a Decline-stage product.</description>
      <reason>Acquisition spend compounds losses — acquired customers still generate support cost during the sunset window with no long-term LTV payback.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Refusing to declare Decline because the label is politically costly — lobbying for "late Maturity" indefinitely.</description>
      <reason>Delayed Decline classification extends over-investment; pre-commit numeric kill thresholds (e.g., "MRR YoY &lt; 0 for 3 quarters = automatic Decline review") to remove the political judgment call.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
