<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-process" title="Lifecycle Assessment Process">
  <summary>Four-step process for assessing a product's current lifecycle stage, validating the classification, applying stage-appropriate strategy, and planning for the next stage transition.</summary>

  <section title="Step 1: Assess Current Stage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Collect at least 4-8 quarters of MRR, growth rate, churn, gross margin, and market share data before classifying. With fewer than 4 quarters of history, default to Intro with low confidence.</statement>
      <rationale>Stage transitions can happen in 2 quarters; short histories produce high-variance classifications that reverse on the next data point.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>Intro signal: MRR &lt; $10k OR growth &gt; 50% YoY AND negative profitability AND &lt;12mo since launch.</item>
      <item>Growth signal: growth &gt;= 20% YoY for 2+ quarters AND improving profitability AND increasing competition.</item>
      <item>Maturity signal: growth &lt; 15% YoY AND peak profitability AND saturated market signals.</item>
      <item>Decline signal: growth &lt; 0 for 2+ quarters AND customer migration evidence.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Validate Stage">
    <rule>
      <statement>Review metrics trends over 3+ quarters, compare to market benchmarks, consider external factors (category shift, new technology), and get cross-functional team alignment before finalizing the stage label.</statement>
      <rationale>Single-person classification is subject to optimism bias; team alignment surfaces conflicting signals that a solo reviewer misses.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using revenue YoY growth as the sole classification signal for network-effect or bundling products.</description>
      <reason>Network-effect products can show low revenue but high engagement (still Growth); bundling products can show stable revenue while the real value is migrating to a different SKU.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Apply Stage Strategy">
    <rule>
      <statement>Explicitly map current investments (% engineering cost on acquisition / retention / optimization / sunset) against the stage-appropriate allocation rubric. Flag and resolve any misalignment before next quarter planning.</statement>
      <rationale>Investment misalignment — growth tactics in Decline, optimization tactics in Intro — is the primary source of wasted product budget at the portfolio level.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Plan Transitions">
    <rule>
      <statement>Pre-commit numeric transition triggers when entering Maturity, not when entering Decline: e.g., "if MRR YoY &lt; 0 for 3 consecutive quarters, automatic Decline review." Document in portfolio decisions log.</statement>
      <rationale>By the time Decline is obvious, the org has already over-invested for 2-4 quarters. Pre-committed thresholds remove the political delay.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat stage transitions as bidirectional. A Maturity product can re-enter Growth via a new segment, pricing tier, or 10x feature unlock. Always evaluate revival vs. sunset before committing to harvest mode.</statement>
      <rationale>Default-to-sunset is expensive when the underlying user need still exists. Re-platforming can recover Maturity-equivalent performance for 20% of new-product cost.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
