<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Lifecycle Stage Examples">
  <summary>Two concrete worked examples — a SaaS product in Growth and a legacy product in Decline — demonstrating stage-appropriate strategy selection and transition planning.</summary>

  <section title="SaaS Product in Growth">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Assessment: 40% YoY growth, just reached profitability, 3 new competitors entered the market in the last two quarters.</note>
      <note>Stage: Growth (confirmed by 2 independent signals: YoY growth &gt; 20% + improving profitability).</note>
      <note>Strategy: Accelerate customer acquisition, expand feature set for enterprise segment, build sales team, invest in infrastructure to support scale.</note>
      <note>Transition trigger: Growth slows to &lt; 15% YoY for two consecutive quarters — begin Maturity strategy shift (reduce acquisition %, increase retention %).</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Legacy Product in Decline">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Assessment: -10% YoY revenue, customers actively migrating to a newer platform, core technology becoming outdated.</note>
      <note>Stage: Decline (confirmed by 2 independent signals: negative YoY growth + customer migration evidence).</note>
      <note>Strategy: Maintain core functionality only, help customers migrate, reduce support costs, plan explicit sunset timeline of 18 months.</note>
      <note>End goal: Complete migration of all active users within 18 months; communicate sunset date 6 months in advance; wind down support contracts at sunset.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Same metrics tracked regardless of lifecycle stage.</description>
      <reason>Growth rate is the primary metric in Introduction and Growth but meaningless in Maturity (where profitability and churn matter more) and actively misleading in Decline.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Emotional attachment to a declining product preventing objective sunset decision.</description>
      <reason>Emotional attachment delays the inevitable, extends over-investment, and wastes capacity that could accelerate a Growth-stage product. Pre-committed numeric thresholds are the antidote.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>No sunset plan drafted until Decline is obvious.</description>
      <reason>Sunset planning requires 6-12 months of lead time for customer communication, contract wind-down, and team transition. Waiting until Decline is confirmed leaves insufficient runway.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
