<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="product-lifecycle Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for product-lifecycle as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying growth acquisition tactics to a Decline-stage product.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Acquisition spend compounds losses — acquired customers still generate support cost during the sunset window with no long-term LTV payback.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Refusing to declare Decline because the label is politically costly — lobbying for "late Maturity" indefinitely.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Delayed Decline classification extends over-investment; pre-commit numeric kill thresholds (e.g., "MRR YoY &lt; 0 for 3 quarters = automatic Decline review") to remove the political judgment call.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Using revenue YoY growth as the sole classification signal for network-effect or bundling products.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Network-effect products can show low revenue but high engagement (still Growth); bundling products can show stable revenue while the real value is migrating to a different SKU.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Same metrics tracked regardless of lifecycle stage.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Growth rate is the primary metric in Introduction and Growth but meaningless in Maturity (where profitability and churn matter more) and actively misleading in Decline.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Emotional attachment to a declining product preventing objective sunset decision.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Emotional attachment delays the inevitable, extends over-investment, and wastes capacity that could accelerate a Growth-stage product. Pre-committed numeric thresholds are the antidote.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>No sunset plan drafted until Decline is obvious.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Sunset planning requires 6-12 months of lead time for customer communication, contract wind-down, and team transition. Waiting until Decline is confirmed leaves insufficient runway.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
