<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-tuckman" title="Tuckman Team Development Stages">
  <summary>Five Tuckman stages with PM-action menus, diagnostic evidence patterns, and a stage-transition trigger rule.</summary>

  <section title="Stage Model">
    <rule>
      <statement>Re-run the Tuckman stage assessment after every team-composition change (hire, departure, reorg) — not on a calendar schedule.</statement>
      <rationale>Teams regress to Forming or Storming when key members change; calendar-based assessment misses the regression window where intervention has the highest return.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Forming">
    <p>Polite, cautious, high dependency on the PM for direction. Members focus on defining their role rather than executing work.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: provide explicit direction, clarify roles and responsibilities, set working agreements in writing</item>
      <item>Evidence signals: members ask permission for small decisions, few spontaneous collaborations, low conflict but also low velocity</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Storming">
    <p>Conflict, competition, and frustration surface. This is the highest-risk stage — teams can stay here for months without structured facilitation.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: facilitate structured discussion, mediate (meet separately first), focus conversation on shared goals not positions, document agreed decisions</item>
      <item>Evidence signals: heated retros, PR review comments with sharp tone, recurring same argument, velocity drop, attendance issues</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Document Storming-stage decisions in writing immediately; unrecorded verbal resolutions get re-litigated within two sprints.</statement>
      <rationale>Heated decisions feel resolved in the moment but lack shared memory; written record prevents the "we never agreed to that" pattern.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Norming">
    <p>Trust building, cooperation, shared processes forming. Team starts solving problems without PM involvement.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: delegate, support, encourage cross-team ownership, step back from day-to-day mediation</item>
      <item>Evidence signals: team resolves issues in standup without escalation, PR reviews are constructive, velocity stabilizes</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Performing">
    <p>High productivity, autonomy, self-organizing. PM focuses on removing systemic obstacles, not directing work.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: empower decisions, remove organizational blockers, protect from external interruptions, provide strategic context</item>
      <item>Evidence signals: team ships without PM in daily loop, retros produce non-trivial improvements, velocity at or above target</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Adjourning">
    <p>Project closure or team restructuring. Focus on knowledge capture and individual transition.</p>
    <list>
      <item>PM actions: celebrate accomplishments, facilitate knowledge transfer, document lessons learned, support individual transitions</item>
      <item>Evidence signals: project marked complete or team restructuring announced</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section title="Limitations">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Using Tuckman stage labels as an excuse for inaction ("we're just Storming, it will pass").</description>
      <reason>Storming does not self-resolve without facilitation; teams that skip active mediation can stay in Storming for months and lose key contributors.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Applying Tuckman to distributed async-only teams without adjustment.</description>
      <reason>The model assumes synchronous dynamics; async teams show attenuated stage signals and require additional indicators (response lag, async thread sentiment).</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
