<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-activities" title="Team Development Activities">
  <summary>Structured activities for trust building, skill development, and process improvement with evidence-backed practices and agent integration patterns.</summary>

  <section title="Trust Building">
    <list>
      <item>Regular 1-on-1s with explicit agenda (block 30 min weekly per direct report)</item>
      <item>Psychological safety — teams must be able to raise concerns without punishment</item>
      <item>Transparent communication — share context behind decisions, not just decisions</item>
      <item>Team-building activities tailored to team size and remote/in-person split</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Keep the team charter short (one screen) and treat it as a living document; review every 8-10 weeks or after any team-composition change.</statement>
      <rationale>Long charters are not read; short ones are consulted at conflicts. Staleness destroys trust in the document and by extension in the agreements it captures.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Skill Development">
    <list>
      <item>Skills matrix: rate each skill 1 (beginner) to 4 (expert); pair every "1" cell with a named owner and a quarterly improvement target</item>
      <item>Pair programming and cross-training for knowledge transfer across sole-owner skills</item>
      <item>Mentoring programs — internal, with explicit goals and check-in cadence</item>
      <item>Training opportunities — budget per-person per quarter, not per-year</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Skills-matrix scores must be evidence-backed (PRs, incidents, code reviews); self-reported scores without evidence drift toward inflation.</statement>
      <rationale>Inflated matrices mask critical knowledge gaps that surface at the worst moment — when the sole expert is unavailable during an incident.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Process Improvement">
    <list>
      <item>Retrospectives: every sprint; action items must have owner + due date + verification method in next retro</item>
      <item>Process experiments: time-boxed (one sprint), measured, documented as ADR if adopted</item>
      <item>Tool optimization: quarterly review; only add tooling that removes friction, not adds ceremony</item>
      <item>Workload balancing: use contribution data (git shortlog, PR review counts) to surface imbalances</item>
    </list>
    <rule>
      <statement>Retro action items without an owner and verification method are not action items — they are wishes.</statement>
      <rationale>Unowned actions do not get done; unverified actions get closed as done regardless of outcome; both undermine retro trust over time.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Mistakes">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping team building because "there's no time."</description>
      <reason>Dysfunction deferred costs more time than investment avoided; unresolved Storming can freeze a team for months.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>One-size-fits-all management style across all team members.</description>
      <reason>Different Tuckman stages and different experience levels require different leadership approaches; uniform style over-manages high performers and under-supports strugglers.</reason>
    </antipattern>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Blaming individuals for systemic failures.</description>
      <reason>Individual blame destroys psychological safety and repeats the failure; root cause is almost always process, tooling, or system design.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/team-charter.md">Team charter with mission, members, working agreements, and meeting cadence</reference>
  <reference path="templates/skills-matrix.md">Skills matrix template with 1-4 scale and gap-action column</reference>
  <reference path="templates/retro.md">Retrospective template with owner and due fields on all action items</reference>
</text>
