<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-examples" title="Team Development Worked Examples">
  <summary>Two worked examples: navigating Storming-stage conflict and first-hire integration for a solo-to-team transition.</summary>

  <section title="Example 1: Navigating Storming Stage">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Situation: two developers in architectural disagreement that is slowing the team and heating meetings.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Symptoms observed:
- Developer A and Developer B argue about microservice vs. monolith in every planning meeting
- Retrospective atmosphere is tense; others are silent
- Sprint velocity dropped 30% over 3 sprints
- Both devs are updating architecture docs independently

PM actions (in order):
1. Meet individually with A and B — understand each person's technical concern and personal stake
2. Facilitate a structured session with explicit ground rules: one speaker, no interruptions, timer
3. Frame the discussion as "what does the system need?" not "who is right?"
4. Document the agreed-upon architectural decision as an ADR within 24 hours
5. Share ADR with full team; name the decision-maker if no consensus

Week 3 follow-up:
- Both devs cite ADR in code reviews instead of re-litigating
- Retro tone returns to constructive
- Velocity recovers to baseline
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Example 2: Solo-to-Team Transition">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Situation: solo founder hiring first team member; no existing process documentation.</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Before hire arrives:
- Write down every implicit process (deployment, code review, naming conventions)
- Create a "how we work" document (2 pages max)
- Set up repo access, Slack, 1password, and dev environment guide

Week 1: Orientation
- Walk through codebase together; explain architectural decisions
- Shadow founder for 2 days: observe how decisions get made
- Define initial responsibilities in writing

Weeks 2-4: Gradual Ownership
- Pair on first 3 features; founder drives, new hire navigates
- Swap: new hire drives, founder reviews + explains
- Give feedback within 24 hours of PR submission
- Weekly 1-on-1: what's unclear? what would help?

Month 2: Independence
- Assign a feature with clear acceptance criteria; no pairing
- Check in at midpoint, not daily
- Ask new hire to document one process they think is unclear
- Celebrate first solo ship in team channel

Key: document everything before hire arrives; verbal-only onboarding creates dependency on the founder and slows the transition to independence.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Skills Matrix Update from Git Data">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Use git history to provide evidence-backed initial scores for a skills matrix.</note>
      <code lang="bash"><![CDATA[
# Infer expertise per directory from git contribution history (last 180 days)
since="180 days ago"
for dir in $(git ls-tree -d --name-only HEAD); do
  echo "## $dir"
  git log --since="$since" --pretty=format:'%an' -- "$dir" \
    | sort | uniq -c | sort -rn | head -5
  echo
done
]]></code>
      <note>Use output as starting evidence; do not auto-populate scores without human review.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <reference path="templates/team-charter.md">Team charter template for the onboarding examples above</reference>
  <reference path="templates/skills-matrix.md">Skills matrix with 1-4 scale and gap-action column</reference>
</text>
