<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="team-development Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for team-development as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Using Tuckman stage labels as an excuse for inaction ("we're just Storming, it will pass").</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Storming does not self-resolve without facilitation; teams that skip active mediation can stay in Storming for months and lose key contributors.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Applying Tuckman to distributed async-only teams without adjustment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>The model assumes synchronous dynamics; async teams show attenuated stage signals and require additional indicators (response lag, async thread sentiment).</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping team building because "there's no time."</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Dysfunction deferred costs more time than investment avoided; unresolved Storming can freeze a team for months.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>One-size-fits-all management style across all team members.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Different Tuckman stages and different experience levels require different leadership approaches; uniform style over-manages high performers and under-supports strugglers.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Blaming individuals for systemic failures.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Individual blame destroys psychological safety and repeats the failure; root cause is almost always process, tooling, or system design.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>LLMs over-pattern-match Tuckman labels without evidence.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Require evidence quotes in the diagnosis prompt to avoid false classifications.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Letting an agent auto-publish a retro without human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Humans must redact attribution and tone before sharing.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents writing 1-on-1 notes verbatim into shared docs.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Privacy boundary violation; separate personal feedback from team-level insights.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-09" severity="medium">
      <description>Agents generating a generic charter instead of citing team incidents.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Force them to cite the team's actual incidents and patterns to ground the charter in reality.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-10" severity="medium">
      <description>Skills-matrix scoring by an agent without evidence backing.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Must be tied to PRs, incidents, or code reviews; hallucinated scores hide critical gaps.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
