<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-cold-outreach">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>gtm-strategist</domain>
    <summary>Convert strangers to customers via targeted cold email and LinkedIn: build prospect list, personalize, keep emails short, follow up 4-5 times. Requires deliverability infrastructure.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>cold-email</tag>
      <tag>outreach</tag>
      <tag>sales</tag>
      <tag>b2b</tag>
      <tag>lead-generation</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>Cold Outreach</title>

    <summary>A structured approach for converting strangers into customers via targeted cold email and LinkedIn: build a focused prospect list, personalize using research, keep emails under 5 sentences, and follow up 4–5 times. Deliverability infrastructure (separate domain, SPF/DKIM/DMARC, warm-up) is a prerequisite — without it, emails never reach the inbox. Inbound marketing takes months; cold outreach can produce customers this week.</summary>

    <why>
      <p>Inbound marketing takes months; cold outreach can produce customers this week. Done right it outperforms paid ads on a cost-per-meeting basis at early stage. The mechanism: tight ICP targeting reduces wasted effort, personalization improves open and reply rates, and systematic follow-up captures the 80% of replies that come after the first message.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Zero or small audience; need customers before inbound scales</item>
        <item>Targeting a specific niche (role + industry + company size) where lists are buildable</item>
        <item>B2B products or services where individual decision-makers can be identified</item>
        <item>Outreach to potential partners, collaborators, or press</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>B2C consumer products — cold outreach doesn't scale to consumer segments</item>
        <item>Regulated industries with anti-spam laws that prohibit unsolicited commercial email (check GDPR, CAN-SPAM, CASL for jurisdiction)</item>
        <item>Low-ACV products where the CAC of manual outreach exceeds LTV</item>
        <item>When deliverability infrastructure is not set up — sending from primary domain risks blacklisting</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="ideal-prospect-criteria">
      <p>Sending to unqualified prospects wastes send quota and damages domain reputation. A tight 100-prospect list outperforms a bloated 1,000-prospect list on every metric. High volume with an unproven sequence burns deliverability reputation. Validate messaging at low volume first, then automate scale.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Qualify every prospect on five criteria before adding to the list: Pain (has the problem you solve), Budget (can afford), Authority (can decide), Timing (current priority), Reach (contact info obtainable).</statement>
        <rationale>Sending to unqualified prospects wastes send quota and damages domain reputation. A tight 100-prospect list outperforms a bloated 1,000-prospect list on every metric.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Start with 100–200 highly targeted prospects, not thousands. Scale volume only after validating a sequence that achieves 10%+ reply rate.</statement>
        <rationale>High volume with an unproven sequence burns deliverability reputation. Validate messaging at low volume first, then automate scale.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="prospect-sources">
      <list>
        <item>LinkedIn Sales Navigator — B2B, specific roles and industries. Filter by company size, title, and geography</item>
        <item>Industry lists (Clutch, G2, Product Hunt) — curated niches, often with direct contact context</item>
        <item>Job boards (LinkedIn Jobs, Indeed) — companies hiring for a specific role reveal that the function exists and has budget</item>
        <item>Trigger events (Crunchbase, news) — recent funding, new CTO hire, product launch create natural outreach hooks</item>
        <item>Competitive displacement (BuiltWith, G2 reviews) — competitors' customers who have pain points with current solution</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="personalization-levels">
      <p>Deep personalization at low ACV produces negative ROI — the research time exceeds the customer value. Batch personalization at high ACV signals you haven't done homework and reduces reply rate by 50%+.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Choose personalization level based on deal size: Batch (30 sec, company name only) for under $500 ACV; Light (2 min, recent news or post) for $500–5K ACV; Deep (10 min, specific pain from research) for $5K+ ACV.</statement>
        <rationale>Deep personalization at low ACV produces negative ROI — the research time exceeds the customer value. Batch personalization at high ACV signals you haven't done homework and reduces reply rate by 50%+.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="research-sources-per-prospect">
      <list>
        <item>LinkedIn profile and recent posts — current priorities, recent achievements, interests</item>
        <item>Company blog and news — recent product launches, partnerships, pain points mentioned</item>
        <item>Twitter/X activity — opinions, frustrations, topic engagement</item>
        <item>Job postings — reveals what's being built, what's broken, what skills are missing</item>
        <item>Podcast appearances — deep interview content; quote their exact words back</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="email-anatomy">
      <p>Longer emails have lower read rates. Prospects decide in 3 seconds whether to read or delete. Every extra sentence is a reason to stop reading.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Keep the entire cold email to 5 sentences or fewer: subject (4–6 words), personalized opening (1–2 sentences), value prop (2–3 sentences), CTA (1 sentence). No company history, no feature lists.</statement>
        <rationale>Longer emails have lower read rates. Prospects decide in 3 seconds whether to read or delete. Every extra sentence is a reason to stop reading.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="subject-line-formulas">
      <list>
        <item>"Quick question about [topic]" — curiosity, low commitment</item>
        <item>"Idea for [Company]" — specific, implies value</item>
        <item>"[Their recent achievement]" — personalization shows research</item>
        <item>"[Mutual connection] suggested I reach out" — social proof, warm bridge</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="opening-formulas">
      <example type="good" title="Observation-based opening that shows specific research">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Saw your post about [topic] - the point about [specific detail] resonated.
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Trigger-based opening tied to a recent event">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Congrats on the Series A! With 20 new hires coming, [challenge] becomes real fast.
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Generic opener with no personalization — goes straight to spam mentally">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Hope this email finds you well. I'm reaching out because...
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="follow-up-cadence">
      <p>Cold outreach data consistently shows that 5+ touchpoints are required for most replies. Single-email campaigns leave the majority of potential responses on the table.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Send a 5-email sequence: initial (Day 0), bump (Day 3), new angle (Day 7), case study (Day 14), break-up (Day 21). Do not stop after the first email — 80% of replies come from follow-ups.</statement>
        <rationale>Cold outreach data consistently shows that 5+ touchpoints are required for most replies. Single-email campaigns leave the majority of potential responses on the table.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Break-up email (Day 21): signals respect for their time, leaves door open, generates not now but later replies">
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Subject: Re: [Original subject]

I'll assume this isn't a priority right now.

If things change, feel free to reach out. Happy to help when timing is better.

[Name]
]]></code>
      </example>

      <templates>
        <template path="templates/cold-email.txt" purpose="Cold email template with subject, personalized opening, value prop, CTA"/>
        <template path="templates/linkedin-outreach.txt" purpose="Connection request + follow-up message pair"/>
      </templates>
    </section>

    <section name="deliverability-requirements">
      <p>If cold outreach domain gets blacklisted, primary domain email remains unaffected. Missing SPF/DKIM causes 20–40% of emails to land in spam regardless of content quality. High daily volume from a new inbox triggers spam filters. Bounce rate above 3% degrades sender score rapidly and can trigger blacklisting within days.</p>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Never send cold outreach from your primary domain. Use a separate domain (e.g., tryproduct.com vs product.com). Warm it up for 2–4 weeks before sending at scale. Configure SPF, DKIM, and DMARC before first send.</statement>
        <rationale>If cold outreach domain gets blacklisted, primary domain email remains unaffected. Missing SPF/DKIM causes 20–40% of emails to land in spam regardless of content quality.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <rule testable="true">
        <statement>Send fewer than 50 emails/day per inbox when starting. Increase by 10–20/day each week. Use email verification (NeverBounce, ZeroBounce) to keep bounce rate below 2%.</statement>
        <rationale>High daily volume from a new inbox triggers spam filters. Bounce rate above 3% degrades sender score rapidly and can trigger blacklisting within days.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <section name="metrics-benchmarks">
      <list>
        <item>Delivery rate: good 95%+, great 99%+. Below 90% means deliverability problem — stop and fix infrastructure before continuing</item>
        <item>Open rate: good 40%+, great 60%+. Below 30% means subject lines or sender name need work</item>
        <item>Reply rate: good 10%+, great 25%+. Below 5% means personalization or value prop is not landing</item>
        <item>Meeting booked rate: good 3%+, great 10%+. The final metric that matters</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="real-campaign-examples">
      <example type="good" title="SaaS outreach to marketing managers at e-commerce companies">
        <note>500 prospects, personalized on recent company news.</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
List: 500 prospects (LinkedIn Sales Nav)
Personalization: Light (company news + pain signal)
Sequence: 5 emails over 3 weeks

Results:
  Open rate: 45%
  Reply rate: 12%
  Meeting rate: 3%
  Customers acquired: 5 ($25K ARR)
]]></code>
      </example>

      <example type="good" title="Consulting services outreach to CTOs at Series A startups">
        <note>200 prospects, trigger-based (recent funding).</note>
        <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
List: 200 prospects (Crunchbase)
Trigger: Funding announcements
Personalization: Deep (5 min/email)

Results:
  Open rate: 60%
  Reply rate: 25%
  Meeting rate: 10%
  Clients acquired: 3 ($15K each = $45K)
]]></code>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section name="common-mistakes">
      <antipattern>
        <description>No personalization — sending the same template to everyone.</description>
        <reason>Reads as spam. Personalization is what distinguishes cold outreach from email blasts. Even batch-level personalization (company name, industry) improves open rates by 20–30%.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Sending from primary domain without warmup.</description>
        <reason>A single spam complaint can blacklist the primary domain, breaking all transactional email (receipts, notifications, support replies).</reason>
      </antipattern>
    </section>

    <checklist>
      <check>ICP defined: role, industry, company size, budget tier</check>
      <check>100-200 prospects identified from at least two sources</check>
      <check>Separate outreach domain registered (not primary business domain)</check>
      <check>SPF, DKIM, DMARC records configured for outreach domain</check>
      <check>Warmup scheduled for 2-4 weeks before full-volume launch</check>
      <check>Email templates drafted: subject line, opening, body formula, CTA</check>
      <check>5-email sequence defined with clear differentiation per email</check>
      <check>Personalization hooks identified for each prospect (news, trigger, pain)</check>
      <check>Email verification service (NeverBounce, ZeroBounce) integrated</check>
      <check>Sending platform configured (Instantly, Smartlead, or Apollo)</check>
      <check>A/B test design: 2-3 subject line variants, 2 copy variants minimum</check>
      <check>Sample of 10-20% drafts reviewed by human before sending</check>
      <check>Tracking configured: open, reply, click, calendar booking</check>
      <check>CRM or spreadsheet for prospect follow-up status</check>
      <check>GDPR/CAN-SPAM compliance reviewed for target jurisdictions</check>
    </checklist>

    <section name="best-practices-summary">
      <p>Never send cold email from your primary business domain — use a separate domain (e.g., [yourname]-hq.com) with proper SPF/DKIM/DMARC to protect deliverability of your main domain. Start at 20 emails/day per inbox and ramp by 10/day each week; never jump to 50+/day on a new domain without 3+ weeks of warmup. Write every email as if you are sending it to one person — mass-sounding copy gets low reply rates regardless of personalization tokens. Trigger events (funding round, new hire, product launch, leadership change) multiply reply rates; invest in enrichment to find them per prospect. Track positive reply rate (not just open rate) as the primary KPI — open rate is inflated by Apple Mail Privacy Protection and bot opens. Build a "not interested" suppression list and honor it permanently; re-contacting opted-out prospects is CAN-SPAM/GDPR violation territory.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="agent-gotchas-and-validation">
      <p>Agents may generate emails that are too long for the format (greater than 5 sentences); enforce length limits explicitly in the system prompt. Personalization hooks hallucinated from vague trigger_signal data (e.g., "recent activity") produce obviously fake opening lines that destroy credibility — require the agent to flag missing or ambiguous trigger data instead of inventing context. GDPR compliance: agents must include unsubscribe mechanism language in every email draft; this is non-negotiable for EU prospects. Subject line generation is highly task-specific; validate against real A/B data from your niche — what works for SaaS may fail for consulting. Human-in-loop checkpoint: review 10-20% of drafted sequences before loading into sending tool; spot-check for tone, accuracy, and compliance. Agents should not configure sending infrastructure (Instantly campaigns, inbox rotation, warmup settings) — these require understanding of current domain reputation state that agents cannot assess without live data.</p>
    </section>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://instantly.ai/blog/cold-email-guide"/>
      <link href="https://apolloio.github.io/apollo-api-docs/"/>
      <link href="https://www.zerobounce.net/email-deliverability/"/>
      <link href="https://reply.io/resources/"/>
      <link href="https://developer.instantly.ai"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
