<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-process" title="Release Planning Process">
  <summary>Six-step process for planning, executing, and following up on a software release.</summary>

  <section title="Release Types">
    <p>Major releases are quarterly, cover large features and breaking changes, and carry high risk. Minor releases are monthly, add new features and improvements, and carry medium risk. Patch releases are weekly or as needed, fix bugs and security issues, and carry low risk. Hotfixes are immediate, address critical production issues, and carry very low risk.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 1: Define Release Goal">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every release must have a stated outcome for users, a success metric, and an optional theme. Template: "Release [Version]. Goal: [Primary outcome]. Success Metric: [How we measure]. Theme: [Optional narrative]."</statement>
      <rationale>Without a goal, a release is just a list of changes. The goal connects the release to product strategy and makes post-release retrospectives meaningful.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 2: Select Release Contents">
    <rule>
      <statement>Include: completed features at definition of done, related bug fixes, documentation updates, configuration changes. Exclude: half-finished features, unrelated bug fixes (next release), scope creep added after freeze.</statement>
      <rationale>Half-finished features create technical debt and confuse users. Scope creep added after freeze is the top cause of delayed and broken releases.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 3: Assess Release Readiness">
    <rule>
      <statement>All seven readiness items must pass before deployment: code complete, tests passing, documentation updated, migrations tested, rollback plan exists, support team briefed, release notes written.</statement>
      <rationale>Missing any one item creates a predictable class of post-release incidents. Rollback plan especially: without it, every incident response starts with a debate instead of an action.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 4: Plan Communication">
    <rule>
      <statement>Identify all audiences (internal team, support, sales, customers, partners) and prepare each asset: release notes, blog post or changelog, customer email, social media, in-app notifications. Announce every release — even small patches.</statement>
      <rationale>Silent releases frustrate customers who noticed a change and can't find context. Support volume spikes when communication is missing.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 5: Execute Release">
    <rule>
      <statement>Execute in order: final staging test, maintenance window announcement if needed, production deploy, deployment verification, metrics monitoring, public release announcement.</statement>
      <rationale>Order matters. Announcing before verifying deployment creates a second announcement ("actually it's delayed") that erodes trust.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Step 6: Post-Release">
    <rule>
      <statement>Monitor for 24 hours post-release. Gather user feedback. Run a retrospective. Update the roadmap based on what you learned.</statement>
      <rationale>Issues spike in the first 24 hours. Early monitoring contains blast radius. The retrospective closes the learning loop that makes future releases better.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
