<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-antipatterns" title="Release Planning Antipatterns">
  <summary>Seven common release planning mistakes with concrete fixes.</summary>

  <section title="Antipatterns">
    <antipattern>
      <description>Shipping on Fridays.</description>
      <reason>Weekend incidents have slower response. Engineering and support have reduced coverage. A Monday–Wednesday release window keeps the full team available for the critical 24-hour monitoring window.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>No rollback plan.</description>
      <reason>Every release should have a one-click or one-command rollback path. Without it, incident response time multiplies and pressure leads to poor decisions under stress.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Last-minute feature additions after the feature freeze.</description>
      <reason>Late additions skip testing and break the readiness checklist. Institute a 24–48 hour feature freeze before every release.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping communication because the release is "just a patch".</description>
      <reason>Users and support staff notice changes regardless of size. Silent releases generate confused support tickets. Always publish a changelog entry.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Skipping staging deployment.</description>
      <reason>Staging catches integration issues that unit tests miss. A staging deploy is mandatory for any release that touches data migrations or third-party integrations.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>No monitoring after release.</description>
      <reason>Error rates, latency, and conversion metrics can degrade subtly after a release. Watch metrics for at least 24 hours before declaring success.</reason>
    </antipattern>

    <antipattern>
      <description>Monster releases bundling months of features.</description>
      <reason>Large releases have higher risk, harder rollbacks, and diluted communication impact. Smaller, more frequent releases reduce blast radius and keep users engaged with steady progress.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>
</text>
