<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="release-planning Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for release-planning as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Shipping on Fridays.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Weekend on-call has reduced coverage and slower mean-time-to-restore. A Monday-Wednesday production window keeps the full team available for the critical 24-hour monitoring period.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>No rollback plan.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every release must have a one-command rollback path that has been dry-run on staging. Without it, incident response time multiplies and pressure leads to poor decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Last-minute feature additions after the freeze.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Late additions skip the readiness checklist and break the test baseline. Enforce a 24-48 hour code freeze before every release; later changes go to the next release.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping communication because the release is "just a patch".</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Users and support staff notice changes regardless of size. Silent releases generate confused tickets. Always publish at least a CHANGELOG entry and an in-app changelog link.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Skipping staging deployment.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Staging catches integration issues that unit tests miss. Mandatory for any release touching data migrations, third-party integrations, or infrastructure.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>No monitoring after release.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Error rate, latency, and conversion metrics can degrade subtly after a release. Watch for at least 24 hours before declaring success and updating the status page.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Monster releases bundling months of features.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Large releases have higher risk, harder rollbacks, and diluted communication impact. Smaller, more frequent releases reduce blast radius and keep users engaged with steady visible progress.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-08" severity="medium">
      <description>Announcing before verifying production deploy.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>A premature announcement followed by a delay or rollback erodes trust faster than any feature can rebuild it. Verify smoke + 30 minutes of clean metrics before publishing the announcement.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
