<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="ops-contractor-management Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for ops-contractor-management. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Deliver a complete onboarding document before the contractor starts the first task. The onboarding kit must include: business context, role description, tool list with access, working norms, quality standards with examples, and a communication guide.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Front-loading documentation pays back within the first deliverable cycle. Contractors who understand context produce work that requires fewer revision rounds. Without examples of quality standards, the contractor defaults to their own standards, which may not match yours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Use async-first communication (Slack threads, Loom) for daily updates and blockers. Reserve synchronous calls for ambiguous problems only. Set explicit response-time expectations in the onboarding document.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Requiring instant responses creates artificial urgency and degrades contractor autonomy. Async-first respects timezone differences and produces a documented record. Sync calls for ambiguous problems avoid the back-and-forth that inflates async threads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Do not micromanage. Provide goal, context, deliverable, deadline, and reference material. Do not specify process steps unless the contractor requests guidance.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Micromanagement signals distrust, reduces initiative, and creates employee-classification risk in jurisdictions that weigh behavioral control heavily in contractor tests.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task assignment must include: goal (outcome, not steps), context (why this matters, current baseline), deliverable (specific output format), deadline (realistic date), and reference (example of good work).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Tasks specified by deliverable rather than process give contractors creative latitude while maintaining outcome accountability. Without context, contractors optimize for effort instead of outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Give all feedback using the SBI-R format: Situation (what context), Behavior (what they did), Impact (measurable effect), Request (what to do differently). Log feedback the same week the behavior occurs — SBI loses signal at one-month delay.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Generic feedback ("the quality was low") does not change behavior because it does not identify the specific action to change. SBI-R connects a specific observable behavior to a measurable outcome, making the causal link actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Run a structured monthly review even when nothing is wrong. Rate the contractor on five areas (quality 1–5, communication 1–5, reliability 1–5, speed 1–5, proactiveness 1–5), document highlights and improvement areas, and make an explicit decision: continue, adjust scope/rate, or end engagement.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Small frictions surface only when prompted. An informal "things seem fine" assessment misses gradual drift in quality, communication delays, or changes in availability that compound over quarters. An explicit decision prevents engagement inertia.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Maintain a "contractor onboarding kit" repo (Notion or git) that ships intact to every new contractor — versioned, reviewed quarterly.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">A versioned onboarding kit ensures consistency across contractors and reduces ramp-up time. It also forces documentation discipline that prevents institutional knowledge from existing only in the manager's head.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
