<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-onboarding-and-rhythm" title="Contractor Onboarding and Communication Rhythm">
  <summary>Front-loading documentation and setting an async communication cadence to prevent silent quality drift from the first day.</summary>

  <section title="Onboarding">
    <rule>
      <statement>Deliver a complete onboarding document before the contractor starts the first task. The onboarding kit must include: business context, role description, tool list with access, working norms, quality standards with examples, and a communication guide.</statement>
      <rationale>Front-loading documentation pays back within the first deliverable cycle. Contractors who understand context produce work that requires fewer revision rounds. Without examples of quality standards, the contractor defaults to their own standards, which may not match yours.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/onboarding-doc.md">Contractor onboarding document template with all required sections</reference>
    <p>Onboarding checklist: send welcome message, provision tool access, share documentation, assign a first task that is smaller than normal scope (a win builds confidence), schedule first check-in within the first week.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Communication Rhythm">
    <rule>
      <statement>Use async-first communication (Slack threads, Loom) for daily updates and blockers. Reserve synchronous calls for ambiguous problems only. Set explicit response-time expectations in the onboarding document.</statement>
      <rationale>Requiring instant responses creates artificial urgency and degrades contractor autonomy. Async-first respects timezone differences and produces a documented record. Sync calls for ambiguous problems avoid the back-and-forth that inflates async threads.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <p>Communication cadence: daily async updates (Slack, brief), weekly check-in (call or video for planning and review), monthly performance review (structured evaluation with rating rubric).</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Do not micromanage. Provide goal, context, deliverable, deadline, and reference material. Do not specify process steps unless the contractor requests guidance.</statement>
      <rationale>Micromanagement signals distrust, reduces initiative, and creates employee-classification risk in jurisdictions that weigh behavioral control heavily in contractor tests.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <reference path="templates/weekly-checkin.md">Weekly check-in template: completed tasks, in-progress, blockers, next week, hours</reference>
  </section>
</text>
