<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-tasks-and-feedback" title="Task Assignment and Structured Feedback">
  <summary>Writing tasks that produce the right output the first time, and giving SBI-R feedback that changes behavior.</summary>

  <section title="Task Assignment">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task assignment must include: goal (outcome, not steps), context (why this matters, current baseline), deliverable (specific output format), deadline (realistic date), and reference (example of good work).</statement>
      <rationale>Tasks specified by deliverable rather than process give contractors creative latitude while maintaining outcome accountability. Without context, contractors optimize for effort instead of outcome.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Task: Redesign pricing page. Goal: increase conversions by 20%. Context: current page has 2% conversion, competitors average 4%. Deliverable: Figma design + rationale document. Deadline: Friday, Jan 26. Reference: [link to competitor examples]. This gives outcome, baseline, format, date, and reference — no process specified.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Task: "Make the pricing page better." No goal, no baseline, no deliverable format, no deadline, no reference. The contractor will produce whatever "better" means to them.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Feedback Framework">
    <rule>
      <statement>Give all feedback using the SBI-R format: Situation (what context), Behavior (what they did), Impact (measurable effect), Request (what to do differently). Log feedback the same week the behavior occurs — SBI loses signal at one-month delay.</statement>
      <rationale>Generic feedback ("the quality was low") does not change behavior because it does not identify the specific action to change. SBI-R connects a specific observable behavior to a measurable outcome, making the causal link actionable.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Positive SBI-R: Situation: yesterday's blog post. Behavior: you added data visualization and internal links. Impact: increased time-on-page by 40% and shares by 3x. Request: keep using this approach for future posts. Amplifies a specific behavior tied to measured outcomes.</note>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Constructive SBI-R: Situation: last week's email campaign. Behavior: subject line was generic ("Newsletter #5"). Impact: open rate dropped to 12% versus usual 25%. Request: use specific, benefit-focused subject lines — see linked examples. Identifies the specific behavior and provides a redirect.</note>
    </example>
    <antipattern>
      <description>Giving feedback at monthly cadence instead of same-week.</description>
      <reason>Behavioral connection weakens beyond one week. Contractors cannot recall the specific micro-decision that produced the outcome; feedback becomes abstract criticism.</reason>
    </antipattern>
  </section>

  <section title="Common Issues">
    <p>Root causes and fixes: slow delivery (unclear priorities — set deadlines and rank tasks), quality problems (misaligned expectations — provide examples and explicit standards), communication gaps (timezone mismatch — set overlap hours and async tools), scope creep (undefined boundaries — define deliverables upfront in writing), inconsistent work (no documented process — document standards and create checklists for recurring deliverables).</p>
  </section>
</text>
