<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="ops-contractor-management Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for ops-contractor-management as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Giving feedback at monthly cadence instead of same-week.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Behavioral connection weakens beyond one week. Contractors cannot recall the specific micro-decision that produced the outcome; feedback becomes abstract criticism.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>LLM-generated feedback drifts toward mealy-mouthed praise without specific behavior + measurable impact.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Agents default to positive framing. Force SBI structure and require at least one concrete behavior + one measurable outcome in every feedback block.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent over-trusts time-tracker self-reports without cross-checking against PR/commit/asset volume.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Time tracking is vulnerable to gaming. Before passing hours to evaluation, cross-check reported time against verifiable output volume.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent digests Slack history and flattens sarcasm and friction signals.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Any thread with more than 5 back-and-forth messages indicates friction that requires human reading, not summarization.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent auto-paying invoices or auto-approving payment without human review.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Cross-border payments on disputed work are hard to claw back. Each invoice requires explicit human approval against the SOW.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-06" severity="medium">
      <description>Agent pulling Slack or Notion into LLM context without redaction of customer data.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Status threads frequently reference customer names, deal sizes, or support issues. Use a redaction step before any external-API LLM call.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-07" severity="medium">
      <description>Auto-generated SOW addenda re-introducing default IP/confidentiality clauses that conflict with the master agreement.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Always diff any agent-generated addendum against the signed master agreement before sending.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
