<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-privacy-principles" title="VUI Privacy Principles and Trust Indicators">
  <summary>Five privacy principles for voice products and mandatory trust indicators that give users visible control over voice data collection.</summary>

  <section title="Five Privacy Principles">
    <rule>
      <statement>Disclose what voice data is collected, how it is used, and for how long — before the user first speaks, not buried in terms.</statement>
      <rationale>Transparency is both a regulatory requirement (GDPR Art. 13) and a user trust baseline; late disclosure causes opt-out and product abandonment.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Collect only the audio and transcript data necessary for the immediate task; do not retain raw audio for analytics by default.</statement>
      <rationale>Data minimization reduces regulatory exposure and breach impact; users are more willing to use voice features when they know data is not persisted indefinitely.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Encrypt all voice data at rest and in transit; use envelope encryption with per-device keys for recordings.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice recordings are biometric-adjacent data; a breach without encryption exposes users to identification and voice-cloning attacks.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Provide a user-accessible voice history view backed by a separate auditable store; agents must fetch it, never reconstruct or summarize from LLM context.</statement>
      <rationale>If the agent can summarize history from context, it can hallucinate it; a separate store ensures accuracy and supports GDPR/CCPA right-of-access requests.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Implement a hard-delete endpoint for voice history that removes raw audio, transcripts, and derived embeddings; confirm deletion to the user.</statement>
      <rationale>GDPR Art. 17 right to erasure applies to voice data; embeddings derived from voice are biometric data with a separate retention clock.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Trust Indicators">
    <rule>
      <statement>Show a visual indicator (LED ring or on-screen icon) whenever the microphone is active; provide an audio confirmation when it stops.</statement>
      <rationale>Users cannot see whether a microphone is active; a visual/audio indicator is the primary signal that gives users confidence they are not being recorded covertly.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Make the "stop listening" command work without a wake word and without TTS acknowledgement; provide a silent, immediate kill switch.</statement>
      <rationale>A stop command that requires hearing the wake word first defeats its purpose; users in sensitive situations need an immediate, unconditional off switch.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Sensitive Operation Patterns">
    <rule>
      <statement>For banking, health, and personal data operations: require step-up authentication, mask spoken sensitive values, and confirm before executing.</statement>
      <rationale>Voice is inherently ambient; a second channel (push notification or SMS) that must be acknowledged prevents voice-spoofing attacks from completing high-stakes actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <statement>Treat voice biometric IDs as biometric data under GDPR/CCPA — separate consent, separate retention clock, separate deletion API.</statement>
      <rationale>Biometric data has heightened regulatory protection; co-mingling it with regular user data risks using the wrong retention period and deletion scope.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
