<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<methodology slug="growth-youtube-strategy">
  <metadata>
    <tier>solo</tier>
    <group>marketing</group>
    <domain>content-marketer</domain>
    <summary>Build a YouTube channel with niche positioning, searchable formats, hook-first structure, and sustainable cadence. Optimize search-intent videos first (tutorials, how-to) before discovery content.</summary>
    <tags>
      <tag>youtube</tag>
      <tag>video-content</tag>
      <tag>search-traffic</tag>
      <tag>content-marketing</tag>
      <tag>publishing-cadence</tag>
    </tags>
    <difficulty>intermediate</difficulty>
    <created>2026-04-26</created>
  </metadata>

  <content>
    <title>YouTube Strategy</title>

    <summary>A content-discovery loop for building a YouTube channel around a product or personal brand: niche positioning, searchable video formats, hook-first structure, thumbnail + title optimization, and a sustainable publishing cadence. The core rule: optimize for search intent videos first (tutorials, how-to) before attempting discovery content (opinion, commentary).</summary>

    <why>
      <p>YouTube is the second-largest search engine and the highest-trust platform for demonstrating expertise. Early focus on searchable, long-form tutorials compounds — each video generates traffic for years. Most channels fail because they prioritize production quality over consistency and search intent.</p>
    </why>

    <when-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>Building a content marketing channel around a technical or educational product.</item>
        <item>Generating search-driven top-of-funnel awareness where blog SEO is too competitive.</item>
        <item>Repurposing existing written content (blog posts, docs) into video format.</item>
        <item>Adding a YouTube component to an existing content distribution stack.</item>
        <item>Brand authority building for a solopreneur or technical founder.</item>
      </list>
    </when-to-use>

    <when-not-to-use>
      <list>
        <item>No defined niche or ICP — generalist channels rarely grow; algorithm rewards niche focus.</item>
        <item>No commitment to at least 2 videos/month for 6+ months — YouTube is compounding, not quick.</item>
        <item>Audience is not on YouTube (e.g., B2B enterprise compliance buyers).</item>
        <item>Production bottleneck is unresolved — inconsistency kills momentum faster than poor quality.</item>
      </list>
    </when-not-to-use>

    <section name="niche-and-formats">
      <p>Niche formula, validation criteria, content pillars, and video format selection by goal.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Define the channel niche as: [Your expertise] + [Specific audience] + [Content format]. Validate all three axes before publishing.</statement>
        <rationale>YouTube's algorithm rewards consistent niche signals. Generalist channels struggle to build a loyal subscriber base because the algorithm cannot identify who to recommend the channel to.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Niche definition example">
        <note>SaaS marketing + indie founders + tutorials and case studies. Specific expertise, identifiable audience, consistent format.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Generalist niche">
        <note>Marketing tips for everyone. No expertise specificity, no audience definition, no format constraint — the algorithm has no signal to optimize.</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Validate a niche on four dimensions before committing: demand, differentiation, sustainability (100+ video ideas), and monetization path.</statement>
        <rationale>A niche with demand but no monetization path produces views without revenue. A niche with a product but no demand produces content nobody watches.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Demand: are people actively searching for this on YouTube?</item>
        <item>Competition: can you differentiate from existing channels in this niche?</item>
        <item>Sustainability: can you generate 100+ video ideas without forcing it?</item>
        <item>Monetization: is there a product, service, or course to sell to this audience?</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Choose 3-4 content pillars and map every video to at least one pillar. Do not publish videos outside the pillars.</statement>
        <rationale>Pillar discipline maintains the algorithm signal and subscriber expectations. Off-pillar videos fragment the audience and reduce subscriber conversion rate.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Educational: how-to, tutorials, explainers.</item>
        <item>Entertainment: stories, commentary, opinion.</item>
        <item>Inspiration: case studies, interviews, build-in-public.</item>
        <item>Updates: news, trends, product announcements.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Prioritize search-intent formats (tutorials, list videos) during the first 6-12 months. Switch to discovery formats (opinion, commentary) only after establishing a subscriber base.</statement>
        <rationale>Search-intent videos rank for queries indefinitely, compounding traffic. Discovery content depends on algorithmic push, which requires watch-time history to earn.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Tutorials (10-20 min): search traffic, authority building.</item>
        <item>List videos (8-15 min): easy to produce, highly searchable.</item>
        <item>Case studies (15-30 min): trust building, conversion.</item>
        <item>Interviews (30-60 min): audience borrowing, relationship building.</item>
        <item>Shorts (&lt;60 sec): top-of-funnel discovery, supplement long-form.</item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section name="video-structure-and-optimization">
      <p>Hook-first video structure, title and thumbnail rules, and description template.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Write the hook before the rest of the script. The first 30 seconds determine whether viewers stay; a strong hook doubles effective watch time.</statement>
        <rationale>YouTube's algorithm weights watch time and session time. A video with a poor hook that loses viewers in the first 30 seconds generates negative distribution signals regardless of total content quality.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>0:00-0:30 — Hook: grab attention, preview value (one of: question, promise, curiosity, contrarian).</item>
        <item>0:30-1:00 — Intro: who you are, credibility signal, agenda.</item>
        <item>1:00-near end — Content: value delivery with chapter markers.</item>
        <item>Near end — CTA: subscribe, watch next video, product link (30 sec max).</item>
      </list>

      <example type="good" title="Question hook">
        <note>Question hook: "Ever wondered why your YouTube videos get views but zero subscribers?" — creates tension, promises answer, audience self-selects.</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Structure every title as: [Primary keyword] + [Benefit or outcome] + [Optional curiosity element]. Keep under 60 characters.</statement>
        <rationale>Title and thumbnail must be designed together as a single unit — the combination drives CTR. Keyword in the title signals search relevance; benefit + curiosity drives the click.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <example type="good" title="Title formula">
        <note>"How to Get Your First 1000 Subscribers (What Actually Works)" — keyword first, outcome stated, curiosity parenthetical.</note>
      </example>

      <example type="bad" title="Poor title">
        <note>"My YouTube Journey Update #47" — no keyword, no benefit, no audience signal. Only works for established channels with loyal subscribers.</note>
      </example>

      <rule>
        <statement>Every thumbnail must be readable at 120x68 pixels (mobile thumbnail size) before publishing.</statement>
        <rationale>Most YouTube impressions appear at small thumbnail sizes on mobile. A thumbnail that only reads at large size is effectively invisible to the majority of the audience.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Face with expression (surprise, excitement) — highest CTR signal.</item>
        <item>3-4 words maximum on the thumbnail.</item>
        <item>Contrasting colors against YouTube's white/dark background.</item>
        <item>Consistent style and branding across all thumbnails.</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Add timestamp chapters to all videos above 8 minutes. YouTube surfaces individual chapters in search results, increasing impressions per video.</statement>
        <rationale>Chapter timestamps generate additional SERP appearances for each chapter heading, multiplying the indexable surface area of a single video.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <reference path="templates/description.txt">YouTube description template with keyword hook, timestamps, resources, tags</reference>
    </section>

    <section name="metrics-and-publishing">
      <p>Performance metric targets, publishing cadence rules, and common mistakes that kill channel growth.</p>

      <rule>
        <statement>Track CTR, average view duration percentage, and subscriber conversion rate as primary health signals — not absolute view counts.</statement>
        <rationale>Absolute view counts are a lagging indicator and depend on subscriber count. CTR and watch duration are leading indicators that predict algorithmic distribution.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>CTR: 4% good, 8%+ great (below 4% → fix thumbnail or title).</item>
        <item>Average view duration: 40% good, 60%+ great (below 40% → fix hook or pacing).</item>
        <item>Subscriber conversion: 3% good, 8%+ great (below 3% → add subscribe CTA or improve value).</item>
      </list>

      <rule>
        <statement>Choose a publishing cadence you can sustain for 12 months. A consistent weekly schedule outperforms an inconsistent aggressive schedule.</statement>
        <rationale>YouTube's algorithm uses publishing consistency as a trust signal. Channels that publish irregularly receive less algorithmic promotion than channels with consistent cadence.</rationale>
      </rule>

      <list>
        <item>Minimum: 1 video/month — slow growth but sustainable.</item>
        <item>Good: 1 video/week — standard for most creators.</item>
        <item>Aggressive: 2-3 videos/week — fast growth, high effort.</item>
        <item>Shorts: daily — supplemental, does not replace long-form.</item>
      </list>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Waiting for perfect production quality before publishing the first video.</description>
        <reason>The first 20 videos are the learning curve. Delaying publication delays the feedback needed to improve. Ship the first video this week.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Shooting Shorts-first with the intent to convert Shorts viewers to long-form subscribers.</description>
        <reason>Shorts and long-form require separate optimization strategies. A Shorts-first strategy does not convert viewers to long-form subscribers effectively — audiences treat them as different products.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Ignoring keyword research and publishing based on personal interest rather than search demand.</description>
        <reason>Without keyword research, videos are not discoverable via search. Search-intent videos generate traffic for years; opinion videos depend on algorithmic push the channel has not yet earned.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <antipattern>
        <description>Making intros longer than 30 seconds before delivering any value.</description>
        <reason>Viewers drop off during extended intros. Every second spent on credentials before the hook is a lost viewer. State credentials in one sentence, then deliver the promised value immediately.</reason>
      </antipattern>

      <rule>
        <statement>Post the video link to email newsletter, Twitter, and LinkedIn within 2 hours of publishing.</statement>
        <rationale>External traffic in the first 24 hours is a strong positive algorithmic signal. Early external traffic tells YouTube the video has demand beyond its existing subscriber base.</rationale>
      </rule>
    </section>

    <templates>
      <template path="templates/script-tutorial.txt" purpose="Tutorial video script with hook, sections, recap, CTA."/>
      <template path="templates/video-idea.txt" purpose="Video idea card: keyword, hook, outline, CTA, thumbnail concept."/>
      <template path="templates/description.txt" purpose="YouTube description with keyword hook, timestamps, resources, tags."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-script.txt" purpose="LLM prompt to draft a full video script from topic + keyword."/>
      <template path="templates/prompt-titles.txt" purpose="LLM prompt to generate 8 title variants across formats."/>
    </templates>

    <see-also>
      <link href="https://www.youtube.com/"/>
      <link href="https://creators.youtube.com/"/>
    </see-also>
  </content>
</methodology>
