<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="task-creation-principles Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="800" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated testable rules for task-creation-principles. Verify and refine before relying on for production.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">
    <rule id="r1" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task must fit within 100k tokens total (research + SDD docs + implementation + tests + buffer). Tasks exceeding this limit must be split at natural code boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Executor agents that run out of context mid-implementation produce partial or inconsistent code. The 100k limit is a hard enforcement boundary, not a suggestion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r2" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Each task must satisfy all six INVEST criteria before being assigned to an executor. A task that fails any criterion must be rewritten or split.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">INVEST failures cause execution failures: non-independent tasks block each other unexpectedly, non-testable tasks cannot be verified as done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r3" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Task Objective must satisfy SMART: one interpretation only (Specific), verifiable by test (Measurable), technically feasible (Achievable), traces to FR-X (Relevant), has a token estimate (bound).</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Non-SMART objectives cause executors to implement the wrong scope — too much, too little, or in the wrong direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r4" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every task must include inline FR-X and AD-X text from spec and design. Do not link — paste the full text of each requirement and decision the task implements.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Executor agents that must re-read the full spec to understand their task add 10-30k tokens of overhead and risk misreading a requirement out of context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r5" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Task state is determined by which directory it lives in (todo/ / in-progress/ / done/), not by the Status field in the header. The header status must always match the directory.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Executor agents check the directory when scanning for work. A task in todo/ is picked up regardless of its Status header value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r6" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Every acceptance criterion must use Given-When-Then format with specific values. Vague criteria ("system works correctly") are rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Executor agents cannot verify vague criteria. Every AC must have an observable, code-verifiable outcome — a test that passes or fails.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="r7" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>For background jobs with no user actor, use "Given / Triggered by / Then" instead of "Given / When / Then".</statement>
      <rationale source="v1-source">Standard GWT requires a "when" actor. Background jobs are triggered by events (cron, queue message), not user actions.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>
</text>
