<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-decomposition-principles" title="Task Decomposition Principles: Size, INVEST, SMART, and Traceability">
  <summary>Right-size rules (token tiers), INVEST criteria with examples, SMART applied to task goals, traceability format from task to FR-X to AD-X, and task lifecycle states.</summary>

  <section title="Right Size Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task must fit within 100k tokens total (research + SDD docs + implementation + tests + buffer). Tasks exceeding this limit must be split at natural code boundaries.</statement>
      <rationale>Executor agents that run out of context mid-implementation produce partial or inconsistent code. The 100k limit is a hard enforcement boundary, not a suggestion.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Token tier table for task sizing</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Complexity | Token Range | Description
---------- | ----------- | -----------
simple     | <30k        | Single file, clear existing pattern
normal     | 30-60k      | Multiple files, some decisions needed
complex    | 60-100k     | Architecture decisions, research needed
]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="bad">
      <note>Too large — must be split</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Task: "Implement authentication" (multiple subsystems, estimated >200k tokens)]]></code>
    </example>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Right size — single responsibility</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[Task: "Create password hashing utilities with bcrypt" (~30k tokens, single file)]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="INVEST Criteria">
    <rule>
      <statement>Each task must satisfy all six INVEST criteria before being assigned to an executor. A task that fails any criterion must be rewritten or split.</statement>
      <rationale>INVEST failures cause execution failures: non-independent tasks block each other unexpectedly, non-testable tasks cannot be verified as done.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>INVEST criteria table with verification questions</note>
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
Criterion    | Verification Question                    | Example
------------ | ---------------------------------------- | -------
Independent  | Can be done without blocking others?     | Password utils (no deps)
Negotiable   | Can details be refined?                  | Algorithm choice is flexible
Valuable     | Clear user or business value?            | "Enables secure login"
Estimable    | Can estimate tokens?                     | ~30k tokens
Small        | Fits in one work session?                | Not "build auth system"
Testable     | Has Given-When-Then AC?                  | AC-1 through AC-4 defined
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="SMART Task Goals">
    <rule>
      <statement>Task Objective must satisfy SMART: one interpretation only (Specific), verifiable by test (Measurable), technically feasible (Achievable), traces to FR-X (Relevant), has a token estimate (bound).</statement>
      <rationale>Non-SMART objectives cause executors to implement the wrong scope — too much, too little, or in the wrong direction.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Traceability Format">
    <rule>
      <statement>Every task must include inline FR-X and AD-X text from spec and design. Do not link — paste the full text of each requirement and decision the task implements.</statement>
      <rationale>Executor agents that must re-read the full spec to understand their task add 10-30k tokens of overhead and risk misreading a requirement out of context.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <example type="good">
      <note>Traceability section in task file</note>
      <code lang="markdown"><![CDATA[
## Requirements Coverage

### FR-2: User can log in with email/password
Full text: "System SHALL authenticate users by verifying email and bcrypt-hashed password. Returns JWT on success."
This task implements: bcrypt verification in password service.

### AD-1: JWT for authentication
Full text: "Use JWT with 7-day expiry, no refresh tokens for MVP. Rationale: stateless, no Redis dependency."
This task implements: JWT generation and HTTP-only cookie storage.
]]></code>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Task Lifecycle States">
    <rule>
      <statement>Task state is determined by which directory it lives in (todo/ / in-progress/ / done/), not by the Status field in the header. The header status must always match the directory.</statement>
      <rationale>Executor agents check the directory when scanning for work. A task in todo/ is picked up regardless of its Status header value.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <list>
      <item>todo/ — Ready to start, all dependencies met</item>
      <item>in-progress/ — Being worked on by one executor</item>
      <item>done/ — Completed, all AC verified, execution report filled</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
