<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Pivot Decision Framework Core Rules" version="1.1.0" est_tokens="1100" depth="essential">
  <summary>Opinionated pivot taxonomy (segment / feature / business-model / tech / channel) with quantitative trigger signals, sunk-cost guardrails, and a hard rule for distinguishing pivot from quit for solo SaaS founders.</summary>

  <section title="Rule set">

    <rule id="pivot-taxonomy-named" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pivot type MUST be classified into one of five categories: segment / feature / business-model / tech / channel. 'We pivoted' without category is forbidden.</statement>
      <rationale source="Eric Ries — Lean Startup pivot taxonomy">Untyped pivots produce simultaneous multi-axis changes that confound learning.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="trigger-quantitative" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pivot consideration MUST cite &gt;=1 quantitative trigger: trailing-30d MRR flat or down, activation &lt;5%, churn &gt;8%/mo, NPS &lt;0.</statement>
      <rationale source="Eric Ries — pivot/persevere triggers">Gut-feel pivots produce frequent flip-flops.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="sunk-cost-disclosed" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>The decision record MUST explicitly list sunk costs (months invested, code, audience built) and explain why they are NOT used as a continuation argument.</statement>
      <rationale source="Annie Duke — Quit; Behavioral economics">Implicit sunk-cost reasoning is the dominant continuation bias.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="runway-feasibility-gate" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>Pivot is only legal when operator has &gt;=8 weeks of personal runway to execute. Pivoting on empty runway is quitting in disguise.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — solo-founder post-mortems">Runway-less pivots produce two failures.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="pivot-vs-quit-rule" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If three consecutive pivots fail to move the trigger metric within 12 weeks each, the operator MUST quit, not pivot a fourth time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Annie Duke — Quit; First Round — pivot fatigue">Serial pivoting masquerades as persistence.</rationale>
    </rule>
    <rule id="skip-this-methodology" testable="true" depth="essential">
      <statement>If applicability conditions fail (any Skip-If trigger holds — pre-launch (use customer-development); &lt;90 days live; &gt;=2-founder team; profitable product seeking optimization), the agent MUST skip this methodology and route to the named alternative or to the methodology fallback.</statement>
      <rationale source="Internal — F-066 routing convention">Mis-applying a methodology outside its preconditions degrades output quality and pollutes downstream artefacts; the explicit skip-rule keeps the routing tree honest.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
    <link path="content/06-decision-tree.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
