<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Pivot Decision — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="1000" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules governing pivot classification, hypothesis design, and the boundary between pivot, optimise, and quit.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-taxonomy" testable="true">
      <statement>Classify the proposed pivot into EXACTLY ONE of: SEGMENT (different buyer), FEATURE (different value), BUSINESS-MODEL (different revenue), TECH (different stack), CHANNEL (different distribution). Multi-axis pivots are forbidden — execute one at a time.</statement>
      <rationale source="Eric Ries — The Lean Startup, condensed by Dan Olsen">Multi-axis pivots are statistically indistinguishable from quitting and starting over. The single-axis constraint preserves learning from v1.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-falsifiable-hypothesis" testable="true">
      <statement>Every pivot must be accompanied by a written falsifiable hypothesis: "If we &lt;change&gt;, then within &lt;N&gt; days &lt;metric&gt; will improve from &lt;baseline&gt; to &lt;target&gt;. If it does not, we kill the pivot."</statement>
      <rationale source="Customer-development discipline (Steve Blank)">Without a kill-criterion the pivot becomes a perpetual project. Pre-committed thresholds force the founder to update beliefs on real data, not vibes.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-sunk-cost-separation" testable="true">
      <statement>The sunk-cost statement MUST list (a) money spent, (b) time spent, (c) what LEARNING survives the pivot. Pivots that preserve no learning from v1 are quits, not pivots.</statement>
      <rationale source="Mihail Eric / Lean Startup Lab cohort data">Founders confuse "I built code" with "I learned something". A pivot's value is in the learning, not the code. Surfacing surviving learnings is a hard test of pivot legitimacy.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-runway-gate" testable="true">
      <statement>Required runway = max(8 weeks, 2× the original v1 build time). If operator runway is below this gate, the framework returns `recommended_action: sunset` regardless of pivot quality.</statement>
      <rationale source="YC / Indie Hackers cohort observation">Pivots executed with insufficient runway fail at ~85%. Failing the pivot costs the founder the option to start something else from a position of strength.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-quit-vs-pivot" testable="true">
      <statement>If the proposed pivot is FEATURE + SEGMENT + BUSINESS-MODEL simultaneously, the framework MUST relabel it as "quit and restart" and route to founder-mental-health resources. Pivot is a course correction; restart is starting fresh — they need different decisions.</statement>
      <rationale source="Common founder failure pattern (Sahil Lavingia, Justin Jackson essays)">The classic "I'll pivot from B2C consumer mobile to B2B enterprise developer tools" is a restart that founders call a pivot to avoid grief. Naming it correctly improves the next decision.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Pivot type signatures">

    <example type="good" title="SEGMENT pivot (one axis)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
v1: time-tracking for freelancers       (Y = freelancers)
v2: time-tracking for agencies          (Y = small agencies)

X (role) unchanged.
Z (need) unchanged: "stop losing billable hours."
Y changed → SEGMENT pivot. Valid single-axis.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Hypothesis: "Within 60 days, $1k+ contracts will replace $9/mo subs, MRR up 3×."</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Triple pivot (r5 trigger)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
v1: SaaS for freelancer time-tracking, $9/mo.
v2: AI agent platform for enterprises, $50k/yr SOW.

SEGMENT changed (freelancer → enterprise)
FEATURE changed (time-tracking → AI agents)
BUSINESS-MODEL changed (SaaS → SOW)

Framework relabels as RESTART. Not a pivot.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r5. Restarts can be legitimate, but they require a different decision process (closing v1 cleanly, refunding, retaining/firing users).</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
