<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-five-stages" title="AARRR: Five Stages and Key Metrics">
  <summary>Each AARRR stage with its diagnostic question, key metric, formula, and benchmark range.</summary>

  <section title="Framework Rule">
    <rule>
      <statement>Track exactly one key metric per AARRR stage; identify the weakest stage and fix it before increasing investment in any other stage.</statement>
      <rationale>Scaling acquisition into a broken activation or retention stage multiplies waste proportionally. The weakest stage is always the highest-ROI fix because every downstream stage is bottlenecked by it.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Acquisition">
    <p>Question: How do users find you? Key metric: CPA (marketing spend / new users). Benchmark: below $50 for SaaS. Secondary: sign-up rate (sign-ups / visitors), target 2-5%. Track channel mix to maintain diverse, resilient acquisition.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Activation">
    <p>Question: Do users experience core value? Key metric: activation rate (activated users / sign-ups). Benchmark: 30-50% good, 50%+ great. Time to first value (TTV) target: under 10 minutes. Onboarding completion target: 60-80%.</p>
    <rule>
      <statement>Define activation as the specific action that correlates with D30 retention — never as a setup milestone like "created profile" that does not predict long-term usage.</statement>
      <rationale>Wrong activation metrics optimize for vanity actions. The correlation test is empirical: run regression between candidate actions and D30 retention; the action with the highest correlation is the correct activation event.</rationale>
    </rule>
  </section>

  <section title="Retention">
    <p>Question: Do users come back? Key metrics: D1 (target 40-60%), D7 (target 20-30%), D30 (target 10-15%) retention. Churn rate target: below 5%/month for SaaS. Formula: Dx retention = active on day X / signups from that cohort.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Revenue">
    <p>Question: How do you monetize? Key metrics: MRR (paying customers × avg monthly price), ARPU (total revenue / users), LTV (ARPU × avg customer lifespan in months), free-to-paid rate for freemium. LTV target: greater than 3× CAC.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Referral">
    <p>Question: Do users tell others? Key metrics: K-factor (invites sent × invite conversion rate; above 1.0 = viral), referral rate (referred users / total users, benchmark 5-15%), NPS (% promoters minus % detractors, target above 50).</p>
  </section>
</text>
