<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="02-dashboard-and-examples" title="AARRR Dashboard and Product Examples">
  <summary>Weekly dashboard template, SaaS/e-commerce/mobile app worked examples, and implementation checklist.</summary>

  <section title="Weekly Dashboard Structure">
    <p>The weekly AARRR dashboard has five sections, one per stage. Acquisition: visitors, sign-ups, CPA by channel, week-over-week delta. Activation: rate, TTV. Retention: cohort table with D1/D7/D30 for recent cohorts. Revenue: MRR, new MRR, churned MRR, ARPU. Referral: invites, conversions, K-factor.</p>
    <reference path="templates/weekly-dashboard.md">Weekly AARRR report template</reference>
  </section>

  <section title="SaaS Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Project management tool. Acquisition: 2,000 monthly sign-ups. Activation: 35% completed first project (target 50% — this is the priority fix before scaling acquisition). Retention: D30 at 18%. Revenue: 3% free-to-paid conversion. Referral: K-factor 0.05. Priority: activation is the bottleneck; fixing it from 35% to 50% would increase downstream revenue by 43% with zero additional acquisition spend.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="E-commerce Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Acquisition: 50,000 monthly visitors. Activation: 12% add-to-cart. Retention: 8% repeat purchase within 30 days. Revenue: 2.5% overall conversion rate. Referral: 1% share rate. Priority: retention (8% repeat purchase) — email re-engagement sequence and loyalty program are highest ROI next moves.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Mobile App Example">
    <example type="good">
      <note>Acquisition: 5,000 downloads/month at $2.50 CAC. Activation: 40% created first workout. Retention: D1 55%, D7 30%, D30 15%. Revenue: 4% free-to-premium conversion, $8/month ARPU, $48 LTV. Referral: 5% invite rate, 15% referral conversion, K-factor 0.075. LTV:CAC ratio 19:1 — healthy economics, main lever is improving D7 retention to D30.</note>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section title="Implementation Steps">
    <list>
      <item>Define one key metric per stage before building any dashboard.</item>
      <item>Set up tracking in GA4, Mixpanel, or Amplitude with one event per funnel step.</item>
      <item>Validate activation event by correlating candidate actions with D30 retention in cohort data.</item>
      <item>Create weekly dashboard with targets per stage and week-over-week deltas.</item>
      <item>Review weekly; identify worst-performing stage; run one experiment to improve it.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</text>
