<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="03-failure-modes" title="aarrr-pirate-metrics Failure Modes" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="700" depth="essential">
  <summary>Migrated antipatterns for aarrr-pirate-metrics as failure modes. Add detector + repair clauses where missing.</summary>

  <section title="Failure modes">
    <failure-mode id="fm-01" severity="medium">
      <description>Tracking more than one metric per AARRR stage.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Multiple metrics per stage create analysis paralysis and diffuse ownership. Each stage needs one accountable number; secondary metrics are context, not targets.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-02" severity="medium">
      <description>Focusing investment on acquisition when activation or retention is broken.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Every new user acquired into a broken funnel is waste multiplied. Fix the weakest stage first; the downstream revenue impact is proportional to acquisition volume.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-03" severity="medium">
      <description>Defining activation as "created profile" or another setup action that does not predict retention.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Optimizing for setup completion inflates activation rate while the product's retention remains flat. The only valid activation definition is an action empirically correlated with D30 retention.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-04" severity="medium">
      <description>Not segmenting AARRR metrics by acquisition channel or cohort.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Aggregate metrics mask variation. A strong paid-search cohort can hide poor organic retention; blending them produces a misleading average that leads to wrong investment decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
    <failure-mode id="fm-05" severity="medium">
      <description>Ignoring the referral stage until late in product maturity.</description>
      <detector>TBD — observable signal that this antipattern is happening</detector>
      <repair>Referral programs take 3-6 months to generate meaningful signal. Starting instrumentation and basic mechanics early means the data is available when it is needed for scaling decisions.</repair>
    </failure-mode>
  </section>
</text>
