<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text id="01-core-rules" title="Solo Niche Narrative — Core Rules" version="1.0.0" est_tokens="900" depth="essential">
  <summary>Five testable rules for refining the "I am the &lt;X&gt; for &lt;Y&gt; who needs &lt;Z&gt;" statement from paying-customer evidence.</summary>

  <section title="The five rules">

    <rule id="r1-cohort-from-payers" testable="true">
      <statement>Define &lt;Y&gt; only from customers who PAID, not those who replied / nodded / inquired. Cohort threshold: customers contributing ≥ 70% of trailing-quarter revenue.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford — Obviously Awesome (2019), Chapter 5">Positioning that follows attention rather than wallets converges on a brand that is interesting but unprofitable. The 70%-revenue rule names the actual buyer.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r2-verbatim-z" testable="true">
      <statement>The &lt;Z&gt; (the need) field must use language spoken by ≥ 3 customers in the cohort. No marketing copy, no LLM rewrites, no "value proposition synonyms".</statement>
      <rationale source="Bob Moesta — Demand-Side Sales">The customer's verbalised problem is the only positioning anchor with predictive power. Marketing rewrites optimise for click-through, not recognition by future buyers.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r3-negative-evidence" testable="true">
      <statement>Output must include 1-3 customer types EXCLUDED from &lt;Y&gt;, each with a one-line reason citing real lost-deal evidence. "Positioning for everyone" is rejected.</statement>
      <rationale source="April Dunford / Strategyn">Strong positioning is recognisable by who it repels. Without exclusions, positioning becomes a meaningless universal claim.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r4-drift-gate" testable="true">
      <statement>The new statement must change at least one of {X, Y, Z} compared to the previous quarter's statement. If all three are identical, the framework concludes "no refinement needed" and returns the prior statement with a stability marker — DO NOT produce cosmetic synonym changes.</statement>
      <rationale source="Solo-positioning anti-pattern">Operators rewrite positioning quarterly because the calendar says so, generating thesaurus-grade noise that confuses prospects. The drift gate forces a real signal-based change or no change.</rationale>
    </rule>

    <rule id="r5-anti-aspiration" testable="true">
      <statement>If the operator wants &lt;X&gt; or &lt;Y&gt; to be a category they have NOT been paid for in the trailing quarter, this methodology REJECTS the change and routes to `problem-validation`. Niches are refined from evidence, not declared.</statement>
      <rationale source="Trevor Owens — Lean Enterprise / Brennan Dunn">Self-declared niche shifts ("I want to focus on AI startups now") without paying evidence drop quarterly revenue ~30% as the existing pipeline thinks the operator quit their old service.</rationale>
    </rule>

  </section>

  <section title="Statement scoring rubric">

    <example type="good" title="Refined statement (passes all rules)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"I am the API integration developer for D2C Shopify brands
 doing $1-10M GMV who need their Klaviyo and ERP to stop
 dropping order data on Black Friday."

X = API integration developer            (concrete role, not "freelancer")
Y = D2C Shopify brands at $1-10M GMV     (cohort with 70% revenue evidence)
Z = "stop dropping order data on BF"     (verbatim quote from 4 customers)
      ]]></code>
      <note>Specific X, evidenced Y, verbatim Z. Excludes: enterprise (lost 2 deals on red-tape), pre-revenue (low budget).</note>
    </example>

    <example type="bad" title="Aspirational (r5 violation)">
      <code lang="text"><![CDATA[
"I am the AI agent architect for VC-backed AI startups
 who need to ship MVPs fast."

Operator's prior quarter had 0 AI-startup customers.
Pure aspiration. Framework rejects → run problem-validation
on the AI-startup niche first.
      ]]></code>
      <note>Illustrates r5 — methodology refuses to legitimise wishful niche shifts.</note>
    </example>

  </section>

  <see-also>
    <link path="content/02-output-contract.xml"/>
    <link path="content/03-failure-modes.xml"/>
  </see-also>
</text>
